Okay, yeah, let's get started.
Cool, cool, let's get started.
Let's get started, yeah.
Okay, thanks for coming back.
Today, we are going to start,
officially start our lecture.
We all start from here,
as you can see, machine
learning system basics.
Yeah. I believe this lecture
is still pretty
lightweight. Yeah. Enjoy.
Before that, there are
three forms that
worth your attention.
The first one is beginning
of quarter survey.
If 80% of you finish that,
all you get one point.
Okay? One of the most
efficient way and
the easiest way to
get one point, okay?
Second is make sure you sign up
the scribe and we have
a lot of students,
so you don't have to
do a lot of work.
The second most efficient
way to get eight points.
Okay. You just need
to do it once.
The third one is,
we created Slack.
So we will still
send our important
announcement on Piazza,
but slack is for you guys.
So if you need to
get in touch with
your teammate or whatever,
if you want to discuss homework,
feel free to use that space.
Okay? Yeah. Okay, cool.
Today, we are going to talk
about some basics or
machine learning systems.
I think one of the most
important basics is,
we try to understand
our workload,
because we are building systems.
Our system is trying to
support some workload.
So let's first
understand our workload.
So pretty simple.
Our workload is basically,
machine learning
or more dominantly deep
learning competitions.
Yeah. So idea of deep learning,
I think all you guys should
have that understanding, right?
I basically we try
to stack many,
many new layers and
we try to compose
a pretty large and effective
powerful model like this.
So we have a set of
images and we want to
classify them, right?
Uh, so we basically come up with
a few layers and each layer
perform some type
of competition.
And we forward the images
through the network
and we get some labels
predicted, right?
And at the inference,
we basically do this so called
forward competition, right?
But this new network cannot
work if you don't train it.
So the way we train this
neural network is basically
do we do a backward propagation,
right, we update
parameters, okay?
Um, there are many types
of neural networks.
But in this course,
we are going to
simplify a little bit.
I'm going to give you
a master equation,
which is pretty simple here.
Okay. Uh, at the first glance is
basically like we have some
loss function A and we try
to derive the gradients
using this function
against the parameters
theta given
training data D.
And then we apply
the gradients or parameter
updates to the
original parameter.
So we finish on iteration
of computation.
Almost all the new networks or
deep learning programs are
essentially doing this.
Okay? We are going to spend
a little bit time diving
into this equation, o.
But I want to make sure you guys
remember this
equation because this
will be our basic abstraction.
We will develop our system
based on this equation.
Okay, let's look
at the components.
The first component, D,
or training data, right?
It could be images,
could be text,
could be video, could
be audio, right?
And there are many ways
to store this data.
For example, database people,
they develop a lot of
very nice storage or
mechanisms to store data.
But in this course,
we are not going to spend a
lot of time on that, okay.
This data is our
parameter, right?
In deep learning, we have
a set of parameters we
want to optimize
until convergence.
So we already perform a kind
of iterative converging
computation.
That is, we keep throwing
data into our new network.
We calculate the gradients.
We update the parameter until
the parameter does not
change anymore, right?
So that's why we
have superscript
T. That is we perform
iterations, yeah.
We already have a loss function,
right? That defines our goal.
For example, it could be, um,
it could be two loss
where we do regression.
It could be hinge loss,
softmax loss where we
do classification or ranking
loss where we do ranking.
It depends on your
problem. Okay. And in
this etuation the
loss is basically
the capital L. And in
order to make this work,
we usually apply some sort
of optimization
algorithms, right?
So one of the most
famous algorithm
is basically is stochastic
grading decent, right?
And it's variants like
atom or whatever.
And there are also some other
methods that's possible,
like second order methods,
right, new methods or whatever.
But basically, they belong
to the optimization methods,
which is basically the
function F, right?
That is how we apply our
updates to our primeers. Okay?
Any question? Cool. Here, we
basically get our three
most important components
that machine learning
systems will cover.
Okay? The first one, of
course, data, right?
So what type of data we have?
We have a lot, right, images,
text, audio, table, right?
And that actually corresponds
to different kinds of
models we develop.
Second pillar model, right?
So what are the most
important models here?
So in this course, we are
going to cover probably
the most important class models
that will solve 80%
of the problems.
So here's a list. For example,
SNS, RNs, transformers,
and MOEs.
There are a few variants built
based on on top of them.
Okay? And with data
and the model,
the third element is
basically compute.
We want to throw them into
some hardware and we
try to get the results.
Okay? So what kind
of computer we have?
CPUs, GPUs, accelerators,
TPU, and LPUs.
Even like your laptop
can actually do
deploying today, right?
You have arm architecture MOM
two and three, four, okay?
And PGA, right.
Okay. Uh, that's
basically our workload.
But you can see from this list,
it's already complicated,
very very complicated.
So we're not going to
build a system that can
basically solve
all the problems.
So the first uh thing I
want to make clear is,
um there are many,
many great models
developed in history.
But because this is
a system course and we
are not all we are
system builders.
So one of the lesson that system
builders should keep in mind is,
we will not be able
to build systems
that can support all
types of workloads, okay?
So as a system builder,
always ask ourselves, what are
the most important workloads
that can solve 80%
of the problems?
And we're going
to build a system
that is pretty good at this 80%,
and we'll give the rest of 20%
to the PD students, right?
Okay. Um, so basically
system building is
the process to reveal the
most important, um factors.
Then we start asking ourselves,
what are the most
important models?
What are most
important data types
and what are most
important hardware,
and we are going to build
a system for them, okay?
What are the most
important models?
As I already said, four types
of models today, right?
Widely adopted. Almost solve
like 80% of marchinary
problems, okay?
SN recurrent neural
networks transformer
and mixture experts.
Okay? These are basically
the most popular
model families today.
So what is the most important
opmenting algorithm?
I already said, Stochastic
gradient descent.
Yeah. And what is the
most important variant
of stochastic grading design?
It's basically Adam, right?
So we are going to learn.
We are going to grind a lot
on Adam algorithm, okay?
Yeah, SGD and its
variance, for example,
Adam Okay, um,
throughout this lecture,
we are going to keep
asking ourselves,
what are the most
important Xs in Y?
So we can basically gradually
figure out the right
thing to build.
Because when we build system,
we try to figure out the
right abstraction, right?
The abstraction should express
the most important class
problems we care about.
Okay. Uh, next, I'm
going to quickly go
through the important
machinery algorithms
in roughly 30 minutes.
So usually, it takes a whole
quarter to learn them,
but I'm going to go through
that in 30 minutes.
So if you have trouble
following this,
make sure you take
some machinery classes,
or read some books.
Okay. The first classroom
models we care about SN, right?
SN already enabled so
many cool applications.
Here I give six,
classification, retrieval,
detection, segmentation,
self driving, and
image synthesis.
And you can see SN is mostly
adopted in compavon
problems, okay?
So the fundamental
scene is basically,
there is a very magical layer
called convolution layer, right?
And this convolution layer
has basically input and output.
The input, for example,
is to the image.
The output is slightly
smaller to the image.
And one key parameter of scene
it has some so called
convolution filters.
The filter is very small size,
for example, three by three
or four by four, right?
And you will apply
these filters on top
of the input image.
Uh, you will slide
the small filter from
left to right from
top to bottom, right?
And you will apply dot
product on top of it,
and then you will
get uh a result
which will be written into
the output image, right?
So this is basic scene, yeah.
So the magic behind scene is if
you stack these layers
many, many times,
it will basically start
learning the features,
so called features, like
low level features.
And at the initial layers,
it will learn some
very low level edge
and color features.
But as you stack more
and more layers,
you will find that it
will start to learn
more and more high
level features,
like semantic features.
For example, if that is
a catfish or if that's a dog
fish, something like that.
Okay? This is why scene
works pretty well.
Okay. Is this okay as a
starter lessons for CN? Yeah.
Okay, only two slides.
Then I'm going to ask you
the most important question
for system builder perspective.
Okay. So what is the top
three models for CN?
Yeah, Rest definitely
one of them, right?
So I'm going to review,
the first one AlexNet, right?
One most important one. It was
basically the start
of everything.
Yeah. And this paper,
I think is a classic.
I believe most of you have
already read this paper, okay?
Second one, Rest already
pointed out, right?
So Ra is the thing that
brings the thing up to scale,
and people can
start 100 liars or
even more to get
very good results.
The third one is
basically Unit, right?
If you are familiar with
the diffusion
community, you know,
Unit is basically a backbone
for stable diffusion.
Yeah. But today is not,
but we still look at that, okay?
Yeah. Unit is also pretty
widely adopted in medical
image analysis, okay?
So this thing, in my opinion,
is the most important one,
and we are going to optimize
them from a system
perspective, okay?
Cool. With that, then we start
asking another question.
So from a computational
perspective,
what are the most important
components in science?
For example, what kind of
mathematical operations and
computations are performed in
all these types of scenes?
The first one definitely
convolution, right?
It could be com one D,
count two D. Comm three D
is basically the one you
apply on videos, right?
And among count two D was
the most important shape.
It's basically three
by three count. Yeah.
So if you have a kernel that
optimize three count
in extreme sense,
then you're doing pretty well
already on Mtunit systems.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Then the second most
important operator incident
is basically remember
in stress nut,
at the end, we have a few MLPs,
right, multilayer perception.
So what is inside of
multilyer perception?
It's basically math mo
A times B to see where A
and B are both matrices.
Okay? And at the end,
we have a soft max,
and softmax is basically like we
apply some sort of
a romanization.
We try to get a probability
and we try to predict the label.
Softmax is pretty
important. What else?
There are some element
wise operations, right,
like non linear function
transformations
such as u in Rs Nat.
There are some add and sub.
We also sometimes
perform some sort
of pooling and batmanization.
All these are basically
belonging to the element wise.
Okay? I think this list
basically summarize
the most important
computational I call primitive
we performed scenes.
Yeah, we care about that
because we are going
to optimize them.
That basically wraps up SN.
Okay? The problem SN is
basically it basically does
some sort of one to one mapping.
That is, you have image,
you pre label for it.
But in nature, there
are so many data that's
not one to one, right?
For example, in
natural language,
we are speaking a sentence
and we try to predict
next sentence,
in many cases, we want to do
sequence to sequence prediction.
Uh, that's why we have
recurrent nu networks, okay?
Recurrent news has a power that
is they can't do one
too many mapping.
That is, you give
you the one word, it
can predict many
words out, right.
Or you can do many to one or
you can do many too
many in different ways.
Predict future words or
predict a label for
each current word.
Okay? That's why we have
iron the key idea
of RN is basically,
it has some internal
state that is
updated as a sequence process,
right from the first word to
second word third word, we are
going to maintain a state.
We are going to keep updating
state through some competition.
Okay? And theoretically, we
can make any neural
network requirement right.
Because if we enroll RN,
we can see the orange orange box
is basically a neural
network architecture,
and we can basically embed
any neural network into
this orange box, right.
It could be a could be
something basically
any competition, okay?
Then let's go back, right? We
keep asking this question.
So what is the top
three models in Iran?
Yeah, STM definitely
one of them, right?
So here's my list, okay?
The first one, bi
direction ions,
that is you compute
from left to right.
Meanwhile, you also compute
from right to left.
Okay? Second one, LSTM as you
already pointed out, right?
And it has been widely adopted
in analyzing time series, okay?
And I hope you guys already
learned LSTM
somewhere else, okay?
And third one GRU is a
slightly simplified wing LSTM.
It has less, it has
a much simplified,
recurrent mechanism, but
it's still powerful.
Okay, that's the
top three model.
Then we keep asking
the question,
what are the most
important components
in our computational components?
As I said, any model
can be made recurrent.
So if your iron is
based on cong work,
then you basically have
all the operators from CN.
But meanwhile, how
do you basically,
update the states
from step to step?
So you basically still use
a few metamorF example,
you do weighted average
across all the
states in the past,
and you try to get a new state.
And meanwhile, you apply
some linear transformation on
top of the metamo
results, right?
So you still have a few very
fancy linear transformations
such as Valu tangent,
sigmo or whatever, right?
Okay. That's basically
the novel elements
that introduced by
An pretty simple.
Steel metamo and a few linears.
Okay. Then I'm going to
review very difficult multiple
choice question, okay?
So who invented LSTM?
So choice A, Yana
Con Choice B. Jeffer
Hinton, of course, yeah.
Chose three Yoshi Benjo
Choice for this guy.
Yeah. Yeah. This is a pretty
difficult question, right?
B if you actually brows a
little bit on Diploing history,
you probably know
actually the first guy
invented asked him,
for the first time.
But only the first three guys,
they get twin award.
Yeah. So that guy
is pretty unhappy.
Yeah. He was, like,
debating with all the people
deploying community
at Twitter every day.
Yeah, if you check
his tweet, okay?
But we have to give
him credit, okay?
Okay. Then let's ask a
more open ended question.
I Arn is already able to
model sequences pretty well,
why ChIP was not built
using RNs but transformers?
So that means An actually
has some limitations,
right? You want to speak?
Yeah. Uh huh.
Yes. Yes. Yeah.
That's exactly like 80%
of the answer. Yeah.
So Arn has two major problems.
One problem is it keeps
forgetting things.
The reason is pretty easy
to understand, right?
So if you basically
maintain a state
right from the first time
step to the last time step,
normally in deep
unilateral competition,
we basically multiply something
that is smaller than one, right?
The value is pretty
small floating point.
And if you do this and you keep
updating the state, you can see,
if we multiply any
arbitrary large value H
by value that is
smaller than one.
And if you do it
many many steps,
then the value will
approximate zero, right?
That means that when
your sequence is pretty
long at the end,
you are going to diminish
your activation.
Yeah. That's why An cannot
learn very long sequences.
The second reason or
the primary reason is
because as a student already
pointed out, it's
not paralizable.
So every time you
can only wait for
the previous time step
to finish competition,
then you can proceed to
the next competition.
Yeah. So it cannot benefit
from our powerful GPUs.
Okay. Given these two problems,
I think, basically, um,
in 20 I think 17 or 2018,
some researchers from Google,
they wrote a paper called
Attention is all Net.
Okay? And that paper
is pretty famous,
but it's not on our reading list
because we're not
macharing class.
But I highly recommend.
Attention basically
fix that problem, okay?
The idea of attention
is basically we try
to this sequence, right?
But we try to treat each
position's representation as
a query to access
and incorporate information
from a set of values.
Right? So basically now,
when you compute
the hidden position
for each sequence position,
you basically see the query,
and you try to query the key and
values from all the other
posts in the previous layer.
In this way, you
can see layer one,
all the one, all the
positions with label one,
they can compute in
parallel, right,
because they are not
blocking each other.
Okay? There's no
sequential dependency.
And this is perfectly
for GPUs because you can
parleyze these unit
GPU kernels, right.
But in iron, that's not the case
because at least in iron,
you know layer one, you
have to compute from
left to right, right. Okay.
Any problem on the spur?
Cool. Personally,
I think attention
becomes pretty dominant and it
wins over majorly
because of this.
Yeah. It is so paralyzable.
Okay. And as I already said,
attention is massively
paralyzable and
the lumber unparallezable
operations
does not increase
with sequence nons.
That means we can
apply attention to
arbitrary large sequences
and we are not going to,
you know, suffer from that
sequential dependency.
We are going to
dive deep into this
and write down the
mathematical equations later.
Okay? But here I'm just
trying to give you overview.
Okay. And given attention,
we are basically able to
construct the
transformers, right?
So transformer basically
equals to attention plus
a few MLP and plast
few other operations.
So this is the figure I
basically cropped from that
attention or you need paper,
and you can see this
figure basically
illustrates the attention,
uh composition.
So you have a few attentions,
you go through some
operation layer lo.
It's a lomization
operation element wise,
and then you go through
some MLP, right?
The MLP, that is exactly in
the sence and oppose value.
And transformers have two types.
One is encoder,
the other decoder,
and we are going to dive
deep into that. Okay.
So the most famous model
for encoder is Bird, right?
And the most famous model
for decoder is GPT.
Okay. Okay, then let's
ask this question again.
So what is the top three
models for transformers?
I already said Bird,
encoder based.
Second, GPT and LIMs, right?
What's the third
type? Okay. Yeah.
T five, right? You said T five.
But you can think T five
as something that is pretty
similar to bird and GBD.
It's basically a
combination half bird
and half GBT, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah,
wind transformer,
but is basically
similar to bird.
Yeah. In my opinion,
it's DIT, diffusion
transformers. Okay.
That's why I said
Unit is no longer
used in in diffusions.
I think today people
are moving away from
Unit to apply transformers
into diffusion.
Okay? Yeah. And we
are also going to study
that a little bit.
Cool. Okay? Apparently, this
already happened at
least transformer
becomes the choosing one, right?
So everyone now basically
use transformer as
a default backbone for
all types of tasks, okay?
And it becomes the
chosen largely because
of this guy, right?
And this guy looks
pretty wise, okay?
This is a picture of him this
year last year,
sorry, last December.
And you can say ten years ago,
he looks much younger, okay?
And this guy now
is basically very famous
in Silicon Valley,
right, and people treat
him as a perfect.
So sometimes he speaks
something and people
will believe, okay?
And actually, ten years ago,
he has a paper
called sequence to
sequence learning with
Depart works, right?
That model that
paper is basically
the foundation and the
first try of training,
P kind of models, right?
And other talk, he has
a very famous slide,
which I also crop here.
Only three sentence.
So if you have
a very large data set and
you train a very big model,
then success is guaranteed.
Right? This is a pretty
brief statement.
And yeah, yeah, pretty good.
Okay. And I also give
the talk link here
and if you're
interested, go watch it.
It's only 20 minutes.
Pretty good.
Okay. Okay, then let's
come back to the
computational perspective.
So what are the most
important components
in transformers.
Like I already said,
transformer equal to attention
plus MLP plus something else.
Then we just look at one
by one, What is attention?
Attention is basically
a few metamor right?
And after metamo you do
some sort of softmax.
And one of the most common
romanization operation
in attention is called layer on.
So basically attention
is basically composed
with metamor soft max
and the romanization.
Okay. So MLP, you
already know met M,
right? More met moo.
And there are some like Galo,
a special type of non linear
function used in attention.
Okay? That's basically, um,
the computational operators that
we can find in transformers.
Cool. Any questions so far?
Okay, then we'll move
to our fourth model,
MOE, okay Mixture experts.
So there are indeed,
there are not many normal
components from MOE, okay?
Uh, MOE is usually used together
with one of the previous
three types of models.
For example, you can
mix MOE transformers.
You can mix MOE with
something like that. Okay.
But the idea high level
idea of MOE is basically,
um, we try to replicate
some components of
the single model.
So we create a lot of experts,
and the hope is basically
we let all the experts
to produce a prediction and
we take a majority voting,
right, something like that or
weighted average voting, right?
And we hope that the voting from
many experts could produce
a better results than
a single expert.
That's basically idea.
Okay. And as a fact
as a reality check,
okay, latest alums
are mostly MOEs.
For example, Grock
Mas Grock is MOE.
Okay? And the mixture
is the one that
created by the misrEIPrevioc
by Lamantin. Okay.
DBD four uh said to be MOE,
no confirmation, okay?
And the very famous DPC V three,
which was released
two weeks ago,
I think it basically
becomes very popular,
very hot on Twitter.
It is MOE, right?
Okay? And as I already said,
the only novel computation in
MOE is something
called a router.
Why? Because once you have
input going into
all these experts,
you need to basically
embed a router
to decide which expert is
going to ask you that input.
Right? Because you
are replicating
the model with
many many experts.
And for example,
in transformers,
each expert only corresponds to
a few say MLPs MLP layers, okay.
So what constitutes a router?
It's still meta and softmax,
because you basically, uh,
apply a classification
mechanism here, right?
You take the input,
you classify it
into the lumber classes.
Corresponding to the
lumber experts here,
and then you take the
top two value and you
give the output to
the top two experts.
Yeah, that's it. Okay. Then
I'm going to ask a question.
I'm not going to give answer.
You should think about
it, if you have time.
Why router makes it
super difficult?
Yeah, why it difficult
to design systems.
Okay, we are going to gradually
approach it out in
later lectures.
Okay. Any questions so far?
Okay, that's basically our
20 minutes machining class.
Okay, we finish. Um, Okay,
let's do a summarize.
Do a summary. Okay.
So we basically,
look at the computation.
Look at these models from
a competition perspective, okay?
We basically reviewed four
types of models, right?
Sins, irons,
transformers, and MOEs,
and we try to identify
the computational elements
from these models,
okay, which are
listed here, okay?
And if we basically
shuffle them a little bit,
we will see that Mdmol
appears four times,
Softmax appears three
times and then others.
Then I'm going to give
you the true name on
this cours Meta M plus
softmax are all you need.
We are going to grand
on these two operators
from CPO to GPO,
from single device to clusters.
A majority of our
effort will be just
looking at how we
can make metamo
and Soffamx faster or how we can
paralyze metamo and
softmax on many GPOs.
In other words, MLC is
basically equals to met Moss.
If you study metamo pretty well,
you are already an expert.
That's all you need.
Cool, cool. Then we finish
the machining part,
okay, we are going to come
back to the system part.
So as I said, we have
data model and computer,
as the three key components
in machining systems.
So then we are going to study
this one by one, right?
Because eventually our
goal is basically given
the data and given computation
described by the model,
we try to put them onto
our computer devices and
try to get the results.
So how to represent data.
So normally we represent
data in this way,
right? This is our data.
Computers, how do
we represent data.
So in mergin systems we
usually use a format
called tensor,
withdraw this in memory,
and we are going to come
back to this later.
Okay? How do we represent
models in our program?
Like I already
said, we represent
them using a set of
mathematical primitives,
already figure out other set
of primitives, mostly memo.
Okay? But that's not sufficient.
Why? Because we only,
figure out the basic
individual primitives.
We still need to
connect them together,
to represent the competition
of the model, the entire model.
Globally. So basically,
we are going to develop
a reputation that can
express the competition
using these primitives.
Okay? We are going to
connect them together.
And third one, of
course, compute,
how we can make this primitives
into programs and how we can
make programs that can
run on all sorts of
hardware, CPU GPU TPU.
Yeah. That's basically
the third part.
Okay. Next, I'm going to
introduce a very, very
powerful repentation.
We are going to focus
on the middle question,
how we can develop orientation
to express the models.
Okay? And this orientation
is called dataflow graph.
Okay? If you use the
partwortna flow,
you probably are already
familiar with this term.
Okay. Data flow graph
is basically the kind
of language we use to express
marinaring competition.
Okay. Before I dive deep into
that let's recall our goal.
Our goal is we try to express
as many model as possible
using one set of
program interface by connecting
these mathematical
primitives, right?
And remember what is
inside the model,
we have the model and
architecture which basically
express the connectivity between
mathematical primitives.
We have an objective
function, right,
which is essentially another set
of, uh, like computation.
We have an optidor which is,
in my opinion, atom, right?
Everyone is atom.
We need to express
atom pretty well.
And we have some data, okay?
So the way that we find out
the right abstraction or
the right representations,
basically,
we look at our application and
we think about what kind of
representation can
actually serve
better on our application.
So in history, we have
developed many many
systems, for example,
if you study database
courses, you know,
uh, we have a pretty famous
workload called Data
Management, right?
In other words, OLTP.
And in this workload,
how do we represent programs and
communi so the very
famous language
to do this is basically
called SCO, right?
We use SQL to query data,
and we sort data in
some sort of storage,
and we build a so called
relation database.
And in a relation database,
we have a lot of tables to
represent the data, right?
And the SQL will
basically quires tables.
And before it actually ask
you that query it will has
some query processing or
query planning mechanism
to make it efficient, right?
This is how we ended up
building in the past 20
years, right for database.
And as data become
bigger and bigger,
we start moving to OEP, right?
We start moving into big
data and we try to do
some very simple functional
transformation on big tables.
And apparently this plane
SQL does not suffice.
So what we do is we build
something called spark memduc
and we start redesigning
our storage mechanism.
We store them in so called
column storage, right?
And we create some data
warehousing and we start creating
those data flow competition
so we can express
the competition.
Okay. And probably in the same.
Now we are moving to
the third stage that
is machine learning become
a dominant workload.
How do we develop
orientation to basically
express this combination.
Okay. Here, we are
going to introduce
computation dear graph, okay?
So here, you can
see two examples.
I'm going to dive
deep into that.
Remember, this is
probably one of
the most important slides
of this lecture, okay?
If you cannot follow
in a lecture,
go back to check it out.
Okay? So here we define graph
with node and edges, okay?
The node basically
represents the computation.
For example, it's a
primitive, it's an operator.
For example, Mdm
is a node, right?
And like add sub or whatever,
it kind of primitive operator.
Okay. And it will basically
represent a node in the graph.
In your graph, of
course, you have edges.
Basically, the edge represents
the data dependency.
That is how the data flow from
the first operator
to second or third.
Only represent the dependency.
Meanwhile, we're
going to slightly
overload node, the
definition node.
We also use the
node to represent
the output tensor
of the operator.
For example, in the left
figure, you can see,
we have the mo multiplication.
So that node
represents two things.
One is the mod itself,
the computation.
Second is output.
It represents computation
and the output.
That's why there's arrow from
the mount to the add const
because the output of
the mode will go into
the next operator, okay?
And if we also use the nodes
to represent some constant,
for example, you don't have
to perform any competition,
you just have input and
input is a constant.
That's why the A and
B are also nodes,
A and B has the edge
going to the mod,
so they flow into the mod and
perform the mount
competition. Okay? Clear?
Okay. So from this definition,
you can see, on the left side,
we basically define competition,
which is a multiply
B plus three, right?
Okay. And on the right
one is slightly more
complicated and you can spend
5 seconds looking at that
and you all figure out,
we are basically defining
a very small neural
network, right?
So we have the constant X
and a constant W one, right.
And they are nodes and
they flow into the met mo.
So we met mod them together,
we get the results.
The results will going into
the next operator
with Lu, right?
And the results will get
into the second memo, right?
The second memo has a
second input with W two.
Then W two, and the
result value will be
met mode and get into
lots funone MSE, right?
And then MSE you will compare
the computation results and
the two label Y and give you
output, which is the loss.
Okay? So here, actually,
this graph has a
little bit problem.
So MSE is actually
not primitive.
Right, MSE is a function is
a very complicated function,
so I simplify a it bit.
Okay? And you guys need
to figure out how to
actually express MSE
in true primitive.
Yeah, the most elementary
operators from there, okay?
But I think you basically
get the definition, right.
This is dataflow graph. Okay.
In the next few slides,
I'm going to do a case study
of deploying programs
using a very,
very original tensor
flow one API.
U Echo it a classic flavor.
Okay. And, um, but you should
keep in mind that today,
for example, if you
are petrogPower user,
you probably find it slightly
different from what
you wrote today.
But basically, under Hood,
they are using the
same representation,
which is called data ph graph.
Okay? So the use case we
are going to look
at is basically
one linear neural network,
which performs
logistic regression.
It basically takes the image
represented as a vector.
It goes through this like
a single layer MLP, right?
And it will go through
two class softmax,
which is basically
logistic regression, okay?
And here's the program, okay?
You can see, we first
import something
right from the Paton library,
and then we start call
this interface to
define a few constant
X Y X is our input,
Ys put W is the weight, okay?
And then what we do is what
we call the interface,
we continue to
define commutation.
Here we basically um define
loss function and we
call API which is
called the TFRduc mean.
Inside of reduce
mean, what do we
do uh we do a reduce sum.
Uh we like Y times TF log Y.
Then we basically
slightly rotate
the axis in some way and we
try to get the mean value, okay?
And in order to make
this new network,
but because up until here,
we only define the fmmetation we
still need to define some
sort of recommendation.
So what we do is basically
we use other API
called Tift gradient.
So what does this
Tift grading do?
I perform something called
automatic differentiation,
right?
It basically take
this computation
you defined in forward mode and
you try to derive
the backward mode,
how to calculate gradients.
Okay? And then we are
going to specify the
SET update rule, right?
So here you can see, uh,
we have a learning rate,
which is a constant.
From the TF grading,
we have the calculated gradient,
which is W grad,
underscore grad.
And we market them together,
and then we manage
it from the original
with W. We get the next re W.
So recall that master
equation activity
at the beginning, okay?
And here comes to something
that is really weird, okay?
And you can see, actually
the program actually
run here at the end.
So basically, all the code I
showed about this line is
basically defining the graph.
Try to declare the graph,
but it actually runs at the end.
Okay. I'm going to explain
this because this is
a very important thing in
margining frameworks, okay?
So but before I
explain the mechanism,
the execution mechanism here,
so you can see, what
happens behind the
scenes, basically,
whenever you call
the TFEPTflowEPI
to define to write
some competition, uh,
the tener flow will basically
try to comprehend
what you wrote in
program and try to construct
a graph structure here, right?
So every time you
write one line,
you basically add a one operator
and the TF will basically
maintain TF flow
graph, behind, okay.
And you keep writing the
loss function or whatever,
so the TF will keep
constructing one more
nodes into this graph.
And once you call
the TF gradient,
it will automatically
perform auto Div and try to
derive a graph that we call
backward graph, right?
The backward graph
will take some
inputs from the forward graph,
and it will basically reverse
the graph using some
mathematical rules,
which is follow back
propagation, okay?
And it will basically
connect them together.
Okay. And when you
do open matter declaration
and when you do section run,
they basically trigger a graph.
And then the data will flow from
the first node to last
node and then come back.
Yeah. This is what
tender flow does,
for your machining program.
Okay, um, if you're not
familiar with it's
fine because we
are going to come back
to this again. Okay.
But let us discuss a few
problems or questions.
The first one is, what are
the benefits of computing
graph abstraction? Like,
what are the pros?
Sorry? Yeah. So
it's very powerful,
as you can see, because
it's a graph orientation,
you can't represent
any kind of amation
as long as you have
a primitive, right?
Okay. And it's very clean.
Once you take this graph,
you can ask you the graph.
So given this graph,
what are the possible
implementations
and implementations
on this graph?
Maybe we'll focus
on implementation.
If we are going to focus, if we
are going to basically
ask you this graph,
how we can make it faster.
Actually, this data
photograph provides
a perfect platform
for us to optimize
because you probably can apply
arbitrary graph parsing and
graph analyzing
algorithm on the graph.
You try to reduce the
size of the graph,
for example, you try
to field some nodes,
and you try to cut graph,
maybe put one half
on one device,
the other half on
the second device,
you try to paralyze this graph.
So as you can see, this graph
also enables a lot of
possible organizations.
So in the next few classes,
we are going to basically
optimize this graph
because this graph represents
the machine learning programs.
And we are going to
discuss all the ways
how we can make
the graph faster.
Then the third question,
what are the cons
of the graph? Okay.
One major bottleneck of
this computer graph
is very static.
You define it, then
you cannot change it.
You define the compution
then you cannot change it.
The graph is here and it's
very hard to alter
the computation.
You basically need to
redefine the graph.
So in reality, many many
computations are very dynamic.
For example, the graph can
change depending on your input.
For example, if you write
person wrote slaps you probably
usually use something like if
my value is greater than what
I'm going to do something,
otherwise, I'm going to
do something else, right?
And you can imagine if there's
a machinery model does
something similar,
if my tensor value is
greater than something,
I want to ask you that graph,
otherwise, I ask
you another graph.
The reality is you actually
don't know your input.
Your input is
basically some data
generated by somewhere else,
and the screen pattern
can be very dynamic.
But you can see this data
flow graph is pretty static,
so it can only represent
static things.
Okay. Cool. Any
questions so far?
Okay, then we are going
to move into a more,
I would say modern version,
a different flavor,
which is Petrich.
Okay? Uh, Petrich actually
also use, um, dataflow graphs.
But the way that they use
data flow is quite different.
So here is a very nice, uh, uh,
illustration of what happens
under the hood when
you start writing
Petro programs, right?
You can see different from
the previous example I showed
where you define a graph and
then you remember there's a
session door run at the end,
which will trigger
the execution.
In Petrogs quite different.
Whenever you write
the line of code,
you can actually immediately
ask you a line of code.
You will get results. It's very,
very similar to how
you use Python.
Right under the hood
what petri does is basically
whenever you write
some line of code
that will basically
contribute to a
component of the graph,
Petrog will dynamically
constrain the graph.
And meanwhile, it will
trigger the excusion for you.
So you can always get
results at any line,
If you add a print
in the middle,
you will get the results.
But in the previous example,
if you add a print,
there's no results, okay.
Yeah. Sorry.
Yes, exactly.
I'm going to talk about
that in my next step.
I hope you guys understand
this difference, right?
The first one is more like
a symbolic declaration,
but this one is
more like a flavor,
Pythonic, we do have a
name for them, okay?
We call the first one
a symbolic program,
and we call the second
one imperative program,
this basically classifies
the existing emerging
frameworks into two categories.
One is symbolic frameworks.
The other is
imperative frameworks.
And I think most of you what
you use today is basically
belonging to the second class.
Because you can already reason
why the second class
is more popular.
It's more intuitive, because
I always want to print something
in the middle and to make sure
that my program runs
correctly, right?
Okay.
And as I already pointed
out in this slide.
The key difference is basically
in symbolic programming,
you do workflow which is
called define then run.
You first define the
competition, then you write it.
In imperative programming,
you define and run,
you define it and you can write.
You can write anytime, Okay?
Let's basically discuss
a little bit more on
the pros and cons of
symbolic versus imperative.
For symbolic, I already said,
it's good because you cannot
run it before you define.
But once you define, you
actually have a global picture
of what you are doing.
Maintaining a global picture is
good for system developers
because I know what
they are going to
do in the future. I
can optimize for you.
In general, symbolic program
or frameworks is easier to
optimize because I know
your graph and it's
much more efficient.
It could be turn more efficient.
That's why your patgram
is actually pretty smaw.
It has a lot of
space to optimize.
Okay. The bad thing I
already told you, right?
So the way that you program
the symbolic program programs
is very counterintuitive.
You have to define
define device.
So it has a large
overhead on your brain.
Yeah, you need to know
what you're doing.
Yeah. Secondly, it's
very difficult to debug,
because you cannot know
the results until you
define the competition
and trigger
a session door run. Okay?
And it's not less flexible as I.
Okay. For the imperative,
I think it is basically
on the other side.
So it's very good because
it's very flexible.
You can add whatever print or
whatever statement in the
middle of the program,
you can do whatever
inspection, debugging.
It's very easy to program
and very easy to debug.
That's why Python is
so popular, right?
But the bacon is
very inefficient,
and it's more difficult to
optimize because the user
can finish the graph,
finish the graph definitely
in the middle and
through it to you and you don't
know what you're going
to do in the future.
Okay. Any concern on this part?
I can clarify. Cool. I
assume you get it, right?
Yeah. Product. I will
talk about that.
Then let's review MCQ.
Which category symbolic versus
imperative is the following PL
programming language
belonging to.
In a sense of what I define
as symbolic and imperative.
First one, C plus plus,
symbolic or imperative.
It's definitely symbolic Because
you cannot write, you
have to compile it.
You need to wait. Python.
Of course, imperative.
It has interpreter.
How about CQ.
Also symbolic, you have
to send a sequel to
the dabs and compile it for
quite a long and then excv it.
As you can see, symbolic
and imperative is actually
a very common thing already
in programming language.
Then I'm going to give you a
very interesting phenomenon.
We know that Python
is imperative
it's defined and run PO,
we also know that tender flow is
defined in run
machinery framework,
indeed, tender flow when
you program tender flow,
you're programming Python.
There's a conflict here.
TensorFlow is
symbolic, but Python
is imperative. So
how did this happen?
Yeah, it's actually
pretty simple.
So you are indeed using Python,
but basically tenser flow will
overwrite all those python
interface you wrote.
It actually give you a DSL
which stands for domain
specific language.
So all the interface you
call from Tinder flow,
they are in Python, but it's
a domain specif language.
It modifies Python a little bit.
That's why in many literatures,
in many many websites, people
usually complain saying
that Petrox is more
Pythonic than tender flow.
They are both python, but
Petros is slightly more python.
Okay. Cool. I hope
you guys get the concept
of symbolic or
imperative, right?
Okay? Then we are going
to do something fun.
We're going to review
what's going on in
the machinery framework history.
Okay. So basically, like I said,
we can classify the machinery
frameworks into
two class, right?
Symbolic and imperative.
We can draw spectrum,
and we put all these
framework here.
Okay? This is basically
the relatively
famous framework we
developed in the past ten years
when this industry starts.
And you can see petrogs on
the left extreme right
frase on the right.
And between Petrogenflow, uh,
there are many many
frameworks developed,
for example, the very
first one cafe, right?
It is actually symbolic.
Uh, there are siano
and Cafe, too.
And there are some
frameworks that basically
motivate Petro for
example, towards China,
and there's a very famous
one called DMLC MXNet,
which was developed by
a few students in US,
but that one is kind of audtd.
And there's one I developed
called Dnites also adated.
Okay? And on this spectrum,
you can see, uh,
different frameworks
have some slightly
different flavors.
So why N MXNet is in the middle.
It actually had two
programming mode.
Yeah, you can switch symbolic
or, like, imperative.
Okay. As time goes,
you know, some frameworks
become outdated, right?
They are not and some frameworks
have a larger community,
so they are being
maintained better.
And this is what happened today.
We roughly just have
three frameworks, okay?
Pero Tinder flow.
And there's one more called Jax.
Okay, also from Google.
And you can think Jack is a
derivative from tender flow.
Okay. It's more lightweight one.
Uh, Tender flow used to be,
in my opinion, masterpiece.
Okay. Next week, we're going
to read Tener flow paper.
Yeah, that's a require already.
Tender flow is definitely
a masterpiece.
It's written by so many like
excellent google engineers.
But unfortunately, uh, you know,
uh, it's not always good
to have a big team.
Yeah. And people
start fighting and
they try to contribute
different components
in Tenner flow,
which result into a lot of
politics in interflow community.
And you can see Tinnerflow
at some point has
so many random features
merged into their Github and,
uh, people start
getting confused,
especially users
getting confused.
Uh, Piers, which is
much much later framework
than tinder flow,
they have a very small and
lean team and they have one
like solitary goal that
is we are going to
build the most
imperative framework.
Okay? They don't trust
tinder flows like roadmap.
They don't trust symbolic.
They just do imperative,
and they do it in the extreme.
And it quickly gains a lot of
popularity from especially
you guys, like students.
And people students
and researchers,
they endorse Petrich a lot and
Petro become more
and more popular.
And at some point,
I think Petrog has
even larger market here than
Center flow today, okay?
And Jack is some framework that,
you know, Center
flow people build.
They hit Center flow, so
they come out and spin off
and build another framework
called Jax which was used,
um, in Google, especially
on TPUs, okay?
And here is basically the trend
or maybe a reflection
of the market share of
tinder floor versus Petroc.
As you can see,
at the beginning,
um, so many people are
built on tender floor.
But uh Petro comes out
and they start eating
the shares eating the
market of tinder flow.
And Today, if you look at
Hugging fins most of the models
are basically Petros. Yeah.
Okay.
Uh, reason that's one
reason that I told
you about why Petrich
wins the market,
even if it was a
later framework.
But I would like you guys
to probably read
some articles from,
do some search and try to think
about this squat yourself, okay?
Why? Why Petro can wins?
Yeah. Because
machining systems, uh,
things change pretty quickly,
um, if you are pretty
good at coding,
you can go create
your own framework.
You have a chance. Yeah.
By study in this case,
you probably can create
the next port which
will win the market
piracy. Yeah.
Okay. Any question?
No, let's continue.
So as I said,
uh, if you know
the difference between
slides, you can see,
actually, uh, if you compare
the programming flavor of
Pitrg and tender flow,
they all move into the
middle a little bit.
Like at the beginning, Petrog
is extremely
imperative framework,
tender flow is a very
symbolic framework.
But as time goes,
more and more features being
incorporated into the framework,
they become like in the middle,
they can do some
sort of symbolic,
some sort of um, imperative.
Yeah, it's very different
from United States
politics, right?
And uh, the reason
is because, uh,
people discovered
a new technique
called just in time compilation.
Okay? So we're going to
cover that a little bit.
So what is just in
time compilation?
So think about this,
ideally, also to
answer your question.
Ideally, we want some
sort of define and run
during during development,
we are not sure.
We are not sure
about our models.
We are not sure about
our algorithms.
We try to do something that
is friendly to debugging, right?
So we want to define and
run during our development.
And once we lock down the model,
we are pretty sure our
algorithm is going to work.
We want something that
is performance, right.
So we want to define then
run using during deployment.
Then what GIT tries to
achieve is basically
we try to combine the
best of both words.
So what do you do is
basically in DV mode,
you still write this
kind of code like
petrogyde you can debug,
you can insert any print.
But once you lock down the code,
what you do is you
can add a uh, today,
I think the most famous
get framework from
Petrot is called
Tochi compile, right?
Uh, you can define a
more other function,
then you decorate interface,
which is called Toyo comple.
What does this Toch
comple do basically?
It will basically twist
down your program.
Okay. It will stop it from
executing immediately.
Okay? It will basically,
try to twist down
your present program
and it will do something
similar to interflow.
Yeah, I convert all
the passing code erode
into something
something I showed in
the first example in
interflow I basically
started not stop avoid
executing it my line,
but it will trace all
the programs and try to
construct the dataflow
graph as a global graph,
then it will optimize it to
the extreme and then
it will execute.
Which Which means
that in this program,
if you don't decorate
the torch dot compiler,
you can add print
statement in the middle.
But once you decorate
it, you cannot.
Okay? Yeah, it will basically
convert that passing
ggramt another program.
Okay.
Yeah, this is a pretty
lazy technique,
and we are going to
have a guest speaker
coming to us to talk about GIT,
because this is one of
the coolest technology
today in Pirch Community, okay?
Then let me ask you a question.
What's the problem with GIT?
Exactly. T can only
jet study graph.
But you can imagine if this
is up in passing code,
it will have a lot of
weird things if else,
four, it basically has a lot
of conditional exclusion,
which means that the toy comple
actually has a lot
of limitations.
If your patent program is
or your Do mode program
is very dynamic,
the JET will not work.
Okay.
Then we are going
to to summarize,
basically, it requires static
graphs, static programs.
Okay. But we do have a
few solutions, okay?
But before I dive
into the solutions,
I want to first introduce
another concept, okay?
I think we have to
spend a lot of time on
introducing symbolic
versus imperative.
Now I'm going to
introduce 21 more thing
that is static versus
dynamic models.
Okay. So what is static
model? What is dynamic model?
So let's first see
how they differ.
Okay. So CNN is a
static model, right?
Why CN is a static model?
Because, so in static
model like CN, right,
uh, we have a few
operators here is
count two pool. Another
count two, right?
We come together, we
compose the dataflow graph.
So the key point here is, um,
whenever what kind of data
you come, you give it to CN.
The middle part, that
is the graph definition
will not change, right?
And the input data X
will have a fixed shape.
It will be, for
example, 20 by 20
or 5,500 by 500 or
something like that.
And output shape
Y will be fixed.
It could be a ten dimension
vector or whatever,
dimension vector you
define at the beginning.
Okay.
But things are different
in many other workloads,
for example, this is semantic
parsing tree from ALP.
Okay. And you can see this is
already probably give
you a sense of dynamics.
That is, for
different sentences,
it has a slightly
different parsing tree.
For this one, John, he's a boll.
Okay.
And when we model this
kind of input sequence,
we want to basically
apply recurring network
to compute over the
tree structure.
So what we end up with is
a neural network looking
like this, right?
We first compute towards
the boll and then we
combine them together,
we incorporate
another word heat,
and then we combine them
together and incorporate
another word too.
But when you are given
a different sequence,
it has a different
semantic parsing tree.
And then you end up with
a different
computational pattern.
And if I ask you
to express the competition
using Data Po graph,
you will end up with two very
different competing graphs.
That means that the
model competition,
they have something same that
is team is the same, right?
But they also have something
that is very different.
The global Datapgraph
will be very
different depending on
the input you give to.
Okay.
Uh, to summarize
the computation,
like, characteristics, for
static data flo graphs, uh,
we basically define wines
and we optimize the ones,
and then for arbitrary
input and output,
we are going to ask
you them, right?
We don't have to touch
that graph again.
It's basically keep as constant.
Okay. But for dynamic offer
was slightly different.
It's very difficult to
express it in dynamics,
because the data
flow graph cometion
the graph structure will
change with the input.
And it's also pretty
difficult to debug in
because if your
program has a bug,
it's probably dependent
with the input.
You have to figure out the
input and see what's going on.
And as a student
already pointed out,
it's almost impossible
to jet dynamic program.
Then we basically lose hope
because literal
language is dynamic.
Why literal language is dynamic.
Because each sentence has a
different number of tokens.
And that means that the
computation you perform,
um, depends on the length
of the input, right?
Okay.
So then, uh, we start
asking the question,
how we can basically
still in some way,
express our dynamic
neuralnetworks,
or dynamic data graph,
in a static in
relatively static way.
So we can still, get
the global graph,
we can optimize that, and
we can get the best
of the performance.
Okay? And that basically marks,
uh, the last part
of this lecture.
So we roughly have three ways.
Okay. The first way is, um,
Forget about that. We
just do define run.
Okay? That's what you do, right?
You never open your program,
until you take this course.
The second way is, we
have a mechanism that
we can introduce
control flow primitives
into data program,
which I will explain next.
And the third way is called
piecewise compilation.
Okay. And I think
you can actually
already infer the
method from this name.
That is, uh, suppose my graph
has some parts that is dynamic.
I'm going to compae
of each part,
and I leave the
dynamic a dynamic, ya.
Okay. Uh for the first one,
I don't think I need
to introduce, right?
So for the second one, so what
does control flow up does?
So here is a very
famous control flows
developed by enter flow team,
and I think this figure
is pretty clear.
It's basically a
switch and merge.
Okay? In a switch,
basically, you have
one single input data
and you want to give
you a condition.
And depending on the condition,
you want to output something,
either left or right.
You want to switch
between two outputs.
Okay? And for the merge
is a reverse operation.
You have two inputs,
and, for example,
you can compare the values and
depending on which one is
larger, you output one value.
Okay. You can actually
program this into
a primitive computation
primitive in the ho graph,
and you insert this kind
of primitive together with
your mass with your matm with
whatever other operations.
And you can basically
kind of absorb
some sort of dynamics from,
for example, your program.
Like for example, if a program
has a merger operation,
then this one will also
be a problem, right?
And here's a more complex case.
So this is the Lumina function
we have from interflow.
What it does is pretty
straightforward.
We have two inputs X and Y,
and we are going to compare
their value and see which
one is smaller, right?
And if X is smaller,
we are going to do a
computation analyst,
we are going to add X with
Z, which is a constant.
And otherwise, we will do
another Lamin equation,
which we will take a square Y.
This is a very dynamic program
already because you are
conditional on something.
So the way that you can
express this kind of
competition is basically you
use what I just introduced.
You use a combination of
switch and some other
mathematical operators.
You start with X and Y,
you compare the values.
And then, uh,
uh in the output of this
comparison operator,
you basically add a
lot a lot of switch,
and you try to switch
between different outputs,
and eventually into two
branches right on left branch,
you basically do the
left competition
on the right branch,
you do the right combination
and eventually you
merge the results.
Okay? So you can
see you can still
express this kind of
dynamic competition
using a few control flows.
Okay. Uh, it turns out that
control flow is actually
a very natural idea in all
programming languages.
So if you write pattern,
you write C plt plus,
there are so many control
flow ups if then if
sh is the control flow ups which
basically tell your program to
loop while the same, right?
But let me ask questions.
What's the potential
problem using
control flow and
dataflow graphs,
especially from
learning programs?
Yeah, yeah, that's
one thing. Yeah.
I don't agree with
them on that because
I think you can
still paralyze it.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's basically
the complexity argument.
Yeah, because you add
up so you can see,
for such a small equation,
you are making such big graph.
One thing that
dataflow graph for
engineering program must do is
basically you need to do
backward propagation.
You need to auto
differentiation.
Then I start asking
your question. What is
the gradient of switch?
What is the gradient of four?
That's a hard question. You
need to think about that.
But it turns out that there
is a gradient for four.
I'm going to give you a reading.
I'm not going to cover
that in lecture.
Yeah. So at some point,
tensor flow team, they
become fascinated with
these cotlow ups.
And these are writing a lot of
papers to discussing how to
drup the gradient for four
for a while and for if and then.
And they even get
the best paper award
from some top conference.
But unfortunately, as
you already pointed out,
this actually very complicated.
You don't how to do
that, and you can
do much simpler ways. Okay.
A much simpler way, which
turns out to be really well
adopted and more adopted than
control flow is basically we
do piecewise compilation.
Okay? Piecewise compilation
is very easy to
understand, okay?
So say, we have a graph which
basically accepting
input shapes of X,
C one, C two, where C one
and C two are constant.
They will lane change.
But X is variable.
Right? So what case
we map to this case?
It's basically literal
language, right.
X is the number of
tokens, and C one,
what basically embedding
dimensions of the token.
So we have a graph we
accept variable number
of input sequences.
So if we want to
compile this program
to compile dataflow graph to
make sure they can work
on X, what do we do?
Yeah, you are pretty close.
Basically, we compile
for X equal to one,
x2x2 all the way
to X equal to the
largest value we can do.
Yeah, that's basically
piecewise compilation.
We just compile all the
possible input dimensions.
And when we accept a sequence,
which is X ex to five,
we basically equal the boundary
that is compiled with
X equal to five.
Straightforward. But we
can do slightly better.
Can someone give me
a better solution?
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, that's
a better solution.
We basically reduce the
number of bonaries we compel,
but we wasting competition,
Because now you only comple
for X, say, equal to 500.
But if you are accepting
a sequence with X one,
you still need to call
that X equal to 500,
which we waste of competition.
Can someone give you
even better solution?
Okay, I'm going to tell
you un we do baketing.
So we can compile the power two.
We compile X to one X two,
then we compile X equal
to four and eight.
And for ab value,
we are going to
map it to the lost
like power or two, right?
That will basically
reduce competition.
Okay? This is already very
complicated and it will
dive into the very deep part
of compson and I'm
going to stop here.
Okay? And we have a guest
already confirmed and he's
the author of a as
probably many of you
already know then is TQ,
author of TVM, okay?
He is basically the guard
of Machining systems
and like the Michael
Jordan to MBAs,
and he's going to come to us and
introduce the compilers,
okay, in deep.
Another use case of um,
piecewise compilation
is basically,
if we have a graph
which is static,
then dynamic and then
static, what do we do?
So we introduce
concept called grad,
and we insert grad at
the end of the first static
and at the beginning
of the second static.
We compare the first we
compile the first
static into a binary.
We ask you to get
results, right?
And then we fed the results
into a dynamic part
and let it run using
pure pison then we
get the results
and comp unfed the
results to a second part,
which is static and we
also compile that part.
This is another way that
you understand
piecewise compilation.
Okay. Cool. Um, I
think I finished most
of the contents. Okay?
Now, let's basically
review a little bit.
We know how to represent
the mass primitives.
We summarize the four
most important models.
That will be our targets,
mostly math more.
And we haven't studied
how to represent data,
which we'll cover soon.
But basically tensors, okay.
We also already developed
representation that
expressed computation using
primitives, but we're
not finished yet.
Why?
Because by far, we only
covered forward
competition, right?
And in the next lecture,
we are going to tell you how to
derive the backward
competition from the forward.
That is basically the auto diff.
Okay? That's pretty much
I have today. Thank you.
A