Okay, yeah. Let's get started.
Cool, cool. Thanks for coming.
And we are going to continue
to talk about some basics.
Okay. Before that, I want to
give some update on enrollment.
So I think a few students drop.
So we have 60 more seats.
I'm going to work with CSE
to enroll the next
bachelor students.
Then on Thursday,
probably after lecture,
I'm going to work
with CSE again.
I believe at that time after
some students homework,
they are going to
drop the scores,
so there will be more seats.
Which also means that Thursday
likely we'll have our
homework one ready.
Yeah. Okay, let's get started
with the content today.
So so still remember what
we learned last week,
right? Three things, right?
The first one is we took a very,
very fast review of
machine learning,
especially today's
machine learning.
We summarize our workload as
Metham plus softmax plus
a few other operators,
right, from the computational
perspective, okay?
And we start defining the
computational graphs,
um, still remember
the definitions of
nodes and edges, right?
So nodes represent the
computational operators
and its a potential,
and edges are basically
the data flowing
directions and dependency.
And then we start talking about
the programming flavors of
especially TenerfornPatrig,
and we find that they
are quite different.
One is symbolic, the
other is imperative.
We start talking about
static and dynamic, right?
And we also talk
about the latest
technique which is called
JIT just in time
compilation and how
they can basically solve
this problem a little bit.
Okay. Let's do some
MCQ. Very easy.
So you are machine
learning engineer at
a company that is
providing points to users,
your goal is running
efficient inference
for these Ms. For example,
you are open A and you are given
a framework which has both
symbolic and impervid API,
which is true for both
Interf and Petrox today.
While designing your system,
I'm going to give
you four options.
Take a look at that. Which one?
Which one? B, right?
Pretty simple, yeah,
because you want something
that's easier to
debug at development.
And once you figure
out your program,
you basically deploy it using
the most high performance one.
Okay? Second one.
Which of the following is not
true about dataflow graphs,
take a look at AB and C
and D.
Which one?
C, right? So static data.
Data flow graph means
that it's static.
So you just define
once and it will
run forever for bitter data.
And given static data graph,
batching is natural, you
just throw batches into
the graph and it will run.
Because the shape is static.
For D is obvious.
Define run is a possible way
to handle dynamic
data for graphs,
because you don't care
about performance.
So let's see. Okay.
Pretty easy, right?
This is basically
the level of difficulty
in final exam.
Okay. Yeah, let's go back
to the main contents today.
So I think last lecture,
we talk about representation
that express the computation
using primitives,
and that repent is
basically data flow graph.
And we also talk
about how to define dataflow
graph at the forward
path, right?
But we are doing
deep learning, we
are not going to be ending there
because we care about backward
graph back propagation, right?
We want to optimize
the model weights.
So in this talk, we are going to
talk about we're going to start
with how to basically define
the backward competition
using data flow graphs.
And this learning goal, we
first talk about auto
differentiation.
And once you understand that,
I can start presenting you
basically the grand problem
of machine learning systems.
What do we try to optimize?
And if time permits,
we're going to talk
about a little
bit lower level things, okay?
So, auto differentiation, right?
So what do we do when we do auto
We basically take
graditsT derivatives.
Okay? So I hope you still
remember your undergrad course,
how to take derivatives.
So given F Theta,
what is partial F by Pi Theta?
So we can take it by definition,
which is basically
this limit, right?
So we find a very small epson
and we try to derive the limit.
And this is doable
in computer program.
What do we do is
basically we evaluate
the function value F at
Theta and Theta plus Epson,
and then we just
follow this right.
As long as apsnon is very small,
we can actually
approximate the grading,
right, the partial derivative.
But what is the problem here?
Why DplingFramwork
does not use this one?
Okay, the first problem
is, it's very slow, right?
Because every time we need
to evaluate two values to
get one gradient, one
derivative, okay?
Second problem is, this one
is not accurate because
it's it's basically we
are approximating the
grading values, right?
And we are basically take
small enough apsion
to approximate that.
You know, computer has a lot of
floating point arrows,
and if you do this way,
that floting point arrow
will propagate all the way
through neural
network and we are
not going to get
accurate gradient.
So in reality, we don't do this.
What we do is basically we
do symbolic differentiation,
and we basically applied
what we learned from
the calculus class and
we try to derive
the gradient or
partial derivative
using these derivative
rules, right?
I hope you still remember.
If you don't take a look,
okay, try to remind
yourself, okay.
And we are going to walk
through a very simple example.
So here we have a very
small commutation,
or you can also think this
as neural network, right?
Were we have two
inputs X one, X two,
and going through
some computation
which I defined
here, pretty simple.
And following what we
taught in the last lecture,
we basically write visualize
it as commutation graph.
And we also instantiate
the values for x1x2.
So you can see, following
the competon we can
actually derive
the value of the
outcome, which is Y.
And our goal is we try to
calculate the value of
partial Y by partial X one.
For example, we want
to take the derivative
against X one.
That's what we normally do
in neur twork training.
So we basically follow
partial derivative rules,
and also chain rules and
um and in this regard,
we actually have two ways.
So which I list here, one
is the forward way
that is we can,
if you look at the
function on the left side,
so you can take the derivative
from left to right, right?
And you can calculate step
by step from X,
all the way to Y,
that is from the inner of
the function to the outer
part of the function.
Or you can do something that is
taught in machine learning class
that is back propagation.
You do from right
to left, right?
You take the derivative
Y against the
V six and the V five and
then all the way back
propagate through,
um, X one and X two.
You can always get a results.
We are going to reason a little
bit on these two modes, okay,
because there are a lot
of softwares basically
implementing two
different kinds of modes.
Okay, we call the first mode,
forward mode, auto
differentiation or forward ED.
The second mode,
backward ED, okay?
So let's first run
through forward mode.
Okay. The way we do
forward mode is basically,
we are going to
define this VI dot.
The dot is basically defined as
the partial derivative
of VI against XI.
So that is the IS node in
the graph against the input.
Okay? So what do
we do is we are going
to our goal is try to
derive the value of partial
Yi partial X one, right?
So what do we do
is we are going to
start with from X
one all the way
to Y and we try to figure out
how we can get that value.
So it's pretty simple, right?
So by definition, uh,
we one dot is basically one,
right, because we one
is equal to X one.
Right, so the dervative
is basically one.
And we just do it all the way,
following the graph
from left to right,
and eventually we are going
to reach we seven dot,
which is basically, uh, 5.5.
Okay? I'm not going to dive
deep into the calculation,
but I think this one is
very straightforward.
You just do it step by step.
Okay, function my faction. Okay.
Any question? Cool. And finally,
we can write the answer,
which is a partial Y by
partial X one is equal to 5.5,
which is equal to the
value of V seven dot.
Okay. And from this process,
you can see, um, uh,
the characteristics of
forward forward mode 80,
basically, we start
from the input node
right here is X one or X two.
And we derive the
gradient all the
way to the opt nodes, here is Y.
So what is the pros and
cons of forward auto diff?
Maybe let me ask you a question.
So does petrous use this one?
No, right? Yeah, there
must be something
that happening that,
you know, prevent
Petro from using that.
So let's read it a little bit.
So in for more alternative,
the problem is we are usually
solving this function F,
from N dimensional space input
to a k dimensional space output.
And in order to
derive the partial Y
against input X or X or X N,
we basically need to run
one forward pass to get
the gradient with respect
to one input, right?
So if we have many many
inputs, then we need to.
So for example, here,
if N is pretty large,
then we need to run
in forward pass
to get the gradients against
every X I from one to
n. In deep learning,
uh, this is the case.
Basically in deep learning,
in many mansing problems,
we have a high dimensional
input, For example,
we have a lot of parameters,
we want to derive the gradient
against each parameter.
Like in GB three is 175 billion.
But we only had one output
that loss loss value.
For example, next token
predicting loss or
classification loss.
So if we apply
this forward mode,
80 into deplening
then it's very,
very inefficient
because we need to dp
gradients for each input
that is a parameter,
and we need to run as
many times as the
number of parameters.
Okay? That's why forward 80 is
actually not very
useful for deperning.
Okay. But it's very
easy to think about,
yeah, because you
just go through
the computing graph
from left to right.
You don't need a backward pass.
Okay. So that
basically brings us
to the reverse mode 80 or
backward mode 80, okay?
Here, I'm going to, uh,
spend some time to run
through this graph again,
but we are going to apply
the reverse mode ED, okay?
So in order to run
this real mode ED, uh,
apparently different
from the foreign mode,
we are going to run from Y
all the way back to XR x two.
Okay? And in order to run that,
we are going to bring a new
definition that is joint.
Okay? Here I define the V
bar equals to partial Y.
By partial I, that is
the partial derivative
of the output
Y against the current
node I. Yeah,
I is basically the index node.
We are going to
basically compute
each I bar in the reverse,
sorry, reverse not reverse
reverse topological order of
the graph, from Y
all the way back.
So here's the commutation.
We are going to run a
few equations, and then,
um, probably you can take
more time to
understand the rest.
So for the first one, uh,
seven bar is basically
like we are teaching partial
derivative of we are
taking partial derivative of
partial Y against
partial seven, right?
Because Y basically
equals to with seven,
so the value is one,
right, identity function.
And then we run to the
second equation, which is,
partial, sorry, with six bar.
And I hope you still
remember chain rule, right?
So when we take the partial
partial Y against with six,
we basically change the
gradient of partial Y
against seven and the
partial derivative
of V seven against six, right?
We tie them together, yeah.
And we basically get six bar.
And we do this one by one
using the chain room,
which you learned in the
neuralnetwork class,
and we can basically run
all the way back to X one,
and we basically can get the
value of 1 bar and two bar,
which is there, and you can
see the value is also 5.5,
which is equal to the form.
Okay. Um, here, there's
a little bit one more thing
I need to mention that is,
you can see for week
three and we two,
when we take the when we
calculate the value of
W three by and we 2 bars
a little bit more difficult
complicated here.
That is, we have
this kind of like
a graph structure, right?
Here, we one basically
contributes to both
we two and with.
And we four has two inputs.
That is wet and W. So do you
still remember how to derive
the gradients of this
kind of like structure?
So it takes we want two paths
to reach the outcome of Y.
So how do take the grading.
It's pretty simple, right? So
basically t is done, right?
So we want byte basically equal
to partial Y by partial V one,
and we basically
enroll the function
Y. Enroll Y as a function
of we two and we.
And we also find we we
are function over W one.
So we just use partial
derivative rules
and write it all the way.
So we basically get the
equation that is throw bar
times the partial derivative we
two against and the second term.
Okay? That's what happened here.
What happened here in
these two equations.
Okay. Okay. This is
just a warm up, okay?
I hope you'll still
remember all this.
Okay? This is basically
basic calculus, right?
So if we generalize
a little bit,
we can basically derive
this statement that is for
node in the data flow graph,
right for we one used
by multiple consumers,
we can basically calculate
this at joint Wi bar equals to
so basically the sum of all
the all its consumers, right?
And here, we define another term
which is Wii two J bar, okay?
Where I two G bar
is basically WJ bar
times the partial derivative
Wig against one. Okay?
This is like,
basically bifurcation.
Any question? Cool. We are good,
right? Pretty simple math.
Okay. Then now, you basically,
understand both forward mode
80 and backward mode 80.
And we are going to summarize
a little bit about
backward mode 80, okay?
So in backward mode 80,
compensation workflow
is basically
start from output nodes, right?
And we derive the grading
all the way back to
the input nodes,
which is a reverse
order or for mode 80.
So what is the pros and
cons of backward mode 80,
sorry, this is backward mode.
So basically the pros of, uh,
forward mode, it is the cons
of the backward mode 80, right?
Because here, still,
we have a function
of wishing maps from
N dimensional space
to a key dimensional space.
And if we want to
take gradients,
uh, using the backward mode,
we basically need
the backward pass to
get gradient with respect
to all the inputs.
Okay. But like I said,
why this one is
adopted in deploying?
Because in deploying
K is pretty small.
N is pretty high, right?
Pretty large. Okay.
That's why backward mode, AD is,
um, uh, basically the default,
uh, a differentiate rules that
we use in deploying libraries
in merging systems.
Okay. But remember that
in other areas where we
have a pretty large K,
but a small, we can still
go back to use four mode.
For example,
in many many scientific
computing scenarios, yeah,
where we don't we have
low dimensional input,
but high dimis output.
Yeah. Okay. Then back
to our question.
Now, you understand the
underlying mechanisms of ED.
But remember, our mission
is we try to use ED to
derive dataflow
graphs because we
want something that can represent
the competition, right?
ED helps us to get
the gradients,
but we want to write
ED into the graph.
Okay. So how can we construct
a competition graph that
calculates the gradients?
We know that gradients
can be calculated
from the adjoint values.
So essentially how we can,
uh define computer graph
that calculate the
adjoin values, right?
Okay? I'm going to
give you the answer.
I'm going to run
through this algorithm.
Basically, all the different
libraries they basically
use this algorithm.
This is algorithm that
basically calculate
the gradients using
backward mode 80.
I'm going to run through
this algorithm a
little bit okay?
The way I rest, I'm going
to give you an
example commutation,
um and the commutation
is basically very
simple function F,
which will take one input,
take exponential plus one as in
times u itself and
get the output.
But before we run
the uh algorithm on
this dataflow graph,
what do we do I try to give you
a high level picture of
what's going on in
that algorithm.
Okay. Let's read
it line by line.
So basically, we
want to take the
gradients of a
specific node, right?
So we are going to maintain
all partial joints of a node.
Because once we have a list of
partial aljoints can
sum them together,
we get the gradient
value, right?
That's what I defined
in my previous slide.
So this organ will basically
try to opt the values
for all the partial
adjoints for each node.
The way you get the
values basically first,
it traverse the graph
following a reverse
topological order
that is defined by backward mode
80 right because we have
to traverse in that way.
And what we do is, uh, we first,
sum all the partial
algoin of that node
together in order to get
its partial duptive.
Does that make sense? That
is by definition, okay?
And then once we have the
partial derivative of this node,
what do we do is we are going
to look at is input node.
That is, that is,
all the nodes that
contribute to this one node.
Okay? Have incoming edge on
the ph graph to this node.
And we are going to compute
the partial adjoint, okay?
Here is for any input K,
we compute B, K to I bar,
which is by definition
this equation, right?
Okay. And then we are going to
update this value
into that node,
which is with index of K, right?
That is next time we
traverse the graph following
the rewards order,
we are going to visit
this K, right here.
We are going to get it
basically partial duptive.
Okay? And you can
see this program is
basically recursive,
right, because it will go
through all the way
back to the IR node.
It traverse or the node,
and basically it will
return the value of this.
That's what we
want. Right. Okay.
Any question about
this program. Okay.
Let's run through this. I think
I already explained this.
This one is basically sum up
all the partial joints to
get the gradient or partial
dtiveT one is compute and
propagates the partiality
joints to its inputs.
Let's run through this, okay.
So given this graph,
we are going to follow the
rewards topological order,
we are going to start from
W four, which is the last node.
And here, I equals to four,
which I take note here.
And we are going to basically,
uh, run this line, right?
And we find that for
the open node, uh,
we four it only has one partial
aloin which is one equal
to one because it's identity
function, nothing special.
So we basically
something together,
uh, and we find that the
value is basically one.
And now I want to represent
this in my graph.
So I basically choose
a more convenient method that is
directly assign value one,
right to a node
called wifour bar.
And this function is
basically identity.
Okay. And we finish
this line, right?
And the next step
is basically we go
into that inner loop.
Okay, we are going to
check all the nodes that
basically contribute values into
WFO and we try to derive
this partial adjoint.
Okay. Uh, here we are going
to inspect two things, right?
One is the pair W
two to wafer because
WIR is a function of two and
the second is wi wi four.
Okay. Um, meanwhile,
we are going to basically,
uh, document this.
We are going to record this
last note grad, right.
And here, um, you can see,
when K equals to,
so here I equals to four and
we already have W four bar,
and we are going to start
from the list inputs I
and we know that input I
basically equals to either
wet or with three, right?
So we are going to start
from K equals to two, right?
And we are going to run
this program, okay?
So we 224 bar equals
W four bar times partial we
four by partial W two, right?
And we already have the value
of w four bar, which is here.
We assigned a value
equal to one.
And we are going to write
down this value with 24 bar,
and how to represent
as dataflow graph.
We find that the partial
four by partial W two is
basically equal to equal
to with three, right?
Because here, you can see,
we four equals to wei
two times with three.
So if you take the
partial derivative,
basically our value
is with three, right?
So in order to represent
this way two to four bar,
we construct a graph in a way
that we connect this
with three node and
W four bar and the operator
basically is multiplier, right?
So we basically get the
repetition of wei 224 bar.
Okay. Any question? So remember,
our goal is we try to
represent everything in graph.
Yeah, because once
we have that graph,
we can represent both
forward and backward.
Okay. And same thing,
right, we can run.
We finish the K equal to two,
then we move forward to
the next node with three,
right, which is another
contributor to Wi four.
And same thing, we
basically apply that rule.
So with three to four
bar equals to wei
four times partial four
by partial with three.
And partial wi four
partial three is
basically equal to W two,
right, because it's multiply.
We take a directive
against multiplier,
and so the value is w
four part times W two.
That's why we basically add
an multiplier here, right?
So we multiply with
four part and W two,
and we get with bar.
Uh, actually, we
didn't get with bar.
We get with three to four part,
but we found that with three
only has, uh, one input.
The other input is constant.
So basically these two
values are the same, right?
Right. So for the
simplicity, we basically,
uh, uh, create another
node which is with bar,
and we put it here.
Okay? Still follow, right?
Cool. That means that
this loop finish the
first iteration,
we finish with I
equals to with four,
and then we proceed. Okay?
And meanwhile, remember,
we are going to
document all the partial
adjoint here for each node.
Okay. And then we continue run
this and we go back to with
three because we are using a
reverse topological order.
So we go back to with three.
And what we do is basically
we find that with three
is already done right because we
three only has one
partial adjoint,
so we just sum them
together, which is here.
Okay. And then we go into
this inner loop and we
inspect how many nodes,
uh, contribute to with three,
and we find that there's
only cakes to two,
we two, right?
Uh, so we basically take
we basically try to calculate
the wei two to three bar,
uh, and following the equation,
we get with three bar times
partial by partial way,
two, and we get this value
is basically with
bar itself, right?
So, yeah.
And we continue following
the reverse topic order,
and we get back to W two.
Okay? In this example,
we found we two is actually
a expensive function of
the input that we one.
Okay? So here, we first
follow this equation,
we found that we two
has two partial joint.
So we sum them together, right.
And here we sum them together.
And these two partial
joints basically we two,
two, four bar and
we 223 bar, right?
Following the data photograph,
we basically add two edges
and sum them together,
and we results into
we two bar, okay?
And then we run into
the inner loop,
and when cake to one,
we try to calculate
we want to burn.
Following equation, we get
this uh basically this result.
In order to represent
this into Dataflograph,
what we do is we are going
to connect this node.
And the value of
exponential one.
And we find that the
exponential value
of one is essentially way two.
So we add another edge
all the way here,
and that gives us uh we 122 bar.
And we also find out one
does not have any input.
So we 12 bar basically
equals to 1 bar.
So we basically simplify
the graph a little
bit and create another
node to 1 bar here.
Okay. That's basically how we
run this algorithm
through data pho graph.
And as we run through,
forward data photograph,
we also create
another graph that connected
to the photograph.
That is our backward graph,
which is the red
part of this graph.
Okay. Any question? Okay, cool.
If you have any trouble
following any part of this,
uh, go back and take
a look at this slide.
I think it's pretty
clear. Just think
a little bit and
it we figure out.
Okay. So in summary, uh,
during this process, what
we do is basically we
construct the backward
graph in a symbolic way.
Um, we don't actually
calculate the values, right?
And the reason is
because we really,
really want this graph because
like in neural network,
we are going to give
different kind of
data and the data
will run risk graph.
And we cannot just do
one time competition
because this competon should be
applied to all different
kind of databtches.
So given this graph,
we can basically, uh,
whatever input it comes,
we are going to derive following
the competon defining
graph, it can be reused.
And this one is commonly
used in tf patric.
Okay. Now let's do reasoning
reason a little bit,
okay on the trade offs.
So So in a typical
machine learning class,
I think the teacher
will tell you,
we'll teach you like bipagon.
And remember B
propagation, basically,
you take that left figure and
you run a backward pass through.
But in this class, we are
actually not doing backprogion.
We are doing reverse
mode allots different.
Why? Because in set,
we are going to construct a
backward graph and we connect
the backward graph to
the photograph and we
get even bigger graph.
And in the initial set
of machine learning frameworks
design like ten years ago,
they are actually
using that mode.
So basically in the system,
they are using back propagation.
So they never construct
a backward graph.
They just take the
photograph and
take the gradients and
propagated gradients.
But in the modern
dpling frameworks,
we are using this graph
approach, that is,
we construct the backward graph,
and it has been
used by basically
every framework to prog.
So my question is why this
one become more popular.
Like, why do we care about
getting a Brograph? Yeah.
Information Exactly.
That's one primary reason,
because if you only
have photograph,
then your system will only read
the phograph and you can
optimize over representation.
But if you also have
a background graph,
your system can my system
does not care about
for backward.
I only have one perspective
that I'm given a
computing graph.
I'm going to optimize
other graph, right?
So we basically want a holistic
representation of
the competition.
Any other reason?
Exactly.
It's very amenable.
So for example, you
probably know that
today's marginy
model can be very complicated.
Sometimes you need to take
the gradient of the gradient.
If you do that mode,
how to take the gradient
or gradients very
difficult because the gradient
is hidden somewhere
in the graph.
But in the right
side of the graph,
you see the gradient
is explicitly
represented in the graph
and what do you do?
If your competition needs to
care calculate the
gradient or gradient,
you just add more
nodes on top of that,
the Autolibrary
will basically help
you derive the gradients
following the competition.
Okay. So in other words,
this graph it represents
the holistic basically, uh,
like representation
of the competition,
and it's very
friendly to systems
because system does not
care about semantics
opportunity layer.
I only care about competition.
Okay? Uh a third
reason which I'm
going to talk about in
detail is because we are still
missing some piece here.
So what is missing if we want
to complete the deep
learning program?
We hold forward,
we held backward.
Yeah, we need a grading update.
If you do this approach, then
your grading update rule
is going to be isolated.
You are going to
write your own optim.
But if you do this mode,
what you do is you
can continue adding
one and more nodes that
represent the grading update.
In the later lectures,
especially in the arm sessions,
we'll find that grading
updates is one of
the most memory
consuming operations,
and we are going to optimize it.
And if we have a graph
repton for that part,
then it's pretty easy for
the system to look at that.
Okay. Now, let's try to
finish this part, okay.
We are going to put
this into practice.
Sorry. We are going to go
back to our mass equations
and we are going to instiate
this master equation
using a few models.
That is a simple
regression model,
two layer neural network.
We have two ways W one,
W two, one input X.
Uh, this will go through
a nonlinear function,
and then the value
will be compared to
the ground Y using
mean square loss.
And in order to represent this
two layer neural network,
what we do is
basically, by the way,
we also have a grading
update rules here.
That is every time
we fit the bat,
we are going to get gradients
and we are going to follow
this rule to update the
updated parameters.
And in order to represent
this as a neural network,
we essentially have three parts,
and you need to remember this.
Every time we try to
represent the new
net recommendation,
you don't need photograph.
We have three parts.
The first part is forward,
right? We define photograph.
And then we take the auto
differentiation library
to basically automatically
derive the backward pass,
which I already ran through,
in the previous slides.
And that part, you
don't have to do that
because Pat will
do that for you.
And the third part
as I mentioned,
you need to perform
with the update.
Now I'm going to we're going to
put all this together
into one graph.
So for forward, uh,
uh, same definition,
nodes represent the operator
and it's a potential,
and the edges represent the
data flowing directions.
For forward is pretty
straightforward.
We have X and W one.
They go to Melmo and all
the way to the MSE loss.
And then you give it to Petrog
and the petrog we are
going to derve the
backward following what
I just uh went through.
Okay. And the critical part
is we also need to add
the optim meter operator.
So how to add op meters.
That is what we
basically find out
the op meter update rules
and we connect some nodes,
right? We update parameters.
Okay? Uh, very simple.
Basically, in the
right hand side,
you basically see a full graph
that represent this new network.
And this can go arbitrary
complex, right?
Remember, in reality,
this is a neural network
with thousands of nodes
with forward,
backward and updates.
So this graph could
be maintained
by a system at a lower level.
Yeah. Okay, as a homework,
we are going to implement
this auto different library
with a few operators
I give it to you.
And one operator is
basically softmax,
and this is a very
interesting operator.
I think it's greeting is
a very uh elegant form,
and you are going to do this.
Okay. Cool. That basically
covers auto differentiation.
Any question?
Okay, once you understand
all the differentiation,
I think it's the right time to
introduce the
architecture overview
of machine learning systems.
So what people are cooking here.
So as I said, no,
I give you a neural network,
you are going to represent as
a data flow graph like that?
Pretty nice animation
from tensor flow.
It has input nodes, I have data
flowing through that graph.
For that graph, it also
represents both forward,
backward, and we update.
So what is our system go here?
So our system is
pretty simple, right.
We try to make this very fast,
because we want to optiment
the system to achieve
the best performance.
So our system go here
is basically we try to
make it fast so it
can run super fast.
Secondly, we try to
make it scale, right?
Because sometimes you cannot
run the scrap on a single GPU,
so you need to scale this
to many many GPUs to
make it even faster.
We want to make sure it's
memory efficient because
you already know
that GPU memory is
very scare resources in
order to treat models
like GPD three,
you have to basically
optimize your system
to use the memory as
efficient as possible.
And sometimes we want to
run on diverse hardware,
GPU CPU, iPhone or whatever.
Yeah. Okay. We try to
make sure this graph
can run across different
platforms, okay?
And we don't want to
consume a lot of energy,
because we have to pay
for the electricity,
of course, you
already know this.
We try to make sure that
users feel very easy to
program or debug this neur
network dataflow graph. Okay?
That is basically a spectrum
of problems that merchant
learning system people
are trying to solve.
Okay? That is given a graph,
given some hardware, you
try to achieve these goals.
I'm going to give you an
overview and it's a very,
very simplified overview
of how people realize
this in the existing machine
learning frameworks like
Petro and interflow.
Um, maybe frameworks
can be different,
but basically, my overview
will apply to all
these frameworks.
So in the future, uh,
maybe when you start
working on something,
you can try to map
some code written in
your framework into
these layers and think
about what their
functionality are, right?
So at the higher layer,
maybe start from there.
We have a data ph
graph, right, and
we have a cluster of GPUs.
Okay? And at the higher layer,
we already know that
we are going to
represent the neuralnetwork
as the data flow graph.
And there are some auto
differentiation libraries
that will basically
take your photograph,
drupe the backward and connect
them together to
represent with updates.
These two parts we
already covered.
Okay. And this is
only the higher layer
of machining systems.
In order to make it fast, uh,
the system people actually build
a lot layers behind this.
So what they do is they will do
a so called graph
augmentation layer.
So what is graph opening?
I will give you a
overview pretty soon.
But you can understand
that that graph,
which is written by the
user may be inefficient.
Then the system will take
that graph and try to
analyze it a little bit to make
it more efficient version.
And this can be done using
many existing graph theory
or whatever kind of
graph transformation.
Yeah. Basically, I try to
derive a graph that is
equivalent with
the initial graph,
but the second one will
be the new one will be
much more efficient.
That is a layer we call
graph augmentation.
Okay? And in petrogentener flow,
there are so many codes that is
basically doing
graph augmentation.
And after Graph organization,
what we try to do is we
can optionally have
a parledtion layer.
That is we try to distribute
this graph on many GPOs.
But I said this layer
is optional because if
your graph is fine on
a single GPO, then you
don't care about this.
That means that
this code pass is
not going to be able
to activate it.
But in many cases,
in today's case,
I don't think a GPU can
actually train a model
in reasonable amount of time,
so you have to do this.
You're going to take this graph
and going to distribute
this graph over
many many devices and
make sure the results
are still correct.
Okay? And then we also
care about the run time.
That is once it runs,
how many memory consume,
how it should run.
There are so many
operators, right.
There's a left branch,
there's a right branch.
How should I schedule
each branch?
Should one branch
run ahead of time,
or should delay the schon
one branch over the other.
And this matters because it can
basically affect your
efficiency, yeah.
And we're going to talk
about this as well.
And finally, at the
Louis layer, remember,
these graphs are
constructed by a lot of
primitives and the
primitives could
be Mm, softmax and whatever.
Eventually, if you want
to run this graph,
you need to run
those primitives.
That means that you
have to provide
a library of primitives that can
run on different kind of
devices like GPU CPU, whatever.
Lower layer, we basically have
operator library where we
implement the implementation,
the exact we call kernels
of these operators,
primitives on those
target devices.
This is a pretty low level code,
and we are also going
to touch base on that.
This basically gives you
an overview of what's going
on in terms of flow and impacts.
Uh, it is simply not working.
But if you go to
TenderfowKolbs or Patrick
obises you'll find there are
much more layers than this.
But basically, you can condense
several layers
into one of these.
Okay? Any question?
Cool. Okay, let me give
you overview basically what
each layer is cooking.
So basically, if you want
to do research in this,
you can actually choose a layer
that is most interesting.
And I can tell you each
layer actually has
already more than 1,000
papers published.
Discussing how to do openation.
Yeah.
Okay. The first layer,
graph openation as already said,
the goal is basically rewrite
the original graph G,
defined by users into
another graph, which
is called G prime.
And my goal is G prime will
run much faster than G. Okay?
You probably are wondering
why this could happen.
I'm going to give you an example
and look at the left
piece of graph, right?
So can you guess
where is this from?
Apparently, there's
a count to D,
so it must from
convolutional network.
And to be more precise,
is from resent. Okay.
And in restaurant, you
basically have input X.
You have to wait W and B.
You first apply a
count two, right?
And once you get the output,
you are going to
get the output Y,
and you have another
two parameters R and P,
and you run a bachelor and
you get the second O Z.
And to simplify a little bit,
we can basically represent
the commutation there, right?
So the first layer is
basically count two,
which is some loops
and sums, right?
And then plus bias B.
And the second layer
is basically take
the output of the first layer
of Y and do something else.
Okay? This is a simplified
version of this graph.
And one way we can
make this faster is
we don't run this
graph, but we do this.
We find that we can actually
enroll this computation
a little bit,
we try to define some other
ways called W two and B two,
where the definition of
W and B two is there.
What do we do oicly we
perform some
computation ahead of
time, on the graph level.
We define W two as the
original width W times
the R which is the weight
of the batm and
similarly for B two.
And then we don't
have to run batom.
Right, we field all
the computation
into one operator
with count two,
but we behind the scene
we basically switch the
weight from W B into w2b.
And it turns out that
the second graph
runs much faster than
the first one, right?
Because it's quite obvious
because you alwayd running
one more operator, ok?
Um, and we can do it
more aggressively.
The way we do it is we
are going to look at
the holistic repetition
of the dataflow graph.
We are going to look for
every opportunity that
we can put C D and
Bachelom together.
In this one, I'm
going to give you a
very extreme example.
Here we have input. We are
going through two convolution,
which is one by one convolution,
then we go through C
three by three and then
add the results together and
go through value and
get the results.
And here, apparently, this one
by one and three by three,
their filter size are different.
One is three by three,
the other one by one.
So it's not very
easy to put them together
into one operator.
So what do we do is we are going
to enlarge this one by one
into a three by three.
We can do that, right,
mathematically equivalent,
you can do that,
but the problem is through
enlarging operation,
this operator
apparently will become
slower because previously we
only calculate one by one,
but now we calculate
three by three. Okay.
Remember, this step
becomes lower.
But the benefit is
now this one by one
becomes equivalent at least
on shape with three batter.
We can write the
mathematical equation
together and we can fill
them into 13 battery.
Okay. And this step is going to
be slightly faster, right?
So we become slower
and then faster.
And we continue doing this.
So here, you can see, uh,
we are going to fill this
split come and add all
together into a more
complete sstry.
And if you compare this
graph and this graph,
you'll find that we reduce
the number of nodes from
this graph to this graph.
Like this graph only
have two nodes,
but this graph has
so many nodes.
And we can continue to
fill and eventually
we fill the autograph into
into one, only two nodes.
Okay. You can see,
this is pretty
interesting because we
first make the graph slower
and then we make it faster.
And if you evalue
the vital graph,
you'll find as as
the vital graph is faster
than the first
graph, we are good.
Okay? This is basically
what we do for
graph augmentation.
And given that our graph has
thousands of nodes and there
are so many different operators,
you can imagine there are
so many opportunities
that we can do this kind
of augmentation, right?
And that's what people
do in this layer.
Okay. Um, I think in
the initial lecture,
especially in last week's
lecture, some people,
some students ask me why
fusing can be faster
than the original graph?
Let's do a deep dive.
But before that,
let's look at a more
realistic example.
This is familiar.
This is attention transformers
attention, right?
And if you still
remember in attention,
what we do is we are going
to play with meto that
is we have weight for
QK w and we have input,
which is the edge hidden vector,
and we are going to me met
mood them together
together the capital QQ,
then we are going to
perform attention.
But if you go into any
transformer library you
will find that they don't write
mathematical or
programs in this way.
They are going to write
in this way, that is, uh,
they are going to merge the
QQw and then they directly
calculate the QQv in one output
which is called QQvO
thing variable.
Apparently this is fusion.
We are basically, reducing
the graph size by
fusing some operators.
Okay then back to the question.
Why this could be
faster? What is
the fundamental mechanism
that makes this faster?
So remember that in computing,
we care about
arismtic intensity,
which is denoted as AI,
another AI,
arithmetic intensity,
this is defined as the lumber
mathematical operations,
uh, like compute operations,
divided by, uh, the
lumber memory access,
like how many bits you
are going to rate from
your memory or whatever
kind of storage.
Okay? And the higher this value,
then that means you can
utilize your computer
hardware better,
and that will translate
into faster competition.
Okay. Uh, the reason that
this fusion works because if
you look at this example,
what we do is basically we
have to array flowing
point rage A and B.
We try to add their values
and throw the value into
C. And this is a
very simple example,
but it helps us understand
AI, okay, original intensity.
So the way we do that
is we rate loop, right?
We look through the rays and
we write the result into
C. And we can estimate
the resin intensity.
So in this process, we
first read AI right.
This is one ad, then we read
BI and we add them together.
This is a computer operation.
And then once we
have the results,
we throw the result into C. So
how many like a computer and
how many read and write.
So one computer, right,
and three ran rate.
So the AI is essentially,
um, one divide by three,
right? Okay, one by three.
Same thing if we
continue doing this,
we make more
complicated algorithm
and written in this way.
That is, we try to add all
the results together and
store result in E. Uh,
sorry, we try to add A and B
and T C and plus D and throw
result in E. And what we
do is basically we
first add A and B,
strew results in temp.
Then we follow this order and
continue to compute until
we get the final
results we want.
And so what is the
AI of this program?
It's also one by three, right,
because this line is one by
three. This line
is one by three.
And this mall is
also one by three
because we read temp one,
C and write results
into temp two.
And this one is
also one by three.
So in total, it's
still one by three.
Okay. Okay. But if we
slightly write this program in
a more efficient way that
is we can get this program.
Instead of I calculate
the results step by step.
I basically calculate
in a long equation.
I'm going to read A, B, C,
and D. I directly perform
some competition altogether,
and then I throw it out into E,
what is the AI over this one?
So we can see there's one rate.
There's one rate, right, read A,
second road B, third,
first rod D and
the fifth write E.
So the IO is basically five.
And the computer is
there's one plus,
one plus, and one multiplier.
So the computer is.
So the AI is essentially
three by five.
And we can see this is
basically opera fusion right.
Because if you map this
program into computer graph,
this one only have one node
that basically connect
everything together.
But this one has
so many nodes that
will write and read results.
So if you do this
kind of o fusion,
you will find out your
AI is much higher.
That's why we really want
fuse as much as possible.
Okay? And we're
going to go back to
this in probably
two lectures away,
and we are going to talk
about how we can find
these opportunities.
Okay. As I said, in
order to perform this kind
of graph ormentation,
there are many ways.
One way is you can
write many many rules.
For example, you can write
a scanner on the graph,
and that scanner program will
basically uh check
your templates.
As long as I find there's
a com operator connected
with another con operator,
I'm going to apply
a specific fusion.
This is the most adopted,
uh, fusing technique.
And if you check
tender flow code,
uh,
they have so many templates
that are written in this way.
Okay? They have a graph
scanner will scan
the graph that basically
find opportunities.
Another way is some cutting
research where people find that
there are some automatic
mechanism that we can
discover this kind of
fiting techniques,
and we'll cover a
little bit later.
Okay. This gives you
an overview of what's going
on on the graph oppoiation.
I hope it's interesting.
Any question?
Okay. Then let's go
to one layer deeper.
Once we open this graph,
we want to deploy
this graph over many,
many devices, that is
called paralyzation.
And the problem paralyzation is
that I have a computer graph,
and I have some device cluster.
And this visualization gives you
a picture of what's
going on in media,
media basically shapes
it kind of cluster
to Google opening Amado.
The key point I want to make
through this visualization,
you can see, vida usually make
this cluster in this way.
That is, it has many many nodes,
and each node has a few GPUs,
typically eight or four.
And inside of each node, uh,
those GPUs are connected
using communication
technology called
veilink that unveiling super
fast is almost as
fast as reading things
directly from memory.
Okay? But if any two GPUs
located on two different
nodes wants to communicate,
they are connected using
some other interconnect.
For example, infinite
band or whatever.
That one was not manufactured
by media by someone else.
That one is ten times slower or
even 100 times slower
than the link.
So if you want to distribute
this graph over this,
you have to take this into
consideration because this
is what media giving to us.
You have to find a way to cut
this graph and put every part
of it on different devices.
So some communication
will happen inside node,
and some communication
will happen across nodes.
So in general, what kind of
communication should
happen inside of node,
and what kind of communication
should happen across nodes.
As I said, inside of a node,
you have not bandoes you
communicate pretty fast.
So you can put heavy
communication inside node.
But across nodes, you have
some snow interconnect.
So you want to make
sure you place in
a way where you minimize the
communication between nodes.
Okay? That is basically
what pi trying to solve.
So when we try to
cut this graph,
we try to find a
way that minimize
communication across nodes and
maximize communication
between nodes.
Yeah. Okay? You can see
this boils down into
another opimenting problem.
And depending on the
communication pattern,
we are going to put different
algorithm on top of it.
And this is also the
essential part needed for
training models at large as
GBD and we are going to do
a deep dive on this later,
okay? Any questions
on this layer?
Yeah, maybe I can speak more
like Groni language, okay?
You probably heard about things
like tensor paralism, right?
Pipeline palism, sequence
paralism, context paralism.
They are basically
trying to figure out
a way that basically
solve that problem I
just mentioned, okay?
And we are going
to cover all this.
Like I said, you
want to figure out
how to graph, how
to communicate,
because now you have
communicated computer,
so you want to schedule
the communicate computer
so they overlap as
much as possible,
uh, because you are doing
distributed communication,
so you care about consistency,
you want to make
sure distributed
versus non distributed
the results are the same,
sometimes you want
to automatically
paralyze it because
you are going to
develop new neur networks
and you don't want to
care about you don't want
to craft paralyzing strategy
for ach new network you wrote.
Okay and then we go to
another layer behind,
right, runtime and scheduling.
So in this layer, I think
it's pretty
straightforward, right?
It's what do we do in
operating systems,
how we make a program run.
So we basically want to schedule
the computer and
communication and
memory in a way that basically,
first, you need to be fast.
Second, we want to overlap the
communication and compute.
And third, our memory
is not infinite.
We have 80 giga for A or H 100,
so we want to be subject
to the memory constraints.
Okay? That is basically
what runtime does.
Yeah. So what?
Uh that's a great question.
No one is limiting that.
That's why there are
many many startups
building silicons, today.
And they are raising
a lot of money.
And they are basically
trying to build
different configurations
from media.
For example, media, give
you a memory of 80 giga,
and AMD is basically giving
you a memory of 160 giga.
Eventually, it depends
on your workload.
Your workload probably
only need 80 giga,
so you don't have
to pay extra price
to buy the 160 giga cards.
Yeah. So there are
so many uh silicon companies
are building different
kind of hardware,
we are going to talk
about that a little bit.
Maybe next next, okay.
And finally, we go
to the layer below,
we are going to talk about how
to implement a really, really,
really fast primitive,
especially for metamo.
Like I said, if you solve metamo
you solve 80% of the problem.
Um but it's not that simple
because when you talk about
operator implementation,
you face a lot of
diversity issues.
That is first you have
different hardware architecture
like that you mentioned,
you need to optimize for
different generations
of MDA GPUs BD will ship
GPUS every two years,
you also even have TPU
CPU and for example,
M three, four, this
kind of things.
You want your to
run on everywhere.
You have to craft
operator imitations for
every hardware platform.
Eight. Second, you have
different ways of storing
these tensor values.
You can store it in
different precisions.
For each precision, it will
use different curves
from the device.
So the program
will be different.
So you have to craft a different
kernel for each precision.
As you probably know,
media is strongly
advocating for
reducing precisions.
Like ten years ago,
we are training
neural network on 32
bits of precisions.
And today, if you check
the latest neural network,
they are trained on
16 up to this year,
the std art AM is basically
trained on FP eight.
Jensen who give a new
card during Christmas,
he said, no, you can
train on FP four.
That is each weight is basically
represent using only four bits.
How could that be possible?
And we are going
to dive into that.
The third issue is basically,
remember, our operators
have different shapes.
We could have three
by three come,
we could have five by five come.
And for MTM, we could have 2d3d.
And because of this
because of the way we
store the values, um,
uh, a a same kind of probably
will have very different
performance on different shapes,
and we are going
to dive into that.
And sometimes we index
on some specific shapes.
As I said, for example,
for count two D,
we really care about
the performance of X
because it is a cornerstone
of ret net, right.
And for this met Mo, uh,
2d3d, we really care
about some value,
some dimensions of
power two because it
is the way how people build
transformers and TPD,
and we want to optimize
to the extreme for them.
Okay. And all these
factors basically
make the implementation of
operators really,
really complicated.
Okay? Okay. With that,
I think I basically,
give you an overview
of what merchant learning
system people are
doing and what basically people
are cooking in petro
and tender flow. Okay?
Let's go back to our
high level picture.
So now we know how
to represent our models,
right dataflow graph.
We also know how to basically
represent our backward pass,
okay, for backward pass.
Um, we are going
to talk about how to
represent data a little bit,
but in general, data is
represented using tensors, right?
But there are some magics in
tensors, we are going
to talk about that.
And remember, our ultimate goal
is we take this data and
this mode representation,
we are going to make it
fast on different hardware,
okay? Any question?
Okay, cool. I think that
basically wrap up the basics.
Then let's basically go
into the first layer,
and we are going to start from
the operator optimization layer.
Okay, we are going
to talk about how to
really implement
some fast operators.
So remember our goal, given
this kind of operator
here, I give you a meto.
Our goal is try to find
implementation that is very,
very fast on CPNTP
building from there,
we are going to compose more and
more complicated data phlograph.
Um, I think I already
said that and I repeat.
The goal of this layer
is we try to find
implementation that is well
that will maximize AI, okay?
We try to basically
make the number of
compute as much as possible.
But we try to minimize
the memory IO access.
That is basically the
fundamentals of compute, right?
We try to maximize the
original intensity.
In this part, we are going
to talk about three
things, right.
First is the image learning,
how we can make the
operator fast in general,
regardless of
platforms, for example,
no matter you are
using CPO or GPU,
how we can make operator fast.
Then, as I said, MTMo
is so important,
so we are going to
dive into MT MO.
We're going to very deep dive.
And then because GPU is
a major platform for
computing today,
is special machinery, so
we are going to dive deep
into how to make this
operators fast on GPUs.
Okay, so let's start
with the first one.
So how we can make operator
fast in general, okay?
In general, there are three
ways to make operator fast.
The first ways we try to
vectorize our operators, right?
And this is pretty
straightforward if you
write Lump Pi operators
every day, right?
Uh, writing vectorized
code is always
faster than writing a oop.
The second way is we try
to play with data layout.
And by defining the
right data layout,
that is representing the data,
inspite tensors
in the right way,
we can actually reduce overhead
in many many operators
in machinery.
The third way, of
course, per addition,
we just give it more threats
and we compute in parallel.
Okay? Let's start
with the first one.
Like I said, the first one
is pretty straightforward.
And this is a piece
of code where we
add the values to
erase A and B and write
values back to C.
One version of it
is basically we
use unvectorized, uh, version.
We just loop over
all the values.
And we can vectorize it.
The way we corize
basically we are going to
call some more
advanced functions,
which is called load flow four.
In this case, every time
we are going to load
four floats inside
one from the memory.
And we are going to
add the four flows
together and the write value
into another destination memory
address which store four flows,
which is called C, and then we
store the value and
we move the pointer.
And this is a write version.
Okay? Can anyone tell me why
the version is faster than
the left one? Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. In many
modern hardware,
they have this kind of load flow
four that allows you to load,
many values in one pass.
This is given by the
hardware manufacturer.
So if you are able
to leverage this,
you basically can vectorize
your compute in this way.
This has been built into
petrogentensor flow.
I think as long as you
call the default API
and you try to write
your code in a way that
is as vectorized as
much as possible is what
work in this way, okay?
That is recordis. The second one
is we also play
with data layout.
Remember at the beginning
at the global picture,
I said our input
imergiO data immersion
is basically stored in tensor.
But what is tensor? Tensor is
basically a high
dimensional array,
fundamentally, how is high
dimision array stored in memory?
Okay. Fundamentally, in memory,
we're not going to store
anything that is
high dimensional.
We can only store things
in one dimension, right?
So we store things
in a sequential way.
Okay? That is from
a memory level,
we don't have any
tensor awareness,
and this basically visualize
the way that we store values.
We basically store from
the left to right.
For example, here, each value
basically takes eight
bytes in memory.
And the way we represent
tensor is basically,
uh, we usually introduce
two ways, one is row major.
The other is column major.
And I think all
of you guys should be
very familiar with this.
In row major, we basically
store each row first,
and then we start with the
second row and the third row.
In column major, the other way,
this is for the two
dimensional case,
but you can generalize
into many many dimensions.
Okay? And this is
a visualization.
The first one red
one is row major,
the second one is column major.
Okay. And we need to be
aware of data layout because
if you look at this program,
assuming that our data
is stored in row major,
that is we draw a zero,
zero all the way
to zero minus one,
and then we start from uh
A 10 and then, following
the row major.
Okay. So do you think
this program is good?
Why? Because if you pay
attention you will
find that the loop is
written in a way
that it first loops
from the inside of dimension,
and then outside of dimension.
And this is going to
be extremely slow.
Why? Yeah, cache is one problem.
Second is going to every time
when you try to tu loop,
you are going to move
the pointers array
of stress that way
introduce some overhead.
One way to improve this
program is basically we try to
swap those two loops
we loop I and then J.
This is pretty straightforward.
Okay. Now we know
that our data is
stored in tensor and I'm
going to give you MCQ,
Machine learning
systems store data
in row major or column major.
Who wants to answer?
Like for example Piro.
Yeah. Okay. Actually,
I can tell you,
um, they don't throw data in
row major or column major.
They throw data in a new
format which I'm
going to introduce.
That is called
strted format. Okay?
So what is the strategy format?
This is basically the
last part of this class.
Okay? So in strted format,
you introduce two more
parameters, okay.
The first parameter
is called offset.
That is when you try to
index value from a tensor,
you first add offset value.
Okay? The second, parameter
is called stress,
and the stress is also tensor
with a dimension equal
to the original tensor.
Okay. So like I said,
the offset basically
means that the offset of
the tensor relative to
the underlying
storage, the stress,
I basically indicates
how many elements
need to be skipped
in memory to move when
unit in the dimension
of the tensor.
That means that here you
have array three
dimensional tensor,
the way that index
value is basically,
you take underlying
storage and you
first try to calculate
index as well plus offset,
and then you multiply
each dimension by strett
and eventually you'll
get this value.
This is called strategy format.
This is pretty
straightforward? Let's end
this lecture with a
very simple question.
These two visualization
basically give
you what it means
by strategy format.
Take 5 seconds to look at this.
Okay. We easy to understand.
Let me ask you two questions.
So what do we have when
we have two dimensions.
we have the stress
zero equal to one,
and the stress one equal to
a shape zero. What is this?
This is a column major, right?
You can see we can use, uh,
different values of
stress to represent
the row major or column major.
And we can do something
similar that is once we
set the first dimension
of stress equal
to shape one and
the second dimension of stress
equal to one, then we
get to the row major.
Okay. You can see
stress actually gives a lot of
flexibility. So why is flexible?
Last question, okay? If
a tensor of shape one,
two, three, four is shared,
it stored continuous in
memory following row major.
So what is the stress? So we
all know that stress
is definitely
a four dimensional array.
Sorry, array was
four entries, right?
So what is exactly the stress?
So if you do this, um,
in inter non pilot petrol,
you will find that basically,
we create array
with 24 elements,
and we ship using one,
two, three, four,
and we try to put
stress on well find stress
be 24, 12, four, and one.
That means, if you try to move
an element in the first dimension
that is this dimension,
you need to skip 24 elements.
And if you try to move element
following this dimension,
you need to skip 12 elements.
Okay. Pretty straightforward.
Okay. The reason we have
stress is because once we
have this kind of definition
of storing elements,
we can actually using
this thread to optimize
a lot of operators,
which I will cover next lecture.
Okay. That's all I
have today. Thank you.
H
h.