Okay. Thanks for coming back.
Yeah, let's get started.
Cool. Enrollment updates.
We have sent out two
batches of invitations.
One on Wednesday, the
other on Thursday.
I think we try to enroll
another 100 students.
And if you want to take this
class, you need to accept.
You have a 24 hours due.
After the deal, we
are going to enroll
the next batch tomorrow morning.
Yeah. Okay.
Um, let's get started
with today's contents.
So I put that graph
there so make sure you
understand where you are now.
Okay? Well, at the
bottom layer, okay?
Operators. So last lecture,
I think we start
talking about how to
make operators fast
in general, right?
And we said we can vectorize
them by leveraging
the torized functions
from platforms,
accelerator platforms.
And we also touch based
on data layout and
haven't finished yet.
Okay. Today we are
going to finish that,
and then we are
going to talk about
something that is
very, very deep.
And that is our
first metam lesson.
Okay? We are going to have many,
many these lessons, but
today we are going
to take the first.
And if we can finish it part,
and then we are going
to talk about something
that's really interesting that
is the current GPO market.
We are going to repurpose
that class as a economics class.
We try to understand
what's going
on in Silicon Valley. Okay?
Yeah, let's resume
with data layout.
Um, so still remember
this one, right?
So more than
deploying frameworks,
they basically use
stress format.
We like compared to column
major or row major,
we introduce two
more parameters.
One is offset, right?
The other is the stress,
which is a list,
okay with a dimension equal
to the shape of the tensor.
And this visualization
basically give you
a concept of what does
strat means, okay?
And we also did a
very small exercise,
if we have a four
dimensional tensor
with a shape one,
two, three, four.
So what stress?
I hope you guys actually
understand that. Okay?
And then we start
asking the question,
column major and row major
are actually pretty good.
Why do we care about saving
stress when saving tensors?
So in order to answer
this question,
I think most of you when you
write petard or programs,
you probably often
use this API view.
You can view a tensor
in different shapes.
For example, the original shape
is one, two, three, four,
but you can view it as 24
by one or something, right?
And the reason we have
this stress because it can
facilitate a lot of this kind
of array manipulation operators.
And view is such an example.
Um, the core concept
here is stress
can separate the underlying
storage and the view tensor.
So basically when we store
the values of the ray,
we are always stored
sequentially in memory.
But we can view it in
many many different ways.
And, um, and because of this,
we can basically every
time we try to view
the test in a different
shape in a different way,
we don't have to
copy the content.
We don't have to copy
the content from
the original array in
the lower level memory into
another part of the memory.
We just need to we can do
a zero copy for this
kind of operators.
Okay? And in the
next few slides,
I'm going to show you some
very common operators
you use to manipulate arrays.
And I'm going to
tell you, actually,
in petrich there or zero copy.
That is when you perform
this kind of operators,
you don't have to copy anything.
It's zero overhead,
very fast, okay?
And all this could contribute
basically attribute to
this stress format, okay?
When I preoperat I want
you to first spin
off your second to
think about how to
implement that when
I give you this stress format.
The first one slice, how
we can slice the tensor?
For example, here, I have four
by four tensor four
by four matrix,
and I want to slice that piece.
So rudimentary way,
you probably just
copy that pyro content
into another array
and you get that one. But
we don't want to copy.
So one way to do that is
we can just manipulate
the values of the
stress and offset.
So we first add the
offset by one, right?
And then we rewrite the
shape into three by two,
and we pass this
offset and shape
into the stress
and offset values,
and you basically
can slice the sensor
out from this bigger tenser.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Cool.
I think the key part here I
want to make is the copy.
Basically, the sliced tensor,
it shares memory with
this original tensor.
But you still get a kind
of a new tensor that with
a different shape, right?
And slice is a pretty
common operator,
but another very common
operator is transpose.
Here, I think everyone
understands trasposeOPermute.
So here you have a tensor with
original shape of two by three.
You want to transpose
it into a three by two.
How does that? Okay, let's see,
we can run through a very,
very simple example.
So here I have a tensor
four dimensional tensor,
and I directly print it stress.
And as we said in
the last lecture,
the stress is basically
24 12 for one, right?
And then this permute
is basically,
uh transpose but it's in
high dimensional, okay?
And we try to permute
the dimension,
we basically shift the
first dimension to the end,
and we put the next
three dimensions
one position ahead, okay?
And you can see if we
print the permuted value,
the underlying storage is
still the same, right?
Sequentially from
one all the way
to 23 from there to
all the way to 23.
But what changes
here is basically we
kind of modify the stress
a little bit, right?
But only modifying the stress.
Remember stress is
a scatter values
not going to be a lot
of memory spaces.
You just need to
modify a small value,
and you can actually achieve
this kind of transpose.
In fact, in all petroloNpi
when you do transpose,
you are also doing
they will copy.
You don't have to copy anything.
You are still sharing the
original nye storage.
That's why transpose
is super fast, okay?
All because of this
stress format. Okay.
Then let's do one more, okay?
And the third operator is
some operator you
use a lot, okay?
Broadcast.
This broadcast operating
is something that
you always face when you try to
multiply or when you
try to add a race
with only one
dimensional matched,
but the other two
dimension proper one
is higher dimension and the
other is lower dimension.
So how do you do
that? And magically,
when you do Lum pi, uh,
they will do that for you.
When you multiply these
two tens together, uh,
there's an implicit, broadcast
happening behind
the scene, right?
But how you achieve
this kind of thing.
Like one rudimentary way is
basically in order to
broadcast the second tensor,
you just copy the
row four times,
and you get a target sensor.
But like I said, it is not
good because copy is slow.
I don't want to copy. And copy
will consume some memory.
Okay? I don't want
to waste memory.
Okay? Let's think about how we
can achieve this using stress.
I'll let you think
about 10 seconds.
Okay. Anyone want to answer?
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, exactly. Yeah.
We just insert one strut
that is zero. Let's
see how this works.
Okay?
So here, let's inspect
the original tensor.
The original tensor has a
stress equal to one, right?
Because it's one dimensional,
and its shape is 13,
this data is
sequentially in memory,
which is one, two,
three, straightforward.
Okay? And the target
tensor one is
basically with a shape
or equals for three,
because I want to
furs three columns.
Like I said, I don't
want to copy data.
I want zero copy. The data
should be kept in memory as one,
two, three, only three elements.
Right. So how to basically
modify the stress.
So remember the
definition of stress is
basically like how many elements
I move along that
dimension, right?
So in order to get that tensor,
what I do is basically I insert
one more thread at the
beginning at zero, right?
That means along the fake
dimension I added here four,
right, the board carts sensor.
Every time I move
along that dimension,
I just time zero, and it will
go back to the beginning.
Okay. That's how we
basically do this kind of,
uh, array manipulations
in behind patters, yeah.
Um, okay, that's all I have.
These operators
actually are very
important and they all
benefit from stress.
Okay, let's do something
that's more hardcore.
Uh, here, in some cases,
I want to swap the tiles.
Okay, I have a tensor where
you can see it still 0-15,
but I want to swap
the pink part with the
blue part, how I do that.
Okay. I wrote a little program
here and you can see my
programming is pretty stupid.
I need to copy a lot of things,
I basically need to slide some
tensor and swap elements.
And I will leave to you
how to implement
this with zero copy.
Okay? I'm not going
to give you the answer.
Think about that. Okay.
But here, the important thing
is whenever you write this
kind of program in Patric,
you need to think about if
you are doing zero copy.
If you can't do zero copy,
you should always do
zero copy, right?
Like I said, zero copy
is zero overhead,
and you don't have to
consume any memory.
Yeah. Okay?
Um, with that, I think I
finished introducing the stress.
And then let's think about, um,
so what is the problem stress?
I think the problem stress
is quite obvious, right?
Uh, say, if we view
a tensor or select a
tensor or whatever,
um, yeah, indeed, we
can get a tensor,
but, uh, the new tensor,
returned by the operator, uh,
under its values are
not continuous in
memory anymore, right?
Because only the original
tensor is continuous in memory.
Once we change the stress or
whatever, it's not continuous.
But like I said, in
many, many, for example,
element wise or is
multiplication or
many many other
accelerator platforms
when you do this
kind of operator,
you have to make sure tensor
has a continuous storage, right?
So which means that
every time when
you apply this kind
of or manipulation.
And if you proceed to next
operation and the
next Operation,
have a requirement
on the continuity
of the underlying storage,
what do you do is you
sometimes need to call
this operator torch
or contiguous,
and it will basically
rearrange the um,
underlying storage
for you. Okay?
So this one sounds similar.
And if you don't do
this, you probably
made this error
many many times in
torching you don't
want to complain that
your tensor is not
continuous in memory,
so I cannot proceed
next operation.
Okay? Cool. Any question? No.
Okay, then we finish this layout
and so the next thing
that we want to
introduce is basically,
we can also paralyze
um, operators, right?
So here, I think the palsiton
especially for this
kind of operation.
So here, I hope you still
remember the operation here is
basically element
we side, right?
We add A and B and rather to
C. We do that element by
element from left to right,
in this kind of element
wise operations,
it's very easy to
paralyze it, right?
For example, in
most CPU platforms,
you have this decorator
which you can decorate
on top of your loop,
and it will basically split
the addition operations to
different CPU course and it
all perform in parallel.
The key thing here
is the partition or
the split is
straightforward because it
is a element wise
at each element,
addition is independent
from other elements.
So you can easily
split the repetition.
This is a very simple way
to paralyze operators and
leverage mark course.
We'll talk more about this
because suppose there are
some operations
where one elements
add is dependent on
another elements add,
how can we basically
split these operators,
and we are going to dive
deeper into that part later.
That basically will
cover our lecture
in how to paralyze the operator.
But this one is too
straightforward,
so I put it here.
You understand.
Okay. To summarize how we
can make operator faster,
we can do arization
We can leverage
the platform specific
Corize functions,
for example, the
load floor four.
Okay? We can also
manipulate the data layout.
Um, we introduce
the strat format,
which allows us to do copy
for many, many operators.
And for some very simple
straightforward animal
wise operators,
we do very simple parison, okay.
Okay.
Now, let's go into
the next part and
probably a difficult
part of this lecture.
So how we can make
met moo faster.
Previously, we have to talk
about, array manipulations.
We talk about element wise,
but met moo is apparently
not animal wise,
you have to multiply the role of
the first matrix of the
common second matrix,
and it's not performed
element by element.
So how we can make these
kind of operators fast.
And this is so important
because we know
marching system is all
about met moo, okay?
Um, there are in
general, two ideas.
One is, we have some
algorithm for that,
and we are going to dive
deep into the algorithm.
The other is we can use
some more ace hardware.
That's why we start talking
about accelerators,
okay, in the final
part of this lecture.
Okay?
Um, before we talk
about the optimization
techniques, so what is Mtmo?
Okay. What is essentially
a Mthmo in code?
So I believe most of you
have implement Mthmo
by yourself, right?
Metamo is essentially a
a three layer loop, IJK,
here we are trying to multiply
two matrices A and B,
and we try to write
the results into
C and each of them
are two dimensional.
Here, I simplify the problem,
their dimension or equal
to N, both dimensions.
In order to implement
this met mo,
we basically write this
loop we loop over I, J,
and then we take a
row and column from
two matrices and we do
a dot product and write the
result back to C, right?
No question, right?
Okay. What is
the complexity of this loop?
Cube, right? A cube.
Okay. So what is
the best complexity
the human society
can achieve? Do you guys know?
It's definitely
better than cube,
because you guys
probably know a lot
of researchers pH
networking in this area.
Okay. Yeah. So
here's the number.
It's roughly 2.37 1552. Okay?
But no one can reduce it to
square, of course, okay?
And mere complexity
is actually very,
very, um, I wouldn't say active,
but old line of research, right?
People work on that from
50, 60 years ago, okay?
And you can see, there are many,
many notable papers
published along the line.
And this is how we
do on this research.
Okay you can see
originally we are at cube,
right, and we
gradually reduce it.
We try to invent one
algorithm to make that fast.
Um, but as you can see,
the Y access is actually
very fine green,
which means that it's
already saturated.
So I conclude that metamo is not
a good area to research
because if you do this,
it's unlikely you can
publish a good paper.
Okay? Yeah, it's very saturated.
Um, but require our goal, okay?
We try to make memo fast, right?
There are two ways
to make it fast.
Our ultimate goal
is, yeah, please.
So from 1990,
very little, very little. Yeah.
Yeah, you can think there's
almost no difference.
Especially when you put
this into real system,
those kind of improvement
will diminish.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Okay.
Let's go back to
this slide, okay.
Our goal maximize arithmetic
intensity, right?
And apparently this AI equals
to compute divided
by memory, memory o.
So what these people are
doing basically they try to
increase the number
of the compute,
right? Make it faster.
Okay. Okay. And like I
said, it's saturated.
So we have to take an
alternative, right?
We try to reduce the IOs so
we can still make it fast.
Okay?
Does that make
sense? Big picture.
Okay. Okay.
Then in the rest
lecture, what are we
going to talk about how
we can basically
make the second term
smaller when we perform at them.
Okay.
Uh, in order to talk about that,
I think I need to remind you of
something you learned
from operating systems.
Okay? Remember in computers,
we have memory hierarchy, right?
The reason we have
memory hierarchy is
because memory becomes
more and more expensive,
right when it is closer to
the processing units, right?
For example, in the
processors, we have registers.
It's super fast, likely fast.
It's basically
local, but we cannot
make many of them because
it's so expensive.
That's why we add layers
and layers and layers,
and we ended up with
memory hierarchy.
One catch two catch
then memory DRM.
What is behind dram?
Disks, right? And in discs,
we have different kind of disks.
We have SSD, we have different
kind of disks anyway.
Yeah. Okay. But we don't
care about that part, okay?
And here, it is a rough speed
read run speed for
each layer, okay?
But we want to put memo
on top of this, okay?
So apparently, this
is too complicated.
Okay, we are going to
simplify a little bit.
We only have three layers.
The first layer is the
course ALU, right?
Course which are
performing competition.
The second layer are basically
those storage that are
local to the course,
which are basically registers.
Okay? The third layer is a DRAM.
And we know this is
computing units, right?
And we also know registers
are local to cross,
so they are like to invest,
compared to registers,
apparently,
DRAM is so slow,
it's turtle is slow,
we are going to apply Mm
on this and see how
we can do better.
Before we do that, I
still want to remind
you to calculate how to
estimate aismont intensity.
We just count how
many red and reds,
still remember this loop,
and the aismon intensity
of the first loop is 1/3,
and the second one
is three by five.
Because in the second loop
we fuse operating together.
Okay.
Then I'm going to rewrite
the three layer loop of
metamol into this format.
I will let you
appreciate this loop
for 10 seconds, then
I'm going to explain.
Okay.
Nothing changes,
but I just noted
the origin of the arrays.
So here, uh, I noted
that originally the array
was stored on DRAM,
which is the second layer, if
you remember the
memory hierarchy.
In order to perform
computer on ALU,
I have to move things
from DRAM to ALU
to local storage,
which is register.
So I have to basically create
a tempor storage here and I move
things from DRAM to register,
and this will trigger IO ad.
Okay.
That's all. Nothing changes.
Now let's try to
count how many ads we
did in this loop
because this is the
most original version,
original flavor of metamo,
we basically count
how many times we
read A read B and how many times
we write to C Bet
A, B, C are on DRM.
So when we count the
number of times we read A,
we basically see how many times
this line was executed
and it's pretty easy.
This line is inside of
this three layer loop,
so it's cube, It was
executed cube times, okay?
And similarly for B, it was
executed in cube times.
When we read the results back,
you can see this line was
outside of this loop, right?
Because, yeah,
we basically multiply this in
order to get one results in
the resulting array C. So we
can get the readon right
which is basically
in cube and cube
and square. Okay?
Does that make sense? Cool.
And this is the number
of read and red we have.
And the second question is,
how many space we use here.
Of course, we use
some space in dim,
but dim is pretty large, so
we don't care about that.
So we care more about how
many registers we use.
And from this loop,
you can see we actually only
allocated three registers,
one to store the
intermediate value C
and the other two small ANB,
which basically read
things from dim. Okay?
So the space we use
is three, okay.
Basically the reading
cost is basically
two times cube times the speed
of moving one element from
dram to register. This
is the time cost.
Does that make
sense? Cool. Now I'm
going to introduce a more
advanced version of Mm.
Sorry. Like I don't think
I get the question.
Because the original
value was stored in DR,
we have to move it to register.
Move it manually?
Yeah, we
can do that. I will
talk about that later.
Yeah. I think you
already spot point.
It's not efficient. You don't
have to move it once. You
can just put it there.
You don't move it again,
right. That's why
here we only use
three registers.
In your case, you are going
to use more than three
because next time
you need to move.
Okay. Okay.
Then I'm going to introduce
something that is
so fundamental that I hope
all of you guys can understand?
Because this is so fundamental
that if you don't understand,
you are not going to understand
the flash attention,
and you are not going to
understand all the
attenon related stuff.
This is called registered
tiled metamor.
This is a slightly improved
version of met Mo.
Um, and I'm going to give you
a very short description,
and I'm going to
give you 10 seconds
to appreciate this loop again.
Okay. What we do is
basically we reship
the original three arrays
by from the two dimension
to four dimension.
Here, what we do is basically we
introduce two smaller numbers,
definitely smaller than
the original dimension.
And we tell the array.
We have so many of these kind
of smaller matrices, right?
And we put the rest
of dimension here.
Okay. And here we apparently
introduce three uh
telling factors.
V one, V two and V three.
And then what we do is we
rewrite the original
loop into this. Okay?
I would like to appreciate
this loop a little bit.
I want to make sure
that this loop is
equivalent to the original
loop I wrote, okay?
Okay. Indeed, it's
equivalent, why?
Because we are
basically transforming
the original memo into a
block wise memo, here.
Every time I basically
will take a row
with the number of original
rows equal to one,
and take a column from
here with umber of
original columns from
B equal to weight two.
And then I have a
third loop which
will basically scan
from left to right,
from top to bottom,
and calculate the results in
this small block and write the
result back to this block.
Does that make
sense? Cool, cool.
Okay. Now, you understand
this loop, okay?
And this loop is so magical
that we can basically again,
count the red and red
and see what happens.
We are going to first,
like what we did for
the original loop,
we are going to count
how many times we
read A from DRM to register.
I think it's straightforward.
So from this line,
you can see every time we read
array of size one by way three.
We write it to this small array.
We just count how many times we
ask you this line.
How many times?
The first loop is
undivided by we one.
Second is undivided by way two,
and third is undivided
by way three. Right.
We time all these
three together,
and we also time the
shape of the array.
So how many times
we read? You can
see this we one will be
canceled here, right?
And this week three
will be canceled here.
So it's basically cube
by week two, right?
And you found magic here, okay?
But just rewrite the loop.
I already reduced the
time I read A from
cube to a factor that
is divided by we two.
Okay? Any question? Cool.
Similarly, we can do that for B,
we just time this shape with
the loop factors and
loop iterations and
we get the times
we read B is basically
cubed divided by w one.
We're already doing pretty
good because we already reduce
both BofactorF it's the
same because results back
from register to DRAM,
so it's still square.
Then the next question is how
many register we use here?
So in order to count
the lumber register
we use, basically,
we just count how many
intermediate memory
we need to store when
performing this loop.
And you can easily see
the lumber register we use here
is this one, this
one, and this one.
And this one is of shape
way one times w two.
This is we one we three,
we two with three.
So lumber register we
use is this number.
We just add them together, okay?
And at a high level, you
basically get the point.
Here we are basically treating
space for time, right?
And we slightly use
more registers,
but we will reduce the
lumber risk we did, okay?
And we also summarize the
ad cost here is cube by
two plus cb did
but we want times
the speed of moving contents
from DM to register.
And this is already doing
better than the previous loop.
And you can verify by yourself.
You go back and bring
up C plus plus,
editor and try to
register loops.
You'll find the
second one actually
actually much faster than
the first one, okay?
Yeah.
So here, in order to
perform this loop,
I need to allocate
something register, right?
And we just look at this loop
and see where we allocate.
So in this line,
we allocate array
of shape w by way too, right?
And in these two
lines, we allocate
another small array A and B.
We just add them together.
Okay. Clear? Cool.
Okay, before I move into
something that's even deeper.
Let's try to understand
reveal what's going on here.
Okay? So the first thing
you noted by looking
at these terms,
the first thing you
notice is you'll
find that when I do telling,
actually I introduce
I introduced
three tell factors, we
want me with three.
But it ended up with a cost
that is not related
to with three, right?
Okay This is something
really interesting.
That means that when
I try to optimize
this kind of metamor,
I can arbitrarily choose with
three and that will not
affect my performance.
Does that make sense? Cool.
The second question
I want to ask is how
we can set the value for.
Apparently, we want to
influence a lot of things.
I influence our speed.
Apparently, we want to be as
large as possible, right?
Because otherwise, um,
because if they are large,
then our read will be smaller.
But we are subject
to constraints.
That is, we have limited
number of registers.
So we are subject to
a constraint that is,
um, basically, this number,
this line should be smaller than
the total registers
offered in ALU CPU,
right in the core that's
one constraint we have to,
uh, you know, respect, okay?
Let me ask a
fundamental question.
Why essentially can
telling reduce the cost?
Yeah, at a high level, yes,
we are essentially treat
space for IO, but why?
Can anyone explain?
Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
In the original cube
implementation,
every time we try
to perform element,
we have to move them from
memory from DRAM to register.
But here, we first move a block,
but we fix them and
we read the rest of
things which means that when
we read the rest of things,
actually we are using
the previous load
from DRAM to register.
I hope everyone get this one.
This is called
register tut Mm, okay?
Okay, let's go deeper.
Okay? So you know, reality
is not this right.
In reality, we don't have
three layers of
memory hierarchy.
We have CPU A, we have
registered, we have DRAM,
but we actually have another
layer that is called
LON catch and I think LON catch
is fast, is rapidly fast.
Okay. It's definitely
faster than DRM.
Okay. So in reality,
we probably have three layers.
Okay. So how we can
make this happen,
how we can basically put metma
on top of this memory hierarchy.
Okay.
I'm going to introduce
another telling technique
that is called
catch away telling.
Um, so here, there's nothing
significantly different.
Okay. What we do
is basically now,
we cannot directly move
contents from DRAM to register.
We have to move from DRAM to
LON catch then Oca register.
And we're going to embed
these two loops together.
Uh here we first tell
between DRAM and ON catch.
The way I do telling
is the same.
Um, I just basically tell
one dimension, okay?
I introduce two parameters
B one and B two.
You know, B three
doesn't matter, right?
So I already explained that
B three doesn't matter.
I simply said B
three as one here.
Because B three is not going to,
um, influence our
performance. Okay.
And what I do is basically,
um, I do this kind of tilling.
So for here, every time I
pick up a row for this,
every time I pick up
a column and then I
do a dot program and try
to get the results, okay?
And this happens between
DRAM and RNCchm you know,
once I read them, to
perform computer,
that computer won't happen
in RN cache so you still
need to move contents
from OCach to register.
So at that layer, you also
perform metam but in a
much smaller size, right?
And what I do is I'm going to
apply the technique I just
introduced um in
the previous slide,
that is, I'm going to do that
register wire telling, okay?
Does that make sense? Cool.
And this will ended up with,
um, so I already explained this.
The data movement
passes basically
it first starts from DRAM and
then move content from DRAM to
L one cache and then
one cache to register,
This ended up with this loop.
But before we proceed to
the ultimate loop, okay?
We're first analyzing
the cost here, okay?
And I think you guys
already get the idea.
It's very easy to count
how many rates it
happens between DRAM
and catch, right?
So in order to move
A's content from
DRAM to ON CAT what
we do is basically,
um, A happens here, right?
And there's one outer loop.
So we just time this
number divided by B one,
and we time the shape
of the we move,
which is times B one.
So the lumber IO happens
between these two layers
is basically square
for A, right?
And here, what do we do for B,
it has one more
loop compared to A.
So what happens if
we time this lumber,
this lumber, and this lumber
and the shape of the array.
So we get the cost
as Nub div by B.
Okay? And the total cost is
The total c is basically,
um, these two number together.
And as I said, you still
subject to constraint.
That is your LO catch size
cannot be greater than
the available L one catch
offered on your course, right?
So you also care
about the space,
and the space we use is
basically B one Tison
and B two Timson and
we sum them together,
and they should be smaller
than one catch size.
Okay? Exactly the
same thing. Okay.
I just reduce one dimension.
Good with this one,
right? Okay. And then
we are going to put these
two loops together.
And this is a more realistic
more implementation
in today's architectures,
for example,
in GPU and CPU, apparently,
this is still a simplified
version because,
you know, there's
still to catch, right.
Yeah. Okay.
So in the outside of
this loop, we are doing,
catch a wire telling and
inside of this loop,
we are doing register
aware telling, right?
That's what I said
before. And here,
we simply said with
three equal to
one because we know we
three does not matter.
It won't affect performance.
And in order for you to
understand this loop,
we can see on this box,
basically we are doing catch
telling using B one and B two,
and it moves things
from DRAM to OCach.
And then in this green box,
we are doing register
telling using V and V two,
we are moving things
from one to register.
And finally, things
are in register,
we actually proceed
the competition.
Okay? And let's try to
analyze the cost again, okay?
The cost of moving things from
dm to one can be analyzed
in this way, right?
We roughly just look at this.
This is the operation
where we move things.
And the first term is
basically moving this array.
And this array was executed
divided by B one times.
Very tEveryt excuse it
move something in this shape
basically time together.
And we get the cost of moving
things moving A
from dram to one,
which is square, okay?
Similarly, when we move things
from DRM to catch and move B,
we just time this factor,
this factor and the shape
together and we get this number.
And then we proceed to the
inner loop and we can also
count uh the times we move
things between one and register.
And you can double check.
This is correct.
Okay. Yeah, that's
all we have for this loop. Okay?
And you can see in reality,
this is super
complicated, right?
So what makes it complicated?
So in practice, um,
for example, on CPU,
we have a disc to dram to
one to one to two
to one to register.
That means we are doing telling
across at least three layers.
Probably we can ignore disc.
That's one thing that
makes things complicated.
The second thing is, we need to
determine the values for 1b2b1,
b2c1 and C two, Because if
you still remember, uh,
these telling factors
need to be subject to
the space constraints
at each layer.
We cannot be more than that.
Otherwise, this loop is
not going to run, okay?
And the third thing that you
can make this even faster
is when we are reading
things from DRM to L two,
for example, you can also
pipeline in the reading, right?
You can also let the
CPU to read scenes
2-1 or concurrently
one to register,
and all this can be pipeline,
so you can basically even
reduce the time that you
use to read scenes, right?
You transfer contents
between memory hierarchies.
And all these, like I said,
need to subject to
the size of L two,
L one cache and registers. Okay?
That basically finish most of
the contents about
telling, please.
Yeah. Most cases.
Yeah. Yeah. Please. D was what?
That's a really good question.
I don't know. Yeah,
I don't know.
I think those line
of implementation,
they focus on different parts.
They focus on reducing
the compute complexity,
if you remember.
This telling is essential
in reducing the IO.
So they are fungon
theoretically,
you can implement more
advanced method that has
a lower complexity while
you still implement this.
Yeah, there are
some limitations,
but in Koda, I think
most people still
adopt cube algorithm.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah.
Yeah, we are going to do
this on GPO again next week.
And that will be
more complicated.
So make sure you spend time
to understand these loops.
Okay? This is so essential.
And I can't see more on this.
Okay? So flash attention is
basically based on this.
But in flash attention,
what do we do is on
top of that met M we
add another operator
which is even guess.
Softmax. We just put
softmax and Mtmo together,
and we do telling.
That's basically flash
attention. Okay?
Oh.
They, they do this. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. This was
not something super new,
but it is so fundamental.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Okay.
Now, let's review
the final question.
While telling works? The reason
telling works
basically you reuse
some loading many of you
already understand this.
If you look at the
mathematical format of
Met M you'll find
that there are some independent
access of the array.
So the acess of the array
A is independent of
the dimension of
J B J is
only one dimension of B
and A does not have
that dimension.
You can always read something in
the other irrelevant dimension
and you try to reuse some
loading from the first array,
we can tell the J
dimension by one,
and it will enable us
reuse of A for one times.
That's why we can reduce
the load by one times.
Okay. Okay. After
finishing this,
I'm going to introduce a very,
very good homework candidate,
is this. This is pretty good.
This is what I did
for my homework when
I learned machinery systems.
Can anyone guess what is?
This is a operator that we
all are very familiar with
it's count two D. Okay.
Count two is essentially
seven layer loop.
It's much more complicated
metamor, okay?
That's a joke. I'm not
going to let you do this.
Okay. The reason I do
this is because when
I learned this count is
the chosen one, right?
But when you learn this,
count is not the chosen one.
I think transformer and
tenting is the chosen one.
I'm going to let you do this
telling for a tenting, okay.
Because it's more
relevant. Okay. And we
can go through this a little
bit because we are going
to talk about this later.
But essentially count two is
basically a seven layer loop,
and you have a
simple spatial loop.
You have some stencil
computation loop,
and you have a reduction loop.
Remember, this reduction
loop also exists
in met Mol Metamlthird loop
is basically reduction loop,
you have another reduction loop.
But usually this KH and
Kw is basically
the filter size, so you
don't care about that.
It's so small that you
just do it as it is.
Okay. And in order
to do telling, uh,
you basically need to tell
some layer loop against four
layer memory hierarchy.
A lot of possibilities.
And this is really hard
and that's why you know,
when people do this, you
can get lost, sometimes.
Okay. Cool, cool.
Yeah, that's our first lesson on
Mtmo and I hope you
understand this tell
the Mtmooa that's the deepest
part of this lecture.
And next, we are
going to proceed
into something that is
really interesting. Okay.
So one way, like I said,
one way to make Mtmo is
basically you do this ting.
The other way is you
utilize DPU accelerators,
and those accelerator devices
will make this super fast.
And next we are trying
to understand why
this can make more fast.
Okay, how does that
accelerator work, okay?
So before we talk
about why, I think,
um, at a high level, you
probably already know.
Essentially GPU is trying to
paralyze this loop, right?
And GPU has so many courses that
each can work on different
part of this loop.
So essentially the same
fundamental to CPU.
Like you allocate more threads,
more curs to work on different
parts of the competition.
But how exactly that works?
Before I introduce
GPUS I think, uh,
I need to bring up a concept
that most of you should be very
familiar with is basically
single instruction,
multiple data, right?
That is the, um, um,
essential part of multi
core computing,
parallel computing.
So in single instruction
multiple data,
um, what you do is essentially,
um, you have a different course
and each core will ask
you the same program,
and you part in the data.
You give each core a part
of the data and you will
proceed with the same
program and output results,
and then you grade results,
you get the final results.
Okay. Because all these course
process together and they
only take a part of data,
so you can you enjoy the
benefit of paralization,
right, which is speed ups, okay?
And as you probably know,
CPO is not pretty good at this
because CPU has a limited
number of course.
The reason is because, um,
the reason is how ChiP
was designed, okay?
Like, originally, we try to
in order to design
a chip like CPU,
we need to put a lot
of components in
addition to compute
units, right?
So we need to put some control.
For example, CPU needs to
understand the IL, okay?
We also need to
put some catches,
L cache to cache.
And we only have a limited
area because we need to
make CPU small and it cannot
consume a lot of power,
otherwise, it cannot be
deployed on laptop
or phones, right?
So we need to have a
physical limitation on area.
So if you put some controls,
you put some catches then
you only have that blank area
where you can put cross,
so we put four ALERs here.
Then people try to make this
faster and faster faster.
That's what happened in
the last 20 years in
Cilic Valley people are making
better and better chips.
They are able to still
put controls and catches,
but where the technology
advances is basically
they are able to
make smaller and
smaller ALUs that
will basically have the
same computing power,
but much smaller.
Because it's much smaller,
so you can put more of
them in this small area.
That's why this CPU
becomes much faster.
Makes sense? Okay. Um,
but at some point,
due to physical limitation,
we cannot further reduce
the size of ALU, right?
So basically, we are
basically reducing it
from 70 anomeres to 60 to 50.
And this is basically the
history of value, right?
And at this point, what we
can do best is basically
this one, right?
By Apple, our favorite company,
and they can do 300 meter, okay?
That means you can put
a three indremere here.
And apparently, compared to
70 anomere you can
put a lot, right?
That's why Apple's chips
are so good, right?
Okay. But we cannot
do better because we are
subject to physical
limitations, okay?
So if you observe this trend,
you can see, uh,
this is Morse law,
by the way, okay?
Everyone understands this.
And apparently Morris
law is ending.
Uh, we cannot reduce
the sight of ARU,
so the computing power
of CPUs or similar chips
cannot increase anymore.
You can see the
plateaus at some point.
Okay? So how to
break this limit.
And you can see this
already plateau as 2015.
But that's not a reality.
If you writing check,
our computing power is
still increasing today.
Okay? There are two ways,
in my opinion, you can disagree.
Okay, feel free to comment.
One way is basically you
go to the quantum world,
I'll become admin and you
try to develop
quantum computing,
quantum computing is definitely
a active area of research.
I think in UCSD, there are
quite a few factory doing this.
But this is too far away for me.
I want something that
is closer, okay?
So the other way is basically
we try to build
something that is
called specialized
hardware, okay?
Basically, we can
convert the Morse law
into horns law, okay?
I'm going to explain
this. Makes sense, right?
Okay. By the way,
quantum computing is a pretty
good area of research.
If you are a person
with patients,
you can invest into the
field for ten years,
maybe after ten years,
even something that's
so good, okay?
The reason specialized
hardware works
that instead of basically
putting a lot of controls,
putting a lot of
catches, putting a lot
of very complex
logic into the ALU,
I try to simplify the
core a little bit.
Okay? The CPO core
is so was told that
it can do many many things
like EFLs blah, blah, blah.
But I don't care about
that because now,
I only care about
machine learning.
Like I said, in
machine learning,
I only care about metmo.
So how about I just make
course that can only do Mtmo?
But nothing else, right?
And if I simplify that a
little bit in this way,
we can put so many
cores and we can make
the core even smaller and we
can put so many cores here.
Two reasons one reason
is because we can make
the core much smaller.
Second is we can
basically remove
those control units
from the board.
So we can basically take
their space and put more
and more cores, okay?
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, computing
units, yeah. Okay.
But if you compare the crew
on the left and right,
the red crew is
actually more stupid,
I can only do met mo.
But that's fine. Okay. We
can make it smart, right?
Okay. That is at
the lower level,
this is basically how GPU works.
Okay? And because of this,
we are basically from
some point in 2015,
we started massively
manufacturing GPUs, okay?
And one notable or
accelerators. Okay.
And GPU is one type
of accelerator.
So, um, uh the
idea, like I said,
is basically use tons we
use but weak and more
specialized and we do
massive data parism or SIMD,
it was first popularized
by media in early 2000
for video games for graphics
because originally,
they only find application in
video games because video games,
you also do mathmo a lot.
But at some point,
deploing takes off,
so this is fit with
deploying pretty well, okay?
Media has been investing in
this area for so long and they
also develop some software and
programming language
to make it faster,
to make sure people can
program on top of it.
One notable programming language
we are going to learn is Koda.
That's how Koda comes from.
Okay. Does that make sense?
Cool. Um, uh,
usually you need to take
architectural class
to learn this,
but in this class, we are
going to cover it in 20 minutes,
and we are not going to
do super deep, okay.
Um, but I want to add a
little bit more here.
So there are usually
type three ways to
basically build specialized
hardware or accelerators,
which I summarize, next.
But here, I list some very,
uh famous, uh, what I
call accelerator, Okay.
The first one, TPU, you already
know Google Divided TPU.
The reason Google
Divided TPO because they
want to pay a media,
quite apparently,
TPU is one type of accelerator
and TPU can only do,
as you can infer from the lame,
tensor related operations,
mostly just memo, okay?
And the second one is basically,
Nvidia is trying
to manufacture in
their next generation
GPO is called
B 201 feature of B
200 is that they can do pretty
well on certain precision.
For example,
originally we do P 32,
in transformer, we do P 16.
At this point, media
is saying you should
do LP four P eight.
Okay. And specializing in
precision is also a type
of specialization, okay?
And the third one,
of course, M three.
That is what we have in
my loft laptop, okay.
It's also a
specialized hardware,
and we are going to dive
deep into that, okay?
And to summarize a little bit,
so what s value are
building today,
there are major three
directions, okay?
The first one is we try to
First we try to specialize
the functionality, okay?
For example, we
produce chips that
are only good at
metam that is TPU,
or only good at certain
computation with sparsity.
Okay? Or we can probably make
a chip that is not so specialized,
but still specialized.
For example, I can
mix CPUs with GPUs,
and that is essentially
what Apple does, right?
Because if you see the
marketing material from Apple,
every time they
release a new laptop,
they're saying, I
have so many cores.
Some cars are so good
at video processing.
So cores are good
at deep learning.
Essentially, they're
building different
cs together into one board.
Okay. Makes sense, right.
Functionality specialized.
I call it. Okay?
The second way to
specialize is basically reduce
precision, I already mentioned.
So I don't I probably
want to I can make it faster
by computing on a shorter,
like rate shorter floating
point reprendton.
Yeah. Okay. This is
what media is strongly
advocating, right?
And I think ten years ago,
when I studied machine
learning, people
only operate on LP 32.
But today, the up to date model,
for example, the
deep sik model with
three trained on P eight.
You can see the
precision already
reduced by four times, okay?
And the third way you
can specialize hardware
is you try to tune
the distribution or
configuration of the board.
Remember, when we
do met telling,
we have a few parameters
from the from hardware.
That is how many L
one cache you have,
how many L two cache you have.
How many memory you have and
how many cores you have.
Okay? In general, people have to
try to strike a balance
between these parameters.
But there are companies
in Silicon Valley.
They try to specialize
the hardware.
For example, they
just give up memory.
I just build a chip with
L one cache no memory.
And this kind of chip can do
so well on certain tasks.
That's another way that you can
specialize your hardware, Okay?
Now, I'm going to teach you a
very important thing, okay?
You should be able and you
should have the ability
to read the sheet,
product specification
provided by
MDia AMD and by
whatever chip company because
I think it's so important.
That's why sin value is
called siting value, right.
So this is a pronoun sheet
that we are going to
take as is study, okay?
And this is GPU spec provided by
NVDIa for their GPU current
generating GPU 100,
my lab has a few, and my
students really love that, okay?
And by looking at
this pronoun sheet,
you can see, the
first few rules,
what are you talking about?
It's talking about
the computing power
of this card, right?
One thing that you notice that
the computing power on
different cores are different.
That's why one core in immediate
is called tensor core.
That means they build
a core that is just
good for tensor related
operations, for example, metamo.
If we perform the same type
of precision, for example,
here, both of these
two rules basically
perform competition on 32
bits of floating point.
But if you use tensor core,
you get a number of
almost 1,000 Terra flops.
By the way Terra flops is
the unit that describe
the computing power.
We are going to
cover that later.
But basically number
higher is better, o.
But if you basically perform
the computing on
the normal core you
can see, it's ten times slower.
That's one type of
specialization.
Okay. GPU. Yeah, but
majority is centerc.
For this GPU, the
majority is center core.
Because this GPU is
manufactured for deep learning.
There are different
types of GPUs.
And it spends quite a few
rows to describe, um,
uh, the flops that is
for different precision.
And then it also specify
something that is important,
for example, the
memory bandwidth.
What is the memory bandwidth?
Yeah, essentially
moving things from
the GPS memory to
catch or to register.
That's the speed
term that we applied
when we do that memo,
and that number basically
determine how fast
it is to move a floating point
between memory hierarchy.
One interesting factor is,
if you read these flops,
you will see all these terms
comes with a star. So
what is that star?
It's a very small font,
you can see, marketing
people really cheating.
They're lying.
Okay. The star means
with sparsity.
That means if you want to
achieve the peak flops,
you have to apply a
sparsified competon.
Okay? And I don't know
why media does this,
but this is so confusing, right?
Because when you try
to buy a GPU you saw
your GPU can achieve
1,000 flops,
but it's only applied
with sparsity.
Does anyone know how many
it has without sparsity?
Sorry? Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, it's only half.
Yeah. If you apply
compution without sparsity,
it's only half of the flops.
That's why you need to learn
how to read product set.
Otherwise, when you spend
money, you need to be wise.
Please. Yeah, I why
explain that later.
Okay. So what does spars
mean? This is sparsity means.
I would like to appreciate
this plot again
for 10 seconds and try to
find the patterns
on the left plot.
Okay. Any pattern you you
found. Yeah, exactly.
In media, if you
are able to write
a kernel or a function,
that always perform computation,
subject to a constraint that
is average will only have
half elements and the rest
of them are basically empty,
then you basically
get these flops.
That is what sparsity means,
you can see this is
pretty hard to to do,
at least for me, I feel
it's very hard to convert
my original competition into
something that fits into this.
Cool. This is specially means.
This basically echoes what
I said at the beginning.
So one way you can
specialize your hardware
you make some course
that is so good at
some type of specified
competition.
That is what media does.
Okay, um, to continue
this case study,
you can also see if you
compare different
precisions the computation,
uh, the peak flops,
the peak computing power
also differ, right?
And we are going to
talk about this later,
and this is the fundamental
for quantization.
So what do we do in machinery
in quantization is we
try to quantize the
original precision,
for example, FP 32 all
the way down to FP eight.
Okay? And in media,
the reason people
really love quantity
is because of this,
if you are able to quantize
your original computation
into a lower precision,
you can benefit from more
powerful computing PC flops.
It will become
faster. Okay? Why it
can become faster, is very
easy to understand, right?
So original IP 32,
you have to operate on 32 bits,
but now you only
operate on eight bits.
Of course, it's four
times faster, right?
Okay. But the question
here I want to ask,
and I'm not going to give you
answer is why this could work in
machine learning programs.
Okay, think about that, right?
This is magical, right?
Because in many other areas,
which is not machine learning,
you reduce precision.
You are going to have some
errors, right on your results.
Yeah. But in margine learning,
this can be made work.
That's why immerge learning.
There's such big
field called qtison.
Okay. Cool. I think we finish
our kids study one, okay?
The next study is basically,
we try to read the product
sheet of Apple silicon.
What is Apple cooking?
So this is what Apple
cooking, right?
By looking at this,
you're basically saying
they are conveying
a message that
Michip can't do anything.
It can do video, it
can do machinery,
it can do graphics,
it can do anything, but
how Apple achieves that.
Okay? The way Apple
achieves that is basically,
you can see, this is a por okay?
And they are going to put a
16 core CPO in this corner.
Okay. And then for
the rest of areas,
this area are basically
put some control
or catches or whatever,
you don't care about it.
Okay. And in the area below,
what they do is they
put a 40 chord GPU.
So what happens is essentially
this M three Max is
mixing some CPU course,
which are super versatile
with some GPU course
which are not versatile,
but really good at memo.
So why Apple can do this?
Because Apple is a
software hardware company.
So they can optimize
their operating system in a way
that if there's
something that is
related with machine learning
with Mtmo I'm going to
dispatch my program to
run on this course.
But if something that
is normal, for example,
dit a doc, I'm going to
dispatch the computer
here, right.
No one else in the world can
do this because they
cannot do software,
hardware co opplementation.
Does that make sense?
Okay. Okay. That basically
finish our second is study.
I hope it's interesting.
Okay? I hope to teach you
some economics in
Cynic Valley, okay?
Is it sorry?
Yeah, Intel is
studying doing that,
but they are catching up.
Yeah. And also, Intel does
not own software layer.
Mc OS is Apples,
right? Windows is Microsoft.
Okay. Okay. The third study
will wrap up this lecture.
Okay. Let's try to see what's
going on and what people are
innovating Cynical Valley.
So what they are
trying to how you can
beat MD Apple to monopoly, okay?
I believe most of you
already heard about this,
um, three companies, Grock,
cerebrus and Sabava.
Okay.
These are three companies
that are basically trying to
manufacture a new
next generation
of chips that are so good
at machine learning.
So what are the cooking, Okay?
So they basically fall into
the sort of category I mentioned
in my previous slides.
They are trying to tune
the configurations,
for example, catch
size, uh, memory, uh,
like register size, to make sure
that they try to
find a combination that works
best for certain workloads,
for example, language
model inference.
Okay? And if you look at
this performance chart,
you can see the chips produced
by Grock on this workload,
which is basically trying to
generate tokens from Lama,
it can achieve almost ten
times faster than the rest.
The rest of companies are
some endpoint companies,
startups, very
famous ones, okay?
But they are bit so hard by
Grogu the rest of companies
are all adopting media GPUs.
This is basically the power
of reinventing hardware.
Okay. I don't think
you can achieve
this on software level,
but we're still
going to study that
okay because it's
a software class.
The reason it can
achieve this is
basically if you compare
the product sheet of
Grock card media,
you will find a key
difference that
is there's a line called SRM.
What is RM? Okay, fine,
you don't understand it because
I'm going to teach
that next week,
but you can understand SRM
as something similar to LON cat.
It's basically a layer
in the memory hierarchy,
but it's not a memory,
it's faster memory,
but it's slower
than register. It's
a layer there.
And if you compare the SRAM
says on the left hand side,
you'll find this GR card
basically make a card
with 230 megabytes of SRM.
But if you compare to
the latest idea chip,
they only have 164
kilowatt of SRM.
That's how Grock wins,
okay. Why it wins?
Because if I remind
you about this loop,
you will find that suppose
this register is
equivalent to SRAM.
You can imagine if I
have a register of size
of 100 megabytes versus
100 kilobyts, which
one will be faster.
Because I can't tell my matrix
multiplication in a way that
is I don't need to even
move anything actually.
I just put everything
in my register.
That's why it's so fast.
I hope I give you
a high level intuition
what's going on here.
Okay, that pretty much
is all I have for today,
but I'm going to give
you two questions. Okay.
The first question is, I
want you to study B 100.
You should basically follow what
I teach you today
and you try to study
the pronoun sheet of B
100 and C. You know,
media is claiming that B
100 is continuing the
Morse law, right?
By Mrs law, it means
that every 16 months
you can double your
computing power.
I want you to answer
this question, how B
100 continue Morris law
compared to the previous
generation which is h 100,
o also B 200, which is
another generation.
Okay. The ultimate question
here is basically,
you know, OID stock
is like this, right?
Is buy it. Yeah. Okay.
And the question I ask
is so you already say,
I introduced the economics,
the dynamics in sic value,
how people manufacture chips.
But you can see,
there are many companies who can
make really better
chips than OIDiA.
But then what is OID mode?
Like why OID stock is so good?
Yeah. Yeah, the software.
One primary is the software.
And if you want to
be more precise,
I think the reason
is because Koda
they have Koda and other
chips do not have Koda.
And KODA will be our
next week's focus. Okay.
Thank you.