Okay, let's get started.
Yeah, thanks for coming.
Um, just to recap what happened
in last lecture, right?
So we talk about how to
make operator faster
in general, right?
And then we realize
that we have to use um,
accelerators because
the current CPO
is hitting a wall, right?
And then we start
talking about how to Um,
how to build
accelerators, right?
And we talk about the
accelerator market.
Okay? And in today's lecture,
we are going to continue
to talk about GPUs.
But before that,
let's do a few MCQs,
okay, to help you, okay?
And the first one,
I will give you 1 minute.
Okay, so which one? A. So so
the steel and the cost,
could you explain?
Uh huh.
So the IO is 12, right?
You load a load B and write
C. Be because A and B
are two D matrices,
so the shape is two by two.
So in order to load A, you
need to load four floats,
and we can't number
flows we load, right?
So we are pretty sure the IO
the denominator is basically 12.
Then the question is
how many compute here?
Oh second answer.
C. Okay?
The answer is actually D. Okay.
So this is something that
I have to introduce,
and you guys need to memorize
because this is
very fundamental.
So one important note
that you need to know is
the flops of basically flop
is a major that we count
how many floating
point operations we
do for operator flops
for Mt M for this kind of form
where C equals to A and B,
where A and B are shape of
MN BP and the result
is M P. The flops of
this operation is it's two M and
P. Can anyone tell me why
is why there's two here?
Yes, exactly. You need to
count multiply and add.
Okay? Yeah. If you go and
um basically do this,
you'll find out how to
count multiple and add.
Okay? So basically, any form
of metamol you basically
get these flops, right?
And then on that line,
you say equals to Mmo A and B,
and it's basically two
times eight, right?
It's 16. Okay, 16/12.
Okay. The original
intensity is 1.3.
Yeah, okay. Very good.
One thing you want to compare is
comparing this program to
the program that I
presented last lecture.
Remember in the last lecture,
I use example where
you basically
perform a very simple add
between two matrices.
You'll find that the IO
is essentially the same.
I read two matrices and I
write the result into one.
But you can see
this one has a much
better response in
intensity, why?
Because metamo is very
dense competition.
If you know the fact
that basically,
when you use GPU to
perform this metamo
and use GPO to perform
that element wise ad,
they roughly take the same time.
That's why GPU is so powerful,
GPU can perform Metamo
much more efficient
than animal wise.
So this fact actually needs to
the kind of needs to design
many modern machinery models
because we really want to use
met M because at
least mathematically
met Mo is more expressive than
a simple animal
wise aisle, right?
But they take the same
time running on GPUs.
Okay? Very important, you
need to memorize this because
we are going to
use this to derive
the flops for language models,
yeah, down the road.
Okay? Second one, 1 minute.
This
is
the easy one, right?
So which one?
It's basically F, right?
Except F, all the others I
hope introduced in
the lecture, okay?
Okay. The third one?
Maybe half a minute.
This is the easy one.
Which one? A, right.
So basically, if you remember
the definition of
stress is basically
if we move along this dimension,
how many elements we
need to move along
the row major sequence.
So here I play a trick
that is I introduce
a very like a trivial dimension,
which is one, right?
So you basically just copy
this one here because if you
move along this dimension,
you just move one element, okay?
Cool. The last one.
Which one? C, right?
Yeah, let's go with one by one.
So cache telling
definitely does not save
memory on catch because
we are going to use more
memory in catch, okay?
And it reduce memory
between rhyme and catch,
not cache and register, right?
Okay. The one that reduce
this is basically
register telling, okay?
And this one, yeah, true.
Does it increase
arithmat intensity?
Yes, it increases, but
it's not because it
makes compute faster.
It's because it reduce IO, okay?
Cool. Yeah, that's all
it. And let's continue.
So today, to this
learning goal, okay,
we are going to continue
last lectures topic.
We are going to dive
deeper into GPUs,
and we are going to
talk about some very,
um, simple examples
in Cuda. Okay?
So, so this is a picture
that illustrating GPU,
let's parse this picture
a little bit because
this one is basically
quoted from dia,
it's very similar to
any other processors
you have ever
played with, right?
We have a global memory,
and we have some L
two, L one catch.
Okay? This is GPU
memory hierarchy
and we have some LO catch here,
which is one layer upper
than L two, right?
And we have some registers.
This is GPU memory hierarchy.
The thing that makes
GPU different,
you'll find that there are
so many things called SM.
Okay. And normally in CPU,
you just has a few course.
But in GPU you have a
definition called SM.
And SM defined basically stands
for streaming market
prorocessor, okay?
And I'm going to
talk about this.
So in GPU, we have a few
very basic concepts, okay.
And the first concepts
are basically
kernel threads,
blocks and grids.
Okay. And we probably
want to talk
about talk from threads.
So threat is basically
the smallest unit to
process the chunko data.
That is the thing that is
actually working in GPU is
basically a thread, okay?
And a thread basically
corresponds to the acuda core,
okay or tensor core on GPU.
And this core is
basically those ALU,
like you embedded
into your GPU, okay?
And I know then we also have
the definition of block,
and block is very
easy to understand.
It's basically a group of
threads that share memory.
So in GPO, we group
some threads together
and we form a block.
Okay? And this block is
the thing that makes GPO
slightly different from CPU
that is remember
in this picture,
we have so many SMs.
Okay? So roughly each SM
streaming microprocessor
will corresponds to a block and
each block has
many many threats.
And this all these threads
will compute in parallel,
oh for some given task.
And then we have another
higher layer concept
called grid and grid,
you probably already
infer is basically
a connection or blocks that
ascue the same kernel.
So what is a kernel? Kernel is
basically how we call GPU code.
We don't call it a program.
We call it kernel.
It's a fancier name, okay?
In other way, we
basically know like in
GPO we roughly launch
a kernel to grids
right then Griz launches
things into blocks and
blocks give those
things to threads.
And there are some kind
of hierarchy between
all these three layers.
Okay? Any question?
Cool. This is a thread,
like I said, it
actually doesn't work.
It's a los level worker
and it basically corresponds
to a quota core.
And this is a block block
has so many threads,
and we are going to map some
computation to a block.
And what I mean by mapping
the commuting into a block,
we map the commuting
into all the threads in
a block and each thread of
the block will take a part of
the computation because
remember in the last lecture,
I mentioned GPO is basically for
SIM D single instruction
multiple processing.
You ask you the same program,
but you ask you the program
on different partition
of the data.
Yeah, that's how we split
work between different
threads of the block.
Okay. And this is grid,
a grid is basically
many many blocks.
Then given these definitions,
I want to ask you
a few questions.
When we say that a GPU is more
powerful, what do we mean?
When we say H hundred is more
powerful than A 100 or do we?
More flops, when you reflect
this on thread on the
blocks what do we mean.
There are three
meaning, The first one
is you probably have more SMs.
You can build more SMs into GPU.
And that's what media is doing.
We build more and more
SMs every generation.
Okay? Because when
you have more SMs,
you have more threads and you're
better, you're more powerful.
Or we can build more
cost per exam, right?
That is we increase
the number of threads
in streaming
multiprocessor, okay.
And each thread corresponds
to, like I already said.
Okay. Or we can build
more powerful cross.
But this line is
actually hitting wall,
like I said, because we are
subject to the physical limit.
Yeah, the cross is nanometers,
that we are not able to
reduce it anymore now.
Okay? So roughly,
if you look at the
immediate trajectory,
they are basically doing
these two things. Okay? Yeah.
Every year, release
a GPU with more SMs
or probably more
cross per SM, okay?
Okay. Let's look at how
media release GPUs,
This is a timeline that
I get from Internet.
And I think there are
some code that you want
to get from here that
is this is a product line
that we do for deep learning.
Okay. It starts from a
code called P P 100,
and that was released,
about ten years ago, okay?
It's very weak DP today.
But at that time, I think
it's still quite expensive.
You have to pay like 20 k to
purchase one of these, okay?
And then we start, like,
evolving the
architectures from P
100 to V hundred to E 100 to
today's um, H 100, right?
And probably by the
summer of this year,
we'll basically going
into B 100, okay.
And meanwhile, you can
also see there are
a few other GPUs that is, um,
slightly lower
lower tier than is,
uh, this code with 100.
Okay? It's called p4t4 and P 80.
So this is another generation
of another line GPO media build
for you can think
it in a way that
is for those less
computation intensive jobs.
Okay. And this is for
the more coming jobs.
Therefore, the GPU are a
little bit cheaper
than this one.
For example, less memory,
less exams or whatever, okay?
And this is roughly timeline.
And if we basically align
this with media stock,
and you can see
when it takes off,
it's roughly from here, right?
Yeah. When media
ships Ava hundred,
the stock price start exploding.
What happened this year?
I GBD The paper?
Yeah, GBD The paper,
was released this year.
And the real taking
off is basically here.
At this point, I think
the language model market
becomes very very
competitive and more and
more big corporate
want to purchase
and H hundred build
really large clusters,
and they are ordered from
Nidia and roughly
last year in 2023,
Nidia stock price growth
and, you know, yeah.
Crypto is another
reason, yeah. Okay.
Um, so another
interesting phenomenon
you want to be familiar
with is basically,
um, the number of
Ms and threads on
WDA GPU generating GPU
and how the market goes.
Basically, media is the
one that sells GPU, right?
But when you try to use GPU,
you don't directly buy
from media, right.
You actually use
from, for example,
Cloud from Abs from
GCP or whatever,
this kind of to Cloud.
Basically, there
is a layer of, uh,
infrastructure on top of media,
which build software, build
infrastructure for you, okay?
And um so for Vb hundred,
which is the one that
we use to trim many,
many models like a bird
in the bird generation,
for Vb hundred, we
have roughly 80 SMs.
And for each SM, we
have two case threads.
Okay, that's computing power.
Okay, you can actually This
actually give you a sense of
how many floating point it can
calculate per second
because roughly,
I can have this lumber that
is uh computing, right?
This lumber floating point
operating that computing
in parallel, okay?
Yeah. And then we fast
forward to Av 100, right?
That is the GPU
that is basically,
uh start twining GBD three.
And you can see what
media does is basically
increase the number
of SMs, 80-108.
But it keeps the number
of threads per SM.
Okay? And then we go to H
100 and we keep increasing.
We increased 108-144.
And from this hardware
specification,
you will notice the fact that
every time media shifts
a new generation,
the computer is
not double. Right?
Because if you count
the number of SMs,
apparently, this number
is a lot double of 108.
But how could the media
claim the fact that uh,
the mores law is
still continuing?
Yeah, that's because, uh,
in every generation
of the GPUs they
are building some lower
precision course.
So they advocate you
to use lower precision
to train departing.
And we use lower precision,
uh, and also when you
have slightly more SMs,
you indeed can double your
flowing point per second,
you have a new
generation of GPUs.
Okay? And then let's
play a very simple game.
Okay. So how much price
do you think this one?
Like, if you want to
get 1 hour or 100,
how much do you
need to pay on AWS?
Okay. Today, the price
is basically 3 hours,
$3 per hour per TPV
very expensive.
Okay. And when we evolve
from W 100 to 100, how much?
So if we count the SMS,
it should be roughly $5, right?
But the fact is, uh four, y.
And if we evolve 100-100,
how much and maybe
five or six, right?
But yeah, it's 12.
Okay. I increased
more than double.
In fact, if you go to ABS and
you try to run the H 100,
you are not going to get it.
You know why? Because all
these H hundred are basically
occupied by big corporates
train language models.
I don't think
students or faculty
in university you
are able to get it.
Okay. Yeah, it's
very competitive.
And I think by the
middle of this year,
ATBs and all the
cloud providers,
they are going to
shape B 100 and um,
but basically, at that time, we
will be able to get H 100.
So the academia is basically
one generating behind.
Okay? That's what
we are doing, okay?
Cool. That is a little bit more
about the GPU market
and the cloud,
and this is a huge
market, by the way,
yeah. And, um, cool.
So I will give you a
task that is, um, uh,
go and survey the price of
100 and the number of SMs,
uh we just going
into shape, okay?
And that is basically
the kind of
hardware architecture and
abstractions WDS GPU build
into Koda apparently is
the programming language
that WDA build for
developers to write
code on top of GPU.
It history about Koda.
So it was introduced in 2007
with MDS Tesla architecture,
and it has a C language
for programming GPU,
and its design exactly matches
the uh grade block and
read three layer hierarchy
I just introduced.
Let's dive into
it. Okay. And this
is a piece of quota code.
So for the understanding,
I also um,
put the grid on the
block definition,
uh, on the left
part of this slide.
And you can see, uh,
maybe you can parse
this one a little bit.
But this is actually
not quota code.
This is the CPU code,
and only this line
is quota code.
And you still remember
what we call this, right?
It's a kernel. We
call it quota kernel.
And what it does,
you can see, um,
I first do a few like,
uh, preparation before I
can launch the kernel.
And in preparation code,
what I do is I define some
dimension variables X and NY.
And then I define a
three dimensional array,
which is called a
threads per block.
Okay, three dimensional.
Okay. And from this,
you can see per block roughly
have 12 threads, right?
Okay. And then I also
define some three dom no
we called lumber blocks.
Okay? And the way
I do it is I use
the original shape
array to divide it by
sra per block in order to
get these lumber blocks.
It's also three dimsion array.
And then I start launching
Qunar kernel and
the grammar of Quada
kernel looks like this.
So this is where you pass
argument into the kernel.
And meanwhile, you get this
where you pass two metadata.
One is the three dom array
I just created called
lumber blocks.
The other is the thre per block.
And this basically means
you are going to launch
your kernel that will basically
run on this number of
blocks and this
number of threads on
TPU. Okay. Any question?
Cool. From this figure we can
actually figure out how
many threads and
blocks is going to
run Because this
is declared here,
very explicitly. How
many blocks will run?
So basically multiply
these two values, right?
And for this x is
12 and the first dimension of
threads per block is four.
So this value is three,
for this one is two,
we are running on six blocks.
And then how many
threads are running?
It's basically the
product of two values,
right? It's 72 threads.
Okay? So we are
roughly running on
six blocks with in
total, 72 threads.
So each block will
have 12 threads. Okay.
Clear. So we are
basically mapping
the community in
72 threads, okay?
Yeah, this is what I just did.
Okay? So remember when I write
that code where I mix
CPC and PC together, I
do some preparation.
In that preparation,
what I do is basically I
define the shape of the threads,
the three dimensional array,
threads under the blocks.
In Coda, there is a few uh,
definitions about that shape.
Okay? So here in this slide,
you basically definition.
We first have a definition
which is called a grade Dam.
Okay. This grade deem basically
defines how many blocks
I have that grade.
I have in one grade. So remember
in one GPO I only
have one grade.
Okay? So basically this grade
deem is the total number
of blocks in a grade
basically should be
equal to the number of SMs,
right in GPU because
each SM maps to a block.
So this grade dam basically
defines the dimension
of the grade.
And this will give you example,
this is a grade deam X
and this grid Dam Y.
If I index on this graded array,
I basically get one M which
is a block. Okay, here.
And then because my block
is arranged in a way in a grade.
So what I do is I will
have a block index,
basically help me index
which block this is.
Okay. And similarly, I
have a block dam why
I have a block dam.
Because a block has
many many threads,
so I have to organize them in
a way that I can
map my competition.
I also have a block D.
And in this figure,
you can see this block D is
basically three by three.
Okay? I organize nine
threads, into D in my block.
And finally, of course,
I have a thread index,
because thread is
the smallest unit,
so I have index to index them.
Okay. Then I have two questions.
So what is a great D?
So grade I always
equal to zero or one,
depending on how you
index it because
we only have one grade, right?
So what about thread dam?
It's also a trivial thing,
because it reduced to one.
Because thread is
the smallest unit,
so I only for eareads
one dimension.
Any question? Yeah. Sorry.
Grade ID is basically
index of the grade, right?
Because I only have one
grade, so the index is zero.
Okay. Cool. Okay, this
basically give you an
example of a coda program.
And in this a program,
what we do is basically try
to we try to add two matrices.
I think for this part,
you guys are already
for miliar I already explained
this is the CPU code.
And in addition to
this part of the code,
you also need to
implement the kernel,
this is basically the
implementation of the kernel.
So what this CPU part
of the code does
is basically it
launch a grade of
da threats and it
will basically so this call
will basically blocks,
um and until all the threats
you launch return. Okay?
And what it happening
is basically
you pass the array A, B, and C,
which is A and B are
the two arrays you want
to add together and C is
where you want to write
the results, right?
And you give this argument
to the qua kernel,
and this squaar kernel is
going to run this, okay?
And let's move our focus on
this quadar kernel, okay.
So there are some very weird
grammar in quata kernel,
but you have to remember it.
The way that you
define quata kernels,
you use some annotation.
For example, you give you
the global notation which
basically denotes a quaakernel
function runs on GPU.
Okay. And if you start
function with global,
basically, it means
it's a quadra kernel.
Okay. And, um, and of course,
you pass array into that, right?
But the interest thing here is
when you implement
quadra kernel, uh,
because this function is
going to run all the threads,
you launched from CPU.
So when you implement uh kernel,
you have to think
about like what
is the job of that thread.
Because we do SIMD,
so it split works.
So each thread will
take only a split
of the global data ABC.
So you have to think
in a way that what is
the job of this thread.
So in this program,
you can basically say,
what do we do is we use Block
index and block Dam and
thread index to get uh
get index over this
array A B and C, right.
And then we use
this array to index
a part of data and we
add them together,
and write the result
back to C. Okay.
Any question? Okay.
So the metal point
here is basically,
you have to use this
block dam thread index,
this kind of thing to figure out
what is the proportion of
data that you want this
thread to process on.
And then you write the
result back to the array.
And you need to also address.
You need to address
the memory in
the correct way to
avoid conflict,
because you cannot
write to array
where another thread
is also writing
to that why have a problem.
So we're essentially
writing SMD code, in perl.
Okay. Basically the essence
of GP programming is
you have to think in
this way and you
try to figure out
the most efficient way
that you can partition
the job and write this
kind of SIMD code.
Okay? One important thing
you want to note that when
we implement Coda on top of GPU
is we have a very clear
separation of CPU and GPU code,
apparently on this
host code, uh,
this is very easy to
understand and this
follows our intuition
of programming.
It's a serial code.
It basically ask
you line by line,
by a single thread on CPU.
But on the green part,
we have the device code,
and this code is a little bit
counterintuitive because
it is a parallel code.
It's going to be
launched on many
many threads in the GPU.
So, uh, it's SMD parallel
execution on GPU.
Then, I hope you understand
this part and I have
a few questions.
So what happens post
launching the kernel?
That is, if my CPU ask you
this code line by
line all the way
down to here and
after I launch this
kernel, what happened?
So suppose there's another
line of code here.
Will my CPU continue to
ask you this code? No.
Why?
A, my CPO will continue to
ask you the next lines of
code because like I said,
this kernel actually runs on
GPU and this code runs on CPU.
CPU code is 100% like a serial.
But once my CPU launch,
give this code dedicated
to GPU and it will
continue to launch
next line of code.
It's not blocking, o?
What if this function
has a return value?
For example, I return
the value to arrayed X,
then my code is
my following line
so my CPU code is going
to basically play some
other operations,
say operate on this array X.
What do I have? You
shouldn't do that.
That is very bad code because
this is something you
really need to remember.
If you launch your
da kernel, um, uh,
it's not guaranteed
that the returned value
will basically because this code
will run concurrently with
this code kernel code before
this kernel finishes,
if you operate on
the return RAX,
it's going to give you
undetermined behavior,
because you don't know if theta
or GPU has finished your job.
Okay? Uh, do you know what
is the solution for this?
So in CDA, there's a very famous
API called CDA synchronize.
So in order to block this call,
you have to add DA
synchronize here,
and that means that you want to
synchronize the execution
of CPU and GPU.
CPU has the CPO code
has to wait for
this kernel to return and then
continue the rest of the code.
Okay. And if you go to
Petroc and if you go to
the lower level of Petroc
you'll find in Petroc so
many coda synchronize
everywhere to make sure that
the user at a higher level,
they actually get
the values, okay.
Okay. One characteristics
of Koa program
is the threads are basically
explicit and static in programs.
So it's the developer's
responsibility
to provide this kind of
CPU and GPU separation.
You have to write a part
of CPU and then the CPU
you embed a few da kernels
and then another file,
you probably implement actually
provide implementation
of the a kernel, okay?
And also it's responsibility of
the developers to basically
explicitly declare the block
deem the shapes and
the threads number
threads you want to use.
And it's also the
developer's responsibility
to map the data to
blocks and stress.
At least, you have to think,
uh, in parallel in
your brain and,
you know, at least SIMD,
so you can launch the jobs
to many many threads, okay?
And this is one primary
reason why many compilers,
for example, torch dot compel,
they require static shapes
because uh if you don't
actually declare the ships,
then you have to do
a lot of padding
or whatever kind of
operation to make this ship
static in order to
launch these jobs
into explicit number of
threats that you declare
in quaakernel, right?
Okay. That means that
Koda is very very static.
It does not allow you to
basically declare
a variable number,
for example, blocks and threats.
Okay?
Any question? So
because of this,
I think when you start
writing a Ka program,
is very important to check
boundary conditions.
So what do I mean by
So here, I give you example.
In this a kernel,
what we do is, we
durt a control flow.
Okay. So what do we
do is basically we
check the value of X
and the way we get X,
basically, we use the
block index and read
index to index the value
from the input array, SMD.
Okay. And we check
the value of X,
and if X is greater than
zero, we do something.
Otherwise, we do something else.
Okay, this is the control flow.
And if you write this
kind of, like, um,
Koda kernels is not going
to be very efficient
because like I said,
Koda is very static.
So all the cores, they
basically operate at
the same pace and they have
to do exactly the same job.
But in this kernel,
what you write is
basically you are asking
different stress or courts to
do slightly different job.
So how Koda can handle
this kind of thing, okay?
So the way it handles
that is basically,
um, so it's going to,
for example, here,
I have eight cores, okay,
and we are going to basically
map to eight stress,
and we are going to map this
job to this eight thress.
So in the first step, we just
do our competition, okay.
At some point, we hit this E
and L s and we are going to
check if the value I get in
this thread is
greater than zero.
And in this example,
you can see, uh,
we have three threads that
basically return true,
and the rest return force.
So like I said,
Coda is very static.
So uh, it actually
cannot process this
kind of EFL sematic.
It cannot for some course
do this and for other
courses do this,
they have to do exactly
the same thing.
So how can I handle this?
So the way Coda handles
that is basically,
I'm going to make I'm going to
ask you the true branch
and then the first branch.
So for the true branch, when
I ask them I'm going to
actually do the work for
all the threads that are
with the value
greater than zero.
But for the rest of them,
I just put them
idle, doing nothing.
They have to wait.
And then I'm going to
ask you the else
branch, same thing.
As you can imagine, this
code is very efficient
because there are so
many idle times, right?
And we basically
call this bubbles.
In Koda, if you do this
kind of control flow job,
you are going to hit
a lot of bubbles.
No problem. Cool.
Then once we finish
this ELS branch,
we are going to proceed
with the rest of the job.
The reason could not do
this is because they want
to keep all the cross
on the same pace.
They have to exactly actue
the same thing at
the same time point.
Okay Actually,
this is a little bit irrelevant
from the global
picture of quota but
the reason I introduced
this because um uh,
here I give the definition
of coherent excusion and
divergence execution
is basically what
I described but with
a fancier name.
Coherent exclusion is basically
the same instruction
applied to all data,
divergence is
basically the case I
give it to you. So why
would care about this?
Um, Because if you guys are
familiar language modeling,
you probably know that in
language modeling there
the thing that we often
do is called masking.
Right? I do some attenting but I
mask something out because
I don't want that part of value.
A very common masking mechanism
is called the caudal masking.
Right. I always attend to
the previous tokens, but
not the future tokens.
And if you want to implement
this kind of masking in Coda,
it's going to be
super efficient way,
because I'm going to
check if that thing is,
uh, on the caudal mask, right.
And if it's in the cod mask,
I'm going to remove the value.
Otherwise, I keep
the value, right.
And this kind of mechanism is
very hard to implement Coda.
So how we can make
this fast, okay?
And this is going to be
something we study when we, um,
go to the um,
transformer park,
okay? Yeah. Cool.
That basically covers the
execution model for Koda.
Okay. And then we are going
to talk about the memory.
Um, so Koda memory model is
basically illustrated here.
Uh, you can see, um,
because you have a
horse memory, right,
which we often call emergency
system as RAM, right?
And this is basically
Quota memory.
We call it GPU memory.
Okay. So do you know
what is lower level,
like mechanism for
GPU memory today?
So it's called HBM,
high bandwidth memory.
Okay, it is much faster
than CPN memory.
So to distinguish this
today imagining system,
we call the CPO memory
called DRM, okay?
This is what we did last week,
right, for the telling.
Okay. And in the future,
we will use HBM to
denote the GPU memory.
Okay? It is a memory mechanism
that developed by media.
Okay. It has a higher bandwidth,
um, than host memory, okay?
So imperical, this
figure already tells
you how the memory works, right?
So basically, uh, CPU has
its own memory on the
computer and CODA devices,
for example, O OS GPUs,
they have their own memory,
which is called HBM, okay?
Okay. And the way
that computer manage
memory space basically,
I hope you still remember, so
how is the host
memory managed in OS?
We organize them
into pages, right?
It's called page memory, right?
We page all the memory together,
so we can index the pages, okay?
Um um but the Cut memory
is slight different.
So it has it has distinct holes
and device memory spaces.
Okay. Which means that if
you launch a CPU code,
that ZPU code is
not going to access
any pages in GPU memory.
Okay. And if you
launch GPO code,
the GPO code is not going
to access the pages in OS.
Okay? And also in GPO,
we do not actually explicitly
manage memory in pages.
Okay, we just put it as
entire memory pool, and we
will get it from there.
Okay. And in order to
populate the memory,
uh, between RAM and GPA model,
we do is basically we
use this API memo copy.
So we have to call Malloc.
And that Malloc also has
a prefix that is
called Koda Malloc.
We first Coda Mock
on GPO memory,
and then we do quota memo copy.
This memoco you basically copy
some memory from
the RAM to device.
Okay. And this device, uh,
you can see it is allocated
using Koda Malloc,
so it's part of
the quota memory.
Okay. Okay? This is a pretty
standard things, okay?
There's a little bit
more concept that
you need to remember
that is pin memory.
Okay? So when we see pin memory,
it is basically a
part of the RAM,
the host and CPO memory. Okay.
Um, the reason we have
pin memory because sometimes
we often need to move memory,
populate contents
between DRAM and HBM.
So we already once your
computer installed with Koda
and the media driver will try to
pin a part of the host memory.
So it can reserve this
part for this kind of
memory copy between
host and HBM.
And because media striver
basically reserve this
part of the host memory,
so it's not pageable by OS.
Okay, it's locked. Any other
protests cannot use that.
Okay? And in CUDA,
there are a few APS that they
can only use pin memory.
They cannot directly copy things
from HBM to any part
of the host memory.
They have to first
copy from HBM to
pin memory and then let
the CPU to do the rest.
Okay? Okay, that is
a higher level introduction
of how memory works in Koda,
and we are going to
dive deeper, okay.
We introduced the HBM.
But actually, we know
any device like this,
they have a memory hierarchy,
they have catches,
they have registers.
So how does that work?
From this picture, you can see,
internally, for each thread,
it has its own
private memory space,
it's even lower level
memory other than HBM.
It is a private space
only by that thread.
I must be faster because we
build this kind of
memory hierarchy, okay?
And also because each block has
many threads and that block also
has a certain memory
space where very small,
and all those threads
will be able to share.
All those threads in a block
will be able to share
that part of memory.
That means all those stress
can access that memory.
But stress in
another block cannot
actually access the
memory in this block.
Makes sense. Okay. And
as I already said,
you also have a
global device memory
which is called HBM, right?
That is every thread
can actually access
that part of memory.
And this part is
probably pretty large,
a lot of space, but
much slower, okay?
So why we make it so complex?
This is because we want to
make our program faster.
The reason we do
this kind of memory
has all because we want
to make it faster.
So in order to understand this,
um, I'm going to
give you an example.
So in this example,
what we want to do
is basically we
do a window average, okay?
And I think implement
this Window average is
very easy on CPU, right?
You basically looping
over the input array,
and you take every three
adjacent elements and
you take the average,
and then you write results
back into the output array.
Okay. Then my question is,
because we are going
to launch this to da.
So when we start writing the
da kernel for this array,
the way we think need
to be different.
We need to think
about which part
of this computation
can be paralyzed.
And then the high level
idea is basically we map
those part that can
be paralyzed into
different threads so they
can ask you in parallel.
Then my question is what
is the paralyzable part?
Yeah, exactly. So you
basically each thread to
grab three elements, right?
Computer average and write back.
And each operation
that is each operation
of computing the average of
three elements are independent
from other operations,
so they can be
perfectly paralyzed.
Okay? That's basically
our high level idea
that the hot rate is
square kernel, okay?
So like I said, every
three adjacent elements,
um, uh, can be reduced
as an output, right?
And this operation
is independent.
So I can basically map
them to different threads.
Okay? Um let's do that.
Okay, let's go
through this example.
So what I do is I start
from, like I said,
you need to its
users responsibility
to separate the
CPU and GPU code.
So I have to start
with my CP code.
And in my CP code, my
mission is trying to define
the block and thread ID
and their shape in order to map
their computon into these many
many threads on Coda GPUs.
So in this one, I'm given
array of one Kb one K, okay.
It's a pretty large array.
And what I do is I'm going to
allocate allocate enough
memory on my device.
Here I call Coda Mock.
I'm going to allocate memory
onto array called Dv input.
And the amount of memory
I'm asking is basically,
it should be times the
size of the float.
But here I ask one more.
Why? Because I want to handle
the boundary condition.
I ask two more because
remember when I loop
that array, at the
end of the element,
I how to read another
two elements,
for the output, I don't
know how to do that
because I'm going to just
write the results back, right?
So I ask Koda to
give me two arrays,
one for input and one
for output, okay?
And then I basically
launch my kernel, right?
In this kernel, what I do is,
I define some global variable
that is stress per block,
and, because I define this,
I can infer my
number of blocks and
it is undivided by
stress per block.
Okay. And I give this to them.
Okay? This is the CPR
part of the code.
I hope you still This
one is easy, right?
And then the rest of
my job is basically I'm trying
to implement this kernel.
Okay. And still
remember hw idea,
I'm going to let
each thread to fetch
elements and ever
read without back.
Right. Okay. So the high level
thing that I need to do in
this squad kernel is I first
index that thread, right?
And I make sure that thread
knows which is three
elements you need to fetch.
And I also make sure it
knows that where I
write the results back,
and I need to avoid
conflicts because I
cannot two threads read
into the same element,
otherwise, the value will
be undetermined, okay?
So this is this is the code.
I would like to take a
look at maybe 10 seconds.
Okay, this one is simple, right?
So this is my signature
of my Koda kernel.
I have to start with a
global like I already said,
because it helps the compiler
to identify this Coda.
And then I pass the arguments
into this Quota kernel.
And what this line is doing?
It's basically trying to index,
trying to figure out the
current thread index.
Okay? Remember, like I said,
the block ID, the block D
and thread ID, the
global variables.
So basically, each thread
remember their own value.
You just need to basically
code that value and
it all return out.
Once I have index, what
I do is basically,
I allocate a thread
local variable.
Remember this variable
is thread local,
only this current thread
consist variable.
And I'm going to basically
fetch the three elements,
and do my average.
Here, I have a loop which
basically perform
three times, okay.
And because I have this index.
I use this index to index
my input array, right?
And I read the index from
the current element to the
future three elements, okay?
And I basically
add them together,
and then this one basically
take the average,
right, and write the result
back into output. Okay.
So when you launch this kernel,
this kernel actually
run on one thread.
But because Kota is
going to launch this kernel
onto many many threads,
so basically they
run in parallel.
Okay? Any question?
Cool.
This is the one simplest
kernel we are going
to do in this class.
We are going to do much
difficult ones in the future.
Okay. Then I have two questions.
How many thread in
total here I launched?
It's basically one k by one
times one k. How many blocks?
This variable
basically gives you
blocks it's basically
eight K. Because here,
threads per block,
I define it as 128.
What I do is basically use
undivided by 128.
I'm going to launch.
Basically this kernel is
going to be launched on
eight k blocks where each
block has 128 threads.
Then you probably come
up with a question.
What GPU has eight
k blocks? Right?
Like I said, at
the beginning, uh,
today's H 100, they only
have 44 exams, right.
So welcome to that
part later, okay.
But in general, this
code is correct.
And in general,
you want to launch
more blocks than GPU has.
And this is called
oversubscription to GPUs.
And when we write GPU code,
we always want to
oversubscribe because we
want to keep all them busy.
And we actually know that
in GPU in Kota Bacon,
there's a scheduler that
is trying to schedule
a job one by one until
it finishes, okay?
So yeah, we finish
our first kernel.
Okay. So identify a problem.
You guys know there's a
problem in this kernel.
Otherwise, I'm not going
to talk about this.
It's not going to
be that simple.
Sorry? Yes, exactly.
So if you look at this,
so each thread is going to
read three elements, right?
But for adjacent threads, yeah,
it's going to read
adjacent elements
many many times, right?
So in this program,
what do we do is basically
for each thread,
we read three elements
and we have that thread.
So we read three times
and times. Right?
But the hall intuition
tells me that we don't how
to B when we calculate
this chunk of the results,
right, we actually don't
how to read for example,
this is one, two,
three, four, five,
we don't how to read 15 times.
We just need to read this
part of the content.
This is one, two, three,
four, seven times.
Okay. So in the previous kernel,
each t has to repeatedly
read the three elements.
Okay but ideally,
we should only read seven times
to calculate the five results.
Okay? So how to do this.
So this is basically why Coda
has shared memory, right?
Suppose we have
some shared memory
that all the threads in
one block or access.
What we can do is basically
we utilize this kind of
memory hierarchy, right.
We first read the seven elements
into the shared memory,
and then we launch this code
into all those threads
in another block.
And because those
threads in our block
can actually access
shared memory,
they don't have to read
directly from HBM.
They just basically
fetch contents
from the intermediate layer,
the shared memory, right?
So we only need to do
seven times, okay?
With that highlintuion,
let's try to dive deeper,
we are going to improve
this kernel a little bit.
We try to reduce
the lumber rates.
Okay. And here's the example.
I'm going to let you
look at this kernel
for maybe 30 seconds.
Okay.
Yeah, let's try
to go through it.
Okay? So here,
what we do is basically we
add this chunk of code.
For the rest is
roughly the same.
So what this chunk of code
is doing is basically first.
I try to declare a memory
space which I call support,
and this support has a size
of threat per block plus two.
The reason it plus two is
because I try to handle
the edge condition, okay?
One weird thing you find
is basically I have
another prefix,
which is called shared with
two double underscores.
This is how you
declare those shared
memory in Quota kernel,
if you pass this
to Quota compiler,
they know that you are
asking memory from
the shared memory in one
block across threads.
I ask for this memory,
and then um, I'm
going to, um, read.
I'm going to read the
input to the part of
the support and write the
results back to the support.
Remember, this index is
basically already
calculated here, okay?
And because I need
two more elements,
so I'm going to ask
the first two threads to
do a little bit more job.
Okay? This is not good,
by the way, right?
Remember, because this is the
I, this is a control flow,
which means that when the first
two threads are reading
into two elements,
all the other threads
are basically waiting.
I wit a little bit. I
produce a little bit bubble.
But that's fine.
Once I have this,
I basically add another line
which is called synchres.
This sync rise is quite
different from the Koda
synchronize I introduced.
This syncs basically think
all the threads in one block.
It tells all threats to wait.
Until all of you have finished
any code above this line.
And at this point,
I think the rest and then what
I do is basically
I do the sum job.
Um, I think for this loop,
the only difference is
instead of directly reading
from this input
which rests on GBM,
what I do is basically I read
the results from support,
which is the shared
memory that block.
Okay? So if you compare this
code to previous kernel,
what I do is basically, uh,
I save a lot of as in
the previous block,
in the previous
version of the kernel,
I basically do three
times 128 per block,
uh, because each
block has 128 res.
But in this kernel, I
only read 30 times 130,
which is almost three times
smaller than the
previous kernel.
And this kernel is much better.
Yeah, that's why I like Hua
needs to introduce
a shared memory.
Okay? And to summarize
a little bit, yeah,
there are two kind
of synchronize
sync threads and in
synchro threads,
uh when we call that, it
means that we need to wait
for all threads in a block
to arrive at that point.
Another thing synchronized
could not synchronize,
as we want to sync the CPU
code and the CPU code.
Okay? And that basically
answer this question, right?
So if you don't s here,
you CP code to continue
to execute without
waiting for results,
then you shouldn't actually
rely on the return results of
this uh kernel because
you are not sure
when it will finish,
your program is going to
have undetermined behavior.
Okay. Okay. That basically
wrapped up our first kernel.
Any question? Yeah.
Why we have what?
Which block? You mean this one?
What is the question,
by the way.
You mean, why we
allocate this support?
Y y plus two in this kernel,
we are going to launch
it into one block.
That block only
have 128 threads.
But we need to handle
boundary condition.
Remember, we need to scan the
array from left to right,
and we need to make
sure each thread
exactly has access to
the same elements,
same shape of inputs and
produce the same output.
We have to handle
boundary condition.
Okay. Cool. Okay. That
wrap up our first kernel.
In the next lecture,
we are going to do met
more Mt Mo is going to be
more complicated than this,
because we have
three layer loops
and you can already predict
that we are going to do telling.
We have to do telling on DPs.
But before that, I
want to introduce
a bit more on the
fundamentals of Coda, okay.
So when you launch this kernel,
um, uh, to dA to media devices,
what happen any C
plus plus code,
so what do you do is you
need to comple this code.
Okay. And after you
put you give this
code to compiler, uh,
the compiler is going to convert
this code into a very
low level instructions,
right, the processor
can understand.
So the compilers basically for
dA program roughly uh can
be summarized as this.
So it has some program
texts instructions, okay?
And it also has information
about the required resources.
Okay? For example,
in this program, uh,
because you explicitly define
the number of threads
and blocks you ask for,
the compiling
instruction is going to
contain the resource
requirement.
So in this program, the
resource requirement
is I need to I'm the user.
I'm asking for h 128
threads per block.
I'm asking for eight bytes
of local data per thread.
This is the local
data allocated here,
this kind of thing.
I'm allocating this.
I need this part of
memory to see the
temporary variables.
I'm also asking for 31
30 floating point spaces
of shared space per
red block, right?
This is the resource
requirement is kernel ask for.
Okay? Once you have this kind
of resource requirement,
what do you do is basically you
submit this instruction to CODA
to GPU and GPU
actually has built
in scheduler to schedule
this kind of jobs.
Okay? So let's see how
the scheduler works.
So the way that
scheduler works is
basically they try
to accommodate uh,
different requirements
of blocks,
threads or whatever kind
of memory requirement
that user could come up
with in their Ka program.
Okay? Uh, the user could ask for
a static but large number
of blocks that is,
for example, greater than
the total blocks
of the entire GPU.
And also GPU,
different GPUs have
varying number of SMS
or number of threads.
So but Koda is a
universal language.
It basically schedule all
these kind of things.
Okay? So the way this
schedule is basically,
uh it has a crestin that is, uh,
the thread blocks can be
executed in any order.
Right. This is a very
reasonable assumption because
your code is supposed
to be AMD, right?
Uh, because each thread basically
asks you independently.
So this assumption
is quite reasonable.
Okay? And then what the TPO does
is going to map the
thread blocks to cross,
uh using a dynamic
scaling policy
that were trying to fulfill
your resource requirement.
Okay? So basically
let's see this example.
This is our Window sum, right?
C we D equivalently, okay?
And we try to schedule the
kernel to many many exams.
Okay. What we do is basically,
um, we have this code here,
and we have a GPU.
Suppose we have a GPU
with only two SMs.
Okay? And the specs
are given below.
So if you uh,
slightly read this spec,
you can see, we have two SMs.
We have a few
stress in this stem
this SM has shared memory
space equal to 1.5 kilobytes.
Okay, very small.
Okay, so how will Koda
schedule this job?
So let's go through
them. So first,
the host sends Koda
kernel instruction
to TPU devices. Okay?
And then scheduler basically
maps the block zero to
the physical SM zero to the
first streaming processor.
And it will reserve
a few resources from this
streaming processor.
So how many resources reserve?
Because as I said, the
previous compiled instruction
said I need 128 threads,
and I also need roughly uh,
420 bytes of shared
memory, right.
So it will basically
split these per
resources for this
block of jobs.
And then because you
are asking for many,
many blocks, right, remember,
you are asking for
eight key blocks.
So but I only have two
blocks. What I do.
What I do is
basically, I'm going
to schedule the
one by one, okay?
I'm going to launch
the next block to
the second exam, okay?
And then I launch the third
block to the first AM,
right, because I
still have space.
And then I launched
my first one.
Okay. Then at this point,
I find that, um,
you can see the memory
here is already full,
because each block of job is
going to ask for, um, 430.
But my total SM only has a
shared memory of 1.5 kilobyt.
So when I try to
schedule my fifth job,
I find I don't have space.
This is basically called
oversubscription.
That means that Koda is going to
put the rest of blocks in queue.
It's going to wait
for this block to
finish and continue
launch and launch launch.
In this way, you can keep the
GPU utilization always high.
Okay? This is how
Koda schedule works,
okay? Any question? Yeah.
Sorry? It's basically
in media driver.
Yeah. Not in CPU, yeah, yeah.
Okay. Yeah, this is
what I just explained.
So basically, you have to
queue all the block jobs
and launch it one
by one depending
on the available resources.
And you can see this
is pretty advanced
because if you look at
today's cluster scheduler,
for example, Copernint slurm,
and they basically use
very similar things.
Yeah. Okay, that's pretty
much wrap up all the deep
technical contents of today.
Then we have some other
things to talk about, okay?
So let's look at how media
evolves your GPOs, okay?
So this is a very
famous GPU GTX line 80.
I think many of you
probably purchase
this for your GGiveF
playing games, okay.
And this can also be
used for deep learning.
Um, because now you understand
SMs and the stress,
we can look at the specs,
right at lower level.
So for this GPU you
roughly only have 16 SMs.
Okay. We very small number
because if you remember,
H 100 is 144, right? Okay.
And for shared memory,
that is how many memory
threads in your block here,
it only has 96
kilobytes very small,
ESM can offer you
roughly two k threads,
ESM physically have
128 quarter cross.
That is a spec, but here
you spawn a problem.
So why the number of cross
is not equal to
number of threats?
Because I said each core,
each thread is going to
ask you on one core.
Okay, this is a part
that I didn't cover,
so please check
out the readings.
In Koda, you can create more
threads than physical core.
There's one concept rap
and you have to
understand the part.
But that is too deep
because normally,
if you don't use
the concept of rap,
you can still write pretty
efficient quota code.
But if you want to go to the
level of flash in three,
you have to
understand rap. Cool.
That is a little bit further,
but try to figure this
out by yourself, okay.
And then let's compare this
gaming GPO with H 100, right?
What the media
does is basically,
you can see this thresher
block is unchanged,
still two k, quota cross
changed, still 128.
But shared memory changes a lot.
For example, when they evolve
this from the original
GTX to A 100,
we almost double
the shared memory.
But when we evolved
from E 100 to H 100,
we almost increased
by 1.5, not double.
We keep increasing the
the shared memory.
There's another name for shared
memory, it's called SRAM.
If you attend the last
lecture, you probably know,
SRAM is a very
critical resources
for for language
model inference.
That's why media, when they
evolve from 100 to hundred,
they try to increase SRAM.
We are going to cover why
this SRAM is so critical for
language model infracelaor.
But from this trend,
you can see media
is trying to increase
the SRAM memory,
also the SM apparently greatly
increased, almost ten times.
And as a result, the
flops increase a lot.
And these flops many comes from
changing from normal Quota
cre into tenser core.
Still remember
tender core tender
Core is very good at Mtmo,
and it can only do meto.
Okay, so why energy is so fast?
I will leave this to you.
Okay, I have readings,
and if you do readings,
you will understand.
Okay. Then let's try
to echo what I said
in the last lecture.
Remember, in last lecture,
I talk about accelerator
market, right?
So there's a company called
Grock that company
is crazy because
their language model
inference speed
is basically ten or
20 times medius.
And I basically tell you
that they do some kind
of adjustment on the
accelerator configuration.
So what is that adjustment?
Now you understand.
It's basically like they have
23 megabytes of as well.
So for each streaming
multiprocessor,
they almost 100 times
the uh 1,000 times of the
shared memory, compared to GPU.
And one weird thing
about this chip is that
they don't have HBM.
They only have SRM. Like,
they don't care about HBM.
The large part of
memory, they only build
SRM into this chip.
And because as I said, SRM is
a critical resources
language model inference,
that basically explains why it
is so fast at language
model inference, okay?
Okay, then that's pretty
much what I have today.
I have three questions
for you after class.
Okay. I think you can
find most of the
answers in reading.
One is, how about B 100, right?
I already left this
to last lecture.
Second is how does
the tentercre works?
Third one is why the
umber physical course is
not equal to the lumber
active threats in SM.
Okay? Thank you.
H