Okay, uh, yeah,
thanks for coming.
Let's Let's get
started, but today.
Yeah. Yeah, so let's do
a recap of last lecture.
So last lecture, we
talk about GPUs,
right, and Olympic Coda.
So what we learned is
the GPU execution model,
where we know GPU has
thread hierarchy,
from grade to block to threads.
And when you write the GPO code,
we call it a GPO
kernel and the way we
basically write that
code is basically we
launch that kernel to many
many threads through this,
uh thread hierarchy, okay?
And we know GPU has a
distinct address space
compared to the host memory,
and we call that GPU
memory or device memory
or HBM, high bandwidth memory.
And in order for
your program to access
this part of memory,
Coda provides you some APS,
like Mock Coda memo copy,
something like that. Okay.
And there's still remember
the definition of pin memory,
pin memory is a part of
the host memory that
is reserved for GPUs.
On the inside of GPO,
besides the HBM,
we also have other
memory hierarchy built
into the GPO itself.
We have per thread,
private memory.
For example, when we
write a GPO kernel,
when we try to ask for
temporal variable,
that variable was
basically created
in thread local memory.
And we have per block memory,
which we call SRAM, right?
All the threads in one
block can access memory.
And the way we
access that memory
is we use prefix called shared,
under square shared, okay?
And like I said, we have HBM,
which is the global
device level memory.
And we also touch base on two
synchronization primitives.
One is the synchronization
between CPU and GPU.
The other is the
synchronization between
all the threads in
one block, okay?
And we also finish our
first GPU program,
which is the Window average or
equivalent com one D, okay?
Cool. Okay. Today's
learning goal,
we are going to grind
the math mo on GPU.
We'll probably spend half
of the class on that.
Then we basically finish
our GPU programming class.
Okay. And we're going to
talk about how we can there
are some other
alternative methods
to make operator faster,
which is basically compiler.
So we are going to
talk about compiler
a little bit, okay.
Um, yeah. And if time permits,
we are going to basically wrap
up this operator
augmentation layer,
and we are going to
touch another layer
which is graph ogenation.
Cool. Okay. So before
we get deep into Koda
programming on met,
we try to basically, uh,
change your way your normal
way of programming, right?
So before we try to
program some Koda,
we need to do a few things.
So you need to
convert your brain
to SIMD because Koda is SMD.
Okay. So whenever I give
you say operator and I
ask you to write a Koda,
you should think
about three steps.
The first one is
you should identify
the work that can be
performed in parallel, right?
And then you partition the work.
And also you need to partition
the data associated
with our work, right?
And then you map
the partition and
the data partition to
Koda thread, right?
And you implement the
logic in that oda kernel.
And GPU will basically
launch your code onto
many many threads, okay?
That's the way how you think
when you program Coda.
And in order to make
this program fast,
I hope you still
remember how we improve
our CdI programming for
the C D last class, right?
So first, we need to make sure
we oversubscribe the GPUs.
We create a lot of
partition work,
and we try to push all of them
into the limited number
of blocks on GPU,
That is called oversubscription.
We also need to
mitigate stragglers.
We don't want to we want to
part workload as
equal as possible.
So every thread roughly get
the same workload, right?
So we don't want to write
those kind of ELs, right,
because some thread
will get work,
but other threads are not, okay?
And we need to minimize
communication.
And here, communication
means we need to
minimize the data movement
between memory hierarchies,
we should use the shared
memory as much as possible.
Okay? But subject to
their constraints, okay?
Cool. Then let's get started.
So we're going to do this,
right, S equals to A,
Mtmo B and this
basically give you visualizing
what is Mtmois doing, right?
And let's follow our
three steps, right?
Let's try to first identify
work that can be
performed in parallel.
So what is the work that can
be performed in parallel?
So basically, every time
we can grab a row on A and
a column on B right and we
just do a dot product
between row and columns.
So we basically can get
one result entry in C,
and all this row
and column product
can be done in parallel.
So the most straightforward
implementation for
this kernel is basically we
do what I just described.
Each GPU thread to grab one
row and one column, right?
And then we launch them to
many many blocks with threads.
Okay? And in order to
write that kernel, uh,
what do we do is, we
basically each thread
compte one element,
and we ended up
with this kernel.
And please look at that
for maybe 15 seconds.
Okay, yeah, let's try
to go through it.
So this one is
three, four, right?
We have matrix we have to
matrix which is the dimension
N here N is roughly 1024.
And we are going to
ask for a few blocks.
Here we ask blocks of the
shape of 32 by 32, right?
Two dimensional blocks because
this one is trivial, okay?
And because we are going to let
each thread to computer
one element, so in total,
we need to ask for 1024 threads.
That's why thread per block
is also this shape. Okay.
And this is our
kernel launch, right?
This is CPU code. We ask CPU
to launch the kernel to GPS.
And then we go into
this kernel, um,
and what do we do is
we use the block ID,
block D and thread ID to
get index for each thread.
Here, we let the
X to take care of
the row from the A left matrix,
and we use Y to index
the column of B, right?
And then what do we do is we
create one variable per thread.
So this variable we'll use
the the thread local memory,
right, because we don't
use the shared prefix.
So this will be allocated
on thread local memory,
which is essentially
registers, okay?
And then we loop over, we board
this dimension, right? Okay.
And what do we do is we
will grab one element,
it them together, and we
will accumulate results
into this result, right.
And eventually we this thread
to write the result back into
our result array C. Okay?
Makes sense, right?
So basically, we launch
one K threadach thread
taking care of one element.
Okay. Okay. So let's try
to analyze the memory,
the IO, right, because
we care about that.
Okay. So the global
memory rate per thread is
basically each thread need to
read one row and one colom.
So it's basically two N, right?
So so how many threads,
I already said is
unsquare threads, right?
Because that thread should be
corresponding to the
shape of the result,
number of elements
in the array, okay?
So the total memory access is
essentially unsquare
times two, right?
Is cube.
Okay, that means in order
to launch this kerdle,
we need to read
the global memory,
read the content from HBM
to register this
many times, okay?
And how many memory will
use thread local memory?
So basically, we only use
one float per thread, right.
Okay. That is the basic
version of Mtmo kernel.
I hope this makes sense
to you, straightforward.
And you know what we are
going to do next, right?
We are going to improve this
because this one is not good.
According to the class we
did for CPU MTM, you know,
we can actually use
more memory from
either thread local memory
or from the shared memory.
And we can do telling, right.
So we are going to
apply telling to
this CPU kernel, okay?
Another intuition, I don't
think I need to repeat.
That is, by looking at this,
P memory hierarchy, we know
we have some additional
memory we can use.
One is the register,
that is local memory,
the other is shared
memory as well.
Okay, so we'll try
to utilize them.
Okay. So how do
you utilize them.
So instead of letting,
yeah, please.
Is the amount of registers,
similar to how much registers
CPU? It's slightly different.
So in GPU,
usually one streaming
multiprocessor
have a fixed number of threads.
And those threads are shared by
all those registers are
shared among all the
threads in that block.
Yeah, yeah. Does that
make sense? Okay.
Which means that if you allocate
more register per thread,
and you are going to
have less threads.
If, so then you need to share
some register built into
that stream
multiprocessor, okay?
Oh.
No, register is
definitely much faster.
Yeah. Okay. Okay, cool.
So our first step
to improve this we
try to utilize a little
bit more on the register.
So in the previous program,
we only use one register per
spread now we are going
to use a little bit more.
And if you recall the telling
register telling in CPU,
what we do is we
let u in a loop,
we do some memory reuse, right.
We let each, each
loop we read a little bit
more than one element,
so we can do more memo.
So here, the high level idea is,
um instead of let
each thread compute just
one element in the result.
We can let E thread to
compute a V by V sub matrix.
And this V is apparently
our telling factor.
It's very similar
to the CPU telling.
This figure basically give
you a high level idea.
So instead of computing
that one element,
and I'm going to extend
it a bit into V by
V. I'm going to let E
thread to grab a few rows
instead of one row from A
and a few columns inside
of one column from
B. I perform some sort of
submetrix multiply and I
write the result spec.
So why this can reduce memory?
Because if you look at B,
from the perspective of B,
every time I read the B,
I can reuse the previous read
from the ad of A, right?
So there are some memory reuse.
Okay. Let's try to
implement this kernel.
Okay. Please take a look at
this kernel for 30 seconds.
Okay.
Okay. Yeah, let's
pass this program.
Okay. So from the
previous program,
I think the main difference
here, in the previous program,
we directly index, the
thread index one
element from A and B.
But here we are trying
to index a block, okay.
Another difference is we are
allocating array
in the register.
So which means that we are using
we square registers, compared
to the previous one.
And we are also allocating
random array, okay?
And what do we do is
basically, uh, every time,
I'm going to read this
row and read this column,
I'm going to type them
together and write
the results accumulated
results and
then write it back to here.
Okay? And I'm going to
read a little bit more
because I'm going to read
all this into the register.
So when I scan
through this from this
column to this column,
I can reuse my previous
read on this area, okay?
So that we ended up with
this loop that is, um,
I'm going to first index
for this current thread,
I'm going to first
index which block
I'm going to read, okay?
And this is basically the index,
X space times V plus X. Okay.
I use my thread index to
index the area I
need to read from A.
And then I'm going to
do the similar thing for
this column here, okay?
And once I get to
this row and column,
I'm going to perform
another inside of, like,
a reduction loop where
I do a dot product
between those elements
of the row and
columns and cumulal
results, right.
And eventually, I will
write the results back
into this particular
block for this thread.
Okay. So here, compared
to the previous version
of the program,
uh, this program did a
little bit more work, right?
So it computes the results of
the entire BV instead of
just a single element.
So you can also get a high
level sense that is we
are going to if the matrix
shape is unchanged,
we are going to
need less threads
because compared to
the previous one,
we need squared
threads, but here,
definitely, by a factor of
divided by a factor of square.
Okay? Let's try to
analyze the memory IO.
So global memory
rate per thread.
So it's V plus U square, right?
So why is NV plus U square?
Because we are going to
basically read this part, right?
And also, we are going
to read this part.
That's all our read.
Okay? And this part is
only tied to this
outside loop, right?
But this part is tied to
these two loops, right?
And every time we are
reading an elements.
Okay? So that is why this
is square on this V, okay?
Cool. And how many threads?
So compared to the
previous version,
we are doing undivided
by times undivided
by wave threads,
now we only need unsquar
divided by w squared threads.
Okay? So the total
global memory access
is basically we market
them together and we
get this element.
Compared to the
previous version we
did we have been doing
a little bit better.
In the previous version, we
basically have two cube.
Here we have one cube,
which is basically divided
by the factor of V,
so we reduce a little bit.
Okay. And for memory,
like how many register we use.
So this is the memory
we use, right?
We use basically Wquare
plus two float per thread.
Okay. Are we good with this one?
Cool. So, I think the
high level idea of
this one is going to
is basically we like
each thread to compute a
region instead of one element.
But from the title of this,
you know, this is just 1.5,
and we can do a little bit
better than this region.
So we all follow the
same idea as, um,
we still like each thread
to compute one region,
one result region in C.
But can we still, improve
this program a little bit,
so we don't have to,
like, read this many times.
Anyone has an idea here?
So one efficient you find
is when I do this
kind of tiling,
every time I basically read
one row from A and
one column from
dira I basically do a
dot product together.
And for each read
of the row here,
we are going to read we are
still going to read
B multiple times,
here the way we
read the elements
from B is still cube, right?
So can we do better
here? We can right.
So there are two ways of doing
multiply multiplication.
You can do a row by column,
um, uh, door product,
and you directly get the
results on one element,
but you can also do column
by row product, right?
You pick you first locate
that small region from here.
And you grab one
column here, right?
And you also grab one row here,
add them you multip
them together and you
get you get one result matrix,
which is the shape of V by
V. But this V by V is not
the eventual results
we need, right?
So in order to get
eventual results,
what we do is we can scan from
here and we scan from here
and we basically read
one small column here,
one small row here.
We basically get one
region of results.
And then we read one column
here and one small row here,
and we get another
region of them.
And this is called partial sum.
So every time we
get a partial sum,
and what we need
to do is basically
we add all the partial sum
together and we get
the eventual results
of this region, right?
And in this pattern, you can Oh,
for A, for each route,
we still read the entire region.
And for B, we are doing
better because we only need
to scan the entire region
once instead of times,
right? Let's see this.
Okay. Mathematical
mathematical intuition
behind this is basically,
in order to get
that result matrix
here, there are two ways.
One is a row by column.
But we can do it differently.
That is we can basically break
this region into sub
matrix like this.
For example, we break
this X into X one,
X two, many many columns.
And we break this Y
into Y one, Y two.
And we find that this region can
actually be expressed as X,
Y one plus x2y2.
Right. And if we break into
many many small regions,
we find that in order to
get this part results,
we only need to read this
time once and read this once.
And in the previous version,
we need to read this once
and read this cube times, right?
So that is the intuition.
And we are going to follow
in this intuition and we try
to modify our previous program,
progress kernel into
this version, okay?
Please take a look at
this kernel little bit.
Yeah.
So you mean,
where I get this?
Uh huh. Yeah, you
get the by, right?
And then you just
scan from left,
right from top bottom
of my asthm altogether.
You get the by V. So that
you multiply two s get one Yeah,
in the previous, I
read this, right?
I read this, this entire row.
In the previous I read
this entire row, right?
And I read this entire column,
I get one element out.
And in order to get
this second element,
I need to read I read this
and I need to read
this one again, right?
Yeah. So basically, for
each read of this row,
I need to read all
this column one.
That's why it is square, right?
But in this one, I just
need to read this and this.
Yeah. Does that make sense?
And that basically
give you intuition
why this memory are
always smaller.
Okay. Yeah, uh, I
think this program,
once you understand this, uh,
block wise, matrix
multiplication
and partial sum, you
understand this program.
So what it does is it still use
that block index and block
D and also thread index to
locate this region, okay?
And once it locates the region,
it's going to create the exact
same amount of registers.
Okay. But instead of like I
loop I loop over the rows
of A and the column of B,
I'm going to loop over the
columns of A and rows of B.
Okay? That's why there's
outer loop K, right?
This K basically scan
following this direction.
And every time I'm going
to grab a small area,
right here, is this
area and this area.
And I do dot product. Okay?
And then I add all the results
together into this region.
And I add all the partial sum
together and I get the by.
Okay. And let's try to
analyze the memory IO.
So the global memory
rate per thread
is noise and squared, right?
So it's much better, okay?
And the number of
threads we need
is basically, uh, same, right?
Divided by w and nib.
And squared divided
by way square.
The total memory access is,
we multiply this together,
and we find that for
both the cubic term,
we can divide them by.
Okay? And the number
register we need is also
we square plus two,
essentially this
part we allocate.
Okay. Cool. Are we
good with this one?
Yeah.
So you mean,
yeah, you can swap them.
It's fine. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. Doesn't matter.
It's just like messes
make like this.
Yeah. Okay? Okay, cool.
This is already a pretty
good version of Mtmo.
I think in many today's
machinery frameworks,
if you only have
one layer of memory hierarchy,
you end up with this one.
Okay? But we are not
ending here, right?
So we know we have another
layer of memory hierarchy.
That is we want to use
our shared memory.
Okay. So our initial
content was here, right?
And we have to go through
this memory iarchy we read
it from here to shared
memory then to registers.
Okay? Now, we are going to
make things more and
more complicated.
So how to basically leverage
shared memory and try
to implement this two level
telling or math on GPS.
So here, the intuition is
still quite straightforward,
but the coding is a
little bit difficult.
Okay, uh, in the lecture,
I'm going to focus on intuition.
I think it's very hard to
if you are new to this,
it's very hard to explain
this very clearly to you.
So please put time on
this on the program.
But I'm going to
give you intuition.
So here, if you still
remember the uh,
met M in CPU right,
remember that program,
we do two level telling.
The thing is basically we keep
telling and telling
telling, right.
We do a recursive telling.
We first tell it at some
shape and then inside
of that small shape
we're going to
tell human smaller ship matrix.
So here, what we do
is we try to let
know we are using the SM,
which is shared memory.
Remember shared memory
is at the block level.
So all the threads in
one block is going
to access to that shared memory.
So what we do is
we let each block
to compute a region, right?
And this region is
denoted here as L by L.
And then we know that
inside of the block,
all the threads can
access that shared memory
so they can work together
to calculate by, right?
And then for each thread,
we are going to let
them to compute
a smaller sub region
from this by L, which
is essentially by.
Okay. And white telling
can help because
of memory we use,
right? So think about this.
So when we compute
this small regime by,
right, we essentially
need this row.
We need to read this row, right?
And these are many roles,
not just a single, this
block of rows, okay?
And we need to read this
part of column, right?
But when we compute this
regime, what do we need?
So we still need the many rules,
right? But we need to read this.
This is the hoteling
works because
if we basically perform
some reading ahead of time,
that is we read this part into
the shared memory and
keep it there, okay?
And then at the thread level,
we are going to iterate through
the many many columns so we
can basically have some memory
reuse for this reading.
Therefore, we save
some memory, okay?
And same thing, right? And
you can basically do this.
Okay? This is tally. And I'm
going to show this
program a little bit,
maybe give you 30 seconds.
And I think this one is hard.
Yeah. Please spend some time
later after the class
to understand this one.
Yeah.
Okay, I'm going
to give you some
high level things.
Okay, so you can think
about sync either way.
First the difference you
noted is this line, right,
where I started using
this prefix to allocate
memory from SRM.
A? So I allocate two
chunks of memory,
one is SA, the other SB.
Here, I simplify a little bit
because we should allocate
one of the shape
of S by L and the other
is the shape of L by S.
But I basically unify
them a little bit,
because you can think
that I transpose
the matrix a little bit, okay?
So I'm going to allocate memory
for this part and for this
part in shared memory.
Okay. And what I'm going
to do is I'm going to scan
from here to here and here
to here at the block level.
Okay? And I like each block
to basically scan
from here to here,
here to here and
compute this part.
And inside of this block, what
I'm going to do is I will like
each thread to read
a little region
of this and a little
region of this.
Right. I have another inner loop
that basically let me
clean this a little bit.
I have another inner loop
which basically reads
a small area of this and
I scan from here to here.
Sorry, from here to
here and here to here.
This is recursive, one
is basically telling at
the block level and the
other is basically telling
at uh the thread level.
Okay. I'm going to
first use my block index to
index this region, right?
And this is what I'm doing.
I'm indexing it regi.
I basically start reading
things from HBM
because it's A and B,
allocated on HBM, I
reading things from GBM
to my shared memory.
Okay? And the and
this line of code is
problematic because if you
still remember the window sum,
in the Window sum example,
when I try to let
all threads to read
things from GPM to share memory,
what I do is I need to
also partition read,
I only let each thread
to read one part of it.
And this is called
cooperative fetching.
I think we covered a little
bit. Still remember?
Okay. And here I simplify
this code a little bit
because we are going to
cover how we implement
this chunk later.
But the high level idea is you
cannot just let all threads
to read all the regions
into shared memory because
this shared memory
is going to be
accessed by all the
threads in the block.
So each thread only is
responsible for
reading its own part.
Yeah, I hope to write some
code part in I
read a little bit.
Okay. And if you still
remember the two sync threads,
why we need a syn thread here?
Yeah, it's shared memory.
I need to wait for this
to finish the job,
and then I can start access
that part of memory, right?
Otherwise, there will be
undetermined area,
undetermined behavior.
Why I need this single stress?
Because I want to avoid that
one thread properly finish
the computation here and
come back to the next
iteration of that loop,
I want to avoid that
thread to start reading.
I want to make sure
all threads finish
the computation and basically
accumulated results,
and then I add
a barrier and I start
reading new contents.
That is the next columns here.
So that's why I need to add
another barrier here, okay?
So with this barrier, you
understand that this loop
is doing is basically reading
this area, reading this area.
Okay? And then what we do is
basically this is something that
we have been talking about
in the last slide, right.
We basically use ress level
telling to handle the
multiplication of this.
Okay? We each thread to
take a smaller region
from that and we have
another three layer loop,
and you can see,
this is like we are
accumulating results
from all the way
from here to here
and inside of this.
So we are adding all
the results together
into the result entry, okay?
Yeah. Like to report
about the control and
the here in this program,
I don't think there's
a control flow, right?
It's very unlikely. It's very
unlikely, but just in case,
because sometimes
maybe one core get
a little bit higher
power than the other.
Yeah, because of physics.
Yeah, it really is.
But I spell this is for
the safety of the code.
Because you don't
know if this happens,
it's very hard to debate. Yeah.
Okay. Okay, spend some time.
Basically, what do we do
compared to the
previous versions,
basically at this area?
Yeah, this regional code that
basically telling
at the block level.
Similarly, we do we can do
calculation on memory IO,
and I'm going to
present results to you.
I'm going to leave
this to yourself.
But I think this
part is easier than
understanding the code
because what you do is,
uh, you basically read the loop,
and you count how
many registers and
shared memory allocated and
how many IO is happening
between memory hierarchies.
Okay. Looking at
this part, right?
I said this part of code is
problematic because if I
read my code in this way,
that means that all my
thress is going to read
the entire region into the
shared memory, which is wrong.
First, it is it is slow. I
don't how to do that, right?
Second, um, there will be
some conflicts, for example,
some threads reading things
into that register, sorry,
that shared memory entry,
another thread is doing
the same thing and
they are going to
have some conflict.
So what do we do is we need
to change this protocol,
and this is a very
very common approach
in GPU called
cooperative fetching.
That is all fetching memory
from one source area,
for example, GPM into
a destination area.
And this cooperative
fetching also need to be
implemented in a
way that is SMD.
So we need to it's the
developer's responsibility
to think about which region,
which is separating
that should be
responsible for and
try to calculate
the offset a little
bit and let us
write to fresh things and
write things into SM,
into into into the
uh, shared memory.
And so the true implementation
of this line should
be looking like this.
And I will let you guys look at
this for 15 seconds
because I think this
one is easy, okay?
Okay.
Um, so if you are
familiar with C plus pass
programming and indexing,
you know what you've
been doing, right?
So basically, for this
block of threads,
I'm going to get a thread ID,
and then I use thread
ID to calculate
which entry are responsible
for this current thread.
And for this current thread,
I'm going to only I'm going
to index that element I'm
responsible for reading and
read it into shared
memory, right?
Yeah, very standardized
offsetting indexing code,
in CPlusPas Okay, cool.
That basically is,
in my opinion,
the second most difficult
code in this class.
Okay. And we are going to
touch base with flash
teaching later,
and that one will be more
complicated than this one.
But this is the
second difficult.
So as long as you get a good
understanding of this code,
I think you already finished
half of flashing teaching. Okay?
A good? Cool. Okay,
let's wrap up this part,
okay, because we have
been doing a lot of
GPU programming in the
recent two lectures.
Um, so there are
many more GP organization
I didn't cover,
but I give you some readings,
in this week, right?
There are some readings on how
to understand the
GPU performance.
And I think in our
documentation,
media provides a
lot of readings,
and someday if you
need to use that,
you know where to
find pointers, okay?
But in general, um,
there are a few other
important aspects
to make TPO kernel fast.
The first one is global
memory continuous read.
That is when I
myths write to read
AHGPM I need to make sure
that they read continuously.
I cannot read one element
and apply offset and it's
going to read another
element because we know
that even in CP memory,
this is slow because we want
to avoid reading with offsets.
We want to always
do continuous read.
Okay uh, shared
memory bank conflict.
I think here I'm just giving
you a fancier name, okay?
But the things that
I think this term you
already understands,
remember in this
cooperative fetching,
if I let all threats to read
GBM without calculating
this offset,
there will be some conflict, and
we call this bank conflict.
Okay. And sometimes
we need to avoid
this kind of shared memory
bank conflict, okay?
Also pipe planning,
and this one is very easy
to understand, right?
So because we have
memory hierarchies,
we have different stress doing
IO and doing competition.
So in order to even save time,
we can add some stress
to doing reading and
another group of thread
doing competition.
And then we can overlap the
memory IO and computing time.
We don't know how to do
it in sequential order.
Another two things,
one is tensor core,
I hope you guys already read
the readings I give to you,
and I think you understand
what is tensor
core doing, right?
It's a more specialized
core for MTM, okay?
So it will be faster in MT
M. And the last one
is lower precision,
which we'll cover next week.
Okay. Cool. That basically
covers all the lecture
contents for GPUs.
Any question? Okay.
Then let's move forward. So if
we come back to
revisit this program,
we find that, yeah,
we have a high level
idea how to do this
uh kernel how to
basically utilize those
memory hierarchy.
But if I ask you to do this,
you are still going to
face a lot of problem.
Because remember in CPU tolling,
there are a few tolling
factors that are critical.
For example, the way you
use shared memory cannot
exceed the limit the
shared memory provided
by the device.
Same thing here, how many
threads should you ask for?
Okay. How many regiers
you should exactly use?
Apparently, it cannot
exceed the number of
regiers in that streaming
microprocessor, okay?
And how many amount of SRAM
should I ask for for my program?
Because different devices have
different number SRAM, okay?
And this is basically
the practical concerns
when you implement this kernel.
And even if you
can write the entire
code of this program,
it's not guaranteed
that this program
is efficient because
you still need to
tune the hyperparameters
configurations for this kernel.
And imagine learning, we
call this kernel tuning,
and there are a
lot of frameworks
like petard and tender flow.
When you just set it
up on your model,
you are with a
pretty long time for
it to profile program and try
to tune those parameters.
That's basically kernel tuning.
And Kert tuning is a very
difficult problem because,
uh we have so many models,
transformers, STRs Net, they
have different operators.
Each operator ready
have different shape.
For example, metam
of one kb one k
and fourk definitely different
than the configurations
that I applied on this
telling because they require
different amount of
processing power
and also the memory
hierarchy capacity.
There are different frameworks,
of course, we already
covered that.
I think the thing that
makes since most complex
is there are many different
devices, different GPUs.
For example, media itself has
so many generations of GPUs
with different
configurations, right?
And there are also CPUs.
There are CDN, uh,
there are like TPU bacons,
we also want to
deploy our kernels
on iPhone MacBook, right?
So which makes this
things complicated.
Uh, so if you ask
developers to do this,
for example, even for a single
Mdm, you have to, like,
at least every company, Apple,
Vd Intel, they need to hire
a bunch of engineers to
tune the kernels, right.
They are basically working
on the same original code,
but they just need to tune
different kernel parameters.
Okay? There are essentially
two solution to this.
One is you just
hire more people,
and like I already mentioned,
you ask the experts to craft
those kernels and tune
their performance
day by day and you
give them salary.
You enumerate all these
conflicts and make sure,
yeah, it is good after profile.
The second solution is basically
a more ambitious
solution that is
basically what machinering
compiler people are doing.
They are saying, like,
how about I give you
a system, which is a compiler,
and you give me your operator,
and you also give
me your devices,
and you through them
to that compiler,
and that compiler will
automatically figure
out everything for you.
Okay. That basically brings
us into the second part of,
uh, and also a very important
topic emergency system.
I think, between the
year 2018 and 2020, uh,
the entire community,
they are doing compilers
because they are
really like this vision
because they can
reduce labors, right?
They can pay salary
to engineers.
They try to automate something.
Okay. So here is
machining compilation.
Obviously the primary goal
of machining compilation is
I try to automatically generate
optimal configurations
on the kernel code,
giving users high level
code, for example,
written in ten flow
Petro or even Python,
and target hardware, if
I can build this layer,
then this is going to be
superpower because it's going to
compare any code into a
highly efficient version
and basically eliminate
human labor, okay?
So let's look at how
machining compiler is different
from traditional compiler.
Okay? So I hope you
guys all took at least,
know what is traditional
compiler, right?
It's basically, for example,
when you write some code,
C plus plus, you can
write in whatever way.
But compiler will
guarantee that they
pass your code and make
it very efficient, right.
It also lower your code into
some machine instructions
and so the instruct the
processors can understand, right?
So this is a
traditional compiler.
Human basically write some code,
for example, CPP or whatever.
And the compiler
will take your code.
It will eliminate all
those efficient code
or repeated code,
unnecessary code.
And then it will try
to lower it into
another format that
is probably not
human readable, but
the process readable.
Instructions. Okay. I need
to give the instruction to,
uh, uh, basically to
the target hardware and hardware
will ask you your code.
E. Imagine learning,
this is very similar.
And here I basically
draw the stack here.
Remember immerse learning
how we write code.
We basically compose
dataflow graphs,
we use Tinder flow
and Patrig API,
and we try to take
care of this layer.
We convert our idea about
our model into
dataflow graph, okay?
And the promise of compiler is
basically, starting from there,
you don't have to optimize
say graph transformation,
you don't have to
optimize your kernel code
or whatever, random scheduling.
And I'm going to take a full
stack solution for you.
I'm going to take over.
I will take your code.
I will automatically transform
it into Dataflograph.
And then I have
some code that will
automatically translate
your data flow graph
into efficient version.
And then once I
have the eventual version of
data flograph what I do is
basically I ask you
from forward and backward
following the
operator definition.
So I will also help
you to generate
efficient kernel code for
each operator you use
in your data flograph.
Okay. And this is
what machining compiler
tries to permiss.
And once you add this layer,
I think we are good because once
we have that efficient
kernel code,
we studied in the previous
several lectures,
we can just give
the code to Quota
compiler or whatever compiler.
And they will basically
they will basically
take over and transform
it into machine code.
You can see machining
compiler is
slightly higher level than
traditional compiler.
It will take your
data flow graph and
compile it all the way down
into kernel code and
then traditional
compiler will take over.
Okay. Any problem here?
Okay, this is a pretty big scope
because if you have a compiler,
that means most of the marchey
system problem will be solved.
Okay. So so what kind of
problem we face here?
So uh, apparently,
there are three layers.
At the first layer,
programming level,
we face very difficult program
that is automatically transform
arbitrary and usually
imperative code by developers,
into a compatible code.
And I think we talked about
this in the second lecture.
This is already pretty
hard because like I said,
dataflow graph is so static,
but user code are so dynamic.
And there's a gap,
how we do that.
We touch based on that. I
hope you still remember.
And you can see this area of
research is basically being
conducted by most of
programming language people.
Programming language people
really like doing this
and they all look at
this area that is taking
your machine learning
code and try
to convert your dynamic
code into study code.
Okay? And this touch base
with programming language, okay?
In a graph level, what the
compiler does is basically,
we try to perform some
automatic graph transformation.
We also talked
about this a little
bit, in our early lectures.
That is, we have a stNt
we can optimize it in
many runs and then
eventually get a graph
that is 30 times
faster or something.
And this is basically being
touchb by some graph
theory people.
Okay, they like to
analyze in graphs,
so they take graphs and try
to find the equivalent graphs.
Okay. And at the last layer,
what do we do is helping
heavily doing this, right?
So how to make operator fast.
So basically, they will take
a high level definition
of your operator, for
example, metamor.
When you write Metamo in Python,
what you do is basically
you do a layer loop.
But they will take that loop
and they try to generate
a very efficient kernel code
that we did in the first
part of this tecture.
Which is auto those
kind of code.
Okay, coda, on GPS and which
was automate the
entire process. Okay.
Um, uh, this is a
pretty big area,
but in this lecture
because you still
remember the big picture,
we are trying to
optimize operator code.
So I'm going to touch
base a little bit on how
to do this using compilers.
Okay. And in later lectures,
we are going to touch
base other layers, okay?
So before that, I
want to give you
a high level picture what is
going on in the compiler domain.
So I'm going to lame a
few famous compilers
and give you an introduction
of what they are cooking.
And what are the people
behind them, okay?
So the first one, of
course, from Google,
right, uh, it's called XLA,
XLA, if you look at Logo.
It's very similar
to tens TF. Okay?
So this SLE was actually
uh I would say it's
the first compiler
for machine learning.
It was released together with,
um, with Tenerflow in 2016.
And you can see how Google is,
uh, visionary on this.
So basically, when they build
the first region of tener flow,
you already think
about the compiler.
Yeah, because I think when
they build Tener flow,
they realize that
they have to ask
their Google
developers to develop
more than 200 operators
on at least three
kinds of hardware,
CPU GPU and TPU.
And that is already 60
combinations, right?
And that takes a lot of time.
So they start thinking about
how to build a compiler,
this compiler is called
SOE and if you look,
if you look back,
you can see, uh,
this is so good that today,
most of tenser flows back
is based on this one.
So basically what I mean is
the throw away all the operators
written by their own developers
and use SLA to
generate code. Okay?
And SLAs also
extending its scope to
support petarg and any
other frameworks, okay?
Second compiler TBM, right,
Tensor virtual machine.
This is a very, very famous
project from academia.
And after two weeks,
the leader of this project,
TQ Chen, was he's a
professor at CMU.
He's going to give
us guest talk.
Okay? And this one is one of
the most successful
compiler in academia, okay?
And it mostly focus on
it's also open source,
and it mostly focus on,
like, compiling code for
inference, not for training.
Okay. That means there's
no backward pass for the
code generated by TVM, okay?
And I think the researchers
and students who develop TM,
they went out and do a startup,
which is octo, they
raise quite a lot.
I think there is
almost 200 M. Okay.
But the company was not doing
pretty well and it
was acquired by
Amedia last year at a similar
price to what the risk.
Yeah, that is a set story.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. The third one,
you probably know,
and this is the one
that attracts the
most user, right?
2.0, uh, which is essentially
torch dot compile.
And like I said, torch is
really good at doing
something really late,
but still win over the
previous, players.
Yeah. So I think the reason
it wins is because like I said,
tort starts from imperative
programming without
compilation, right?
But they gradually migrate into
a compiler friendly framework.
Uh once you have
a deep user base
that is get addicted to
your programming model,
they are not going to
switch, and you can
add whatever feature you
want, and they will use that.
Okay. Uh in fact,
Excel is much better
than Toti Compil.
But I don't think people
like that because
Tn flow itself is too
hard to program, okay?
And, and in to two point,
all what they do
is they add, uh,
a few like compiler related,
interfaces and
they are trying to
advocate to use T
D comple. Yeah.
No. Today, SLE also
works for Torch.
Yeah. So I think Meta and
Google they are collaborating.
Yeah. The reason Torch
wants to support XOI is
because XLA is the best
backend for running on TPUs.
And people like users or
petri they also want to
deploy their job on TPUs,
so they have to integrate, okay?
Each of these compilers
are specific?
They are not
specific frameworks.
I think today, if you
look at mechanism,
the frameworks concept
is kind of fitted.
It's more like a front end
programming language,
a Bon engine.
I can essentially combine
my Petros favorite imperative
programming language or
programming interfaces to
a bacon that is XOI based.
That's also fine.
Yeah. But of course,
I think if you want the
best user experience,
you should use that
framework. Yeah. Okay.
And for this one, uh,
I think you guys use a lot.
And the last one
is modular, okay?
This modular is a company
which raised almost 300 today.
Okay? It was built by a
guy called Chris Lautner.
And if you guys are
compiler people,
you probably know his name.
He was an inventor of LLVM.
Okay, LLVM is a
default compiler today
for compiling many C plus
pass code into
diverse platforms.
Okay. He's one of the
most successful compiler.
And this guy, apparently, he
wants to do machinery as well,
and he tried to build
under startup that tried
to build the world's
greatest compilers.
And this guy, Chris Lateran,
if you search Google,
you'll find him.
He's a very famous
people. So he worked for
Google for a few years.
Uh, but, and Google gives
him a pretty high title,
at least director level,
and, of course, big package.
But he only worked
there for one year,
and he was not able to
work with Google people
because he wants to push
his own idea on compiler,
but Google is not
going to accept that.
Google wants to push XOI.
So, then he basically left
Google and joined Apple, okay?
And in Apple, he wants to
push a language called Swift.
So you guys know
many many Apple apps
are basically program
using Swift, not Python.
And you can understand Swift as
a very magical language that
can interpret between
Python and C plus plus.
So you can write, it's like
today's machinery framework.
You can write in a way that
is very similar to Python,
very easy to understand, but
you can directly convert
that code into a symbolic
version that can compile.
So he really likes that,
and he pushed pretty hard
on Swift on both
Google and Apple.
I think he was successful
on Apple and many,
many Apples code was
written in Swift.
And then at some point, he left
Apple and started
doing this modular.
And I think while
or two years ago,
he start this company,
posted something like,
um they are 20 times faster
than priority, okay?
And that post actually messed
up with priority people,
uh, because, you know,
in the world, it's very hard to
be 20 times another baseline,
There must be something that
is not correctly evaluated.
And there was a strong
debate on if modular
is indeed 20 times
faster than priority,
and if you do some
search on Google,
you will find it out. Okay?
These are two main
compilers, okay?
Uh I think four years ago,
there are more compiler
than this, but they all
died. Only this four survive.
Okay? That means it's not a
good research to do today.
Okay. Yeah, I
wouldn't do compiler.
Okay. So what is,
let's focus on the
underlying uh,
um, mechanisms for
compiler, okay?
So today we are going to focus
mostly on operator combination.
That is a low risk layer.
That is Uder give you
a operator code at a high level
with a high level definition,
how we can compile this code
into low level programs,
for example, Coda kernels
or tiled matm this kind of code.
Okay? I think this
basically give you a
higher idea, right?
So der write this kind of code,
which is mostly
just declaration,
not for efficiency, okay?
And the mission of the
compiler is basically,
I'm going to take
this piece of code.
I'm going to find
a loop that works
best for your code
on your hardware.
Because there are so
many ways to loop,
depending on the looping factor.
Okay. So eventually it
boils down into finding
the perfect loop for
your hardware for
that shape that memo
for the operator.
Okay? In order to do this,
I will give you a
workflow, okay?
So here the user writes a
very simple code that is,
um this is ready at
A plus B equal to
C. But depending on
the shape of ABC and also
the target hardware,
for example, the
lumber registers,
the lumber shared memory,
you can generate many different
versions of this code.
You can basically
loop in this way.
You can also loop in this way.
We probably know the
difference because I can't
tell this layer tell this layer
at a different memory hierarchy.
And also, I can
switch the access.
I make this for about
this 32 and I will get
probably a different performance
depending on the memory
hierarchy capacity.
And eventually the compiler
wants to find the perfect loop
and then basically lower
this kind of loop.
This loop is in Picon code,
I want to lower this loop
into some kernel code.
And all this is being
done automatically.
Okay? That is the high level
idea of operator compiler.
So now you understand
the problem and let's dive
deeper on the exact problem
we're trying to solve.
So we are ficing a
lot of problem if
you want to build this
kind of compiler.
One is and we need to enumerate
all the possibilities.
Then the problem is how I can
represent all the possibilities.
Or more concretely how I
represent the loops. Right.
I need to represent
loops. Okay, I
need to find the repreenton so I
can basically search over
all the repenting space.
Second is once I have that
repenting space of loops,
how to find the close
to optimal value.
Like should I loop over
the first dimension
of four second dimensthirty
two or another way?
I need to This is
optimiing problem.
Right I have a space.
I want to optimize
that space, okay?
And finally, I want to
basically accelerate this
process because I cannot
put this as unsolvable
problem that I have
a program that I search
over for my entire life.
I want to reduce
the search space,
and I want to generalize
this kind of thing from
one device to the other.
For example, I search one
loop for GPU even hundred.
I also want this loop to work
reasonably well on H 100,
something like that.
Okay? So there are
many ways to build
this kind of compiler,
and I'm going to
introduce roughly one way
that adopted in
today's compiler, TVM.
Okay? So in TVM,
in order to solve this problem,
what they do is, uh,
they will first define
the three space.
And then, they have
some algorithm,
which basically what
navigated this space.
Okay? And why enumerate
all the possibility given
your user code and,
uh, your target hardware.
And they also have
some code generator
that once you lock down one
possibility, for example,
you have a high level repeton
with that loop and
you figure out,
the register and the looping
factors you try to choose.
Another layer, we'll
take that loop
and convert that code
into kernel code.
This is a typical
problem in compiler.
It's called code generation.
And today, this can be
done by ARMs, by the way,
but this was done by,
uh, like handcraft coding, okay?
And eventually you will
get a lot of data,
which is a loop and
a compiled kernel,
you're going to
apply this kernel
directly into your
target device.
So you'll get a performance.
For example, this kernel will
run in 100 milliseconds,
uh, on this given chip.
So you're going to get all
these kind of data pairs.
So you can either stop here.
That is, you just pick
the best performing
one and you return the code
to the user, you are good.
Or if you want to
generatee a little bit,
you can take this as a
machine and training data.
Okay. The X is
basically the loop.
The Y is basically
the performance of
that loop on the
target hardware.
And you train these XY pairs
into a neural network,
and you let this new network
to predict in the future,
if you want to switch the loop,
how much performance
I would get.
And in this way, once I have
this performance model,
um, I can basically,
uh, you know, generalize
a little bit.
Like s I have a different shape
when I have a
different hardware,
I can immediately do
inference and try to get
the perfect loop for me.
Okay? Does it make sense?
Cool. And this one is
called Auto TM and, uh,
it's a very famous layer,
uh, in TM compiler, y.
But here, uh, you roughly get
the idea of this workflow,
but there are still
many many problems.
Why is actually represent loops.
Okay? One way to represent
the loop is basically,
uh, we still need experts to
write a lot of templates.
Okay? So we just ask some
expert to write this template.
For example, this is
a loop we did for
com two D and we are going
to ask this experts
to generate many,
many of these versions loops.
But we leave this looping
factor as a placeholder,
and we let our compiler
to automatically find out
the values to fill this
value into looping factor.
And then I can go back
to this workflow, right?
Um the other problem
is once I have
this kind of looping templates,
how do I basically navigate
the space and try to search
for the optimal answer,
right, in the fast possible way.
There are a few ways. One is,
this is a typical
search problem, right?
So say, I have one looping
template, which I want to try.
What I do is basically
every time I fill
some proposed values
into this loop,
and I can go directly evaluate
this partial loop and try to
get some performance indicator.
And if this performance
is already pretty bad,
I can basically prune
the next possibilities
build based on top
of this looping.
I do some backtracking or do
some whatever search
opplementation,
and eventually I can, um,
get a reasonably good loop for
the kernel implementation.
Okay. And similarly, as
I already explained,
I can also build some cost model
using my historical data,
and I can't predict if this
loop is going to do well
or bad on this target
hardware or shape.
Yeah. So it's two ways
that we can basically build
these kind of competors.
Okay, any question?
Yeah.
It's basically, I don't think
there's track solver
to solve this.
This is basically exponentially,
uh, complex, okay?
And so people in
Compiler computer,
they just try to
build all kinds of
searching algorithms to prune
the possibilities
and try to locate
the solution as
fast as possible.
But one thing I want to note is
once you locate the solution,
uh, then you are good, right?
Because for that particular
operator and hardware,
you already find a pretty
good decent implementation,
and you can keep that code
forever in the future runs.
Second is, in most cases,
this is better than
letting experts doing
the engineering.
Because for this kind of search,
what you do is you
develop a search algorithm
and you just pull
it run for one month or one week
and eventually it will
return something for you.
But if you the human
to develop that,
that will take even
longer, right? Yeah.
One is human error, the
other is machine hour.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, that
is basically a high level idea
of how we do operate
compilation.
To summarize a little bit,
we need to find a
way to represent
the loop space by possibilities.
And we need to basically,
make sure the search space
have a good coverage
of common ogmentations,
like tailing, whatever.
And we need to build a
efficient search algorithm
to navigate all
the entire space.
And we also need to have
a evaluation metric
that tell if this
loop is good or not.
Okay. Okay.
Then coming back
to this, I'm going
to give you a question so
you can think about that.
Okay. So like I said,
yeah, like I said,
so the premise of
machining compilation
is basically
we try to automatically
generate optimal
configurations that code
giving users machining
code and targetware.
And my question
is, do you think,
machining compiler is
achieving this goal?
I will offer opinion,
I don't think so.
I will give you strong evidence.
Why? We know that
most of today's language model
are trained by flash attention.
Compiler was invented by
flash attention, right?
Like I said, people
doing compiler research
during 2018 and 2021.
Flash attention was
released in 2022.
And it was handcrafted
by a guy called
Trida who is a principal
Princeton professor today.
Then I ask the question,
I will leave this to you.
Why compiler didn't discover
the flash attention?
Right? Because theoretically,
if your compiler is
smart enough and your compiler
can search the entire space,
it should be able to
search for flight engine.
But eventually, we ended
up with someone actually
implementing flight engine using
their own manual engineering.
I will leave this
question to you.
But I'm not saying that compiler
has no contribution because I
think indeed many many today's
other simpler operations,
for example, met M convolution,
compiler people indeed,
build some really good, uh,
kernels that human probably
is not able to understand,
but rather performing
on GPUs. Okay.
Okay, that is a pretty
fast, introduction
operator compiler.
I think next week we are
coming back to this again,
and we are going to talk
about graph compiler.
That is how to transform
graphs automatically.
Okay? So let's move to the
third part of this lecture.
And in the third part, I want to
introduce a little bit
on a different approach,
okay, which is
basically treating.
Very famous one, right?
So which treating?
So we have many treatings.
Why is this treating, right?
We are not talking this
treating. Okay, this is us.
And there's another very
confusing lamin treating.
It's called NVIDIA
Treating inference server.
And if you search
this on WDA website,
it's there's open
source project.
We are also not talking
about this one.
This one is for serving
transformers and we
are going to talk about
this little bit later,
but this is not the
treatment we'll talk about.
We are basically talking
about this treating.
This is open treating,
okay? So what is treating?
Um, we introduced Koda we
introduced the
automatic compiler.
I think you'll get the idea.
So we can basically
put them into
two extremes, Koda on the left.
And Koda is defined as
a device specific DSL,
domain specific language.
Okay? It's basically
the way that
media provides for you
to program the devices.
Compiler is other extreme.
So what is pros
and cons of Koda?
The pros of Koda is
basically developers
can do whatever the
heck they want, right?
Uh, they can squeeze
the last bit of
performce as long as you are
a powerful Koda programmer,
you can do that.
It gives you all the sort
of possibilities, right?
You can use whatever
data structure
you want instead of Koda kernel.
But what is the cons of Koda?
The const is the same.
Developer can do
whatever heck they want.
Which also means that if
I'm not a Koda programmer,
then it requires deep expertise,
and the performance optim
is very time consuming,
as you can see.
When I give you a
piece of quota code,
I have to explain a lot.
You have to convert
your brain to SIMD,
and you have to be
very good at that in
order to deliver a
piece of good code.
Okay? And you can
imagine the code base with
Koda is very messy
because you are
going to add a lot of this
into into CP code and
you Quota code in
another file and that CP code
will launch that kernel.
You need two
different compilers.
One is the CPP compiler and
the other is Koda compiler.
Koda compiler is pretty
slow by the way.
Yeah. Okay. Then let's
go back to this
automatic compiler.
So what is the pros and
cons of automatic compiler?
Very fast iteration
for developers,
because you just write your
high level code in Python and
you decorate Toch Compel
and things are good, right?
You can pull up ideas quickly
and give it to compiler.
But the problem, it cannot
represent certain
types of ideas.
And I already give an example.
Flash attention
was not discovered
by compilers because
in a search space,
there is no such repetition
for flash attention.
Okay? And also, you cannot
use Cosmo data structures.
And in compiler will indeed boil
down to be a problem that
you want to generate code,
and code generation is
old problem in the old
compiler traditional compiler,
which is a very
difficult problem.
I think programming language
and compiler people they are
doing this a lot of
many, many years, okay.
Okay, that basically help you
understand where treating is.
Okay. So treating is roughly
in the middle, okay?
It is a domain spec language,
but it is Python based.
On the other hand,
it's not automatic,
but it also well,
manually, in the bacon,
treating will help you
optimize some things.
For example, telling
it do telling for you.
You don't have to write
your own telling.
Okay? So basically it
trying to strike a balance
between pure domain
speak language,
and the pure automatic
compaer it's in the middle.
Okay. And here I
basically put four
logos and you can see,
I feel these four
logos are so similar.
It must come from the same
designer. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. Okay. So treating
speech is basically,
how about we do something
that is simpler than Koda,
but more expensive than
automatic compilers.
But compared to Coda,
we are less expensive,
but we are more complicated
than graph compilers.
And this is basically
treating market piece.
Okay? I think this is way too
abstract because it's very
hard for a person or
engineer with no experience on
this, understand this pitch.
But it turns out this
is super successful.
And we are going to go
through if time permits,
we are going to go
through two programs,
but I don't think we
have time, so we are
going to go through
one program. Okay.
So, in treating, uh,
the user defined tensors in RAM.
Okay? So treaton gives
you a language that is
basically Python native.
It embody its own like a
program interface in PySon.
So writing treating is
basically equivalent
to writing Python.
Okay. And also
treatments give you
so many primitives that
is basically from torch.
For example, if you want
to write something,
you can use torch
indexing operations,
you can use whatever
torch offers to you,
which is super intuitive, okay?
But the treatment also give
you a few limitations.
For example, when
you allocate arrays,
it has to be a
shape of power too.
That is because in the back end,
the treating will
do some telling,
do some organization
for you automatically.
So it has to restrict
in this way.
Okay? So here, let's go
say one example treating
Here in this one, we
are doing array eight.
They equal to X plus Y.
Okay, I'm going to let you
look at this for 30 seconds.
Okay, let's try to
parse this code.
Um, it's much better to
look at this code, right?
This is so familiar,
right? Like perch.
I think the first impression
you had is it is Python.
Yeah, so much easier to write.
Okay? The second thing you
noticed is I have this one.
Treating do JT is very
similar to torch,
Do compel or any
other Jet competitor.
So treating is indeed a
Jet competitor, okay?
And I basically use
the grammar of PySon.
I define a function.
Uh, I give it a few,
um, like arrays.
But in triton, all the arrays
are pointers to a tensor.
Okay? This is slightly
different from Python because in
pyson you get object, right?
But in triton is a
pointer to array.
Which means it's a
memory address, okay?
And the treating kernels
will basically be mapped
to a single block.
And this is also why Triton
can simplify UDA a little bit.
Because in CUDA, you have to
define your block shape, right.
You also you define
your grid shape that is how
many blocks you want to use.
And then you define your
thread block shape,
that is how many threads
you want to use.
So you have to
think in this kind
of like a two level hierarchy.
But in Triton, it was
simplified a little bit.
That is you only think
about one thing that
is you think about how to
write a program that will
be mapped to one block.
That is many many reads a block.
And outside of this kernel,
what do you do you define a
grade with different blocks
and treating will
automatically map this
into blocks and threads.
Okay? This already simplified
the way we think a little
bit because like I said,
when you write this
piece of code,
you only think about
how to make it run
on many many
threads, not blocks.
Okay. And here,
let's pass this and we'll
finish lecture, okay?
So here, I call a treating
EPA which is range,
and this is a very similar API
from tort that is I'm going to
create rate 0-123, right?
One thing you'll
notice that whenever
you create something
in treating,
using something start
from this package,
it was created on SRAM.
Okay. That is a shared memory
of all the threads in the
streaming i processor.
You'll remember
this code is going
to be launched just
one single block.
So you create this array,
um SRM This is offset array.
And then what you do is, uh,
you try to manipulate
the pointer semantics
using Python API.
So here I have the starting
address of my XYZ, right?
And when I try to
write this program,
I need to think about how
I make sure each thread is
skewed a part of X
plus Y equal to zero.
So here I launch it
into 26 or 24 threads.
So basically, each
thread in that block,
we need to take one
element a, right?
So what I do is
my hello idea is,
I'm trying to make sure each
thread read one element.
From HPM to SRM.
That is cooperative
fetching, right?
And then I'm going
to let each road to
take the competition.
That is I read achrod read
two elements A and B,
and then add them
together and get together
results and then write the
results back into C. Okay?
And this this is
a pure SMD code.
Okay. So what I do is basically
I first create this
point of semantics that
is offset on my SRAM and
um and one thing you'll
notice that in Cuda,
you have to do some
cooperative fetching.
But here, you just go Christ API
and this will be automatically
mapped to 1024 threads.
Which means this
line is going to be
executed SMD in
that many threads.
Then I'm going to add this
offset to each pointer.
This is the add operation.
And in treating, treating
will basically take care
of the lines and make
sure each threading that block
will perform one
add on the offset.
And once I have this
offset, I know,
I need to load the element
from HPM to my SRM,
treating will basically give you
another EPL called TL load.
And this load is also,
um, coptive fetching, right?
Because the treatment
will automatically map
this node into different reads.
But how we tell each right
to load the exact element.
The way we tell that is
basically we give them
the X PTRs Remember
this X PR was generated in a
way where for each element,
I apply a different offset.
So each read will
basically corresponds to
one element and try to read it
a corresponding
element from XN Y.
And this X and Y, basically,
the uh, RM allocated.
And eventually, I'm going
to do a competition.
And this is still
vectorize the code,
but the treatment
will automatically
map this into many many threads.
So each read only compute its
own corresponding element.
And this result was in
the register of
that thread, right.
And eventually,
I'm going to store
this result back
into the Z pointer.
And I know why each thread
knows which position
to write the results?
Because the PTRs
are basically PTR
plus offset and I already
apply the offset
for each thread.
Okay. Yeah, that's basically
our first piece
of treating code.
And you can see, user
will only be responsible
for mapping.
At outside of this kernel,
user is responsible for creating
different blocks and
passes into the kernel.
But inside of this kernel,
the users like salt process
are already being simplified.
I only need to think
about high rat code that
will be mapped to all threats
but not blocks anymore.
And all the code,
APS are basically Python based,
and you can co many many
similar APS from torch.
Okay? Yeah, that's pretty
much all I have today.
And in the next lecture,
we are going to continue grand
this program on triden
a little bit. Yeah.