Okay. Yeah. Thanks for
coming. Let's get started.
Okay. So just a recap
of last lecture.
So in last lecture,
we did GPU memo, right?
I think we went through
three versions,
a very straightforward version.
Um, we start doing some
register level telling,
and then we do two
level telling, right?
RM and register, okay?
And we also talk about a
little bit of compiler
that is how we compile
a good implementation
for an operator,
we have a pretty
large search space.
We basically search the
configurations for those loops,
then I think we touched
a little bit on Triton,
before we started today lecture,
content let's do MCQ to basically
verify we indeed learn.
The first one, what is a
kernel in the context of GPS?
D, right? Yeah, this is obvious.
I try to remember
this word, Kernel.
Yeah. Second one,
what is a function
of shared memory
in the context of GPU execution?
C it's not HBM HBM
means a global memory.
SRM means a layer higher, okay?
And it's not for compute,
it's for storing things,
it's C. What is
the significance of over
subscribing the GPU?
Apparently, A and C and
D are wrong, right?
So it's goes to B, yeah.
So we basically
need to give many,
many jobs to our
streaming multiprocessors
to make GPU busy.
That is what
oversubscription means.
Which of the following is
true about GPU memory?
B, yeah, of course.
All the rest are wrong, okay?
So which of the following
operations is most
likely so most likely to
be limited by
arithmetic operations.
So by looking at all
the six options,
definitely, we can
first eliminate A, C,
and D, and E, right,
because they are not
arithmetic intensive.
So what we need to do is
basically compare
B and F, right?
And the one that has
more that requires
more flops are more likely to
be limited by
arithmetic operations.
So I think I give you
a equation right,
how to calculate the
flops needed for matm and
the for the option B,
I think it is indeed a
pretty big metamol already,
but it has one dimension
that is equal to one.
But for the second one F, uh,
the first two dimensions
are slightly smaller,
but the third dimension
is pretty big.
And if you compare
all the flops needed,
actually, I think F
is very intensive.
Cool. So when picking
a tile size for GMM GMM
means basically stands
for the metamol in GPUs,
why not always pick
the biggest tile size?
B. Okay.
Let's look it one
by one, the tile
might not fit on the
GPHPM for some GMM sizes.
This one is wrong because
HBM is pretty big,
and it's not
contribute to tiling.
The bigger size could
result in low parism for
some GMM sizes. This
one is correct.
Yeah. If you allocate
more larger tile,
that means you are going
to have fewer threads.
So if you have fewer threads,
then your pism will be limited.
Larger tiles have
lower data use,
it's wrong it has
more data reuse.
Uh, larger tiles
means M data is read.
No, this is wrong, okay?
Cool, we're good. Then let's
move on to the main
content of today.
And today, we are
going to talk about
we are going to finish treating,
and then we start
looking at a second,
very important
topic for compiler
that is basically
graph optimiation.
Okay, still remember
this slide, right?
So treating is a very good
sweet spot between, um,
fully automatic compiler
like TM and Koda,
which basically is manual.
Okay? Triton tries
to strike a balance
between automation and
also, um, performance.
Okay? And it achieves this by
basically, uh, for example,
giving you Python from n. It
also allows you to manipulate
or raise using pointers,
even in Python, but
it also tries to,
uh, basically impose
a few limitations.
So treatment can better handle
sort of like some degrees
of automation in the
backend for you.
For example, met mootei
and I think we look at this
program a little bit, right.
I think we go through
this one. So um,
this is quite different
from traditional Coda.
You know a few things.
One is python based.
Second is, um, uh,
this code will only be
mapped to one block.
It's for the user to decide
how many blocks they want to
launch this code too, right?
And the way you decide
is basically uh,
you declare the grid
size here and you
launch this program to a
grade of blocks, okay?
And it's also for the user to
be aware that they need to
write the code in a way that,
um, so they manipulate
array for each thread.
So each thread knows which area
to read from the inputs and
try to basically calculate
its own part, its own person.
Okay, I think we stopped
here last lecture,
and we'll continue from here.
So um in order to basically
change this code,
you can see from this code,
we are essentially launching
this function into one block
because the grid size is one.
We only have one block. So
we want to change this into
multiple block version
because we want to
use as many SMS as
possible from the GPU.
So what do we do is basically
we make these changes.
I think the first thing
you want to note is here,
we slightly increased
array size.
Yeah, because we
have more blocks.
We want to calculate
more elements.
And what we do is
basically we still launch
like 1024 threads per block,
and we divided the array size
by 1024 and we request
that many blocks.
Okay. So in this sense,
so we have these many blocks and
each block still has 24 threads,
and each thread will basically
calculate one element.
And compared to the previous
version of the program,
what we need to do is we
need to now consider blocks,
and we need to make
sure each thread in
each block actually index the
right element of the array.
So when we play with this
kind of pull inter semantics,
we need to introduce another
offset that is basically
uh the number of
threads per block
times the current
index of this block.
Right so we can use
this EPI TD program to return
the current block index.
Then we basically
offset the array by,
for example, each block
will offset by 1024, right?
And then we add this
offset to the original,
offset array we created
for index each thread,
right, each thread content,
and we can basically change
this program in a way that
is it will operate on
many many blocks and
many many threads.
Okay? And here, we add
a little bit mask to
avoid that we read range, right?
So if our number of
threas is greater than,
um, than the array size,
then we basically make sure
we are not go out of range.
Any question for this program?
Cool. And like I said,
you just need to write
this kind of program
and the treating is
going to do many,
many things behind the scene.
For example, if you write
metamo treating is going
to do telling for you.
You don't know how
to tell by yourself.
And if you compare the treating
performance to Petros,
you can see, it's pretty decent.
Remember, in Pyts this
kind of code or this kind
of kernel or manually
crafted by petrod
developers, right?
But in Cuda, in low
level language,
okay, you need to take
care of a lot of things.
But in treating, you just
need to write Python and
you can see the performance
is pretty close. Okay.
Another example, slightly
more complicated.
I think you did this in
homework one, right?
We ask you to do softmax.
Okay? So do you still remember
how you implement softmax?
So I believe most of
you probably just, uh,
use some primitives, from
prior to compose softmax.
Okay. Uh, so basically,
you probably have
expent function, right?
You have some
mission and you have
divided something like that.
You compose them together.
I think up to this
point, you probably
already realize that this is
not going to be super efficient.
Why? Because you are composing
many many elementary primitives
and you are basically
a better alternative,
you can fill them all together,
you just implement
softmax and that can,
um substantially reduce the
Uh, IO, right?
Because you don't how
to read per primitive.
You can read just at the
beginning and do some
in memory using whatever
telling or memory hierarchy.
Okay? One way people
improve softmax
is basically they
implement into softmax.
And that is basically
what uh Petros
did for their softmax API
kernel implement using Koda.
It's not composed by
primitives, Okay?
And you can imagine how
difficult this will be,
right, especially considering
if X is multi dimensional,
you have to do some summation,
normalization and then
do some division,
and that is going to be
rather complicated for
multi dimensional array.
But the treating can makes
this process really simple.
And here, I'm going to
show a second piece
of treating program.
So here, basically what
we want to do is we want
to do a software
mass on this matrix,
and we want ECblock
to basically perform
competition on each row.
Okay. And then we want
each column to basically,
sorry, we want each
threading a block to
take an element from this row.
Okay? And we can do softmax.
And our goal is we try to input
end to end kernel for softmax.
Okay? We don't compose
from primitives.
Yeah. And I think with
the previous experience,
this program is rather easy
to understand compared
to Koda, okay?
So let's parse this one.
So of course, we start
with a treating it,
right, and we define the
signature of softmax.
And uh and with first
index, like I said,
I want each block to
take care of one row,
and each thread will
take one column.
So I play some index
here indexing here.
I index the block and
the map to roll, right?
And I also create an offset so
that each thread knows where
to read as a starting point.
And then I basically
create a pointer,
which basically
is a pointer that
is instructing the current
thread to read from.
And this pointer is created
in a way that offset
this number of blocks and
then this number of columns.
I load this data. I
ask each ready to
load this data and you still
remember what this
load is doing?
It's called
cooperative fetching,
each rater will do its own load.
And then I read all
this kind of code here.
So why this kernel is faster?
Because triton basically
play things in SRM, right?
If you still remember,
it's not going to,
uh if you compose
for many primitives,
every time you launch
a new primitive,
for example, exponential
function, or submisin function,
you are going to
read things from HBM
all the way to SRM
to catch, right?
And you do compution. But here,
Triton created all these
temporary variables at SRM.
So you can avoid a lot of
repeated reading or data
fetching from HBM all the way
up to the memory hierarchy.
That's how fetching
how fusion works.
And you can see, treating
actually allows you to do
this kind of fusion very
easily using Python semantics.
Okay? Any question?
Cool. This is our second
piece of treating program.
Um, I think treating
indeed lowers the barrier
or programming GPUs.
And if you compare
the performance between treating
and petrog you can see actually,
by the way, the access is
basically the latency.
And you can see,
um, at some point,
treating is already matching
the human graphi kernel
using Coda in petrog.
But at some
dimensions as growth,
we have Olympic gap,
but that's fine.
The gap is not significant.
It's definitely better than, uh,
writing composing, for
example, primitives, yeah.
Yeah, that's basically,
all the contents
I want to cover for triton.
To summarize, I think triton,
uh, um, uh, this is,
I think treat market
piece is pretty
successful in the sense
that which is shown
in this curve, right?
So you can either
choose to program Koda,
but you are going to invest
a lot of time in order
to get a pretty
decent performance.
Uh, if you want
extreme performance,
you can program even lower
language, for example,
the streaming
assembly invented by,
uh, so basically is
hardware language
associated with GPUs, right?
I think very few people in
this world can actually uh,
using a programming language
except those in media company.
But yeah, indeed, if you
want extreme performance,
you just need to invest
more time learning SASS,
and eventually you want to
get the highest performance.
But for treating, uh,
for example, for us,
as a machine learning or
system developer who are
not that into GPU or quota,
uh, it indeed provides
pretty good value.
And this is basically the
sweet spot of treating.
Yeah, you don't have to
invest a lot of time,
but you still get disney
performance. Yeah.
This is. Yeah, that's
a good question.
So in my previous slide,
I said treating is a
domain specific language
for Koda, and I was wrong.
Today I think treating is
trying to expand their scope.
So basically, they keep
the fen language the same
still writing Python,
but they can basically
compile the language down
all the way to
different hardware,
for example, AMD, this
kind of hardware.
Okay? Yeah, that actually give
you another good argument.
Now, you just need to
learn one language
and you can write code
for different hardware.
Cool. Okay.
With that, I think, uh,
we have done pretty good here.
We can summarize the um,
operative documentation.
Okay? So let's try
to bring us back to
the big picture, okay?
So, we spent almost
four lectures
on this, right,
for optimization.
Our grand goal is we try to make
individual operator run
fast on diverse devices.
Okay? And we start with
some general ways,
for example, vectorization,
data layout.
We dive deep into met
M, right? The telling.
And then we start
talking about how to
utilize accelerators and
using SMD and paralization,
many, many, accelerator course.
And then we started craft
our own kernel on Koda,
we learned a little bit Koda.
And then I said that this is
pretty hard because it's
very hard to program
this kernel.
So people started inventing
operator compilers to automatic
generate the code, okay?
And I also said
automatic compiler
is still has its
own problem, right.
Sometimes it miss
some opportunities,
sometimes it's pretty
hard, and it cannot
achieve the best
performance for you.
So then we start
about treating is
basically the sweet spot
between Koda and compiler.
Yeah. That is basically what's
happening in the
community that people how
people basically optimize
individual operators.
We can wrap up this
layer and we go
to another layer that
is graph openation.
I hope you still remember
the goal of graph
oglementation, right?
So we basically have a dataflow
graph on the left hand side.
We already know how to make
each individual
operator fast enough,
using all the
techniques we covered
in the previous four lectures.
And now we are going to launch
this entire graph to a GPO.
So how can we basically make
this entire graph
composed of many,
many operators run
as fast as possible?
Okay? That is basically the
goal of graph openation.
Okay, to basically abstract
a little bit, okay.
Our goal is rewrite
the original graph G data
flow graph into G prime.
And we need to
ensure two things.
One is the G prime needs to
run faster than G. Right,
it's called optimization, right?
Second, is we need to ensure
G prime basically outputs
equivalent results because we
shouldn't as a system developer,
we shouldn't alter the results
of the machine
learning side, right?
Okay. Yeah, so one
straightforward solution
for this problem is basically,
uh, we can create a
lot of templates.
For example, we have
so many templates and
this template is basically
a pair of graphs.
X and Y. X is
the original graph and
Y is the target graph.
And for any pair since template,
we know that X and Y is
going to produce
the same results,
but Y is going to be
faster than X, right?
So this freedom of um we
can ask human experts
to write many many kind of
graph or subgraph template,
transformation template,
that guarantees correctness
and performance skin.
Remember, X equals Y
and Y is faster than X.
And then what we do is we
basically run pattern matching
over our entire data flow
graph defined by the model.
And whenever we find a pattern
that basically matches template,
we replace the X with Y.
That is guaranteed to give
us performance and
correct results.
Okay. And we will start by
talking about this first.
Okay, how to run this
kind of pattern matching.
So there are a few very well
known templates
in the community.
And I think you
probably also studied
this if you took a few
courses in compiler, okay?
Because in compiler in traditional
compiler, for example,
in compiling code for CIPs plus,
we also do this kind
of pattern matching.
Okay? The first one,
of course, we have talking
about this so many times, right.
This is so important
that is fusion, right?
Fusion is basically,
when we have
a matmu when we have
a layer nomination,
that is what I give
it to you in homogom
right and if your opera library
happens to have another
operator which is called N,
then you basically run pattern
matching over your entire graph.
You'll find all these kind of
patterns and you replace that
met mo then go to into
field operator fields
the metamn, right?
This is guaranteed
to give you a gain.
Okay? And I hope you still
remember why fusion can
improve performance, right?
The first one is,
um reduce IO right?
Because previously, I need to
read twice, now I
only read once.
Okay? What is the second reason?
So imagine at the
dataflow graph level,
you are going to have
so many operators,
so many primitives.
Every time when you try
to execute one operator,
essentially
eventually boils down
into launching a
GPU kernel, right?
And I think one thing
that I need to point
out is every time when
you launch a GPO kernel,
from CPU to GPU, you are
suffering launching overhead.
Because you CP you need to send
instruction to GPS, and
that has a latency.
And this is not obvious
when your graph
is slow when your
graph is small,
but this becomes very obvious
when you have thousands
of operations,
every time you launch
lunch, lunch, lunch,
and the accumulated latency
is going to be big.
So another reason that
fusion really works pretty
well is because if you
fuse as many operators
as possible,
you are going to reduce
the lunging overhead
from CPU to GPU.
Okay? And apparently the
lunging overhead is a constant.
No matter what
operators you launch,
you are going to
suffer overhead.
So it what grows as
the lumber operators
you launch, okay?
So what is the const
of operator fusion?
One is you need to implement
that fused up, right?
And we know that there are
so many operators and they can
compose in arbitrary ways.
So as long as one operator in
graph cha your original
field operator is
not going to work,
you need to implement that.
And if you continue doing
this, at some point,
your code base is going to
become not able to
be managed, right?
So many random operators
lim for example,
filled the ABC up, right?
And that is indeed
what happened in,
for example today
Tender flow codebase.
If you go there, you
check, they have
so many these kind of operators.
Okay. So um, yeah,
um, but if you don't
care about this,
for example, you
don't you just want
to ship a product and you don't
care about if this
code is going to be
maintained in a longer
term, you can do this.
This is the best way to
squeeze the last bit of
performance. Yeah, please.
Some small graph. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, that's a good
question. So it depends on
the relative
overhead opmentation
and the runtime
latency of that graph.
If your optimization
actually takes longer than
running graph on P then you
don't have to optimize.
Another way of
thinking this is, uh,
optimization, especially in
static graphs, is a
one time overhead.
So you just put that
overhead at once,
and then you can save the
optimized graph on disc.
Next time we try to launch
a different data to that graph,
you just load from disc.
Okay. Okay, back to this topic.
Okay. Like I said, fusion
has its own pros and cons.
So how we can basically
strike a balance.
So we still do decent
amount of fusion,
but without making
the dabs explode.
So that uh one thing
that you need to
know from this course is
there's a very good
library called Koda graph.
Okay. If you start doing
m inference doing, um,
some sort of like basically
inference survey,
you probably know
this Kuta graph is
the technology
invented by media,
and a lot of people
are using that.
And it is well integrated
into Priority.
Okay? So what this
Kuta graph does is
basically uh Odia
provides a library
that it allows the program
allows you to still
program your,
for example, complex operators
or graphs using primitives like
exponential at
multiply this kind
of primitives, from
priority, see?
Um, but media is going to
capture all these kind
of kernels at the DA
level at the GPU level.
And it allow you to open API,
which is called the Koda graph.
And once you turn
turn this API on,
it's going to basically fuse all
these um, kernel
launches altogether.
Okay? So for example,
if you launch like ABCDE,
five kernels, right?
And this is how the
timeline looks.
Sometimes your CPU
probably around
a little bit even
slower than GPU.
That's why you start creating
these kind of bubbles.
Like, you launch A from CPU
to GPU and you
start launching B.
But launching B
actually takes even
longer than executing A on GPUs,
you'll start seeing this
kind of bubbles and
your execution is going
to be slowed down.
And what media does
is basically, uh, uh,
once you turn on this a graph,
it will basically capture
the entire graph of kernels
you are going to launch.
And instead of launching
them one by one,
they are going to basically
put them all together,
fusing them together,
and just launch once.
Okay, once it is
launched, it will
create a sequential instruction
on GPUs that basically will
ask you the actual code or
ABCDE following the order.
And the key difference here is
OD is not doing field fusion.
So it's not actually fielding
the code into a new kernel.
It's basically only
fielding the launching.
That's why this is pretty good
because from a user perspective,
you don't actually
explore your code bis.
You just need to turn
on this API and it will
reduce that constant
kernel launching overhead.
Okay? And this is a
pretty practical library,
and I hope in your own
work in the future,
you can study this a little
bit and try to leverage this.
This is indeed
pretty good, okay.
Okay. Then the second
template approach
is called constant folding,
and this is a very
traditional approach that
our old compiler people
are doing in
traditional compilers.
This is very easy to
understand, right?
Sometimes you probably compose
a dataflow graph that happens
to have this pattern.
Where you first add exam three,
and at some point, you
add another four to it.
And this is not good because
essentially you are doing things
like this, you
basically add seven.
So basically in
graph organization,
we have a few passes,
and this passes
basically, for example,
one pass could be called
constant folding pass.
It will scan all your
current uh dataflow
graph and try to find
all these kind of patterns
and try to basically
feel that three and four
and reduce to add into one.
This is called constant folding.
And there are a
few other patterns
right where very obvious.
For example, sometimes you
write a code called
X multiplier,
and I'm going to reduce it
into a single X. X at zero,
I can fold it into a single X.
Okay? Makes sense, right?
Cool. Okay. The third template
we normally use in this graph
Logunation is called common
sub expression elimination.
Okay. Let me go
through this example.
And this is also a pretty
traditional technique in, uh,
in traditional
compiler, but it's
also adoptable in
imaginary compiler.
So here, the user declare a
sequence of equations, okay?
And, and we want to
optimize it a little
bit because we
don't want to ask
it line by line.
We believe there are some space.
So the way we do that
we are going to add
a superscript for each
variable we created, okay?
So, we are going to add
we are going to notate
A with superscript one and
B with the superscript two.
And of course, C
at three, right?
And then we'll keep
running this, okay?
And the second line D
equals to A, basically,
font A is equal to one and D
is the value of D
is assigned from A,
so we give the same superscript.
Okay. This means that D and
A is actually equivalent,
we'll keep running this.
E two equals to B two.
And at this point,
we find that F three equals
to D one plus E two,
and we find F has a
superscript of three.
Right. So, which essentially
means that this equation,
this line of code is
not essential, right?
We can remove it. And we
can simplify it a bit.
The way we simplify
it basically,
we figure out that F
has a superscript of
three and C also
has the same three.
So we basically assign
the value from C to
F. So we can remove
add from the graph.
Right? And we'll
keep running it.
So basically in this pass,
we basically find
one CSE heat, right?
This is also CSE, by the way.
Yeah. Cool. Another trick
we can do is basically called
data node examination.
That is, we try to find
some data node that will
never be executed and we try
to remove that
from graph, right?
So in this example, we
can actually continue
at another pass, DCE pass.
In the DCE pass, we are going
to figure out some dan node.
And I think you can actually
tell me which one is Dante.
Like, which variable
is never used?
So this one, right? So we
can directly remove it.
Yeah. And, uh, in that way,
the D is repeatedly assigned
by two different lines,
and the first line is not
going to be a skewed.
So we can directly
remove this. Okay?
We can basically run this many,
many times and eventually
we'll convert into
a pretty concise graph
that remove a lot of
unnecessary nodes from the
Uter code or Uer definition.
Okay. And this also
happens in some graphs
with control flow,
for example, we have X and Y.
We go through a
conditional operation if
and we have a true
branch and force branch.
But at some point, we find
that the force branch
will never be used.
So we can basically prune
this graph by completely remove
the entire force branch.
We can propagate the unused
node all the way back to
a point where this node
is not going to be used and
we're going to remove it.
Okay. So basically, this
is a traditional
graph organization.
We run our dataflow graphs,
and all these kind of
passes are actually
implementing our compilers.
So if you go read those
Storch compiled code and,
um, for example, SLE code,
you'll find a lot of files
essentially map into
this kind of passes.
They are going to run
many, many passes
over your graph to make sure
uh they will return more
concent version of it.
And by doing this,
we can effectively
remove the nodes, right,
remove the memory IO and
try to reduce the skill
graph a little bit.
Okay. Cool. Any question? Yeah.
That's a good one. So for
Kodograph you're
mentioning kotograph?
Kodograph requires stato graphs.
Yeah, that's a good thing.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, Kotograph
requires graph never changes.
Okay. Yeah, it's very
similar to Toti Compile.
Yeah. Okay. Okay, these are
pretty easy things, right?
Then let's dive deeper
into something that
is more complicated.
Okay. So one thing you
notice that when we
run this kind of
graph or template matching
pattern matching,
what do we do we do
it in a greedy way.
So we find the pattern, we
replace it into a
more efficient graph.
And then we go and find
the second pattern and remove
it replace it with a
more efficient version.
And this has a problem, right.
I hope you still
remember this one,
right? I mentioned as well.
So this one, eventually,
if you do this kind of
graph organization,
you will get some
performance again, right?
But I mentioned
in the first step
where I basically change
the com one by one into
com three by three.
When I apply this pattern
matching template,
the graph actually
becomes slower first.
I first becomes slower and
then it becomes faster,
and eventually it
becomes faster.
And if we do naive
pattern machine,
we're never going to
find this kind of
Oenation opportunity,
right? That's a problem.
So how we can basically model
this kind of orenation
that is we probably want
a bigger search space
so we can basically
more effectively get more
performance gains, okay?
Uh, that's one problem.
Second problem of
doing aninau pattern
matching is,
um, like we have so many
machinery operators,
and we have so many model
architectures, right?
Even if at the beginning
of this course, I said,
we only have roughly
five models,
but each model has
its own variants.
Like people can define them in
various ways depending
on their applications.
So that create variations
on the uh graph definition.
And also, as I said,
we eventually want
to launch this graph to
many different hardware,
AMD, like Qualcomm,
media, uh, Intel.
So basically, uh, each
hardware each operator and
each operator combination,
they have slightly
different performance,
uh, uh, when you
optimize against
different hardware, okay?
So that means that each
company basically need to form
a team to write templates
for their own hardware.
And they need to do that
repeatedly for every model,
every emerging model defined by
the marche in community, okay?
And that is a pretty
high overhead,
right, human overhead.
So, give you a little bit sense.
So how many operators
in the flow?
So up to today, there
are roughly 300,
300 operators, primitives.
Yeah. That is a lot because you
can imagine how
many combinations
you can result into, right?
So graph architectures, I
think you can just count
the number of papers published
annual ribs and SML,
how many models people created.
Yeah. Maybe not every paper
will be eventually utilized,
but still a lot, right?
And hardware back
and we roughly have
a a scale tens today,
uh, silicon companies.
Okay? So that means we
basically need to address
all these combinations,
and this need to be done by
human experts writing templates
doing pattern matching.
Okay. And this is
apparently not scalable.
Okay. Uh, another problem
I already mentioned,
so it's not robust and
it's not scalable and
performance is not
guaranteed because
sometimes you lose
opportunities,
like the previous
example showed.
Okay? So instead of
doing this kind of
menu graph openation,
uh, we try to seek
more automatic way.
So we start asking the
question, can we actually,
figure out a pipeline that
we can automatically,
optimize this kind of
graphs and guarantee performance
gains and correctness.
Okay? So in the
next few minutes,
I'm going to tell you
two leading lines of
work that basically
addresses in automatic way.
So the key idea here
is we try to replace
manually designed graph
oppmentations with
automatic generation
and verification
of graph substitutions
for central algebra.
Okay. So what does this mean?
That means, uh, uh, first,
we don't want to write
our own templates
anymore because there
are so many operators,
so we want to automatically
generate this templates, right?
And yes, we indeed can
automatically generate,
but we need to
guarantee correctness
and we need to guarantee
performance gains.
So we need to invent
some mechanism that
whenever we try to replace
some graph with another one,
uh, we want to verify that
the replaced one
is going to give
you correct results and indeed
will improve performance.
Okay? And all this can
be automatically
applied and discovered.
So, uh, this work is basically
called Teso and it is
a very famous paper,
um, uh, in Graph organization.
I think it's well adopted
in Patriot today, um,
and this graph is
going to give you
a high level overview
of how Teso um,
address this uh automatic
graph orgenation so basically,
it basically start with some
operator specification.
So for example, the user
provide a list of
operators, for example,
all the 200 operators
in tender flow
and write down in their
specification in mathematical,
formal language, for example,
uh, this is column two D,
and it will take
a shape of M by N
and being applied with a
three by three operator,
sorry, three by three
filter and then
produce another output ary
with another certain shape.
So this is formally
defined, okay?
And this is MathML, and I time
two matrix together
A by B and B by C,
and I'm going to
get A by C matrix,
something like that, okay.
This given set of operators,
what we do is
basically we try to,
um, um, basically put
this operator together.
We enumerate all possible
combinations of these operators.
We just enumerate all of them,
and we put them here.
For example, given four
operators Mm come to
the pool and maybe romanization,
we can basically enumerate all
the possible dataflow graphs
that are composed from
the four operators,
we try to find some equivalents
from the entire site.
Right? And once we
find the equivalent,
uh, we can generate so many
graph substitution pairs.
That is, we have one subgraph A,
and we know that there
are, for example,
at least 100 equivalents, right?
And we can basically replace
the original graph A
with whatever in
the equivalent set,
and we try to figure out those
that basically will give
you performance gains while
still guarantee correctness.
That's a how idea.
Okay? Now, let's
dive deeper into how
this works. Okay.
So here we start with
operators supported by
our framework and
hardware back end.
Here, I give a simple example.
We have four operators.
Our first step is
basically we enumerate all
possible graphs up
to a fixed size.
For example, I want to, uh,
enumerate all the possible
graph shapes with four notes.
They can be connected
in whatever ways.
Okay. And it turns out that
there are many subgraphs,
even only given four ups.
Basically, there are roughly
66 million these graphs.
They can be combined
in this way.
Oh what we try
to do next step is we try
to find the substitutions.
So we define substitution as
a pair of equivalent
graphs in this entire set.
Okay? So um the way
we find graph substitute
is basically,
uh given this 66 million graphs,
we are going to compute
the output fingerprints
with random input tensors
with randomized inputs,
and we fit the inputs
into the graph and we
check the outputs.
And if the outputs are
basically the same,
we think they are
basically substitutions.
Does that make sense?
Okay? Yeah. Um, so basically
by running this process,
we can basically find a lot
of peers that are substitutions.
And if you do this, in my way.
So basically, you
actually can generate
roughly 28744 substitutions by
enumerating graphs with up
to four operators, okay?
Pairs. And this is
still a pretty large set
because like I said,
uh, at this point, we
get a lot of templates,
but it's automatically generated
instead of human written.
But this is too large a set that
if we run pattern matching
using these substitutions,
um, it will not scales too slow.
Okay. And it's not
guaranteed to improve
performance, of course.
I could slow down, right?
So what we do is we
try to prune this set.
We try to prune this set
as much as possible,
according to the if they
are repetive if they
can basically give you
equivalent results or if they
are going to give you
performance gains.
So the way we prune it is
actually pretty simple.
This slide actually
give you a few example.
For example, um, these two
graph is essentially the same,
right basically the first one is
basically variable liming.
I switch the liming of A and B.
Uh, the second one is basically,
they have a common subgraph.
Uh, it's equivalent because I
basically switch
the order where I
put the BT stay when
I add A to them.
Okay. Uh, I can continue
using this kind of
mathematical rules to keep
pruning all the substitutions.
And my input is basically
28744 substitutions,
and after pruning, I can
actually get 734 substitutions.
Okay? Remember, uh,
this is still a lot.
Okay.
The problem is now we ended up
with almost 700 equivalent
graph substitutions.
Our goal is trying to run
pattern matching all of them.
But we are fixing
one problem because,
remember, when we try to
generate substitutions,
what do we do is we use
randomized tensors,
um basically we never
actually formally verified that
they are indeed equivalent.
The problem can be
stated in this way.
So we randomize a field
tensors, A and B,
and we have substitutions
F and G. Basically,
our randomized
tensors A and B, uh,
F A equals to GA and
FB equals to GB.
And what do we what
we try to state is we
try to state that for
it arbitrary input,
we should make sure
FX is equal to GX.
And this is not true because
what we observe is only
the equivalent on ANB.
We cannot state
basically FX equal to X.
Basically, that means that
we are not finished yet.
Given this 734 subsivitions,
we also need to formally verify
that they are indeed
equivalent mathematically.
The way we do that is basically,
um, uh, we have a few
candidate substitutions.
We are going to run
verification, um, uh,
process where we will leverage
the mathematical
specifications written
for each operator
at the beginning.
Okay. For example,
in this example,
we ask the basically
the developers write this kind
of mathematical specifications
for each operator.
For example, convolution is
distributive over
concatenations,
and convolution is bilinear.
So basically try to state
all the characteristics,
mathematical characteristics
of a operation.
So once we have this
kind of specification,
we can basically look
at our substitutes
and we try to check against
this specification.
For example, if two
substitute appear to be
against this kind of
mathematical specific we are
pretty sure that they
are not equivalent.
Right? So basically
we can check against
these facts and make
sure we indeed narrow
down those
substitutions that will
basically conform to the
specifications defining math.
Okay? And the idea here is, um,
writing specifications
are easier
than actually conducting
optimization, right?
Because you just need to
do that for each operator.
You don't how to do it for
each graph because
once you wrote it,
I can basically use
this specific to
check for each graph,
okay? Any questions so far?
Cool.
Yeah. And with this kind of
specification and
verification mechanism,
we can actually borrow a lot of
cool technologies from
compiler from
programming language.
We can run some
automatic therm prover
to prove that these two graphs,
given specifications
are equivalent.
And this can give
us some guarantee
that given to substitutions,
we check if they are
mathematically equivalent.
Okay. To give you some
sense how long this take.
So in order to enumerate
all the substitutions
from four nodes,
four operators and
generating some pruning,
it will roughly take only
5 minutes. Yeah. Yeah.
It's much faster
than human, right?
Yeah. Although Lumber
is pretty big,
but it's much faster than human
because we can't the
computer to automate that.
Okay? And then once we
have the specifications,
we can verify them
against the specs.
We can write some
automatic theorem prover,
that only takes 10 minutes.
Okay. Yeah. But you
can have a basis,
um, basically, if you
want to do this kind
of graph or position on
inner photograph, it
takes a lot of time.
Like you don't need to run
so many passes to do
pattern matching.
And they also need to start
with writing templates,
and that take even longer
than running this
pattern matching
and running this substitution
finder and verification.
Okay. Yeah, once we have
this set of available
unverified substitutions,
what we do is
basically, we apply
the verified substitutions
to optimize the graph.
But like I said, um, for now,
we are not sure if after
we apply the substitution
whether our performance
will gain, right?
Because we can only prove
that two substitutions
are equivalent,
but we haven't observed
that indeed the
second in one substitute X and
why will be faster than X?
We are facing another
problem how to
apply this kind of
substitute to a graph.
So this basically boils down
into another optimizing
problem, right?
So we have a given graph,
and we have a set of things
that we try to do
pattern matching,
and we try to basically optimize
the graph in a way that, uh,
peak a set of substitutions,
the eventual performance
will be, uh, maximized.
Okay? And the and
this problem can be solved
by using searching.
For example, we just keep
trying keep trial and error.
We just keep picking up
any possible substitutions
and we do pattern matching,
we get optimized graph.
Then we run optimized graph
on TPU and we get the lumber,
we observe that if this lumber
is improving performance,
if not, we give it up
and we keep trying.
Okay uh, basically
enumeration, okay?
And we can be a little
bit more like, creative.
That is, every time we
run a substitution and
get a profile number, uh,
we probably document it down
and we try to train
a cost model,
and we try to predict
if we apply this kind
of substitution,
whether we are going to get
some performance scheme.
And that can basically
accelerate our search process.
Okay. And eventually,
we'll basically, uh,
hopefully figure out, a
perfect basically
substitutes graph
that is run faster
than the original one.
But I think the
key the key point
here is all this
process is automated.
You basically if you want
to run optimize your graph,
all you do is basically
launch your program and wait,
you don't have to think
about uh templates,
pattern matching and all this
basically you just need to
wait and eventually you
are going to I would
say you are guaranteed
to get a faster graph.
Yeah. Okay. Cool. And
so how this works,
and I think at some point,
people apply this to some
convolutional and smaller
neural networks, for example,
birth stNt and Nats net and
they indeed observe that
you can do much better than
um human crafted competitors.
Here the taso is basically
the one I mentioned,
you automatically optimize,
you give it to Teso and weight.
And you compare Tasso to
a few other baselines,
for example, tener flow
SLA and tenser RT.
SLA is Google's competor
and tenser RT is basically,
um, Uh, it's not a compiler.
It's a quota runtime
developed by Omdia.
Yeah, basically, there
are many many templates
inside written by
OmdiaEngineers.
And indeed, you can find
something that is even
faster than expert design.
Okay. Cool. That is
basically one way that we can
apply this kind of
graph optimization.
So to summarize the
workflow, okay, um,
the reason I want to summarize
because this work was out,
there are so many
peoples proposing
all kinds of different ways.
You can imagine you can be
more creative in how
to search, right,
how to create substitutions and
how to apply subsidies to
guarantee you how
performance scheme.
So since this work was proposed,
there are I would say
more than 200 papers public in
this line discussing how
to make this faster,
but they basically fall into
this workflow I'm going
to describe next.
So you start by constructing
a search space.
In the work I just described,
you are basically enumrating
every possibility,
up to four nodes of the graph.
And then you enumerate
all possibilities,
and you try to using
some heuristics to
prune all the candidates that
is apparently wrong, incorrect.
Okay? And then you try to select
those top candidates based
on profile or cost model, right?
And you apply these
transformations
to transform the graph
and eventually you will
obtain a graph that is
with higher performance.
Okay. Yeah. And once you
have the optimized graph,
you get real data,
you can come back and
basically iterate your cost
model to make it more accurate.
Yeah. This is like a
slightly involving
something called
machine learning for systems.
That is, I try to use
machine learning to improve
my system performance. Okay.
There are potential
limitations for this approach.
The first one is, maybe
your search space is
not defined as
comprehensive as possible,
so you will still miss
some opportunity.
Okay? So it's pretty
critical that you define
a large enough so space.
But if you do so, you
are going to have
a super large space that will
basically make
searching impossible.
So basically, this
problem is a paradox.
If you want to
optimize more, uh,
you're not going to converge
in a timely manner.
But if you want
to optimize less,
you are not going to
get a good performance.
Okay. Like I said,
the search is going
to be pretty slow,
right, because you are basically
trial on an arrow,
trial on an arrow.
Okay. And if you want to build
this kind of cost model,
you need some real profile data.
And in order to get
this real profile data,
you have to launch your say
automatically optimize
the graph on GPO and run,
say for ten iterations and
get a real data, right?
And that can take some time.
Yeah. Because for example,
when a neural network
is pretty costly,
it will take your GPO cycles.
Yeah.
Okay. Any questions on this?
Cool. Okay, um,
then I'm going to dive into
another way of doing
graph organization,
and this is even more creative.
Okay? So, I think in
the previous work,
we said that we can
actually replace humans by
automating this process
using search and cost model.
Um, I also said that
a key step is you
define search space.
But here we start asking
another question.
In the previous work,
we always try to
find those equivalent
substitutions.
That is given graph X.
We try to replace it
into equivalent graph Y.
By equivalent, I
mean, Y is guaranteed
to give you the
same results as X.
But sometimes, there are
some other opportunities.
For example, maybe I can
find a pattern which is X,
and then I replace X with Y,
but Y is not guaranteed to
give equivalent results with X.
But why much faster than X.
Maybe ten times faster
or two times faster.
And then I can compensate
the results, right?
Uh, S Y and X has a difference
of add a few positions
of the matrix,
but I can add another operator
that compens results
to make sure,
uh, after applying a
compensation operator,
the results will be equivalent.
Right? And then I can
basically in the previous
30 space of tassel,
we miss all these kind
of opportunities.
Okay. And in this work, I'm
going to introduce this way.
That is, uh, in this
in this final example,
uh, on the left hand side, we
have the fully equivalent
transformations.
On the right hand side,
we have the partially
equivalent transformations.
Uh, so basically for FET,
uh, these two graphs is going
to give you exactly
the same results.
But in this PT is not.
But by enabling the PT 30 space,
sometimes we can even get
better performance, Okay?
Yeah. They only
generate a few operators.
They don't generate
field operators.
No. Yeah, yeah.
So at some point,
still need to field by
yourself and you need to write
your own field operator.
But like I said,
the field operator
can be done using
operator compiler.
Yeah. Yeah. You can ask
operator compiler to generate
code of field operator.
Yeah. Okay? These are
two different levels.
Yeah. Cool. The
idea is basically,
um, uh, if we only limit
our 30 space into FET,
we are going to miss
some opportunities.
How about we just
open space to PT,
PT can give us
better performance,
but we need to find a
way to correct it back,
because the results
is not equivalent,
we need to complement results.
Okay? So how to do that.
So to give you a
motivating example, okay,
I want you to recall
a little bit,
um on convolution com two D.
Okay? So in convolution, we
have this example, right.
So here in this pre, we have
two inputs, uh, two images,
for example, and
I have a filter,
which is the green
one, small filter.
Uh I column two D,
I'm going to apply
this small filter over these
two images separately,
and I get slightly, uh, uh,
smaller like feature map,
which is blue at the bottom.
Okay. I hope you
still remember how to
apply this com two.
So one way to do this
is we notice that if we
concatenate this one yellow
orange maps together,
and we apply the same operator,
we can run much faster.
Why? Because we reduce
kernel launches and also a lot
of memory IO, for example.
But the problem is
the two D run at
a very weird way that
is you need to handle
boundary conditions.
You know, original
one, I just scan
each feature map from lab
right from top to bottom.
But if I concatenate the
input fissure map together,
I will find that in a boundary,
those two columns are going to
give you slightly
different results
if you put them together.
Okay. Like I said,
the second column runs much
faster than the first column.
I still want to leverage
the opportunity, how to do.
So at some point,
I still do this.
But I can add some composition.
I can manage some value,
I calculated using
the middle column
and I try to correct
the results back.
Okay? And so this
high level idea is
basically like I try
to redefine space
that um I try
to explore this kind of like
a PT partially equivalent
transformations,
and then I add some results
back to still guarantee
the results are exact.
But uh that allows me
to explore all the kind
of hidden opportunities.
Makes sense, right?
Okay. Cool. So I'm
going to go through
the entire process.
This is another
compiler developed by
the TesoGroup and I
think they are also
applied in torch comple
in some way, yeah.
Um, so how we can basically
automate this entire process.
So So the idea,
the workflow is basically
illustrated on this slide.
So what do we do is
given input program,
we are going to
generate auto mutant.
Uh, you can think of this mutant
basically a u substitutions.
I don't call it substituting
because it's not equivalent.
That's why I call it mutant.
Okay? Uh, I'm going to
generate auto mutant,
and I'm going to apply
this mutant to my
original program to
get a faster version.
And then I check if
the mutty program
has an arrow from the
previous program.
And if yes, I'm going to add
some mutant corrector
to correct it back.
Okay? And because I
add some additional operators
in the graph, right,
in order to fix the results,
so that basically enlarges
the entire graph,
uh, possibly enlarge
the entire graph.
So what I do is I'm going to
manually fuse them
together later. Okay?
And by applying fusion,
then I can basically,
uh, make sure.
So it's basically not
guaranteed fusion,
it's opportunistic
fusion, so I can
basically try to maximize
the last speed of
my performance.
Okay, then it becomes it
boils down to two questions?
One is how to
mutate the program,
how to discover this
kind of mutant.
And second is how to correct,
once I apply a mutant.
Okay? So how to mutate?
Um, it is very
similar to basically,
uh, you can basically
connect this to previous.
The way we mutate it we
continue to enumerate.
Enumerating is one of the best
things you do in
computer science.
Yeah, it's skills. Okay?
You try to enumerate
all possible programs up to
a fixed size using all
available operators.
But this time, instead
of only finding
those mathematically
equivalent operations,
you try to keep
more of them, okay?
Um, so instead of
only finding aft,
you are going to also preserve
those that is PT, okay?
But here, I want
to still make sure
that the search
space is manageable.
So instead of keeping all the
different kind of mutants,
still remember the
base number right
66 million. So that's too much.
So instead of doing that,
what I'm going to do is uh,
I'm going to give
it random input.
And I don't check
the value of the
random, uh, the output.
I only check the shapes
because I can use shape as
weak filter to make sure that
these mutants roughly provide
the same shape of outputs,
but their results
could differ, okay?
So that can control
my search space
to not explode, right?
And then once we apply
this kind of mutant,
we need to basically, uh,
detect if these kind of
results are correct.
I basically they are equivalent,
they turn out to be fully
equipment transform machine,
then we don't have a
problem. We are good.
But if that's not the case,
we need to consider
the second step
that is we need to
correct the results back.
Okay? So then we are figuring,
we are facing
another problem that
is how we can
verify, for example,
in this example, program
F equals to prime G,
considering G is a
mutant of F, right?
So One way to
basically verify we check
position map position, right?
We just give the random inputs
and we check position
me position in
output space and if
all the position
matches, then we good.
But this is apparently
quite slow,
what we do is, uh,
instead we check
positive M position,
we can do some optimization.
But before we
introduce openation,
let's try to see how
slow this is, okay?
So the complexity is
roughly written as
M times N where M is all
the possible inputs, right?
And N is all the
output positions.
So basically, if we want
to really verify if
this are correct,
we basically need to enumerate
all the input M inputs and
check on all the
positions for each input.
So the complexity is bien.
Okay. And in order
to make this factor,
I think our goal is
basically trying
to reduce both M and N,
to figure out how to verify.
Okay? Let's talk
about one by one.
So we'll first talk
about how to reduce N.
N is basically the
output position
of the feature map, for
example, in column two.
So how to basically
make this factor.
And it turns out this one is
pretty straightforward and
very easy big machinery.
Okay? So, our high level idea
is can we just check out
a few or even just one
position instead of
every output position to
assert the correctness
or incorrectness, right?
And it turns out that
we can't do that.
Why? Because, um, for
majority of competition
in machine learning,
they have a very nice
mathematical property that is,
uh, it's called multilinear.
So what is multilinear?
Multinear is basically
a function F is
multilinear if the output
is linear to all inputs.
And I can actually illustrate
this property in
the equation below.
That is, for any
input, I can basically
linearly transform
it and the results
can be corresponding
linearly transform.
For example, adding a scholar,
time scholar or whatever, okay?
And it turns out that for many,
many machinery operators,
like, 80% of them.
So basically they
are multi linear.
And this table basically
give you a sense.
Okay, I want you to
look at this table.
Some very important
operators, for example,
come, met mo, they
are multilinear.
So you can linearly
transform the input and
the output will be
correspondingly transform.
Why we care about this
multinear characteristic.
The reason we care about it is
because we have this serum.
So for two multinear
function F and G, uh,
if F equals to G for region
01 position in upper region,
then we can observe that
fix to G for all positions.
Okay? So why is this important?
Because, originally,
we need to check all the
output positions, right.
And now, if we know that
this operator is going
to be multilinear,
we just need to check a
few positions and we can
assert their their
equivalent, right?
So one example is,
uh, in column two.
Every time we apply
a filter, right,
we all result into
a region that is,
say, three by three
or four by four.
And in that region,
we don't need
to check all four
by four regions.
We just need to
check one. And if
their results are equivalent,
we know the upper region
are actually equivalent.
Okay. And this can effectively
reduce our three space,
the index machine from
lumber output positions into
lumber regions,
we need to check.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Okay. Any question?
Yeah. Uh huh.
What do you mean by activation?
No, no, that's nonlinear.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah.
But you need to
think in this way.
So remember the MS que we
did at the beginning, right?
The one that is your most flops
is linear functions, right?
Because we can't give up
optimizing Lu because
it's going to be slow.
We know it's going
to be slow, right?
Yeah. Okay. This one is
pretty clever, right.
So basically, you try to
leverage this kind of
multineity and try to
reduce the dimension of
N from N to R. Okay.
And now we are trying
to figure out how to
reduce M. You still
remember, right.
So we need to check for
each possible input.
And as long as if
each possible input,
they are equivalent or
they are not equivalent,
then we can figure out
how to correct later,
right directly applying
this transformation.
Okay? How to check M?
Okay. The way we
check them is still,
we are going to
place on math, okay?
And we have this theorem.
Okay? So if there exists input
I uh two transformation F and G,
at several position,
there exists
input at the position P,
their value are different.
Then the probability
that F and G,
given identical results on
T random inputs is very
small, explly small.
Okay, I would like to
appreciate this
theorem a little bit.
Why is this therm
help us reduce?
The reason because
what this theorem,
what we can do is
basically, instead
of running all the
possible inputs,
we can run T random tests
where T is a small number,
and we know that if AT passed,
if AT passed, it's very
unlikely that this F
and G are equivalent.
The probability is very small.
So what we can do is
maybe instead of small t,
we can use relative largity
and we can basically see
the probability that
they are equivalent
in equivalent is
going to diminish.
At some point, if one random
input is going to be um,
produce different results,
we know that they
are not equivalent,
but if all pass,
likely they are equivalent.
Okay. This is a pretty nice
theorem, random testing.
Okay. Yeah. With this theorem,
what we can do is
we can continue,
reduce the search dimensing
M u from M all the
way to T, right?
Here, we notice that T is
greatly smaller than M,
and is much smaller than than N.
Then we can use this
kind of tricks to
basically uh accelerate
verification.
Okay. Yeah. With that, I think,
uh, we figure out
how to basically,
uh, uh, we know how to
generate mutant, right.
We also know how
to verify results.
Then what we do is basically
we follow this workflow.
We generate a lot of mutants,
we try to verify if these
two mutants are equivalent.
If they are equivalent,
we are good.
It's basically reduced
to the problem of,
uh, uh, fully equivalent
transformations.
If they are not equivalent,
then it's PT Pat.
And if it's pat, what we
do is we add some mutant.
So in this example, sorry,
add some multan correction.
So in this example,
we first apply
mutant and then we figure out,
okay, they have some regions
that are not equivalent.
So we try to add
another operator
that basically
perform another very,
very thin, uh,
convolution and try to
correct results back.
And like I said, because
of this operation,
you introduce another
additional com
and this potentially can
harm the performance.
So what do we do is we
try to handle manually
uh field them all together
into one field operator, okay?
Cool. Uh, to do a recap, okay?
So we talk about works, right?
One is um fully equipment
transformation.
The other is p partially
equipment transformation,
and they are basically
fall into the workflow
actually in the middle that
is defined search space, um,
try to figure out the
equivalent graphs, uh,
build a cost model and then
try to apply this subject in
the graph and figure out the one
that basically give you
the best performance.
Yeah. And the reason
they are very,
um, very good is
because they automate
the entire process.
And so the developer
does not know how
to write so many
passes manually and
does not know how to do
that again and again
for each graph, each
model, whatever.
Okay. Any question? Cool, cool.
Okay, I think I
already summarized
this slide and I'm
going to skip this one.
Then let's do something
that's really fun, okay?
I think that's all
the compiler stuff I
want to cover in this lecture
in this course, actually.
I'm not going to I'm
not going to talk about
compiler anymore.
Yeah, this is all
the compiler talk.
But later I'm going
to have a invite
invite speaker to talk about
later in a deeper way.
But I want to do a
retrospective on what people on
this community have done
in compiler research
and where we achieved.
Okay? So to begin that,
I'm going to give you a
history, okay, revisit.
So roughly our compiler
research start from 2013.
Okay? At that point,
we are not doing
machine aring compiler.
It's not at least we
don't give it name called
machining compiler, okay?
The first thing we call
is called highlight.
This highlight was developed
by MIT PD student,
and that guy is not
doing machine learning.
He was doing like graphics.
So he basically developed a
compiler that help people to
more convenient conveniently
write graphics rendering code.
Okay? Why why I
mentioned this because you
probably know a lot of
operations in rendering
is also metmo
something related with Mtmo
So they do a lot of telling.
They do a lot of
operator compilation.
And this highlight actually was
very famous in the
graphics community.
But at some point,
I think, when Machine
learning took off,
people started realizing
that we should
probably double down on
augmenting Machin
learning workload.
That's the first compiler
come out, right, LA.
I mentioned this in L
lecture, okay? Google stuff.
Okay. Uh, it basically
come out at 20:16 to 2017.
Okay. But the problem
with XLA is first,
is a very closed community.
Uh, Google don't talk
about a lot on this.
They try to sell
tenterflow inside XO.
XOE is only a bacon layer.
And I'm not sure if
you guys have experience
working on XOI,
but uh, XOI code is very
hard to understand.
It's very very low level.
It has many many very
deep competitive stuff
where I don't think,
machine learning researcher
can easily, grasp, okay?
So then, um, uh, meanwhile,
Google is pushing a
direction of compilation
for machinery and some
other communities,
they are pushing a
different direction.
So they are saying, I'm not
going to do compilation.
I'm not going to
automate this process.
I'm going to give you a
handcraft free library
where I hand craftly I
manually write many,
many templates and
field operations
I give it to you and you
figure out by yourself, okay?
No automated pure hand graphy.
And some very famous
library tension RT, right?
You probably heard about
this one from media.
And Codon is the one that
still used widely today.
The way that media
ships Codon is they
ask their developers to write
a binary code for a kernel.
And they compare the
binary code into
a very fast kernel
and give it to you.
No one can understand
what's going
on there, but it's just fast.
Yeah. Okay. And also onyx,
OI is another um kind of
mid layer language for you
to exchange models between
different frameworks.
And you can think it does
a semi compiler thing.
Okay? It is basically
intermediarenton for,
uh, for models, and it can
be used across
different frameworks.
For example, you can define a
model in Onyx and it can be
read or understood by both pity.
And then in 2018, we know
TVM TM is open source, uh,
uh, compiler that basically,
uh very famous, okay.
And in 2019 and 2020,
we have a very famous
language called MIR.
Apparently, MIR is
not a compiler,
it's just a layering compiler.
So ML stands for
machine learning and
R stands for
intermediate repton.
That means that
they want to build
machine intermediate repreention
in the compile layer.
So, uh, upper to this layer,
you can define your machinering
model in whatever language.
And it can be lowered into this,
uh IR and lower to this layer,
you can basically, uh,
try to optimize this R,
for example, you can
extract a graph definition.
You can extract operator
definition from this R,
you can optimize operator,
you can optimize graphs, right
across different frameworks.
This one was driven
by Google, okay?
And there are also flex flow,
which basically are works.
I just introduced tassel
and PT and FET, graph
transformation.
And then up to today, I think
the one that is pretty famous is
basically torch touch
compel touch dynamo.
Ti Dynamo is basically,
you can understand it
as intermediate
representation for torch.
Okay. And between
these four years,
I think there are more than
500 compiler papers written,
people are basically
all the researchers
in machine learning and systems,
they are all in this field and
you try to develop
a better compiler.
Okay. Then I have
ultimate question.
So why the community is shifting
away from compeer today.
The reason I ask this
question because in
this course, one of my goal is,
I try to help you
acquire the ability of
predicting the future.
Okay? Because if you look back,
people are not doing
compari anymore, why?
Yeah, that's one partial reason,
but not the primary reason.
Yeah, I feel so.
Yes, it doesn't make money,
but I feel researchers
probably don't have to
go making money, right?
Like for example, PD students,
they also don't
work on computers.
So I'm going to
offer my argument,
but you guys should figure
out this by yourself.
Sorry. So you guys still
remember throughout this course,
throughout the
past few lectures,
I'm keeping saying that the
main argument of compiler
is you are going to
have so many models,
so many operators,
and so many hardwares, and
you are not going to hire
enough people to develop
operators and op ditions
for them, right?
So basically assume that
your machinery model is
going to still diverge.
So most people is going to
develop new architectures
and new hardware
to support this kind of,
like, workloads, right?
Only with a divers enough
machinery architectures
and hardware and operators,
we can see the value of compiler
because it saves humans time.
But what happens today
especially after 2020
is there's one architecture
that dominates all
machinery architecture.
That is transformer
on ARM there's
one hardware that dominates
all the hardware
that is medius GPU,
people have been spending
years optioning compilers.
But at some point, when the
GPD is three paper out,
everyone start working only
on transformers on DPU.
If you simplify this problem,
my mission is I just
make sure I'm going
to maximize the
performance of transformer
on GPU. Do I need a compiler?
No, right? I basically
just need to hire
a few Koula engineers
and who are really
good at transformers,
I just field everything
together, right?
For transformers. That's
all I need to do.
Okay? That's really
what happened.
So you need to see
this kind of trends to
understand how the
technology will evolve.
Oh that's also why
flash attention succeed
at the end because
at some point,
there's a guy who invented
this algorithm and it
rate pretty sophisticated
kernel just for attention,
other attention so fast
that every compeller
cannot compete.
Indeed, a compiler can provide
values for different
operator, but I don't care.
I only hear about flashing
teaching today, right?
Yeah. That's why.
That's my argument.
But you can figure out
about yourself, okay?
Uh, I want to foster this
discussion between you guys.
So maybe you can
predict next thing.
For example, for
me, as a faculty,
I'm trying to figure out what is
the next thing I should work
on because if I work on that,
if I buy the right thing, maybe
I can even something like
a flash and people will
basically, uh maximizes usage.
Okay? Cool. Uh lastly,
we have this guest speaker
who is coming next Thursday.
Uh, If you slightly
into machinery system,
you probably see
this phase, right.
His name is Chen Chen
and I call him the
GOAT marcheing system.
The best one, yeah,
the only best one.
Okay. And he invented
this three frameworks,
probably many of you
have used, right?
X Boost TAM.
And today he's
working on MLC IM.
MLC stands for
marchearing compilation.
Okay. And the date
is February 6.
Okay, cool. That's
all I have today.
And next lecture, we are
going to touch runtime. Okay.