Okay. Yeah. Thanks for coming.
Yeah. Let's get started
with today's content.
Yeah. So, again, recap
the big picture.
So we know how
to represent a machine learning
program, dataflow graph.
We also know it's
competition forward,
backward, which was
powered by AD libraries.
You guys already implemented
in your homework, okay?
And in that graph, we
get a lot of things.
One is, many many operators.
So we talk about how
to optimize operators,
especially those important ones,
right, uh, using accelerators.
The other is we have
a graph, right.
We need to run that graph.
So we have to optimize graph,
and we talk about that.
I think last lecture.
There are automatic ways,
there are template ways,
right, either by experts
or by some compilers.
Okay. Then basically we
have most of the elements
ready in that graph, right?
We are going to orchestrate
the execution now, okay?
We need to put data into
the graph and try to
get results, okay?
And today we are going to start
touching on that part
that is run time, okay?
So before I talk about run time,
so just again, recap, right?
We are doing this
kind of optimization.
Uh, our goal is trying to
optimize the parameters,
and we optimize it
in a way that is,
uh, a loop, right?
So we're looping
over the dataset.
And every time we fetch
a batch of data and,
uh, we calculate gradients
and update parameters again
and again until convergence.
Okay. So here, there's a very,
very important concept, batch.
This word is abused in
many many different areas
in machine learning
in parallelism
in data processing big data,
like everyone using batch.
So before I talk about
runtime, I want to first, um,
make sure we are
on the same page
when we talk about batch, okay?
So what batch means,
there are a few minutes.
So in the context
of this course,
I think we are
basically talking about
batch in the context
of deploying, right?
So here in deploying,
especially in deploying
training, what does batch mean?
It's basically a group of
data samples we get from
the bigger data set that can be
executed on a graph in
the same wrong, right?
So that is a batch.
And we derive a gradient
for each batch,
and we apply the gradient
to the parameters.
And that is called stochastic
gradingt descent. Right.
Okay. But many places,
you probably also hear
about minibatch and
micro baatch, right?
So how are they
different from batch?
Okay. So minibatch actually,
it is a term from option.
Okay? So in optim edition,
we have batch of open addon
and minibatch opmentation.
And here, so basically we
generalize this
minibatch a little
bit into the mini
batch in depending.
Basically in
depending minibatch,
you can think minibatch
equals to batch, okay?
That is every time we
sample bachel data,
and in optim edition, people
call that minibatchel data.
Okay? And what is macro baatch?
So macro is smaller
than mini, right?
So what is micro
baatch? Anyone knows.
Okay. You can tell that
from its name, right.
So micro baatch is definitely
something that even
smaller than a batch.
Okay, I already told you
that batch equals to
minibatch in differently.
So microbatch is a smaller
quantity than batch.
That is we can fer split
a batch into many,
many smaller batches and we call
that small batch a minibatch.
Oh, sorry, microbatch.
I was confused,
sorry. Yeah. Micro baatch.
Okay. And you're probably
wondering why we need a
micro baatch and a batch,
and I'm going to
review that later.
Okay, it's a very
important concept
when we start talking
about memory,
about parlesms, okay?
But just remember, microbatch is
a smaller thing
than batch, okay?
So a batch has many
microbatches, okay?
Okay, back to the second
area in optimation we
study this kind of
opiation kind of
theory and algorithms,
especially grading descent.
I think people there, they use
a slightly different term.
So they have two kinds
of, for example,
for SGD, for grading descent,
they have two kinds
of algorithms.
One is called a full
batch grading descent.
The other is called
stochastic grading descent.
Okay? So in deep learning,
we mostly just use stochastic
grading descent, right,
because every time we just
sample a small batch,
and we try to perform
grading updates.
But in option, uh,
there's, like, ina version
of grading descent.
That is basically,
they will basically
calculate grading over
the entire dataset.
Okay, which means that your
batch is equal to your,
uh, size of data,
okay, entire data set.
So that is called a batch
batch gradient descent.
But we don't use that
depending on why.
Yeah, because data is too
large, we cannot do that.
We don't have enough
memory, right?
Okay? Okay. Just to make sure
that you try to understand
the batch and minibatch
and microbatch.
Okay? And in big data
processing, for example,
in the community
of how to spark,
people also use this
word batch, right?
So usually this word is used to
distinguish it from two kind
of processing paradigm.
One is called batch processing.
The other is called
streaming processing.
And you can also probably
tell from the meaning of
this word that batch processing
is basically offline processing.
That is I'm giving
the engine a task,
and this task is
trying to process
the data in a very big
dataset into another format.
And I directly fed all the data,
the entire data
set to the engine
and I wait for the results.
That is called offline
batch processing, right?
And in contrast,
streaming processing
is basically online processing.
For example, when you
submit Google query,
uh, you can submit it anytime,
right, depending
when you use Google.
But on Google side, they
are basically
receiving your data.
They are listening to your data
and try to basically
respond to your query.
And in order to
respond to your query,
they need to process your data.
And they need to receive
many many queries
from all kinds of users
in the world, right?
That is streaming processing.
Okay. So in big data processing,
uh, well when we see batch,
it basically means offline.
Okay? And when we see streaming
is basically means online.
Okay? Clear? Cool.
So most of today's course,
we are going to
focus on, you know,
batch minibatch, and
microbatch, okay?
Cool. And I also
put the table here.
I think I already repeat
the content in previously,
but you can review
this table layer.
So it gives some, like,
a very clear definition of
what do we mean when we see
batch in different contexts.
Okay, with that, uh, we start
talking about today's
learning goal.
Okay, we are going to talk
about memory and scheduling,
because in order for us to run
the comping graph and operators,
on our target device, we need
to subject to
memory constraints,
because we have
limited memory, okay?
We're talking about a few very
important memory
organization techniques.
And I believe this lecture is
very practical and very useful.
And if you are able to get it,
I think you can directly apply
it the other day because this is
very well adopted techniques
in pets in deep learning
in large model training.
Okay? And if time permits,
we are going to talk
about start talking
about our next big topic
that is quantization.
And apparently, I put this
together because quantization,
uh, its original goal is
trying to save memory, right?
But at some point, you know,
media starts to make
quantization also faster,
so it can also
accelerate the compute.
Okay? Cool. So why
memory is an issue
because of this, right?
I think I repeat this
figure again and again
in different contexts
in different lectures,
B of memory hierarchy,
because of the limit
of one computer,
um, so our computer store
things in memory hierarchy,
and at every layer
at a higher layer,
the memory is faster,
but it's more expensive.
At lower layer, the
memory is much slower,
but we have a lot of space.
Um, so this is basically
the memory hierarchy when we
put GPUs into a computer.
And it gives you a sense like,
uh, how many memory you
have at each layer.
Deplaning competition, where
is the computing happening?
It's on the device on GPUs.
Basically, most of the
time we just put things
on uh global memory
which is HBM.
Sometimes we put data in RAM,
which is the CPU memory,
and we read data from disc
all the way to the RAM.
In general, today,
you can think RAM is
very abundant resources
because if you go,
uh tabs and you try to
swap any GPU instances,
you get a lot of RM for example,
at least one terabytRMs.
Okay. And then the higher level
of memory is mostly used for
accelerating computation,
for example, doing
telling, doing,
those kind of things we
covered in previous lecture.
The important thing here is, we
have limited global memory,
but we still want to train
a decent large model,
so how to do that?
Um, so before we talk about
those ougmenting techniques,
I think one important
thing we need to think
is memory is very
different resources
compared to compute, okay?
So in computer, we want to
be as fast as possible.
So we want to maximize
our computing speed
so that given limited
computing power,
we can compute much faster.
We can get our results faster.
But in memory, our goal is not
trying to minimize memory.
Okay, our goal is trying to make
sure our peak memory when
we execute the computing graph
is smaller than
available memory.
Don't how to minimize it.
We just need to make sure
the peak memory is smaller
than the one that is allowed.
Okay? So to make this
even more clear,
I think, normally we don't how
to me memory. We don't
how to me memory.
As long as we can
basically reduce memory in
a way that can fit into GPO
are good. We don't
want to minimize it.
Okay. And we also do not
want to mi max memory.
So max memory is basically
the peak memory.
We also do not want to minimize
the peak memory, okay?
And so go is
basically we try to make
sure that max memory,
which is a peak memory
is smaller than
available memory unless
otherwise specified.
And I'm going to
talk about it later.
Okay? Remember this go, is
very different from compute.
Okay. Okay. So in
order to understand where
the memory consumption
comes from,
I think we want to do
it step by step, right.
We want to first understand
how deep learning programs,
consume memory. Okay?
Then the first question I ask
is given this kind
of combiniograph,
I think we did this in
our third lecture, right?
This is MSC one layer neural
network with MSE loss.
Okay? Given this kind
of continuo graph,
what is the source of
memory consumption?
Anyone want to answer? Okay,
let me go through that.
So there are major
needs resources,
and I want you to
remember this, okay?
So in the future, when you
touch any deploying program,
you always try to figure
out the usage from
these resources.
Okay? The first one is
model weights, right?
You are given a model. No
matter it's trained or not,
you basically need to allocate
memory for stored model weights.
For example, you want
to train a rest.
A restaurant
typically has several
minions of parameters and
you need to store the minions of
parameters in memory in HBM.
When you try to train three,
it has 175 bunion.
You have to store
this 175 opinion.
So that is a source of
memory consumption, right?
And once you store the
motorways into your TPO memory,
what you need to do is you
need to perform compute, right?
You need to run
run run operators following
the graph structure.
So every time when
you run operators,
your operator is
going to produce
something that is more
than motorways, right?
For example, activations,
we call that activations.
So so the second source of
memory consumption is basically
the intermediate
activation values.
For example, you give a
data badge and you multiply
the data batch with
your model with W
through a metam and
you produce output.
And the output is basically
intermediate activation values.
And you have to store
them in memory in
some way because you have to
store them in the backward pass,
you can use it to drive
your gradients, right?
So the second source is
intermediate activ values.
So there's a third source.
What is that? Data, Data,
you can see the data is
basically the input.
The first version of
intermediate acting values.
Yeah. Gross stutre
is pretty small.
It's basically
code. Yes, exactly.
Gradients. So you have
to store gradients.
But because eventually, you
want to dup the gradients
and apply the gradiens
to the parameters to
get the next iteration
and you repeat.
But, it's more than gradients.
Why? Because we use very
complicated opimeods and
the way we apply updates is
not just we simply add the
gradients to the parameters.
Sometimes we do a lot more
complicated manipulation,
right?
We probably want to
manipulate the gradients
by timing it with something
and plot something
and then apply it to
the parameter to stabilize
the training, right?
And this is typically done in
some advanced opium meters
such as atom, right?
So we call this
part opitor states.
Okay. So that basically
give you a global picture
what consumes memory in
deep learning
program three parts,
model weights, activations
and open menor states.
And I think you need to
memorize this because, um,
a very important factor later
when we talk about deep model,
a big models like
activities language model,
we are basically
grinding this again
and again and again, okay?
Cool. Okay, that'll give
you a global picture.
And then, in order to analyze
the memory consumption,
I think we basically care
about two things right.
Remember our goals we make sure
the peak memory is smaller
than available memory.
Okay? But how to
determine peak memory?
So in order to
determine peak memory,
um we need to figure
out two things, right.
What is the size of
those things, right?
For example, how large
is the model parameters,
how large is the
intermediate activations,
and how large is
the opimeter state?
That's the size.
Okay? The second is
lifetime. Why is peak memory?
Because sometimes some memory
will be used, but sometimes not.
So we care about the peak.
In order to figure out the peak,
we need to make sure
we need to understand
each tensor in the
deep learning program
when we ask you the program,
when it all be alive and when
it all not alive, right?
Because we don't care about
the step tensors because we
don't allocate memory for them.
We only allocate memory
when we need them,
so we care about their lifetime.
Okay? So in the
following lectures,
uh, in the following
contents of this lecture,
we are going to always look at
different tensors
in the program,
but we are going to, uh,
I want you guys to remember,
we basically care about
two things of them.
One is the size. Second
is the lifetime, okay?
Okay, let's start with
a very simple example.
This is a very simple neural
network, right, one input,
two linear, one al,
and one loss, five nodes.
Assume we don't
twin it, assuming
this model is already trained,
we just perform inference,
and let's try to analyze
the memory usage of
this inference graph.
Okay. So in order to inference,
we basically get
input data, right,
and we fit the data
all the way from left
to right. So how
many memory we need?
So these three items,
for motorways,
during the entire
inference process,
we can we basically,
throw them away?
We cannot, right, because we
help to keep them alive on
GPUs in order to perform
this kind of computation
from left to right.
So for motorways it'll be alive
across the lifetime throughout
the lifetime, okay?
So for activations, like
how we basically deal
with activation memory.
So at the first time,
we have a input which
is data, right?
And then we fit the data
into linear, we
get output, right?
And then can through
the data away.
Yes, we don't care
about that, right,
because as long as we get
the output of the linear,
we can basically
through the data
and discard the data
because we can proceed
following this graph structure
and eventually we can still
get the loss, accurate
results, right?
So basically, once we proceed
the computation of linear,
we can discard the data
and we need to keep the
output of the linear,
which is the intermediate
activation, right?
And then we keep doing
this keep doing this,
we rotating those buffer
across different operators.
So basically, this tells us
if we perform inference,
we just need O
memory for computing
the final output of
layer Depar network,
by cycling through
two buffers, right.
Okay. Makes sense, right?
Okay, cool. So we
already any For weights,
I think lifetime is basically
throughout the entire inference.
For activations, we only
care about where we
are now at which
layer we are, okay?
For open matter states,
we don't have it.
It's inference. We
don't care about that.
Cool. This is an easy one, okay?
Then we also need to
estimate the size
of which buffer we
created, right?
So how we store weight,
what's the size of
the weight and how we
store intermediate
activations and
what's the size of them.
And one key factor
that we need to determine
the size is basically,
in what precisions
we store, right?
What what data resentation
we use to store data?
Uh, Here I give three very
typical data resentations
in deep learning.
The first one is floating 0.32.
Okay. The second one is
flowing points B float 16.
And third one is
flowing 0.16, okay?
We already call it the first
one is basically 32 bits.
Okay. Second one BF 16,
third one P 16, okay?
These are very very
common used data types,
we use in deping.
So do you know how actually,
how many of you know how
data was stored
following this bis?
Cool, cool, cool.
We are going to come
back to this later.
Okay. This is very important.
I need to make sure all you guys
know exactly how
it has stored in
this bits because in order to
understand deeper
in contadation,
we have to understand this.
But we're going to come
back to this later.
But here, the big message is
essentially for each
value in a tensor,
we can either store
it in 32 bits,
which equals to four
bytes or 16 bits,
which equals to two bytes.
And we have some other
lower precision,
but here, let's focus
on the three, okay?
By the way, the B flow 16.
What does B stand for?
Sorry? Yes. Bring.
I don't know why,
but it's a lame.
Come up by Google, okay?
Yeah. Cool. Um, oh, welcome
back to this later.
Okay. Then I'm going to do
a very practical example.
Okay. This is a
table. I quoted from
the very phenomenon GBD paper.
One of the best paper
of probably in the
past ten years, right?
And this is the table
that describes the GBD,
different archectures all the
way from the smallest GBD r
to the actual GPs that is
175 billion parameters.
And you can read you
can basically read
the columns, the
column names, right?
The first column is model lame.
Second one, second is
lumber parameters, right?
It gives you a sense, how many
parameters that model has.
Third column amber layers.
Okay. First column D model.
So here D model
basically stands for
the hidden dimension
of transformers.
Okay? So you can understand
it as the H in dpering.
In head is amber he in
much head attention,
come back to this
layer in LM. Okay.
And the Di had is DHAd
is the head dimension.
Okay. Also a hidden
dimension for each head.
And the batch side is
basically the bat side we
use to train this model,
right? Still memory
batch, right?
So it's basically the
batch install castra des.
Okay. And learning
rate is basically how
we update updates
to the parameters.
Okay? We're going to
use this example.
We try to analyze the memory
usage of these models, okay.
So remember three parts
right model ways, um,
uh, activations and opon
states. We'll start one by one.
Okay. So for model ways,
let's just look at the
biggest one, okay?
The biggest one has 175
billion parameters, right?
And for each parameter,
we either store it in 16
bits or 32 bits, right?
So how many memory we use?
We basically times two
values together, right?
And we get, um,
this number 175 billion
times two or four.
So basically, in order
to store TBD models was,
we need a 350 giga or
70 gigabyte memory.
How many memory you have H 100?
80, right? Which means
that it's impossible
to train this model
on H 100, right?
That's a problem.
Okay. We're going to
address that problem soon.
But this is basically
the reality check.
Okay. And in fact,
um, we use two bites.
We use 16 bits for
that, for TPT three.
Okay, so the room thumb to
estimate the model size,
the primter size, basically,
we first check the
precision for example,
when we read the
machinery in paper,
we check what precision
used to model parameters.
Like I said, most
models they are stored
either in 16 bits or 32 bits.
And once we figure
out precision,
we basically use times
two or four to get the size
of the model parameters.
Okay. Clear. Okay. Then we
start estimating
activations or second,
uh, memory consumption, okay?
So for activations, I'm going to
run through a few examples
because like I said,
uh, for different operators
in the dataflow graph,
its activation is
different depending
on its operator definition and
competion we are
going to basically
cover a few very important
operators. Okay.
Still remember this one, this is
column two D. I covered
that in my second lecture.
It's basically like you apply
a filter through
the fissure map,
Your input is the
activation produced by
the previous layer
and your output
is basically your
own activation.
So in order to estimate the size
of the activation
for column two D,
we basically look at input
and oppose size, right?
So for input, we have four
dimensional tensor, right?
BS which stands for byte size.
Number of images you give
to that neural network.
NC is the number of
channels, right?
For the first layer input,
the number channel
equals to three,
because the image was
represented using RTB, okay?
And then WN HI is
basically height and
weight of input
feature map, right?
So basically your input, um,
uh, is BSN WHI,
and you apply a filter and
you basically get BSN C WSU,
where WSU stands for the
size of the fissure map.
Therefore, your activation is
basically the size of
the output fure map.
So how many values we have?
We just time all these
together, right?
And then we need to time
the size of element.
So it depends on what kind of
precision you use
to store value.
But mostly in most
coverution networks,
we use 32 bits.
Okay, it's slightly different
from transformer, okay?
So that value should be four.
In most nutwors, okay,
most commotion networks.
Okay. Then we do a
very simple one,
which is a met M.
X is our input.
W weights and C is the output.
So we estimate the
activation, very easy.
Input three dimensional tensor.
The original matrix was by
the shape of times three,
but we have a B side dimension,
right, so wet all them together.
Uh the W is of
the shape by P. So when
we apply this met M,
we basically get Bs
times M times P, right?
That's our output activation.
Okay. Of course, you need to
multiply a size of element,
depending on what
procedure you use.
Cool. This one is easy, right?
Okay, sort of, of
course, transformers.
Okay? We are going to ground
this transformer a
lot and like I said.
So what is the size of
transformers activation?
Uh, no, let's ignore
all the intermediate
operators. Okay.
We only focus on
input and output.
Okay. So what input it takes?
Yeah, so the first dimension
definitely by size, right?
So we fit a batch of sequences.
But the question is what's the
second or third dimension?
Uh. So there's a
embedding side, right.
Embedding size is
basically how you
encode the word into embeddings.
But compared to Mat Mo there's
one more dimension
which basically
we're not modeling
sequences, right?
So we have a sequence
lens dimension, okay?
So our input is basically uh,
batch size times H,
H is embedding size
and sequas, okay?
And here, you probably
spot the difference.
So basically the
activation actually
grows with a few things, right.
In the previous math model,
it only grows with, for example,
battery size and edge,
but here you add one word
dimension with sequence sans.
That's why, uh, in the
language model community,
people always trying to
develop something that
model longer contexts,
and that will raise
a lot of problems in
either computing model and
also in this kind of memory.
Okay? And same thing,
you basically produce exactly
the same ship output, okay?
Um, so here's the
activating sides.
So here I simplify the problem
a little bit because I
only to focus on the
input and output.
But actually, in between, right,
there are so many operators, for
example, teaching softmax,
and they actually also create
some activation values,
um, and but here,
let's skip that for now.
But later we'll
come back to this.
Okay. Cool. Okay. With that,
then we come back to
this GBD example, right?
We understand the
activity and size of, uh,
transformers, and GBD is
essentially
transformers, decoders.
So we now should be able to
estimate the activations
in GVD three, okay?
So now, let's simplify
problem a little bit.
Let'sume sequence
is equal to one.
Okay. That is we just
model sequences of
one token, one word.
Okay. So what is the activation?
So we basically fact some
values from that table, right?
Remember, we need
a battery size,
six lens and a hidden
dimension, right?
Like I said, the D model
basically is a hidden dimension.
Okay? So the activation
of each TPDray um,
transformer layer is basically
BS time sequence and time
Dmdel we look at
the last row, okay?
So the battery size is
basically, 3.2 million.
That's a pretty large bat size,
okay, and the hidden
dimension is 12288.
Okay. And the six line
is equal to one, right?
I said, I think the problem.
So you can see, in
order to 20 GB array,
I just model like a
six line equal to one.
I already need this many
of active memory, right?
So, like I said, I
already told you that
GBs was trained
using P 16, right?
So basically the
first number 78 giga.
So one Y only have eight giga.
So it's impossible to perform
a single forward pass here.
This is just for one layer.
Like how many layer we have?
It's over there, right.
It's 96 layers, okay?
Yeah, this is a little
bit crazy, right?
You can imagine how many
GP we need to 20 GB three.
Okay. One thing I
want to emphasize again is for
each operator inside
of transformer layer,
we also have activations.
We'll come back to
this later. Okay.
Cool. We are still on the
same page for activations.
Okay? Now, let's move to
the third party
open minor states.
Remember, we need to derive
gradients and we need to
manipulate the gradients
and eventually
apply the gradits to
update the parameters.
We all still use
DVDs are example.
We all try to figure out
how many open mind states memory
we need to store opin states.
Let's cut and cheese, okay?
We don't talk about simplices
because we don't care about SGD,
right. We only care about atom.
I already told you that all the
models they are optimizing atom.
So how about we just pass
this algorithm, Adam.
Okay? This is a AAM algorithm.
I quote it from Adam paper.
Okay, I'll let you look
at this a little bit.
Maybe 15 seconds.
Okay, cool, let's pass this.
So the only difference
that between this atom
algorithm and vana SGD.
So remember in vana SGD,
we basic the gradings, right.
We multiply it by a small
learning rate and then
uh add or malance into the
parameter to get the update.
So the only difference between
Adam and and vana stochastical
grading is basically, uh,
in order to actually calculate
the value that is going to be
applied into the parameter,
uh, we need to
manipulate the gradients
using uh the first
and second moment.
The first moment
is basically the
mean and the second moment is
basically the uh the variance.
So in order to do that,
what do we do is,
as we apply different
mini different batches
and we basically mean
some states to track
the moment across the
optimi intrajectory.
And every time when we
calculate a new gradient,
we are going to
update the moment
for first and second
moment, okay?
And if you look at this
line, the last line,
how we apply this primary
update, that is, uh,
we take we normalize
this gradient
and divide it by
standard deviation,
okay, and we apply it.
Okay? Basically, you can think,
The difference between SGD and
atom is we normalize the
gradients in some way.
But in order to
normalize the gradients,
we have to maintain
first and second moment.
The problem is here, we need to
store the first
and second moment,
along the ultimate intrajectory.
Let's look at how
many memory we need.
Okay? So for gradient, uh,
the memory we needed
is basically,
uh, should be the same
size of parameters, right?
So how many parameters,
how many gradients?
So for gradient, basically
in times size of element.
Okay? The first moment
is also in time
cell moment, right?
It's mean, right. And
the second moment
is also in times set of element.
The total op state
we need to perform
atom is basically three
times size of 11.
Okay. This is a little
bit crazy, right,
because I remember
the CP three itself,
the parameters is already
pretty huge, right?
But here we are basically
triple them again,
in order to perform updates.
Yeah. That's basically
the optimal state.
And I think at this point,
you already understand
kind of the distribution
between the um
memory consumption.
Um, compared to parameters,
which is already large, I think,
this one is even larger, right,
because it's three times
of the parameters.
And also, you got many many
intermediate activations,
and it could be large
depending on how your model,
hidden dimension
is and whatever.
Cool. Okay. So next
let's talk about we already
talked about size, right?
Next, we are going to
talk about lifetime.
So what tensors can be
live and what tensors
can be that tensors,
because we want to allocate
memory for those live tensors.
Okay? So now we need to
basically enhance
the inverse graph
a little bit to make
it a training graph.
Okay? So the difference
between training graph and
inverse graph is basically
we have a backward graph,
right, and we also have
optimized state updating graph.
Okay, we combine all together.
So here, um, uh,
I simplify a little bit, I
remove the grading
updated graph.
Okay. I basically map the
backward graph to photograph.
And we can basically fold
this together into one
line that is like this.
Okay, we fold the edges,
forward, backward,
forward, backward.
Uh, so for model parameters,
can we describe
them at any time?
No, Because we need
them to either,
calculate gradings or
apply updates, right?
So mostly, we cannot
describe them.
Um For activations, can we?
To some extent can.
But in this example,
I show example where
we cannot because
um compared to the
inference forward graph,
every time we
calculate the layer,
we can throw anything
before that layer.
But compared to
that example here,
every time we calculate
layer, after it's forward,
we cannot throw it
away immediately
because at some
point we will come
back and we need that activation
again to derive the greits.
So in most cases,
I would say we cannot
describe the activations.
But later we're
going to talk about
some optimizations where we
will be allowed to describe to
see memory, but pay some cost.
Yeah. So to summarize,
basically, uh,
because the need to keep
intermediate values
around for the grading steps.
So training earlier neural
network, compared to inference,
now we need to basically
open because we need to
keep the activations for
every layers output,
right, in order to
perform backward.
So this is the difference
between training and inference.
Okay, now, let's do summarization
for the TPD rate case.
Okay. So for parameters,
we have 175 billion times
either 16 bit or 32 bit.
Okay? For activations, um, uh,
at the transformer boundary
we basically have,
like I said, 78 giga,
and we have 96 layers.
That is basically seven K,
488 giga memory for activations.
Um, like I said, this is not
accurate because transformer
is a composite layer.
There are many many
other operators that
still consume more
memory than this.
Okay. And for optimal
states, like I said,
um, we have three
copies. One is gradient.
The other is first
moment second moment,
three times N,
which is 175 binar.
Okay? And here, one thing
that you need to remember is,
when we apply atom on
whatever kind of
precisions or model,
we always keep the
precision in 32.
Okay? I will come back
to this later because,
but high level intuition
is when we apply
this kind of obrand we
want to have high
precision in order
to basically make sure our
optimization is accurate.
Yeah, we don't want
to lose precision.
Which means that here, we have
to time that by four bytes,
and that gives us another
12 times 175 giga.
So this is basically the
global picture of how many
memory we need to 20 GB three.
Okay? You can do some math.
Afterwards, you add
all this number
together and divide it by 80.
That is the number of GB
we need 23. At a minimum.
Okay. Yeah. Because I
think at a minimum,
you need to first put the model
into that enough memory, right?
Yeah, you don't care
about how long it takes.
At least you need to
offer that memory.
Okay? Cool.
A little bit crazy,
right? And this model
is 500 B, by the way.
Yeah, for example,
deep S 500 600 B.
So basically four times of this.
Cool. Okay, now, you basically
have a global picture
of what is going on
in the memory, right?
Lifetime, um, how to store
the data and three parts,
um, parameter, activation
and open memory states.
And we're going to proceed
to our next system issue,
right, how we can optimize
the memory usage.
Okay? For this part,
we are going to cover,
and this is basically the main
trend emerging learning system
that is how to basically put
this gigantic model
many many devices and
make sure they work.
I'm going to cover two parts.
One is how we do this kind of
single device memory
oganation and of course,
single device has a limit
because you only have 80 giga.
So at some point you know how to
start distributing jobs
across many, many devices.
So that will basically
brings us to
the second part with
plazon but I want to talk
about this part later.
Okay. So let's look
at how we optimize
memory on single device.
So, um, apparently, um,
uh, during the
activation section,
I already kind of hinted
to you guys that, uh,
for activation, uh, actually,
some part of the activation
can be discarded.
Okay. And here is the example.
So, uh in this example,
what I tried to show is
basically, um, uh, Remember,
when we first perform
forward and then
perform backward and say,
if you look at the second layer,
once we perform forward, it's
activation of the generate a.
We can basically propagate
that activation to the
next layer and try to
compute the rest of layers
and think about is lifetime,
o when will that activation
be needed again?
So basically following
backward cation,
the activation of
the second layer,
when it is needed is basically
your backward proceed all
the way to that layer.
So when your backward actually
reaches the current
layer, you need it again.
Which means that
there's a window where
we can discard that
part of memory, right?
And we don't need that.
As long as that window passed
and when our backward
proceeded to that layer again,
we can basically reflect
that part of memory, right.
Uh, why we do this?
Because we can see
memory. We can
basically during
that time window,
as long as we can
describe the memory,
we can count more
space to basically
accommodate the other sensors,
for example, yeah. Okay.
So this basically give
you some idea, like,
how we can do single
device augmentation.
The key idea here is, uh,
for many activations in layers,
so the activity is
not needed again
until the background pass
comes to that layer.
Okay. So that gives us
a time window where we
can discard memory.
Okay? So the idea is we
can discard some of them.
Okay. And we recompute them
when it's needed again.
Right? Because, for example,
if you look at the second layer,
we can discard it and when
the backroa reaches that layer,
we can recompute from the
beginning all the way.
To get a value again.
And the recomputation
will give you exact
same results,
right, because you
have the program.
You have the data
flow graph structure.
Okay? So this trick is
basically called,
um, recomputation.
People give you many different
kind of names, recompeton,
mtization and grad
checkpoint activation,
all kinds of names.
But you basically get
the idea that is,
um, we can recompute
certain layers.
We can use flops. We can use
computers to treat for memory
if we don't have
enough memory. Okay?
So let's see how
this works. So here,
um, I have a new network, right.
In my vanina version,
I will basically,
preserve all the memory and
all the intermediate tensors
produced at every layer.
So here, if a layers
memory is preserved,
I basically mark it
with orage color.
So you'll still remember
at my Vaina version,
all the blocks,
all the nodes are
basically has a color right.
But here, I will do it
slightly differently.
So what I'm going to do is, I
still proceed with my
four communication.
But what I do is I only save
those layers output at
those nodes with a color,
and I discard all the
other layers output.
Okay. So here in the step zero,
basically only, I already
reduce the memory
by half, right?
I only store, the second,
the first, and the sixth.
Okay. I discarded the
first, the third and fifth.
Okay. What I do is, when I
proceed with my backward pass,
from the last layer
to the first layer,
um, if I hit
a layer where the intermediate
tensor was preserved,
I have no problem, I just
calculate the readings.
But if I hit a layer where
it's activation
tensor was discarded,
what I do is I try
to find a layer in
the I try to find the
previous layer that is
closest to that layer that is
missing intermediate value.
And I launch a forward pass
again, starting from that layer.
So in the second step
one, you can see,
when I propagated to the
second to last tensor,
last note, I found that I'm
missing inter medial value.
So I basically find out
the layer that is
basically one layer before
that layer and I triggered
the forward commutation
again to get its output.
And then once I get output,
I basically drove the adiens.
Okay? So the idea is
basically a checkpoint
at a few positions,
a few layers of the
neural network.
And I only save the tensors at
those checkpoints and I
described all the other values.
And during the backward pass,
I already I always
try to recompute
the missing tensors from
the Cloris checkpoint.
Okay. Cool.
Uh, with this strategy,
we can basically explore a
few alternatives, right?
So the first alternative
is basically,
we don't describe
anything, right?
That is basically reduced
to the Vania version,
that is, we save all
the intermediate
tensors at every layer.
So in this case, we don't
actually need any extra
compute at the backward,
but we have to consume
a lot of memory space.
Another extreme is basically,
we discard all the
intermediate tensors, right?
We don't save anything, okay?
And at backward pass,
we'll find that every layers
output will be discarded,
so we have to
recompute we don't have
a checkpoint, right?
So we have to recompute from
the input again and again.
Okay? So in that case,
we save a lot of memory, but,
um, we are going to pay a
lot of cost on compute.
Then the question is,
can we figure out, um,
some strategy that is probably
best strike a balance
between compute and memory.
So so how to find a strategy.
We can actually model this
cost as two terms, okay?
The first term is basically
the checkpoint cost.
So assume that way for
liner near network,
okay, we are going to checkpoint
every K layers, right?
So basically the checkpoint cost
is basically all divided by K,
right, because we need to
check this many times.
Assuming we check
this many times,
then we also need to during
the background pass,
we have to pay extra
computing costs, right?
Like I said,
the extra computing is
basically like we find
the Case checkpoint and
we proceed forward.
Okay? So basically the computing
cost is basically okay.
Okay. And so if
we apply this kind of
a checkpoint realgy,
we can write R cost as
this sumation term which is
O and divided by K plus o.
And when this
equation is optimal,
it's basically when the
first term and second
term is equal, right?
So which means that
we basically need
to for a near neural network,
what we need to do is we
checkpoint every square layers.
That basically gives us
optimal checkpoint reality.
Okay? And then I
have a question.
So in this case,
what is the total recommit cost?
Yeah. O N.
So what is? It's basically
one forward pass, right.
So basically in order
to compute the, um,
in order to finish the forward,
in order to finish the backward,
you need to perform
one more forward.
Okay? Which means
that if you follow
this strategy and you go
and do diploying training,
uh, your deploying computation
will change a little bit.
Previously, your
deploying computing
is one forward, one backward.
Right? And if you don't have
enough memory and you
use this strategy,
it basically becomes one
forward, one backward.
And during that backward,
you pay one more forward.
It becomes two
forward and backward.
Okay? Remember this. Why?
Because this is very
helpful for you to estimate
your uh, GPU addition.
Okay? Yeah. So, I want
to talk about it later,
but let's remember this, okay?
So basically, if you do this
square uh, checkpointing,
you basically use computer
to trade for memory
and you perform two
forward one backward.
Okay. And if we
visualize this kind of,
like, effectiveness of this
strategy, you can see,
if we don't do checkpointing,
as our commit goes,
our memory will grow all the way
and then become plain, right?
But if we do this kind
of checkpointing,
we can basically flatter
this scribe a little bit.
The reason we still consume
a lot of memory
because like I said,
we need to store parameters.
Yeah, we need to store
gradients, this kind of thing.
Okay. And in practice, this, um,
checkpointing strategy is
very, very well adopted.
And I think you can find
some very readily
available EPS from Pyroc.
In piracy, there's a EPI
called torch uses checkpoint.
And in some very famous
library, for example,
deep speed and hug
in accelerating,
you can find this kind of
activation checkpointing.
And as long as you turn this
on and you give it a
few parameters needed,
it will basically help you
implement this strategy.
Okay, I will checkpoint
at different places
to save memory.
Okay. Any question here?
Cool. Activation check point,
that is basically, our
first single device memory
otenation strategy.
Then let's discuss
a little bit, okay?
So, like I said,
it's also called it's
also called by different
people in different names.
For example, recompetition
remerchanization,
or fancy names, okay.
My first question when
and when not enable it.
So when you have enough memory,
that when your peak memory
is smaller than the
available memory,
should you do this? No.
Because it was slow down
recommendation, right.
Yeah. So basically, uh,
don't turn this on until
like basically you find that
your pick memory is
greater than over memory.
But in many many today
deep learning libraries,
deep learning code, they
basically turn this
on by default.
So I think later
in your research,
if you find I hope you
can inspell that, okay?
Because as I said,
if this return on by default and
you find that your P
memory is actually smaller
than borrary basically
your training program will
be slowed down by three fourths,
right, because you pay one
additional forward, okay?
So the optimal
checkpoint policy.
I think I give you a
theoretical optimal
that is we checkpoint
in every square,
but it's more complicated, why?
Because in my example,
I assume every layer is
equal. All the
layers are the same.
But in many real
cases, real works.
We need to figure out what is
the best strategy
to checkpoint at.
Uh, the reason is because
some neur networks,
they have a very heterogeneous
archecture R layer
are different,
and layer will produce
a slightly different
size of activation.
So you always want to
checkpoint a place where
the activation is small
rather than large, right?
Because if you because the
effect will be the same.
But if you checkpoint
a large distensor you
have to pay more memory.
Okay? So where to
checkpoint actually
depends on the neural
network archecture, okay.
Uh, I could also influence
the recomputing cost because
you want to checkpoint on
some place where you
can easily recompute
with very small cost instead
of large cost. Okay.
Cool. And there's a
decent number of lines of
research basically studying for
different types of
neural networks.
Where should I checkpoint?
But in general, um,
for transformers for
language models,
what do we do
basically checkpoint
at the transformer
layer boundary.
Okay. Okay. And the disadvantage
of this checkpoint activation
strategy is basically
it's only able to
reduce the memory for
activations, right?
There's no way
that you can apply
this two parameters
or to operar states.
Okay. Cool.
Any question here?
Okay. Then let's
move forward to our Bomer
optimization strategy.
Okay. Our second strategy
is basically called
grading accumulation,
and this is also a very
well adopted strategy
in today's frameworks.
Okay? So the idea is
actually pretty simple.
So we find that no
matter what operator use
right in your graph.
So basically the
activity memory is
linear to the batty size. Right.
But in order to compute, say,
we don't have enough
memory, okay?
Because our biset is large,
we don't have en memory.
But we still want to proceed
our commutation with
the given batsts.
The reason is because
probably the bisit
was hyperparameter tuned so
that it can give you
a better results.
Okay? So in order to do that,
what we do is, um,
instead of directly
compute gradients
on the given batsts what we do
is basically computing
in a loop, okay?
So here it comes, uh into
the concept of microbatch.
Okay. What we do is basically we
split the original
batch into many,
many smaller
batches, and we call
each batch a micro baatch. Okay.
What do we do is we loop
over all the micro baatges.
A time we only do a
foreign backward over
the macro baatch.
Remember, activation is
only linear to batch size.
And now we effectively
reduce large bases into
microbees we effectively
reduce the activating memory.
But what we do is
every time when we
calculate the gradient on
the microbatch we do not update.
Okay? We put it in
memory, we put it there.
We keep accumulating
as this loop goes.
And eventually, once we finish
all the microbatch in
the original batch,
we accumulate all the gradit
together and we do update. Okay?
Now, it becomes,
you perform many,
many, many forwards, right?
You accumulate the gradients,
and then you apply grads and
you keep doing this, okay?
And this is a very
straightforward strategy for
reducing activity memory because
you simply are calculating uh,
using a smaller base sets, okay?
But you can still
achieve the same results
of using a larger bad set.
Okay? Cool. Here, it's
very easy to implement
this kind of
grading accumulation in petrog.
So here I give you
two example programs.
So on the left hand side,
it's basically a piece of
Petrich program where you
iterate over a data loader,
you get a batch and
you perform backwards
through the neural network
and you perform
one optimal step.
But in the right hand
side, you can see,
uh, the only difference, uh,
I basically split the original
batch into microbatches.
And every time I drove
the gradients on the microbatch
and I accumulate them,
and I only perform my updates
when a certain number of
microbatches are. Okay.
We are easy to implement
it immediately
distribute memory.
Cool. Any questions
on this part?
Cool. These are very
practical techniques.
If you fice any problem,
feel free to try this,
and this will be
super effective.
Then let's proceed with our last
memory saving technique
on single device.
Last memory saving techniques,
the most powerful one.
So si remember, we have a
memory hierarchy, right uh,
most of the dep
running comton they
basically operate on
the middle layer,
which is the TPHBM.
But we actually are given a
big amount of memory that
is the CPRm And
like for example,
you can compare most of
the AWS Cloud instances,
they have more than
one tibite of CPRM.
So then the question is,
can we actually leverage that
part of memory to make sure
our competition still
prossed even if
our peak memory is
greater than the TPHBM?
Okay. The answer is
yes. So how do that.
It's pretty
straightforward, right?
So here is the photograph
I showed in my previous example.
We perform forwards layer
and the backwards layer.
So what if at some layer,
we cannot actually,
um, do training because
the pick memory is
greater than HBM.
So what do we do is, um,
every time we perform the
competition on one layer,
okay, we basically produce
the output, right?
We give the output
to the next layer.
And meanwhile, what we do is
we ask the program to basically
swap its width and
activations of the previous
layer from HBM to RAM.
Okay? That is, we make a copy of
the contents from the GM
GPU memory to the CPR RAM.
And basically can basically
describe anything
on the GP memory,
right, because we have
a copy on our CPRAM.
And at some point, when we
perform backward, when
we still need them,
what we do is
basically we swap them
back from CPRM to our GPHBM.
Okay. And this basically
give us this kind
of like a pattern.
Like every time we
compute a layer,
uh, we basically
copy this content,
uh, to CPU memory,
and we throw it
through the TPP away.
And then we proceed
to next layer,
we swap out, we swap
out and swap out.
And when we start
doing backward what we
do is whenever we need the
content of the previous layer,
we just swap it in from
CP Ram to GPU memory.
Okay. Cool. So here
swapping swap out
basically two very uh
um primitive operators.
So for swapping is
basically swapped from
CPO uh DRAM to HBM,
and for swap out is basically
swapped from HBM to CPU DRAM.
Okay. So you can see this
pretty powerful, right?
It's much powerful
than checkpoint and
the basically micro
baatching Why?
Because theoretically
you can swap anything.
You can swap
intermediate tensors,
you can swap model weights,
you can also swap opts.
As long as you have CPU
memory, you can swap anything.
And you can basically
put everything
as a copy in CPU
memory and you make
some space on GPU for
the next layer of
commendation. This
is pretty powerful.
But the problem is that
this is super slow, right?
Because GPU is super
fast when you perform
like for micro pass,
But swapping
basically is limited
by but it's band ways, right?
So suppose you want to
swap something between
memory ac, it takes time.
So what happens when you
do this in practice,
what happens is basically
let me get my pen.
Okay. So say, when
you now proceed here,
and finish backcmmendation,
you want to go
back and it basically
instructs programs in,
I need the activation
of this layer,
because you apply this
swapping strategy,
so those activation actually
was on CPU on CPU memory.
What you do is you
have to wait for
them to basically swap
back and then you
proceed the competon.
The thing is the computation
usually only takes
a few miniseconds,
but the swapping will take
tens or even hundreds
of miniseconds.
So you how to wait.
Theoretically, you
can use this strategy
to train uh,
22 GB single GP was
sufficiently large ram,
but that will take forever.
You can play around with
this schedule litt.
Uh, you can play around
this schedule it.
That is, um,
you try to schedule
the swapping and
swap in a way that
is, for example,
um, when I'm
computing this layer,
I know that in the next
probably 100 milliseconds,
my commutation will reach here.
What I do is I basically swap
in ahead of time, right?
I swap in here, whenever
computing is already here.
So when computing
actually proceeded here,
I already have the
continent DPU,
so I can proceed.
But the reality is
the computing is so fast
that the swapping
is so slow that
you actually don't get
this kind of space to
overlap swapping and
competion. Yeah.
Okay? And also, because,
at some point, even you
can use this to address
your memory limit,
you are still subject
to computer constraints
because your computing
is too slow,
like you still want
to train fast to get
your model right.
Okay? Any questions
on this part?
Yeah. In practice, yes,
I think many of my
students they use
this because they can
wait a little bit and
to get the results.
For example, if you
have limited resources,
you don't have GPUs,
but you want to try say
a Lama model with 30
billion parameters,
you have to do this.
Why It's hard to see
it depends on model,
but in general, two times
to ten times slower. Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, I already
explained that you
can use pipeline,
but the problem is, for example,
when you reach this part, you
don't have pipeline, right?
Yeah. Am when you
compute this layer, you
can swap it this way.
But what if you are
computing this layer,
then yeah, you have to wait.
Yeah. Okay? No, it's
very hard to achieve this
kind of perfect pipeline.
Cool. This is a very, um, uh,
practical reality
that at least this
allows you to try some big
models on your laptop.
Okay. But in industry that's
why this matter was not
preferred in industry because
they want to get results
as soon as possible.
But this was preferred
by students.
Okay. A lot of
students like this.
Cool. That's why I introduced.
Cool. Okay. To summarize,
I think I covered three,
very important memory optations
the first one grading
check pointing, right?
Second, gradient accumulation.
And the third one, CPO swapping.
Okay, let's summarize
it pros and cons.
Okay. So for grading
check pointing,
um it's straightforward, right?
It's pretty nice. It can reduce
the intermediate tensors.
But Cs is you paid flops, right?
You slow down your computation.
Okay. Uh, for grading
accumulation,
it seems it's perfect, right?
You don't how to
pay flops, right?
So can anyone tell me
what's the drawback?
That's not the primary reason.
So one primary reason
is in order to do this,
you have to split,
your original bad site
into a smaller value.
You remember the MCQ question
we did last lecture.
So we care about
arithmetic intensity
right because we want to
launch a big enough
memo in order
to oversubscribe our GPUs.
In order to do this, you have to
basically reduce your body size.
So sometimes when
you reduce basis,
you suffer from, like,
cannot you cannot on
the computer side,
you cannot sutGPs because
your basis will reduce, okay?
So, um, in practical scenario,
especially in large
model training,
you want to make sure you have
a large enough buddy cells
to make sure your GPU
utilization is high.
Okay. Uh, sometimes you
probably don't want to
do this kind of thing.
Okay. But we'll come
back to this later.
It's very complicated.
Okay. And when speed
swapping is very powerful,
it can reduce the memory
usage of both parameters,
activations, and
of memory stats.
But the problem is
it's super slow.
Yeah. Um.
So
grading is essentially
microbatching.
Yeah, because sometimes
you want to train on
bigger body size because
the convergence property are
different when you use
different body size.
Does that make sense? Yeah.
No, because I don't apply
my gradiens until I
reach my original basis.
That's out of it. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah. Okay. So sometimes
we just use a fixed basis.
Why? Because this is
relay to probably
emerging learning part.
So I think I can cover
this in liter lectures,
but in general in deploying
training job, okay?
If you train with
many many nodes
with many many data prism,
you want to use a larger basis.
And if you train with a small
nodes with less data prism,
you want to use a smaller basis.
Okay. Yeah, that is something
that we find that will
give you the best model.
Okay. Cool. And for
the CPU swapping,
something's changing.
I think it's worth
mentioning. So I think
media and a few
other chipmakers,
they are trying to make some
unified memory
between CB and GPU.
So this is already
happening on your MacBook.
So basically in
MacBook, you only have
one type of memory that
is unified memory,
and the CPO and GPU can actually
fetch contents from
a unified memory.
That means that the
barrier between
CPU memory and DPP memory
is basically diminishing.
I believe in like
five to ten years,
the CPU and GPU, you know,
probably will share
the same memory.
Then CPU swapping will
become very, very,
like effective, right?
So when you try to analyze
the pros and cons of the
different techniques,
you probably want to
consider the assumptions.
Here the assumption is basically
we still have a
memory hierarchy,
but I think this memory
hiarchy is breaking.
Cool. Okay, I think
we finish most part
of today's content,
and let's move forward
to the next big topic,
uh, uh, quantization.
Why we care about qtation?
Uh, I think we
care about it
because quantization
can effectively reduce memory.
Remember, no matter we store
the parameters, remember,
no matter wetrae the activations
or the oponente states,
we always multiply the size by,
uh, size of elements, right?
And the size of elements is
basically how we store the data.
It could be two bytes,
four bytes or whatever.
And we can actually play
around with the
size of elements.
For example, if we are able to
store value using
a lower precision,
we can effectively reduce
the memory use, right?
So, the quantitation basically
we try to reduce the
size of element.
Okay? So what is quantitation?
So it's very easy to understand
quantitation, right?
So anation is basically the
process of constraining input
from a continuous or
otherwise large set
of values to a discrete. Okay.
And I think these two pictures
give the perfect example.
So on the left hand side, what
we do is we have a
continuous signal.
But suppose that it
is very expensive to
store the signal,
What we want to do is
we want to store it
though using only a
few discrete values.
The way we do is basically
here we find a few
different discrete values.
We try to approximate the
original signal as much
as possible, right?
Okay. And on the right hand side
is basically how we
quantat images, right?
We can either use
a higher precision
so we see a clear image.
Okay? We can also
utaest the values.
We constrain the number bits
we use to storage pixel,
then we get a slightly
blurred image.
Okay. And the second example
will actually give you
a perfect sense why this works
emerginary Because remember,
in most immaginary programs,
our goal is, for example, we
try to classify the image.
We try to tell the image
is actually a cat.
So here, no matter how many bits
we throw at least for you,
you can tell both images you
will tell they are a cat, right.
So as long as our quantization
can reduce the precision,
and as long as it does
not influence the
decision of the model,
I think we are good.
We basically save a lot
of resources, right?
That's why quantiton
works at a high level.
Okay. But in the
next few lecture,
I'm going to dive
deeper to tell you how
we make this quantity
work emotionally.
Okay, so how new emersonaly.
At a high level, our
goal is right to
use a lower precision
repetition of data to store,
like all the things
we mentioned, uh,
model parameters activations
of the United States.
But we are subject to
a few constraints.
The first one is we want
to preserve emergening
performance.
That is, when we
quantize the cat,
we still want the model to
recognize a cat, right?
And we want to
accelerate the compute.
Why? Because, uh,
today's teamer,
they are making this
kind of lower presion
coming much faster than
higher precision, okay?
Of course, we want
to reduce memory.
And you probably know if you
know computer architecture,
if we use a lower precision
to do metamo to do
this in addition to
do multiplication,
it actually saves your energy.
Yeah. Okay. Cool. So inspired,
we are going to talk
about a few things.
We start with how
to represent data.
I think many we probably
already studied
this in some computer or
computer architecture course,
but we are going
to revisit again.
And then we are going to talk
about the basics of codon.
And then we are going to
put that into context of
margining and we'll talk about
post training condition,
which is a very
important technique
because I think as long as
your phone is running
some machinery models,
likely it's actually using
some technique here,
post training condition.
Okay. And then we are going to
talk about content
aware training.
And finally, assuming
we understand all this,
we are going to talk
about mixed present
training mixed present training
is basically the key technique
for training language models.
Cool. Hopefully, we can
cover the first part.
If not, let's first talk
about representi of data.
How data was represented
in computer?
Basically bits, right?
So we rep that in bits,
and we actually have a
standard at standard and
all the computer makers they
basically try to follow
that standard and
try to store data
following those
predefined standards.
So let's talk start
with integers,
we have unsigned
integers, right?
So we basically, for example,
use this kind of one to a Bs
to store unsigned
integers, right?
So here, the BD range
is basically starting
from zero all the way
to two to N minus one.
This is unsigned or
positive integers.
Okay? In order to basically
represent negative integers,
what we do is, um,
we modify the bit
stream a little bit
and we assign the first
bid as a sign bit, right?
So if the first bid one
is basically positive,
otherwise, uh, it's negative.
Okay? Uh what we
do is basically we
allocate the rest of sem bits to
represent the values
and in this way,
we can represent both uh
negative and positive values.
Okay. And one problem of
this uh sign Miverepen
is, we find that,
um, like both the arrow and one,
the first bit being one
and the rest being zero,
they are representing the
same value, which is zero.
Because zero is either
positive or negative.
And this basically was
like one repetition.
And I think, computer
architectures,
they are very, um,
they are very mean on this.
I don't with anything.
Okay? So what we do is
we actually use a very,
uh a different kind of formats
compliment repetition.
Okay? I think that's
why you learn that
in some computer archiecture
course that instead of
designate same beat,
what we do is basically, Uh, um,
we use the first bit as,
uh, the largest
value of negative.
And then we basically, uh,
for the rest of
bits we basically
accumulate them together and
then add that to the
in this example,
it's minus 27, okay?
And this basically give you a
orenon of the tooth complement.
Okay. And with this orientation,
we don't have to wait,
uh, one code, right?
Okay. I hope you guys are
familiar with this, okay.
Ooh. Okay, integer
is important in
machine learning because
sometimes we want to quantize
the marching width into
integer four integer
eight and it still works.
But I think there's one more
we care more about
floating points because
most of the companion still
are performed on floating
point repetitions.
So before I talk
about floating point,
we have a fixed point.
So fixed point is pretty simple.
Like we basically, put
a decimal point at the
middle of the bits.
And to the left of
this decimal point is
basically integer part.
To the right is basically
the fraction part.
Okay. And following this kind
of fixed point orgenation we can
basically represent some
flowing point numbers here,
um, uh, following
flowing this one.
And I assume you guys are
familiar with this one, right?
Okay. But this is not
the one we used in,
uh, machine learning, right?
Fixed point is mostly
used in, uh, security.
Okay? But in machine learning,
we don't use fixed
point because we
want to basically represent
lumber using a new format
called floating point, okay?
So anyone can tell me what's
difference between flowing
point and fixed point.
Okay, I think you can tell from
my name that the
floating point is
that the decimal point can
float from left to right.
Okay. Let's dive
deeper into this.
Okay? This is, uh,
triple standard
floating 0.32, okay?
We basically get 32 bits.
Um, uh, the first bit
being s bit, okay?
And the blue kind of bits,
we call it expolent, okay?
Um, and the yellowish
kind of bits we
have we allocate 23 bit
we call it fraction.
Okay. Uh, so the key difference
between this one and the
fixed point is that,
um, uh, we don't
actually put the decimal
point anywhere, right?
So the way that we represent
the fol numbers is
folly equation.
Okay? Uh, we first figure
out the sign, right?
And then we use one
plus fraction p,
and then we use the blue
part to figure out how we
should flow to the decimal point
from left to right, right?
And that is how we time value,
which is to explain
minus one, two, seven.
And you can understand
127 as, um, uh,
the way that we represent
the exponent part, okay,
I basically the mid value
of the largest value,
the half of the value of
the largest value we can
represent using all the
bits of the expoonent.
Okay? Because we want
to float in the uh,
we want to float to
the decimal point
either to left or to right,
so we have to minus one, uh 27.
Okay. We're still
good with this one.
Cool. So to give you an example,
we basically have one
example below right
where we use this floating
point standard to represent,
0.26, five, six, 25.
Okay. Uh, in order to
understand that we
can basically match
this number using
binary repentation
and following that
repent equation here.
And if we perform some kind
of like a transformation,
we find that it's basically
one plus of fracking
part which is 0.0
0.0 625 times two
to 125 minus 127?
Okay. And we can basically map
this number into the exploding
part and the fracking part
and we get the floating
point repent. Cool.
Um, yeah, if you're not
familiar with this,
I think you can try to,
I think you can basically try
to Google it and you try
to search Wikipedia.
I think there are a lot of
explanations describing how
we represent values using
flowing point standards, okay?
Okay, today's last slide,
I want you to one I want
all of you to do exercise.
So what is this number?
By the way, this is
a floating point.
Just flow in the
equation here, right?
Okay. What you do is basically
you first start with
the sun beat, right?
And then for the green part, you
substitute it into the exponent.
And for the pink part,
you basically, uh, do it
in the fracking part.
And you subsite all
the values using
bailar repetition and you
probably get the value.
That is the sun beat is roughly,
uh, minus one, 20, right?
And for this value,
if you basically read
it is basically 124,
for this value, it's basically
interpreted as a fraction.
And what you do is one minus all
of them, submission
of all of them,
and you basically get
the vitual number,
which is 0.1 5625.
Okay. I hope you guys can do
some extra analysis
because I'm going to
put one of the other
exam question.
You have to understand
this, okay?
Be uh I said,
like I said, we are going to
lower this into lower bits.
For example, how to
basically represent
the same lumber using 16 bits,
using eight bits, right?
What is the closed lumber?
That is basically what
quantity in tests you do.
Cool. That's all I have today
and see you next week. Cool.