Okay. Okay, yeah.
Thanks for coming back.
Let's get started. So today
should be a very
lightwek lecture.
We will only cover a
little bit in quantuion.
Yeah. Okay. And then
we hope you will
attend the Thursday's
guest lecture. Yeah.
We hope you ask very
difficult questions
to our guest, okay?
Yeah. Okay, before we
start the main content,
let's do a few MCC.
Um, which of the
following is not one of
the main sources of memory
consumption? D, right?
Training code is pretty minimal.
Okay, compared to anything else.
Okay. So which of the following
statement is false about
grading checkpointing?
Which one?
A, I heard A. So
let's go one by one.
Apply grading
checkpointing during
model training could
save GPO memory.
This one is true because
that's the purpose
of grad checkpoint.
B, grading checkpointing applies
to both model ways
and activations.
Fourth, like I
already emphasized,
grading checkpointing can
only save activations.
The location of
grading checkpointing
affects how much computation
and memory are needed.
Yes, so you need to be
strategic on that, okay?
So it's possible to describe
some of the activation
from memory since they are
only needed during
backward pass.
Yes, that's kind of the explain
how grading check point works.
Okay, this one
take a bit longer.
I already taught this
right in the last lecture.
I want you to calculate it.
Okay. So given this table
from the very famous
GPD three paper,
what is the activation
size of GPD three? 2.7 B.
Okay, the smaller
version of GP three,
assuming that we
are using a P 16
and also assuming that we are
checkpointing at the
transformer boundary.
Okay, I will give you
1 minute to calculate.
Mm.
So what one?
Yeah. The answer is C. Okay.
But I want to do the
calculation directly,
but I will give you some
so basically strategy.
So here, it said that we need
a GPT three, 2.7 B, right?
So we basically index
on this line, right?
Okay? So in order to
estimate the activation,
what parameters we need to know.
I said LP 16, right?
So basically each value
will contribute to
two bites, right?
And it also said we only
care about activation.
So you'll still remember the
activation for
transformer, right?
It's batch size times.
Sequence length,
sequence lengths.
Okay. Times times three
in dimension, right?
So basically D model.
And therefore,
you need to look for the
parameters from the table.
So what is the battery
size? This table
when they train this
2.7 billion model,
it used 1 million batch size.
Okay. But this 1
million body size
is in a unit of tokens.
That is in each batch,
there is 1 million tokens,
this information is
already surfacing the way
because in this original
activation calculation,
we use batize times
sequence length,
this BS is characterized
in amber sequences.
Does that make sense?
Lumber sequences
times sequence length
equals to Number tokens, right?
Okay. Therefore, this product
is essentially just one, right?
Okay. Therefore, this is one.
D model, this t told
you that D model
is essentially, um, here, right?
Uh, 2560. Okay? This is
basically like you time one
minion with this number,
you essentially get the
activation per layer, right?
Okay. So basically each
transformer boundary,
you are going to meet this kind
of activation, this
size of activation.
But the problem
is, in this model,
270 B GPT three,
you have many many
layers, right?
And I think this question
asks that we are going to
apply gradient checkpoint
every layer boundary.
Okay? Which means
each layer, we all
checkpoint once, right?
We only save them and we
discard all the rest, okay?
So basically, we need to time
this value with a number
of layers, right?
So how many layers in 2.7 B?
You can also get from
this table, right?
It's here, 32.
Okay. So basically,
you multiply another 32,
and then you convert
it into gigabytes.
That's your value. Okay?
Makes sense. Cool.
We will ask a different
question in exam.
Okay, a different model,
for example, Lama.
Okay. I hope you
understand this, okay?
Cool. Okay, I think
in math lecture,
we basically, um,
talk about three,
very important memory
ogenation right?
Um, grading check pointing,
micro baatchingO grading
accumulation and swapping.
I think in practice, you
are facing a challenge that
is whenever you meet
kind of auto memory,
how you actually
navigate this space?
Which strategy should I use?
I got this question from
a lot of you after class.
I basically want to
spend a few minutes on
this slide because I think
this slide is pretty important.
In the future, when you start
working on these kind of models,
you are going to basically
navigate the tricks.
Okay? So you start basically
determine desired
training bad size,
right? So why we
start with this?
Because training body
size is a hyperparameter,
it will affect your model
your converged model
accuracy, right?
You basically want
to first figure
out the best training
body sizes for
your job that will basically
yield the highest
accuracy for your job.
Okay? Because Beside is
a super critical parameter
for sochastic green descent.
So basically, you do
some hyperbarn tuning.
You lock down a body size
that essentially give
you seems to give you
very good results.
So in this example, I said,
maybe we are going to
train with a bit size
equal to, uh, 64.
And here, this is the
global biis, okay?
And then we basically
start the training job
with bad size equal to 64,
and we launched a training.
We train with
bedside equal to 64.
And then we check if we
are on memory, right?
And if we don't go on
memory, we are good.
We don't need to do any
memory orenation, right?
But the problem is
maybe this model is too
big or maybe your GPU has
very limited GPU memory,
so it will go out of memory.
Then you essentially
start navigating this
uh choosing which memory
orienting you want
to apply, right?
So there are three I
mentioned, there's swapping,
there's grading accumulation,
there is checkpointing.
So which one you should
start thinking about first?
Checkpoint. Any other answer?
So you should start with
grading accumulation.
Why? Because swapping
is super slow,
you want to finish your
job as much as possible.
And swapping is kind
of determined by the memory
hierarchy bandwidth.
Which I already told
you, today's computer,
the bandwidth between
CP memory and
chipping memory is very
low, so it's very slow.
You want to consider
that at the end,
then you basically
decide between
grading accumulation or
grading checkpointing.
Why we don't start with
Because in green chain pointing,
you are essentially treating
flops for your memory, right?
Which means that once you
turn on green chain pointing,
what happens is your
training job is
going to be slower, right?
Without green check pointing?
Because you are
treating some flops,
treating some compute
for your memory.
And you don't want to do
that because you want to
finish your job as
soon as possible,
right? So you start with, um
You try to start with
gradient accumulation.
Gradient of accumulation,
how I actually navigate it.
So how many steps
should I accumulate?
Because essentially say, I
want to train with a
global bites out of 64.
I hold many many choices,
I can't use a microbtes
equal to one,
but I loop 64 times,
I get equivalent results.
Or I can use a
microbte equal to 32,
I only look twice, right?
I also get the results.
So which one should I use? So I
should always try to
choose a microbody size
that basically the
largest microboy it Why?
Because if I use a
smaller microbic site,
yes, I can solve
my memory issue.
I will get the
equivalent results,
but the problem is
you still remember
when MCQ gave it
to you last week.
The problem is your
metamol and many many,
kind of like computer
intensive operations.
They will have a smaller
dimension. I reduced to one.
Like I said, in GPO,
if you give a very small
metamo or you give a big memo,
they will compute
at the same speed.
Right? Which means
that if you give
a small mathema with some
dimension equal to one,
the utilization of GPO
will become lower, right?
That means that your training
job will be extended.
Although you basically
get the same results.
So basically you
want to maximize
the possible bist
you can use, okay?
So basically, you
start searching
32-16 to eight to four, right?
And you basically alternate
it two variables.
One is the effective microbess.
The other is lab gradient
accumulating steps.
Okay? You try to figure
out the one that is the
biggest you can use without
going out of memory.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Cool. Okay.
Then if you end
up with figuring out
something, then you are good.
Okay, you have a success.
Then you'll start estimating,
say, with this microbes,
I'm going to train
one iteration with
1 minute and I need
to train, say, uh,
ten k iterations, and
you want to figure
out an estimation of your
job completion time, JCT.
You try to figure
out, you try to
determine if this GCT can
meets your expectation.
For example, your
manager probably ask you
to give that results in one week
and if this is too slow
or it's okay, right?
And if you think it's
okay, then you are good.
You can stop here, right?
But if it's not,
uh, what do you do?
Okay. Which means that
you probably need to add
more compute, right?
You need to add more GPOs.
So we'll cover that next week.
We are going to enter the world
with distributing
machinery, paralyzation.
We'll use multiple
GP for this job.
Okay? So I hope
you and me are on the same
page for this branch, right?
So what if at this point you are
not able to figure
out microbasess
that can actually not
go out of memory?
For example, even if
you use a microbes,
equal to one, you are
still out of memory.
So what is this is possible.
For example, the model
is just so huge that H
100 only have 80 gigabyte
you are going to train
on Nama model, right?
And the Nama model, like I said,
seven model you cannot train on
a single GP you
basically equal one.
Yeah. So what you do is
basically you start
considering the second choice,
green check pointing, ok?
You're going to turn
on if this failed,
you are going to turn on
green check pointing.
So you basically turn on
green check pointing
and you start
looping this again and again.
You try to figure out the
largest microbd I can train on
a single GPO with
green check point turn
and also with gradient
communication turno.
Okay. And at some point,
you are going to
figure out one thing.
Maybe you are going to
figure out microbes
that is going to work,
then you are good. Okay?
You basically come back
to this line, right?
You try to determine your
job completion time.
Okay? But if you
still fail what you
do you basically use a
microbe equal to one,
and you turn on
gradient chat pointing,
you turn on gradient
accumulation,
you accumulate 64 times, okay?
You'll still go on the memory.
Then basically, uh, swapping
is the last word work.
You start swapping was
into CP memory and you try
to use memory hierarchy
to barely make this
straining job work.
But in general, uh,
this is a bad choice
because it's going
to probably make your training
job ten times slower.
If your job is not
very time sensitive,
you are good, you just want
to try out ideas, right?
You probably launch the
job on your labs GPU and
wait for two days and check
the results later, okay?
But if you really
meeting deadline, uh,
you probably need
to consider, like,
prioritization,
you add multiples
because when you add multiples,
you also get more memory.
When you get more memory, you
can basically come back to
this regime where you can
train with a large body size,
maximize your GPU addition.
You get more flops, more memory.
Okay. So basically, this is
a practical guide for how to
optimize memory and make sure
you understand its workflow
because it's super useful.
Okay?
Cool. Okay. Today we are going
to continue to talk about,
our topic last week. So
basically quantization.
I think last week,
we talked lit digital
representation of data, right?
So still remember
this figure, right?
I didn't explain pretty
much last week, but,
I hope you basically look
at the slides a little bit
during the weekend and you
understand what is exponent,
what is fraction, and how
we represent floating
point numbers here.
This is our standard
L P 32, okay?
So the intuition behind the
floating point is that, uh,
we basically designate a
few bits for represent
the exponent and by varying
the values of exponent,
we can move the floating
point from left to right.
Therefore, we have a
pretty dynamic range,
and we can also basically
designate a few bits for
the fraction so we can control
the precision of our
floating point numbers.
Okay. And in order to
move the floating point,
you know, about one
also below one,
we have to add exponent bias.
Exploding bias is basically
the median number of
the maximum number that can be
represented using eight
bits in this example.
So it's the number of bits
in the exponent part.
Okay? Yeah. Any
questions on this part?
Cool. Then we are going to
do something more excise.
Okay. So in this figure,
I give you the
equation, how to read
this floating point
representation in 32 bits.
My question is, how
to represent zero.
Okay. But looking
at this equation,
you figure out that it's
impossible to
represent zero, right?
B in the middle part
one plus fraction,
you can see, we always
have bias term one, right?
Way time something
that is not zero.
So basically, this
equation does not
have zeros like p value, okay?
So how to read
zero. So basically,
we have to do some very
artificial thing, okay?
So in order to represent
zero, we basically, uh,
say that if all the
explosion equals zero,
we are going to change the
floating point representation
into that equation.
Okay, if you look at
that equation compared to
the left set equation,
you'll find the first
change is basically,
um, in the middle part,
the left part is one
plus fraction, right?
You know, in the right
part, is fraction.
There's no one plus, okay?
And the second change is
on the power uh power two.
In the left part is basically
exponent minus bias,
but in the right part is
basically one minus the bias.
Okay? This is a little
bit artificial,
but this is how we
represent 14 point numbers.
Um, and we call this
kind of lambers.
So basically, when all the
expolen bits are there,
we call this kind of
lambs sublomal lambers.
Okay. When the expoolen
bits are not there,
we call it mal lambers.
So essentially, for any
floating point retation
we have two ranges.
One is sublomalumbers. The
other is lomal lambers.
Okay. And it's determined by
if the expoolen bits
are there or not.
Okay. Cool. So to answer
my previous question,
in order to represent
zero, what do you
do is basically, uh,
you go into the sublomer range,
and you set or expollen
bits into zero,
meanwhile, you set or fraction
bits into zero is
basically zero.
Okay. Here, you get
rid of the one plus.
Okay. Cool. Then with
this understanding of
lomal and sublom values,
our question is, what is
the minimum positive value?
Okay. So in order to determine
the minimum positive value
represented by this,
we only hear about
minimum positive
value because we
can take the minus
and we get the mini maximum
negative value, right?
So what is the minimum
positive value?
So that can basically
give us a sense
like how precise we can be,
right, using insenation.
Okay? So the minimum
positive value
we just need to
basically investigate,
uh, the left hand side
and the right hand,
what is what is the minimum
and we'll take a
minimum oppose, right?
So on the left hand side,
we basically use that equation.
Uh, What do we do
is basically, um,
because in left hand
side, we cannot
side all the exponent
bits into all the arrow.
So the minimum value we can
do for exponent bits is
basically one, right?
So, uh, we just basically
Assign this value into one.
That's the minimum we
can do for exponent.
And of course for the
fraction, we can do a zero.
That will give the
minimum value.
And we substitute this
into this equation,
we get this one.
It's basically two
to two minus 126.
It's a very small value, okay.
And on the right hand side, we
just use a different
equation, right?
So, because on the
right hand side,
it is sublomal so this
part must be zero.
And what we can do
is for this part,
we are going to choose
the minimum value, right?
Minimum long zero value, okay?
And we basically get
this one. And this is
the minimum value we can
do for the sublomer range.
And if you compare
this two, apparently,
right hand side is
even smaller, right.
So that's basically the
minimum positive value we
can represent using P 32, okay?
Okay. And we also have a few
other artificial things,
artificial values we designated
into this orientation.
For example, in this example,
all the exponent bits is one.
But in the normal range,
okay all the exponent bits are
one and all the
fraction bits are zero,
we basically call this,
uh, positive infinity.
Okay? This is easy to
understand, right.
So basically this value is
maximized, and this is zero.
And we basically use
this resentation
to represent positive infinity.
And the same thing, we just, um,
change the sun
beat a little bit,
we represent the
negative infinity. Okay?
And meanwhile, uh, in
a subnormal range,
what do we do is,
um, not subnormal.
So basically, when all this
value is one, uh, basically,
we will use and when
this sunbat is not used,
we are going to use
this to represent,
um, not a amber.
Okay? And we don't care
about any values in this.
And you can see this
is a big waste, right,
because so basically we waste,
many, many
possibilities in this.
And, yeah. And we use this
to represent no lumber,
and there are a lot
of waste, right,
because we originally could use
this kind of thing to
represent the other values,
um, Okay, and we will
revise this in FVA.
Okay. To summarize, I
think this table gives
you a summarization.
So we have two ranges, right?
Loom range and the sublom range.
Okay? So when you
exposing to zero,
we basically go into
the sublom range.
And in the sublomer range,
we use this equation to
basically convert the
binary into decimal, okay?
And when the exponent
is not zero,
we go into the normal range
and we use different equation.
And that's the equation
that everybody knows,
okay, in normal range.
Okay. And when the
exponent is full.
So basically every
rabit is what?
Then we reserve all the
other all these kind of,
uh repents and we use that as
either positive or negative
infinity or not number.
Okay. And especially
on this range,
we basically waste a lot.
Okay. Any question
on this table?
Okay. Then one
thing you probably
will gradually understand
is, you can see,
if we basically draw all
the lumbers on the x axis,
and we try to uh,
calculate the distance
between two numbers,
we find that this
floating point operation
flowing point lumber is
quite different from
fixed point numbers.
Remember in fixed
point, we basically
designate a decimal point
at some place right.
So basically, we
have equal distance
between different umbers.
But in flowing point number,
if we put the value
on this axis,
you will figure out that
when the value is small,
uh, we actually have
a lot of precision.
So the distance between
any two lambers in this
area is very small.
Okay? But window
value is pretty big,
you can see Uh,
the distance between two
numbers are very big.
That is well less precision
in this area. So why we do this?
So basically, it's a trade off.
So we want to represent
large numbers.
But we also want
to represent very
small like floating
point numbers.
Okay. We want to trade off.
So basically, um, the
exploding best controls
the dynamic range.
If we give it more
like exploding bees we
are going to represent larger
and larger numbers, right?
And the fraction bias
basically give you precision.
If you give more fraction
bias, you have more precision.
That is the distance between
any smaller two small values
is going to be smaller.
So you can represent
more values.
Okay? It's essential trade off.
Okay? And remember this
because we are going to
revis this again and again,
in quantison machine learning.
Okay, with that, I think we can
basically dive deeper into
the true floating
point representations
we used in machine learning.
Okay. And this is LP 32, right?
And I think we dive
pretty deep into that.
It has eight bits of exposed,
23 bits of fraction,
right, total 32.
And because machine learning
becomes so popular.
So Act basically
establish we also try to
leverage another standard
established from AE 75,
six, I basically LP 60 or 16.
So, uh this one
is basically the one
that we use to train.
Language models to
train a lot of models.
Okay, um, transformers.
And in this LP uh 16,
what we do is basically
we use five bits of
exponent and ten
bits of fraction.
Okay. And like I said,
I previous lecture, I think
Google it comes up
of brain flow 16.
Okay? And what they do
is compared to FP 16,
uh, they adjust a little bit,
so they give more bits into,
um, this exponent bits and
they go last bits to fraction.
And I also said that
there's strength
empirical evidence that
this BF 16 is much
better at training
neural networks. So why?
Can anyone give intuition?
So we can reason a
little bit here, okay?
So compare FP 16 and BF 16.
The only difference is BF
16 is going to have a
higher dynamic range.
It can represent larger values,
but it will lose some precision.
Okay? So why this is
good for training?
Because in machinery training,
especially in the early
phase of your training,
you are going to
derive gradits and
your grading can go up and
down. It's very turbulent.
Okay? And if you have a
very small dynamic range,
what you do is at some step,
the gradient slightly explode,
okay and probably will
explode beyond the
dynamic range of P 16,
then you'll go into
infinity value or a lot
of lumber value, right?
And if you apply that
value into your training,
it's going to destroy
your model, right?
That's why, uh, Google
basically found this and,
uh, they figure out
basically bit of 16.
They give more exponent bits
to the 16 bits of orientation,
and it can stabilize
the training
because you can represent
the larger gradients,
either positive or negative.
Okay? That's intuition.
Cool. Any inference what you
do? Which one is better?
In general, I would
say inference,
P six is better because
inference basically
with a stabilizer.
And if you invest
some margining model,
you probably figure
out the most ways of
marginy model are very smaller
values after convergence.
Why?
Because we have a lot of
regulations during training.
We make sure the value will
not go beyond some values.
We'll do greening called
clipping or whatever, right?
And given this assumption,
what happens is in inference,
we probably prefer
more fraction bits.
Why? Because we want
precise results.
Yeah, we want more precision.
Remember this figure, we want
this to be more precise,
so we want more fraction bias.
Okay. This basically give you
some intuition on these kind
of lumbers we have
been talking about.
Okay? Okay.
To summarize, so if you
have more exploded width,
you basically have a larger
range, dynamic range, okay?
If you have more fraction width,
you basically have
more precision.
And eventually, you
want to treat off
between this depending
on your workloads.
Okay. Okay. I hope
this is clear, right?
You understand the
floating point, okay?
We are going to do exercise.
Okay? So what is this lumber?
I will give you 2 minutes.
Maybe I mean it because
you hold my slide. Okay.
Okay, yeah, let's go through it.
So when you read
this kind of number,
you basically start
with two things.
One is you figure out if this is
mal range or sub lomer range.
So this is apparently
normal because you
look at the expoen bits and
it's not zero, so it's normal.
Once you figure out it's normal,
you basically know the equation,
the first equation, then
this sum bit is pretty easy?
We are going to talk
about it later.
But the second thing you
want to figure out is uh,
for this floating point,
you want to figure out the
bias value, like I said,
The bias value is basically
the median the median
of the maximum value
that are represented
by this exponent bis, okay?
So sine minus, okay?
Uh, then we figure out exponent.
So the bias value
is for this one,
this is zero right, this is
the one, two, three, four.
So the maximum value is the
bias is basically, uh, 50,
okay? Okay, that makes sense.
Because the largest value
that can be really is,
I think, 31, right?
Yeah. Okay. So then
you'll basically read
this value, right?
This is the value
you got, right?
And you want to minus the bios.
Okay? And so in decimal,
this value is 17, right?
And in -15, okay,
you get two in decimal.
Okay? The exponent
is basically two.
And then we figure
out the fraction,
the fraction is pretty
easy to rate, right?
This is half, right? This
is half. This is a quarter.
Okay. You basically
add all them together.
Because only these
two values are one,
so you get 0.75,
right, in decimal.
And then you know the
equation the equation
we're going to use is essentially
the mal equation, okay?
So basically, it's minus B
it's normal equation right
so we have a one plus,
plus this value and this
value is two, right?
So this is a decimal,
okay? Makes sense.
Okay. Cool. In exam,
I'm going to give you
a sub lomer value.
Okay. So you figure out.
Cool. Okay. Let's do
a reverse exercise because
it is so important.
I want to make sure
you understand this.
Okay? So this is
Google Brain float,
BF 16, the one that we use
to train transformers.
So my question is, what is
the decimal 2.5 in B 16.
Okay? Again, 1 minute.
Okay.
Okay, let's go through it, okay?
Um, so when you solve
this kind of question,
the intuition is
basically you try
to make sure you compose
a equation like this,
because this is the
representation for flame point.
And you try to represent
this decimal number
into something
that one plus something
times the power of two.
Okay? So apparently,
this is, um,
so because this is
one plus fraction and
this value is greater than
one, right? It's two.
So you have to divide
it by at least two.
Okay? So you basically
divide it by two first.
Right, you get a 1.25
times two power one, okay?
And then you can figure
out this fraction is
essentially a quarter, right?
And this exponent
should be one, right?
Okay. So then you
use this one value,
you basically get the
actual exponent value,
it should be, so basically
bias is this, right?
X minus 127 equal to one,
and X is actually 128,
you try to represent
128 in binary.
Okay. That I give you
basically remember
this is B flow 16,
so you have the many
bits for expolen.
That's why you get this value
pretty longer than the
previous one, okay?
Meanwhile, you have fraction.
You have seven bits of fraction
and here you already
know your fraction
is, um, a quarter.
So basically the second
value here is basically.
Okay. Yeah. I put
it all together,
you also have the same bit.
That's basically this
number in B flow 60.
Cool. Okay.
Interesting. With that,
apparently, we
start talking about
even lower bits, LP eight.
LP eight is the one that,
kind of shift the curve
a little bit because
if you heard about Deep sik with
three and a major claim they
use that they don't use
32, they don't use 16.
They use FPAight to train
their model, right?
I think you have the intuition
why FB eight is better
because whenever you can use
lower bits to train your model,
you are going to
have more flaws.
Your GP will be more powerful.
Okay. And indeed, they
were very successful
in the sense that
they are able to
use this number of
bits to very large
transformative convergence.
That is amazing.
Why is it amazing?
Because, visually,
you can already feel this
because you can see this is 30.
It's so long, right. It can
represent so many numbers.
Okay? This is 16 and
it's a little bit shorter
but still pretty long.
But if you reduce
this by another half,
you basically only
get eight bits.
Okay. And like I said,
you need to reserve the first
bit as a sign bit, right?
So essentially you
have seven bits,
that need to be allocated
between expoden and fraction.
So you don't have many numbers.
Okay. Probably you
can just write
all the numbers in white paper.
Yeah, that's all the numbers
this IP eight can represent.
Okay. And you can think this.
This is pretty amazing
because essentially you
only have these numbers,
you can you have,
say, 70,700 billion number.
You basically need
to choose each
lumber from this range, right?
Design value to each parameter,
and you will get
a model that can
basically answer
many many questions.
Yeah. Yeah, it's
pretty interesting.
So for P eight, this one is like
a major development by
VDa B NVDA wants to push
for lower precision, right?
They have this drive
because they want to
maintain their more law, right?
The only way that
you can maintain
this law is basically
you use lower precision.
Okay? And there
are two standards.
One is e4m3.
The other is e5m2.
So basically, e43 stands for
exponen equals to four bits
and the Mntisa equal to three.
And the R is basically exponent
five Mantisa two, okay?
And apparently not
already you can
already reason between
the pros and cons
between these two.
So in this e4m3, uh,
I have four bits of explon
and three bits of fraction.
And in this one, can I have
five explot two of
fraction, okay?
And we also have some artificial
designations that is,
for example, in CLP eight,
EMs, we do not have infinity.
Okay? And we reserve some
one as basically lot number.
Okay. And the largest Em
normal value is basically 448.
Okay? That's the
largest you can.
So in order to make sure
your training is successful,
which means that
during the throat,
the training process,
you cannot produce
a grading that is
bigger than this one.
Otherwise, it will disrupt
your marche learning
training, right?
Okay. And we can also do,
e52, and we have a few
artificial things.
I will leave to you to
check the slides, okay?
And the largest
PightE two value is
basically like almost
100 times larger, right?
More than 100 times larger.
So basically, uh, five,
seven, three, four,
four, okay? Then I
ask you a question.
So now,
assuming that I'm only allowed
to use LP eight, okay?
So which one should I use for
training and which one
should I use for inference?
You know answer
because in training,
we want more dynamic range.
So we would use
e52 for training.
And in inference, we
want more precision.
So we would use E for
three for inference.
That is basically what we are
doing today for LP eight,
training and
inference. Okay, cool.
And the quest for even lower
precision number stops.
So I think Amdia
is trying to push
for Integer four is old thing.
Integer four is
already last year,
I think Ing four is
very successful.
If you ever run any
model on your iPhone,
it's likely being
run in Integer four.
But Amedia has been more
and more aggressive.
In the next generation
of GPUs they want
to push for LP four. Okay.
And FP four is
even great, right?
Because if you check this curve,
let's go one by one, okay.
For integer four, essentially,
I can write down is value
in the right hand side.
So here I use to
complement, right,
you still remember to compliment
the reentation integers, right?
So, um, uh, I write
down is values,
and if I basically put
these values X cess,
you can see, uh,
the distance between any
two values is equal.
So, uh basically integers, okay?
And for P four, media
is trying to push
for three standards.
The first standard is
basically EY M two,
one bit for exponent,
two bits for Mantisa.
Okay? I also write
the value here, and
you can check later.
But if I put all these values,
that is represented by EIM two.
I basically get this range.
And you all find
that EIM two is not
very useful Y because it is
essentially, Integer four.
Because what I do
is, for example,
I can skill it a little bit
and it will basically be
skilled into this range.
Basically, LP four E two is
equivalent to integer four,
we don't use that very much
because we often roll back
just to use integer four.
But we have a few other choices.
One is e2m1.
Okay? If you do e2m1
and you put all the
values in excess,
you'll find that is
slightly different, right?
Because here we have
a slightly larger
dameter range because
we give more bits into Epoing.
Okay. And there's
a third standard.
Basically we only do exp
we don't designate any bis
for Mantisa B it
only hold four bits.
Es 30. And it turns out that
e3m0 is basically
the log values,
you can see, all the values were
reason is basically
the power of two.
And this is possible
values. Cool. Any question?
Yeah, by far, there's
no successful job that
is trained using P four.
This is a pretty good
area of research.
So if you are doing
research in this area,
I strongly recommend
to look into this.
I think you can publish
the first paper,
if you can make this successful.
Cool. That basically covers
digital representation of data.
I think you now have
a deep understanding
of how we represent
data in uni machinery.
Then we start talking
about a bit on
condensation. I'm going
to repeat this slide.
Condensation is a process of
constraining an input from
a continuous or
otherwise large set
of values to a discrete set.
And the left hand
side basically trying
to represent a continuous signal
using a few possible
choices, right?
And the right hand
side is basically
what apples does in
their Apposilicon.
So they have um technical
basically contest the values,
uh, and once you
contact the images,
you can store the image
in lower precision.
You can also compute using
lower precision cores,
and you can see what energy.
You can see, uh,
for human, you can
basically figure
out both images are kept, right?
Okay. So in this lecture,
we are going to talk about
two very, very classic.
In this class, we
are going to talk
about two classic
coding technique.
The first one is basically
means based condition,
and this one is the
most adoptive, Okay.
Uh, so likely all your
phones have this. Okay?
The second one is basically
linear condensation,
and this one is the most
powerful, I would say.
So many, many today's
language model,
uh, they basically follow a
linear condition mechanism.
Okay. I think the thing
that we want to pay
attention is when
we apply this codsation
after the condensation,
so what happens on
storage and compute?
So say if we apply
chemist coniation,
what happens on storage?
How we store data?
Because originally
you store the data
in floating point in
hyp precision and
our goal of condiy
represent hypersen data
using present data.
Okay. Second question
is basically compute.
So after quantization, what
kind of course are we calling?
Uh, say, if the
original data is LP 32,
when you compute FP 32,
you can only call epi 32
course VDA if you remember,
uh, I think we inspected
the product sheet of VDA.
So the flops for Epi 32, uh,
is much lower than lower
precision, for example,
tensor core epis 16 or
tensor core FP eight.
So if we are able to quantize
some values into
lower precision,
that can match high flops
tensor core on VDIa,
we can compute much
faster, right?
Uh, given that we can
preserve machine learning
accuracy and results.
Okay. So every time
in the future,
um, I think whenever you read
a quantity paper, you
want to ask yourself.
So after I apply this
quantity technique,
how I store my data,
in what kind of precision
and how I compute,
in what kind of core, okay?
Let's look at the mins cosition.
Of course, we start with, say,
this four by four matrix, okay?
And here, I assume that
we store data in 32 bits.
Okay? So what Cemens condition
does is basically, um,
so we figure out, there are
a few values from this
four by four matrix,
and they are very close.
Okay? They are close in
the sense that probably
we can just reduce we can
represent them all in,
say a lumber or two. They
are pretty close to two.
And we basically try to
represent the unit just
a single value, okay?
And, assuming that we
can suffer this kind of
condensation error, right?
So in this case, each
value has a small
condension arrow,
after condition.
Okay. So how do we do this?
What do we do is basically,
we use chemis if you guys
are familiar with chemist,
you probably already, figure
out what we are going to do.
So basically, we take this
fob formtris as a as input,
and we just use K means
to run clustering.
Okay? And the number of K
is yet to be determined.
But here, let's assume
that K equal to four.
Okay? That is we
want to represent
all the values all
the flow values here,
four by four or 16 values
using just four codes.
Okay? And we basically
find the code at least
clods to that value and we
change the value into
that code, right?
In order to get that code,
I think we run cluster right?
Clustering we basically
get that code book.
Okay. And here,
after clustering, C,
we get a code book of two,
1.50 and minus one.
And what we do is basically for
each value in the
original matrix,
we are going to find
the one that is
the Closs code on the code
book and we change this value.
That is basically a
process of condition.
We want to represent a much
higher dimensional data,
not higher higher pressing
data using a limited
number of choices.
Okay. So in this case,
after the classing and we
basically do some
nearest neighbor,
and we figure out the
quantity should be like this.
Okay. Makes sense, right?
Cool. And we can
characterize the quantat
arrow by basically minus value
from the original value,
and this is the
quantiting arrow.
And apparently, we want
this qding arrow to
be as small as possible, right?
Because, uh,
intuitively it will influence
your eventual machinery results.
Yeah. Okay. Um no,
let's ask a question.
Uh how are we doing on storage?
So if we do this
kind of quantudon,
uh, can we actually
save the storage? Okay?
So originally, um,
we have this four by
four matrix, right?
So each entry in this matrix
is represented using 34
bits floating point, okay?
We have 16 values, so
ten them together,
we get 512 bit,
which is equal to 64 bytes.
Okay? And after condon,
how we are doing?
Okay. So now, because we have
a codebook, of four values.
So in order to
represent four values,
how many bits we need?
Two bits, right?
That's why each entry
we only need two bits.
And we have 16 entries,
so we have 32 bits.
In total, we only
need four bytes.
You can see this is a pretty
aggressive reduction of stories.
Meanwhile, we also need to
represent our code book because
our codebook is still
a flowing point.
So in this example,
we have four codes, Basically
each code is still 32
bits of flowing point.
So in order to
store the codebook,
we have 16 bytes.
Every time we try to
figure out value,
we basically index
on the codebook.
So if we do a comparison,
we can see that we get
a 3.2 X reduction,
which is pretty good on storage.
Okay? This is the power
of condensation, right?
Originally,
you cannot store matures on
your phone, but now you can.
Yeah. Okay. Then let's
generalize a little bit.
So assuming that we are
going to do bed quantuation.
Okay? So this determines
the number of codes
in your codebook.
Right. In our previous example,
we do two bit qdon
and now we do BD and.
That is why we are going
to have more code.
So more Cos means more
pending power, right.
So therefore, there will be
less quantitation error.
Okay. But that
intuitive also means
that you are going
to use more storage.
Right. So we are
also going to assume
that for big matrix,
we have a lot of entries
and we have entries.
And we're going to assume that
uh the number of entries
in the matrix you
are going to quantize is much
greater than two power one,
that is the size
of the code book.
This is pretty reasonable
because in reality, this case.
So for storage on
the left hand side,
will be to get 32 bits times
M equals to 32 bts, right?
On right hand side,
will get the B times
M equal to MMbts,
for the codebook,
we are going to
have 32 bits times
two power one,
which is two power
N plus five bits.
But like I said, this is much
greater than two power one,
so we are going to basically
think we are going to
not count this because
this is a small value.
Okay. Then the reduction rate
is essentially 32 divided by NM,
which is equal to 32 divided
by N times the reduction.
This is basically the power
of KMs condensation effective.
I directly give you a
reduction by factor of N,
and this N is basically, um,
the code book that you want
to choose. Any question?
Okay. Um, uh, this
basically give you a
sense like how way
to basic condition using Kemins.
Okay. But you probably
ask if I do this
kind of condition,
what I do for neur
network training?
Because in neuronal training,
we are going to do
forward and backward.
And during backward,
what happens is,
uh, my values on the
met Mol, for example,
for metamol XM Y,
my values on X and Y is going
to update it by the
grading distance.
So what I do. So this is
pretty straightforward, right?
So what we do is,
we first apply
quantisation on the waves.
And then, uh, for the was,
assuming we are going to get the
gradients and their
gradients are here,
and we are going to
basically follow in
the um clustering
results on the was,
we are going to designate
the same color, um,
for each each each parameters
we gradient, okay?
And then we group
them together, okay?
And we generate a vector
that's trying to
update the codebook.
Okay. And we basically
reduce all these, um,
small values, produced
on each entry of
the original weight using
the emis castering results.
And, uh, this is basically
the update that we are
going to apply to the
codebook and same thing.
As as we update the parameters,
what do we do is we are going
to apply a learning rate and
we use this to update our
centro in the codebook.
So this centre is
basically the results of
the emis clattering.
Basically our codes.
We are going to update
codes a little bit.
So the how intuition
is basically as our
parameter being updated,
we are also updating
our cluster centros.
Okay. So basically, we'll
make sure that our condensation
still makes sense.
The key means we
Okay. So how do this
work in practice.
Okay? And uh, people have
been applying this into,
say, conversion neural networks
and all kinds of
neural networks.
And as we can see, uh,
we can effectively
choose a lumber bits to
quantize and that will give
us a compression rate
for model weights.
And as we can see, this
is pretty powerful, okay?
So if we reduce the
lumber weights by
five times we roughly
we do not lose any
accuracy at inference.
Which is pretty good.
And if we're going
to reduce the lumber
Bs in the code book,
our accuracy is going to
decrease, at some point,
the accuracy will basically
decrease, very drastically.
But we don't want to we want
to basically touch this regime.
This becomes another
hyper primary tuning job,
basically in practice,
you want to tune this
number of codebooks to make
sure you find the largest,
uh, conversion rate, which
does not decrease your accuracy.
This also means that in
today's neural networks,
there are a lot of
space for compression.
Mony parameters are
quite repetive.
So that's why quantity works
pretty well. Any question?
Cool. We can also visualize
basically weight values
their histogram.
Before qdenation you can see
our weight value is
looking like this.
Xs is weight values
and the way discount.
There are a few things
you want to notice.
One is, before quantuation,
our values are
pretty continuous.
It's basically spread
across continuous space.
A second thing you
want to notice
that there are very
few values as zero.
Uh, this is basically
on new works.
After condon, like I said,
still remember my
teacher figure,
what we do is
basically we represent
all the continuous values
using the discrete values.
You can see there are
just a few values that
is used, compared
to a previous one.
If we use this kind of
trick to do training,
that is we update our code a
little bit, um we can see.
I'm going to rotate
between these two, right?
You can see the codes.
So basically the central
is slightly shift
after every iteration of update.
Okay. Cool. Okay. And like I
said, how many bits you use?
This is a hypergrimary
tuning, question.
So you have to figure
out the sweet spot
that best trade off between,
uh, compression rate and
your march learning
model accuracy.
So this basically is a result
from a very famous paper,
deep compression, which I
give to you as a reading.
Okay. That is the paper that
starts all this denation.
Okay. And I think the author of
the paper is basically
a professor at MIT.
He's very famous in
doing denation and he
has a company being acquired
by NVDA, by the way.
NVDA really likes him.
Yeah. And that deal is
pretty good, by the way.
Remember I told you that Okay.
The AutoML, basically the
guest speakers company
next week in search area.
Their company is called AutoML.
They were also
acquired by N media,
the creator of this graph,
condensation, his company
is also acquired by NMDia.
But this guy's company
acquisition deal
is much better than
Octo Mails deal.
Yeah, you can do some
Google search later.
Okay. Cool. The figure
here basically tells you
that you want to
trade off between,
uh, number of bits
you use and accuracy.
You want to tune
this a little bit.
Okay, so in practice,
how does this screen condidon
works, um in runtime?
What do we do is basically, um,
we start with tact
with R code book.
And every time when we
try to do computation,
uh, we still need to
decode the width.
Using our code book
and context like
a lookup table to get
the width, real width.
So remember this width is
a value from the code book
a code from the code
book and the code
is still in flowing point.
Which means that
we have to decode
our uh index into flowing
point values in the code book,
and then we perform
arithmetics in floating
point arithmetics.
That means that even if you
apply this kind of
chemit condensation,
you are still using your
floating point core.
Okay. Yeah. So to
summarize little bit,
so basically for
storage, we save a lot.
We basically we do
not have to save all the
original floating point values.
We basically save the
index, the index.
But for computer,
we still need to
decode at runtime
on the fly and we
try to call our floting point
course to calculate
results, okay?
Okay. That basically
fills this question.
So for storage, we are
going to do integer
with also we have a very small
floating point code book.
And for computer, we roll back
to use floating
point arithmetics.
Okay. Any question? Yeah.
Yeah. Very good point.
So in Kemin conversation,
what you face is basically
your compute will
be even slower.
Why? Because compared to the
original form of computer,
you add a lookup table,
and the lookup table will
basically slow down
your computer.
But the meaning is
basically, like I said,
the compression ratio for
storage is very aggressive.
So in many many devices,
if you have limited storage,
but you have okay compute,
you want to do this.
One example is on your iPhone.
Your iPhone has very
limited memory.
You want to write your model,
use a very limited memory, um,
uh but you're probably
okay with the power
and compute. So use
this one. Yeah.
You basically try to compress
your model very aggressively
into smaller model.
Yeah. Okay. Okay, that
is Kemi condition,
and this chems codon
is most powerful on
the last generation of
neural networks. So
basically cob ont.
And today, people play
with language models,
and that brings us into
this linear codinon.
And this near condition
is very powerful
because there are many ways that
we can do linear codiation.
But I'm not going
to dew too deep.
I'm going to give you a high
le intuition how this works.
And maybe in the next lecture,
I'm going to tell you what are
the common condition measures
we use for language model.
But essentially, they all
fall into linear codation.
Okay. So again, um,
we start with our
four by four matrix,
represented using 32 bits.
Okay. So the intuition we
need condition is this.
So So here, I'm trying to
apply linear quantitation,
and I try to quantize
my original weights in 32
bits into integer values.
My target output
value is integers.
But like I said, inar
quantity is pretty general.
You can also choose
different target values.
For example, you can quantize
from 32 bits to eight
bits of integer,
four bits of integer, or
you can quantize it into,
say, from LP 32 in LP 16
or P 32 into FV eight.
It depends on how you
choose your target.
But here, I give you
the most aggressive one
that is I want to quantize
it into integers.
And here, I want to
quantize it into basically,
uh the integer I
represented here,
two bit integers, four values.
Okay. So what I do is basically,
um, um, I try to
scale my original floating
point value into a new range.
And this new range
is determined by
my choose target range,
for example, in this example,
I just have these many values,
02 bits of integer.
And in order to scale
it, the equation
we try to follow is
basically a linear mapping.
That is, we try to basically
minus it by some value,
and we call this
value zero point.
Okay. And then we scale it
by a floating point value.
Okay. So basically,
we are skinning
original range into a new range.
And in the new range,
numbers are represented.
You need fewer choices.
Okay. You are probably
wondering how we determine,
um, this zero point
and also this scale,
we are going to figure
out pretty soon.
But before we figure
out the mass,
I want to properly characterize
this zero point and
scale a little bit.
Okay. So here, we can actually
express this skinning
process as this equation.
Um, I hold my original
value which is R,
R is at a high precision.
I hold my target value
which is quantat value,
which is Q. Q
stands for quantas.
And so my intuition that,
if I antact my
original value into Q,
I can still recover
the quantat value
back into the original value
so I can preserve the accuracy.
Okay. And the way
I recover is basically
following this uh,
linear transformation
that is I'm going to
first minus u bias term Z.
And basically represents
zero point in the new range.
Okay. And then once I
basically minus the
value from the Q,
I'm going to scale it back
to my original range.
Okay. Apparently, if you
want to apply this
near condition,
you have two critical parameters
to determine one is Z,
or what is zero point in
the new target range?
The other is the
skinning factor,
S. Which means that
for near condition,
Uh, you always carry
two parameters.
Okay? Because if you want to
apply this kind of air unit,
you have to carry
these two values.
So if you go into Hugging
phase and you check those, uh,
see, language models,
especially context version,
and you check their config.
Uh, in addition to
all those kind of,
like, lumbar heads, uh,
hidden dimensions, et cetera,
standard language
model configurations,
you probably will observe
these two values.
So contact point
and, um, and skill.
And for yourself, in the future,
you want to release your
model, in contact working,
you also need to release
these two values.
Otherwise, people
cannot reproduce
the results. Okay. Cool.
There are two
critical parameters.
One is zero point?
The other scale.
Okay. Like I said,
Q is integer here I choose
my target value as integer.
My original point, R
is floating point.
For the Z, this is basically
one quantity parameter because
it's a zero point
of a target range,
so it must be integer,
the meaning of this
Z is basically
we allow real number R,
which is on the left hand side,
which is equal to
zero be represented
by a antat integer Z
in the target range.
Okay. And then we screw it back,
and that gives us S.
S is a flowing point,
and that is the quantaing
parameter that we
screw the value back.
Okay. And geometrically
is basically this.
I'll let you look at
this for a few seconds.
So once you see this figure,
you will feel you
basically understand what
we are doing, right?
So basically, we are doing
some sort of normalization.
We try to normalize
value that is
in original range into a
smaller range target range.
Yeah. We try to
align a few things.
For example, we try to align
the mean value in
my original range,
the maximum value in
my original range
and the max in my target range.
We also try to align a
few things, for example,
zero point, between
these two ranges.
Okay. And for example,
if we do integer condensation,
um and if we choose
different bit of integers,
we will have different Qmax
in the target range, right?
This is to complement, okay?
Then you probably start
asking questions.
So if I have a tensor,
my tensor, how many
many different values?
How can I basically figure
out the parameters,
Z and S so that I can quantize
it into this target range.
For example, if you choose
probably four bit integer.
Okay. Let's do that. Okay.
So how do you determine S and Z?
So this is pretty simple, right?
We just need to play a
little bit in mathematics.
Okay. So we have
our original value,
which is, matrix,
and we try to figure out the
maximum value in a matrix,
for example, which is
RMAx and Rmin, right?
And we follow this
linear transformation,
we try to test it into the
new integer range and we
try to use the new value
in the new text value to
recover following this
linear transformation
back into the original value.
So that gives two
equations, right?
So RMAX in the original range
equals to S times
Qx minus Z, right?
That we try to align
the max value,
RM equals to times
Q Man min Z that is what
we try to align the
mean value. Okay.
And this is like a system
of equations, right?
You have two unknown
and you also have two
equations, so you can solve it.
And we just play a little bit.
We minus these two equations,
and we do some transformation,
we'll figure out S.
S is equal basically
RMAXRM divided by QMS, M's Cmin.
Basically from this
equation, you get it.
This is man addi, kind
of roman addition.
Okay. Yeah. Let's do a practice.
So, I have a matrix four by four
and my target range
is two bit integer.
In two bit integer, I
only have four values,
which I represent here,
minus two is mean value
and one is positive
one is the max value.
I want to use linear
condensation to
quantize this matrix into
this range, what I do?
So I first figure out
the R max and min,
right? From this matrix.
Okay? This matrix, um,
the maximum value
is 2.12, right?
The mean value is -1.08.
Okay. Then what I do is
basically I use this equation.
Okay. I substitute the values,
and also I figure out
and the mean value here,
and I get my S. My skinning
actor is essentially 1.07.
Okay. Pretty simple.
And same thing,
once we have this value,
we can figure out the Z value,
which is Z zero point.
What do we do is
basically we play
around this equation a little
bit and do some transformation
and we can figure out Z.
Because like I said, the Z
is zero point in
the target range.
And in my example, I
I choose the integer.
In my target range,
I only have integer,
so I have to take around here.
Okay. Cool. Similarly, we
can do exercise
for this example.
Um, I basically use this
equation where I try to figure
out Q mean and I minus
M divided by S from it
and I take a wrong.
Okay. So cumin is
minus two, right?
And I already know my
army is that value.
In my previous slide, I
figured out the value of
S. I basically substitute
them and I get my zero point,
which is minus one. Okay.
So therefore, here,
when we try to quantize
this given matrix into this
target range to be integer,
we basically use a
value where S equals
to 1.07 and Z equals
to minus one.
Okay? And if you quantize
your model parameters,
you also want to figure
out the values and you
write down these values
into your model.
Every time you recover
that from those values.
Okay. Then let's come to our
last part of this lecture.
So we want to apply near
condition to matma please.
If Yeah, that's possible.
Yeah. Yeah.
That's a really good
question. So that
is a part that we are going
to cover in the next lecture.
So that is called
posttraining condensation.
You have a few choices.
Okay? You can choose a
different SNZ for each tensor.
You can also choose a
different you can just choose
one constant SNZ
for entire model.
So this is called
calibration conation
You want to calibrate
the values of S
andZ depending on
how much you lose
on the codaon accuracy.
Okay? So apparently,
you can know that if you
do pretensal condensation,
you are going to have a
higher accuracy, right?
If you do one single SN Z
for all the ways and activations
for the entire network and
the entire input data, you are
going to lose more, right?
So that is a trade off,
so people can use
pretensior conduon or
entire model codenonO they
can figure out a
calibration dataset.
They just quantize depending
on the calibration data set.
Or they can use,
some aggressive ones, for
example, per channel.
I have a matrix where when
I'm meeting the channel,
I just try to figure out
S and Z for each channel.
I can even use per
group conidation.
That, I figure out, okay,
this group of value
they are pretty close,
so I should designate
SNZ for this group.
But for that group, they
are quite different.
So I disign different SNZ.
Does that make sense?
Apparently, when you do
more fine grain
condation you are
going to it's going
to be more complex.
Yeah. Okay. I think
that we'll cover that
briefly in the next lecture.
The thing I can tell
you is Fama models,
what do we do with
many popular condi
basically po tensor.
Yeah. Okay. Cool. Here,
we do la X that's okay.
We have Y equals to W and X,
and we want to apply
our condensation.
Remember, at the beginning
of denting lecture,
I said, you want to figure
out two things, right?
One is how you store data.
This one is pretty clear.
The way you store data is you
store the target range values,
which is to be integer.
You also store off SNZ depending
on which scheme you use.
The question is, what kind of
arithmetic course we use
to compute after conation.
So what do we do is, uh,
in the original Y equals to
X, we use floating point.
And now we apply condenation.
Now, assuming we do some kind
of a potential coddation
and we are going to get
SW and SX and w and ZX.
We basically subsue them.
Okay. And we do a little
bit transformation.
We find that our computation
based becomes this.
Here, QW and QX is the
quantized weight and input X,
and QY is the quantized output.
The reason we need quantize
output because this is the layer
of neural work and that
proceed to next layer.
Okay? And we do
a little bit like manipulation
and we get this equation.
Okay? Let's try to
inspect this equation
a little bit. Okay.
So the first part we
notice that for this part,
we can pre compute it because
the weight is fixed,
spit inference.
So we can pre compute
how we tact the weight.
And for X, we can
also, for example,
if we do calibration data
set, we can take a dataset.
Right. We assume we
are going to use
the same skill and zero point
for all the data in the dataset.
Okay. Then using
calibration data set,
we can basically
figure out a value
or the basically ZX Right.
Then with calibrating data
set and with fixed weights,
we basically figure out that all
the values in the
orange box, y constant.
They are not dependent
on the input.
So we basically
pre compute them.
Okay. So this is not trouble.
Okay, they are pretty computed.
And we ask the question.
So basically, what it takes
to compute these values.
So here, si remember,
it is a zero value
in the target range,
so it's integer and
QW is the quantitive value,
so it's also integer.
In order to perform
the computing here,
we only need integer course.
Which is good
because like I said,
integer course are
pretty high flops
compared to floating
point course, okay?
Meanwhile, we are going to
accumulate these values.
We have addition
subtraction, right?
And this addition subtraction
are also performed
only integer range.
So we can still use integer
course, which is good.
Okay. And in practice,
usually, uh, here,
we use a bit integer to
represent the value,
but when we do
additional subtraction,
what we do is we use 32
bit to avoid overflow.
Okay. Any question? Yeah,
QW is the weight, right?
Here we talk about inference.
In inference, we don't
change the weights,
we can pre compute the weight
value. Contact with value.
Okay. Okay. Then we
look at this value,
SW time X divided by Y.
You still remember, this
value is a floating point,
It's a scale in the
original range.
And this is bad
because if we directly
computer this value,
we are going to call
floating point course.
That defeats the
purpose of denation
because in some scenario,
my codiation is that I don't
have floating point course,
I just want to do
everything integal course.
How I do this.
Empirical many nerNtw
this value is in a
range of zero and one,
because it's a skinning factor.
What people do is a
very dirty solution.
So instead of directly
calling floating point course
to calculate this value,
what they do is basically uh,
they use some fixed point
multiplication plus bit shift.
This price represents
value using power two.
Of course, the power
is going to be
a super negative value
times another fixed point,
um, like a fraction,
which is around
you half and one.
And the reason they do this
is because fixed point is
computation is much much
cheaper than floating point.
You don't have to touch
floating point course.
Okay? And also bit shift
is much cheaper, you
just ship the bits.
Yeah. Uh, you ship the bits
in fixed point, which
is pretty easy.
So they use this kind of like
a trick to approximate
the value.
Okay. Then we look at
this value, right.
So this value is W times QX,
and the QX is apparently
dependent on input X, right?
It has to be computed, uh,
just on a fly.
W is the zero point
of, uh, the weight.
Okay? So what we do is, um, uh,
we observe that many many
neural networks, um, uh,
they are basically
their value are
basically following
Gaussian distribution.
That is, they have a zero me,
especially a training
raw inference.
So instead of
calculating this value,
how about we just describe
this value because
they have a zero me,
which means that when
we try to quantat it,
we can also quantat in a range
where we align zero point.
So the zero point at the
target range should also
be zero in the original range.
So here we can assume that
DW equals to zero, so
we can basically im.
Okay. I per, is because of zero,
we try to simplify
it a little bit.
Of course, this is not
accurate, by the way,
because tuning is between
not accurate, right?
You're going to lose accuracy,
but it's fine as long as you
don't lose too much, yeah.
Yeah. And then if we substute
this EW equal to zero,
and we basically get
this equation, right.
So you can see,
all the other parts
have been figured out.
The only heavy lifting
part is basically
this part, QW times QX.
So what is this? Remember Q and
QX are basically the repent of
the original W and X
at my target range.
And in my example is integers.
So basically this QW and X are
the quantit integer reptation
of the weight and X.
And if we tape these two
together is basically
performing met mol
in integer course.
So here we are using integer
courts to do the
highway lifting.
That basically
satisfies our goal.
Our goal is to reduce,
on one hand, we try to
reduce the storage.
On the other hand,
we try to reduce
the previous floating
point arithmetics
into integer arithmetics.
Because like I said, integer
arithmetic is much faster,
much cheaper, save
a lot of energy.
Okay. Cool. That basically
give you a high level intuition,
what basically this kind
of near quarantine does.
Like I said at the
beginning, uh,
you can choose different
target ranges.
So here, if you chose
target range as LP eight,
you basically reduced to
the equation where this QW
and Qx are in LP eight.
Which means that you can reduce
the original LP 16 arithmetics
into LP eight arithmetics,
and that is basically
what DP sig does.
Target range being P eight.
Cool. Okay, this slides
give you a sense how this
performs in practice.
Indeed, if you do this
kind of near condition,
you can still preserve
much accuracy and
because compared to Kems codon,
remember in Kemi Cnation you are
slowing down the compute, right?
But in near connection,
not necessarily.
Sometimes you can
accelerate the computer
by leveraging lower
pricing course, okay?
Okay, that basically comes
to end of this lecture.
Let's do a quick summary.
For Nina condition, uh, uh,
if our target range
are integers,
we are basically represent
the data using integers, right.
We try to use our skill and
point to recover integer
into the target range.
And for the arithmetics,
we are able to
simplify the little
bit and eventually we'll
be able to integer course,
and integer course are much
better than phone course.
Okay. Cool. Thank you.
I'll see you on hasday on Zoom.
You don't have to be
here, go to Zoom, okay?
Yeah.
H