Okay, uh, yeah, thanks for
coming. Let's get started.
Okay, so hope you
enjoyed PA one.
Yeah. So pA two will be
released by midnight tonight.
And we heard your feedback.
So we are going to
reduce workload
in p two, but it's
going to be deeper.
Which means that if you want
to really do pretty well,
you can spend more
time on pA two.
Yeah. But you can
also choose not to
because we all design question
in a way where you are able to
optimize your algorithm
and get more grades.
Okay? Because it's
going to be deeper,
so we will allow
you to collaborate.
You can try to form a team
with up to three members,
and you guys can discuss how
to write a better
version of the code,
you'll be able to collaborate.
And when you submit PA two,
you all need to mark who
are your collaborators,
IP three, we are going to
make it pretty lightweight,
very few coding compared
to PA one and PA two.
And we are going
to give you some
very fun question in ps three,
you'll be able to
understand what is going
on in sync value.
That's one major topic I have
been always talking
about in this course.
Yeah. Cool. Okay. Today, I
want to finish the
condensation part
because I think in
my previous lecture,
we talk about linear
condadonTday,
I want to finish that part.
Then I need to introduce
a very important thing
that like I said,
probably you need to memorize
that part that is
mixed precision,
because mixed
precision is one of
the most adaptive techniques
from contaation, okay?
And then we will start our
next big chapter,
which is paralyzation.
Okay. Okay. Just
to recap, right?
Last lecture, we starting from
the floating point orientation
and the floating
point arithmetics.
And we start talking about how
to quantize floating
points into.
The first one is key
means based condensation,
where we are able
to reduce storage,
but we are not able to
save compute, right.
And we also introduce a more
common more general
codoon method,
linear condensation,
where we'll be able
to reduce the precision from
floating point to integer.
And we can also basically
migrate the computation from
floating point arithmetic into
say integer or target
precision arithmetic,
which we also save
to compute, okay?
I think when we talk
about this condensation,
especially in the
near condition,
we always assume the
first one, right?
Here I give the lime, that
is per tensor condensation.
That is give me a tensor.
I'm going to apply the
same condensation,
right, for all the elements,
all the entries in a tensor.
But in practice, this does
not always work well, okay?
So sometimes we probably need
more fun green
condensation granularity,
and this will bring us
to more common use
cotton technique,
or I would say
quantitation scheme,
which is per channel condensation
and group condensation.
Okay. I many today's RM,
I think people basically do,
for example, group condition
or poteno coddation.
I'm going to
introduce what they.
Before that, let's revisit
potential condition.
If you remember this
linear condition,
we need to determine so
here is the real number,
for example, flowing
point number and
the Q is quantized number.
And if we want to apply
linear codiation,
we need to figure out
two key parameters,
which is the scale S,
and the Z zero point.
Normally, we decide
the Z are zero, right?
So basically we have
one parameter that
is skinning factor, okay?
And given this tensor,
what we do is
basically we figure
out in the floating point
in the original domain,
uh, so what is QMAX and Q?
What is the RMAX? What
is the Rmin, right?
And then we calculate
the skin factor
like this. Right. Okay.
Pretty simple. Okay.
But in reality,
this does not always
work, like I said.
So this is the real
example where I'm
going to do uh matrix
multiplication.
Um, so I have the
weight matrix which
is W and W has
different channels it's
multi dimensional, ok?
And if you draw the
uh values of, uh,
each channel and try to
project it into this graph,
you see, there are
a few channels that
have a very large
dynamic range, right?
But most of the channels
they just basically stay
within a small
range around zero.
But you can see,
there are a few
channels that goes
up and down, right,
very drastically.
And uh and if we use
single scale a to do
quantdation, what's the problem?
So basically, when
we calculate that S,
the problem is the S will
adapt to those large dynamic
range numbers, right?
And we all lose precision for
those small numbers, right?
So a common there is that
when we use single S,
we'll be strongly influenced
by those outlier weights.
For example, in this figure, you
see quite a few layer weights,
very large or large,
positive or are negative.
Okay? And the solution is
basically we try to it's
very straightforward.
When you see this, you come
up with a solution that we
basically do antradt for
each channel that will
solve our problem,
okay? So how do we do that?
So here I'm going to compare
pertensor conuation
and perteno conation.
So given that matrix, okay.
Let's assume we basically
do the same thing,
at least two bit condensation.
So if we do pretensor connation,
we basically need to
figure out the RMX Here I
simply about a little bit by
assuming zero point is aligned,
which means this
is equal to zero.
And then we figure
out RMX is 2.12.
And we basically do
this equation, right,
and we get the skin vector.
And we apply this
skinning factor
using our linear
conduon equation,
we basically get the
contact weight, okay?
And we can use quantat weight
to reconstruct the
original weight,
and we'll get the matrix.
Okay? This is pretty easy.
So what if we do per
channel connation?
So if we do per channel
codation then we have
more flexibility. Okay?
So for each channel,
we are going
to observe the matrix there
and we try to figure out a
specific skinning factor for it.
Okay? So here, each
row is a channel.
So what we do is basically Um,
for the first row,
first channel,
we figure out the
MAX equal to 2.09,
and we can calculate the
first row skinning actor,
which is the lumber, and we
continue doing so, right?
So we need to maintain
four skinning vectors now.
Okay? Remember, screen factor
is floating point lumber.
Okay. That means
we actually spend
a little bit more storage
to store more skinning
actors, okay?
But the good news
is, if we do this,
we can apply this skinning
vector per channel,
and we'll get a
new contest width,
and we can reconstruct it, okay?
And here we can basically
compare the um,
basically the
reconstructed weight, uh,
versus the original
weight we can try to
quantize the try to measure
the reconstruction arrow.
So in the left part,
we basically get
the quantity arrow which
is two point uh 28.
And in the part, we can
do a little bit better.
Okay? That basically
give intuition.
If we do more fun
grand uh conduation
we are going to
reduce coening error.
Which means that this will be
reflected in the model
accuracy, right,
because you all have
a little bit more
precision or dynamic range.
So your model will perform
a little bit better than,
for example, doing
potential condation.
Okay? But at the cost of
saving more S, right?
So S is actually
pretty heavy compared
to two bit integer because
each S is a floating point.
And in order to represent
a floating point,
I think you at least need
LP eight or LP 16, okay?
Cool. So this is very
straightforward idea, and,
um, I think people apply this
a lot in today's
machinery models.
And apparently, uh,
if we want to do even
better that is basically
group connation, right?
I can do more and
more finer green, um,
condensation, and I will o
basically get group
condensation.
For example, I can
basically try to inspect
the values in this matrix and
I try to figure out those
values that are close.
And I basically apply
a skin vector for
that group of values
which are close in range.
And then I figure
out another group
and I calculate
another scale, right?
That means that I'm doing fine
green condensation, okay?
So the prose is basically we
have more accuracy
because if you
do per element codation
you are essentially
doing nothing, right?
Yeah, you are basically
doing no conduation.
Okay. And if you do
percentage quantity,
basically you use one
scale for all the values.
Okay. The pros is if
you are more fun green,
then you are basically
doing more accuracy.
You have less duty error.
Okay? But the counts is
if you do per value,
like I said, you are
not doing dutation,
then you are rolling back to use
the flowing point orientation
and the flowing
point arithmetic,
you are saving nothing, right?
So basically, eventually you
are facing a problem that is
what is what is
the quantuation granularity
you want to do here?
Yeah. H, so it seems
like we got a channel.
We got a fing high
precision and discounting.
That is Yeah.
Yeah, you can do that.
Yeah. Okay. Cool. This is
a little bit extreme
because like I said,
it's very complicated
because it really
depends on how you looking like,
more practical way is basically
do two level condensation.
Here, originally, we have
time quantize weight
minus zero point, okay?
What we can do is we
just two level, okay?
So in this matrix, you
can see, we are doing,
uh, the miss modification
and we get the results
on the right hand side.
So we can do two level.
The first level is we apply
global condensation
factor Gamma here,
which will be applied
pretensor, okay?
And then on top of that, we
continue to quantize it.
But in the first level
condition we quantize
it to lower bit of
freedom 16-8 bit.
And then at the first level,
we contact it from eight bit
two to say four bit integer.
Okay? We do this hierarchical
condadation. Okay.
So if we represent
this as equation
is basically we are
basically changing
from quit to equation.
Here we have two
skinning factor.
Okay. We first scale
all elements in
the tensor using a common
skinning factor gamma,
and then we skill
per group, yeah, SQ.
So the reason this is
better is because we
save a lot of storage.
So we don't have to, like, do
one skinning factor per group.
Um, at least a higher precision,
we don't need to do that, okay?
Here, like I said, the Gamma
is a floating point cross
green skinning factor and
SQ is an integer per
vector skill factor.
We only need one copy
of Gamma for oranges,
but we need many many
different SQ for each group.
Assume that we are doing
four bit quantization.
That is our inventual
target is four bit,
and our original basically
our original weight
is basically floating point,
we are doing this
global condensation.
We are doing group
condition is four bit per
vector skill every 16 elements.
The cost is
essentially four plus.
164 plus four, then amort has
across 16 numbers, right?
Because each group has
16 elements, okay?
Therefore, we are
essentially effectively well
represented each number
using 4.25 bits.
Okay? That is basically
when you read some
papers, some people say,
um, I'm basically
quantizing my weight
using uh four point half bits.
That's where it's
coming from. Okay?
They are basically
doing this kind
of hierarchical condensation.
And there is one skinning factor
which is amortized across
different elements.
And so in average,
you are basically
doing four point,
uh, four and a quarter bit
condensation, per entry.
Okay? And if you really, really,
want to grind this
a little bit, okay,
you can do like,
you know, more like
aggressive weight.
At least, you do multi level
hierarchical condensation.
Okay? You just continue
to reduce your group set.
And at a smaller group,
you are going to
use a lower bit,
and at a larger
group, for example,
at the tensor level, you are
going to use a higher bit.
And I can give you
a lot of accuracy,
but it's more complicated.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. Cool.
Any questions on this?
So basically, this is how
denting looks like in practice.
So, um, so when you start
working on this area,
I think, you really want to
look into the values
of your weight.
For example, you
are given a model.
You want to basically
plot your model
width distribution, for example,
per channel or basically
along some dimension,
and you try to see
the distribution of
these weights and try
to figure out what's
the right strategy for a
perform quandon. Okay.
Okay, we have been talking about
how to quantize the weights,
but, you know, in deepen work,
we have another worry,
uh like memory intensive
thing, which is activation.
We also need to quantize our
activation sometimes, okay?
So how to quantize activation.
So the problem of activation is,
weight, especially
inference time is static.
At the training time, I think
is semi static because,
especially when your model
is going to converge,
you only have a small Delta
updated, um, to your weight.
So your weight will basically
escalate among small range.
I would say it's semi static.
But for activity it's
quite different, right,
because every time you
are giving a batch of
data in inference
or in training,
and the batch of data could be
very different across batches.
So every time when you
give a batch network,
the activation value can
change a lot, right.
So which means that for
every group of activation,
you have to determine
the right army and RMAX.
And for different
batches, this army
and MAX can be very different.
That's why when we try
to quantize activations,
we need to apply a trick
called dynamic ranging.
So we need to
dynamically determine
army and RMAX for
each data point.
Okay? So there are
two ways to determine
army and RMAxu for activations.
The first way is very simple.
We basically do
moving average, okay?
So that is every time
we observe a batch,
we basically using
Apha to control,
how much we want to learn
from this batch, okay?
We use this offa
to slightly move
our Army Max toward the
current batch, okay?
And by doing this, I
think we can adapt
to new badges which
are extremely say,
have a different
dynamic range, okay?
Okay, another way is that,
you know your data. Assume
you know your data.
For example, you
train your data on
some model and you
know that say,
I'm going to deploy my data, um,
in autous driving
environment, and I know uh,
most of the images or
videos I'm going to read
in auto driving crises
from San Diego.
So, um, then that
means that you actually know
your distribution data, right?
So you can connect a dataset,
which is called a
calibration dataset, okay?
And before you
deploy your model,
you first run your condensation
on the calibration data set
and figure out what would be
the possible army and
RMAX for that dataset.
And you can assume that at
the test time inspect
the inference,
your data is not
going to shift a lot.
So this army and
RMAx should preserve
for incoming batches,
new data, okay?
And this is basically the
trick we use in practice.
So in many Ms, when you
try to quantize the model,
you have to figure out
your target domain.
For example, you want M to do
see a specific task
that generates code
or doing chatbard.
If that's your tax case
you basically connect
some chatboard data and
you try to calibrate
a little bit the Arman
RMAx and you quantat using
the calibrated rmi RMAx and
that should work pretty well.
Okay? So this is what we call
calibration in condition.
I think this is a very
essential procedure to
make sure your model indeed, uh,
robust to those kind of
outliers sorry, outlier
activations, okay?
Cool. Any question here?
Okay, that's all
about quantitation.
I think this is a
very important area.
Um, I'm going to talk a
little bit more about this,
but before that, let's talk
about mixed precision, okay.
So I think now with the
knowledge of connotation,
you probably already know
what mixed press is
going to do, right?
That is, for the target domain,
I'm not going to
restrict myself to be
one specific uh, number of bits.
I'm not going to target only
four bits or eight bits.
I can basically mix all
this kind of possibility.
And I try to figure
out a sweet spot
where I can save as
much as possible.
Well, I still have relatively
good accuracy, okay?
So to motivate a
little bit, basically,
my in our previous lecture,
we said that each layer,
we are going to
apply the same, uh,
target number bits for,
uh, either with or activation.
This is called
uniform connotation.
Okay. But we can be a
little bit smarter, right?
So, we can do
a long uniform condui
which is called a mixed
precision condition.
Okay. So for each layer, uh,
I can basically target
different number of bits, uh,
for weights and activation,
because the intuition behind
this is each layer has
a different dynamic range and
different kind of
robustness to precision.
Maybe for that layer,
it's not so sensitive,
so I can more aggressively
apply codaon.
But for that layer, uh,
it's very, uh, like, uh,
sensitive and you
cannot actually
modify any small
amount of value,
so you have to preserve
the original precision.
Okay? And I can basically figure
out what is the right precision
I use for each layer,
uh, at least granularity.
But the problem of
this approach is
u it's too complicated, right,
because a neural network
has so many layers,
and you really need
to do a lot of work
to figure out what is
the right precision I use for
activations for weight
and for each layer, okay?
So how to do this? So, uh,
before we figure
out how to do this,
um, uh, I can show
you the complexity.
So basically, for
each layer, say,
our target bits is our
budget is eight bits, okay?
Then for each layer for the
weight or for activation,
you basically have
64 choices, right?
And you have the many
layers and layers.
So basically, you have a design
space which is 64 power,
okay, which is super huge.
And and this is very,
um, for this kind of
problem, I think academia,
people really like
that because you
have something to grant, okay?
You can publish new papers
when you figure out
a new scheme, right?
So, um, one way to figure out
this is basically you use,
like I said, machine
learning four systems, okay?
I think I talked about this
in compatible class, right.
C era class you are going to
optimize those loops, right?
You have many many ways
to enroll these loops.
So if you ask
human to do that, it
will take a lot of time.
So you can also basically
find some machine learning
models and you try to
basically perform
some guided search
and use a cost model
to guide search.
So this slide is the
same idea, okay?
I'm doing accurate critique.
Okay? Every time I'm going
to enumerate a possibility
that apply certain bits of
condition to the width and
activation of each layer.
And I then apply it
and I try to see
how many accuracy I have and
also how many memory or
computer I can save.
Basically, I have
a cost function.
And then I measure the
real cost and I try
to fit this kind of
actor critical loop
and try to learn some
model that can model
this relation between lumber
bits and the eventual cost.
And then I can
basically do this.
I can basically deploy this
on a computer and let it run
for seven days and return
a good solution
in the discovery.
Okay? And it turns out that
this is pretty effective.
If you compare this HAQ
which is a method that I
just described compared to
uniform codenation, uh,
you can see it can indeed
figure out pretty good and
scheme where you can
preserve accuracy where still
have a pretty good latency.
Okay. Okay. This is
very interesting,
very good research field,
and I think people
publish a lot in this.
But next what I'm going to
introduce is, This paper?
This paper is not put
on the reading list,
but I highly recommend, okay?
This is a mixed precision
training paper written by media.
And for some reason,
this paper becomes
the standard today, okay?
Um, By the way,
this mixed preceding training
is exactly what I described.
So you basically apply
different precision
for different operators
layers in your new network.
But unfortunately, uh,
this scheme is not discovered
by automatic framework.
Okay, it's again, designed
by expert from media.
So basically, I
think media people,
they spend a lot of
time on figuring
out what is the right way of
combining different bits,
um, in Twin Networks
and they eventually
publish this paper,
and this paper
becomes the standard
in train language models.
Okay? So I want to
spend some time diving
into this paper,
and I want to make
sure you guys really
understand what is
doing here, okay?
So the intuition is, in many,
many neural networks,
especially in language models.
Okay? So layers are
more sensitive to dynamic
range and precision.
The reason I brought up this
today is because you already
finished P one, right.
And I think some of you probably
got stuck on softmax, right?
When you do softmax,
you already return,
a lot of lumber value, right.
So that is because for many,
many operations like softmax,
um, where you are
basically involved
with this kind of
operation, normalization.
You take a floating point value,
uh you take many floating
point value and you get
a summion of the values and
then you normalize it, okay?
For this kind of operation,
it's very sensitive
to precision.
Okay. If you use a
lower bit precision,
you are going to lose a
lot of accuracy, okay?
So intuition is when we try
to calculate this kind of
normalization operation,
we need to be very,
very precise.
Uh, Being precise basically
means that you need to
allocate more bits for fraction,
right, if you remember
our lecture, okay?
And similarly, uh, this is
part of Softmax, right?
And remember in softmax,
you also are taking
expansion function, right?
So basically E Samsung number.
And this number can easily
get explode, right?
Because it's a
power of E, right?
And if something really
is going to explode,
then what should we do?
Add a dynamic range, right.
Okay, so how do add
a dynamic range?
Give it more explod, right?
That is allocate more bits
on the exploding part.
Which means that softmax is
such a magical operation that
is sensitive to dynamic range
and sensitive to precision.
Okay? And this is intuition.
So when you perform softmax,
you probably should
allocate more bits
on both explent and
fraction, right?
That means that we really
don't have a choice.
We have to use a higher
precision floating
point for softmax.
Okay. And similarly,
for this kind of
grading accumulation,
you always add grading to
the parameters, right?
And sometimes your grading could
be extremely large, right,
especially at the
initial training
or when you're now,
what do you do?
It's very sensitive
to dynamic range,
so you want to make sure
that when you accumulate,
you don't explode your
rolling point bits, okay?
So with this kind of intuition,
so the paper I just showed,
they basically come
up with a scheme.
They are saying that we
should identify those ops
that are extremely sensitive
to precision in dynamic range.
And then we should use full
precision, for example,
1.32 for them, whenever
we met these kind of ops.
But once we finish these ops,
we can basically downcast
to lower precision
because we always want to
know always want to use
lower precision, right.
Lower precision is more memory
efficient and more
computer efficient, okay?
And with this kind of intuition,
they start doing a lot
of experiments, okay.
They try to figure out what is
the right way to combine
different precisions.
And they come up
with this scheme.
Okay. I'll like you look
at this for 30 seconds
then we go through it in detail.
Okay, so this is a figure
I quoted from that paper.
And if you want to
know more detail,
go read that paper, but
let's go through this, okay?
So this is basically how
mixed precision works today.
It's mixing two precisions.
One is the floating 0.32.
The other is flowing 0.16.
Okay. And this is the standard
today until last month.
Okay? Because last month,
I think deep sik right, they
release a paper saying that
they do everything in AP eight.
Okay. Uh, so I think it's
still good to bring up this,
but I'm going to bring
up Deep sick later.
Okay, how they do Peight.
But this is still like
how CheBT how most of,
like, today's model
are trained, okay.
So here it is seen that,
I have a master weight.
Okay. This master weight was
basically saved
in floating 0.32.
Okay, high precision,
very high precision.
Okay. And whenever I try to
start doing competition,
what I do is I'm going
to first do a downcast.
Okay? This is the dution right.
So basically, I'm
downcasting 32-16 bit.
Okay. I basically get
a floing 0.16 weights.
I'm going to use fpin 16 weights
to do forward competion.
This is pretty good
because if you
still remember the ODS
product sheet in flopping,
uh, I think 16 bit is
much more higher
flops than 32 bits.
You can use 16 bit
tensor word competion.
And because you use weight
and activation is both
in flowing 0.16 weights,
you are going to also produce
flowing 0.16 weight activations.
Okay. And similarly,
I'm going to use
this 16 bits of weights
and activation to
do backward, okay?
That will give me, that will
basically produce um gradients,
right, that is in
flowing 0.16. Okay.
Then the problem
basically last here.
So when we try to apply
these gradients into
our priamter two.
Okay. What we do is basically,
we will take this gradings,
and we are going to apply
this floating 0.16 into
this master weight to
upload to update
this master weight
into version next version.
And the way we
apply it basically,
we are going to upcast it.
We are going to upcast
from 16 bits into 32 bits.
Okay? We are going to basically
only do this kind
of weight update at
higher precision to make sure we
preserve precision and we
can basically be robust
to dynamic range.
Okay. This is a halo idea.
But the dirty part happens
when we apply this to Adam.
Okay? Because
remember in Adam, uh,
Adam is the default optimism
we use for optimize
neural networks.
And when we apply this
I think for this,
we are good, right,
because it's basically
for the backward.
It's not relevant with atom.
But when we apply this into
Adam, what happens is,
if you still remember in Adam,
um, we have two moments, right.
We need to calculate the
first and second moments,
and we use those moments
to basically normalize
our gradient libit
and then apply it
into the original
version of the w. Okay.
And now let's see how we
apply this in Adam. Okay.
So I will still use
this as an example.
So training GBD three,
because this is the best example
that will help you
understand what's going on.
Okay, um, and what
we care about is when we use
this mixed precision training,
um, framework, uh, how many
memory will actually use?
How many memory we
can save, right?
Because our eventual goal is,
um, we want to save memory
through conation, okay?
So just a little
bit recap, right?
For the largest model,
175 B, we need to store the
weights in 16 bits, right?
So which is 350
giga activations,
you did this in MCQ, right?
So we checkpoint
at the boundary.
We get this many of
activations, okay?
The problem is optimal weights.
So I'm not sure if you
still remember in
previous lecture in
the memory lecture
how many memory
we need for optimal states.
We have grading, right? We have
first moment and
second moment, right?
Okay. So basically, uh, uh,
three copies of values and
each value will be sip
in a target precision.
Okay? Now, let's try to
apply this in our mixed
precision training framework.
Okay? So when we apply
mixed precision training,
the story changes here.
We cannot see weight in FP 16,
right, because we want
to preserve accuracy.
Okay? So we have to maintain
a copy of master weight,
right, in this figure.
Okay? So this copy
is basically four,
four bits, right, 32 bits,
four bits times 175.
This is 700 giga, okay?
So here we have a
factor of four Um,
because we perform competition
using our LP 16 inter core.
So we all produce
a copy of gradients
against the perimeter,
and this copy of gradients is
saved in P 16, right here.
Okay? So we have a
factor two here,
which is the original copy of
gradients we produce at 16 bit.
Okay. And we also need to
have a running copy that is
we need to somehow run
this copy and apply
this copy to our wt.
Okay? So another factor two.
And the secret here is
basically when you apply this
mixed precision in atom,
you have to also store
the first and second moments
in higher precision.
Because remember,
malization eventually
you want to use
this first and second
moment to normalization.
Basically lomize
gradients, okay?
And the lomization
is very sensitive to
precision and also
to, uh, dmic range.
So we have to also store
this first and second
moment in high precision.
So here we get another factor
of four times two, okay?
And we get another factor eight.
Okay? This is what we do.
What do we need to save when
we apply this open states.
So here, I'm giving you one
of the most important
message in this lecture.
Okay, you need to remember this.
So when we train
language models, um,
the memory we need is
lower bounded by this one.
Okay? And this is basically
the first factor of four
second factor gradients,
running copy, first
moment, second moment.
Okay. This is the real
real memory usage
for train language models.
Yeah, because in my
previous lecture,
I never mentioned the
mixed preceding training,
but now I'm basically tell you,
we're actually using
mixed preceding training.
So which means that, uh,
you ended up with a factor of 16
N. We N is your
amber parameters,
one copy of amber parameters.
Why is this equation
so important?
Because next time
when people ask you,
can I train a model using H 100?
Can I train Lama
seven B on H 100?
On single H 100, you
immediately know,
I use this, say,
you have a seven B model Lama,
and you use seven times 16
and you know the lower
bound memory that you need.
Which is apparently
this number is
greater than 80 gigat that
means you are not able to
train Lama seven B
on single H 100.
Okay. Does it. Does
it make sense?
Okay. So make sure you
remember this, okay?
This is the lower
bound for training
language models, okay?
Any framework, yeah.
It apples to Petro,
you apply to tender flow
jacks, any framework.
Why you copy gradients?
Because, on one hand,
you need to derive
the activation
gradients using weed gradits.
You have to save that.
On the other hand,
when you apply that
gradient to the primary,
how to upcast it,
you need to copy
to upcast. Yeah. Yeah. Okay?
Okay, 16. And this is not
considering activations.
Okay? So if you want to
also consider activations,
you need to go back
to this slide and try
to study this a little bit.
Okay? So how we
save activations.
Cool. Okay, memorize this.
I think this is extremely
important. Okay.
Yeah, that basically
wrap up my lecture
on quantuon or more broadly,
skinning down machine learning.
I want to spend a few minutes
to talk about this area.
So basically skinning down
machine learning and
deep learning is
a very active area of research
in machearing and systems.
A lot of people a
lot of professors,
students are doing this, okay?
So because running
machine learning on
edge devices is always
strongly demanded, right?
I think everyone
wants to do that.
That's why there's a high
demand on this scale, okay?
But one thing that I want
to point out is, um, uh,
this market of scaling down
merginary it has a very
key characteristics.
Okay? It's a very
fragmented market.
So what do I mean by
fragmented market?
So I'm comparing
this to cloud market
where we scale up marginally.
Okay. So why is if you
think about cloud market,
it's not fragmented
at all, right?
Basically, AWS has 70%,
uh, market share, right?
And then GCP and Microsoft.
Okay, three, big three, okay.
But if you talk about skinning
down marchiney there's no,
like, a winner, okay?
So everyone is doing
their own thing. Why?
Because in Cloud, we
only have media chips.
Okay? We roughly deploy
everything, media chips.
And in Cloud, AWS
is the only winner.
You probably know, yeah.
But when you talk
about screen down,
there are so many diverse chips.
I think in the previous lecture,
our gas lecture change
et cetera, uh, uh,
when we do merginy compilation,
the main problem is there
are so many different chips
that you have to compare
down to different,
like, kernel libraries
or whatever, right?
So it's a very frag
market market,
which means that if you
choose to do research
in this area,
it's very easy to publish
because there's
always a problem.
Right, for target hardware.
Yeah, because there
are not enough people.
And if you choose to do
a business in this area,
I would say it's a
good business, right,
because especially for startups,
right, because you
can always choose
a target domain which
is under addressed,
and you try to address
the problem for them.
Indeed, this is a
pretty good, um, uh,
area that you can build
a startup and get
acquired. I can give
you an example.
Ten chi right, his
company AutoML,
they do pretty well
on Intel chips.
And I think at some point,
they got a pretty good offer
from Intel, to acquire them.
But they declined, because
they want to do bigger.
They want, right?
Eventually market changes.
Okay. Another example is,
um, a mating professor,
the quantititi guy, I
mentioned Songhas company,
and he's doing
condition a lot, right?
He's a guide of
condition, basically.
And he does a lot of
condensation work
for Avidia and for
Qualcomm, okay?
He basically optimize against
Nvidia chips and Qualcomm chips.
And it turns out that
he was very successful.
I think in 2022, his company
was acquired by Nvidia, okay?
I heard that he got
two offers from both,
like, Quadcom and Nvidia.
Okay, he chose to go A
Midia in 2022, okay?
That's a pretty good
deal, good deal, right?
Because in 2022, WIDA Chip,
Amdatock is still here,
right? Yeah, okay?
And I also have a few friends
which do this kind of business,
and they basically choose,
hardware winder
because, you know,
hardware winder lot is
very rich today, right?
And they have a lot of
money. They want to
acquire every small companies.
And they basically target
that speed hardware.
They try to do very deep,
like don or implementation
for them hardware,
and they hope to be
acquired. And they always.
Okay? But the bad news is, um,
if you really want to build
a really big business,
for example, as large as Google,
as a Amazon, I
don't think this is
a good area for doing
that because like I said,
it's very easy to it's very
difficult to unify
every chips, right?
You have to design one
type of condensation
and algorithm and a kernel
library for one typo hardware.
It's very very fragmented,
so everybody is doing their own.
Okay? Um, and in terms
of research direction,
I think there are still a lot
of going on because every
time there's a new model,
when there's a new hardware,
when there's a new kind
of kernel operator,
quanta people is going
to basically tact them.
Yeah, they are going to probably
feel prepared for that.
Okay? And people are
doing a lot in this area,
for example, quantadon pruning,
because you eventually want
to deploy your ID
devices, right,
you start care about energy,
okay, energy efficiency.
And you also do
federation machining,
Okay, which was not
covered in this lecture.
But unfortunately,
we hired a faculty.
He's going to join this fall.
Yeah, he's a quant
editing guy, okay?
And if you're
interested, you can
try to listen to
his classes, okay?
Cool. That's all from
me on quant edition.
Okay. Then let's move on, okay?
Big picture. So we finish
DataFgraph right
AutoDvGraph Oenation.
We also dive deeper
into operator Oenation.
Uh, we also start
talking about run time,
how to schedule, how to do
memory, how to do quantition.
Okay? Now, I think we
are going to enter
our last big lecture
Paradition, right?
Okay. Inspired I want to cover
this many content, okay?
I'm going to justify
why we need to
start why we need to
study paraldition.
Then I'm going to talk about
machine learning parallelism and
how to talk about
connective communication
because it's a cornerstone for
machine learning paralism.
Okay? And then we start
talking about and study
all this data model
interoperator interrupted
palism we wrap up,
uh, by reviewing some latest
work on automatic parallon.
Okay. Cool. So why
we need piston?
I think we basically
need to come back
to our mainstream story.
More slow. So, I think we should
do this when we start
talking about when
we start justify accelerators.
Okay. So 20 years ago, yes,
we are still having
the more slow,
but now it stopped, right?
Okay. Meanwhile in
machinery industry,
what happened is, Okay.
The model size, they
are basically ten times
every 18 months. It's crazy.
And this curve is
still going on.
The latest TipSIg model is
600 biniar perimeters, okay.
So basically the size of
mercenary model is
growing crazily,
why people start developing
all these large models?
Two reasons why.
One is because, um, by
simply skiing the
size of the models,
you are going to have a
way better performance.
So here, the excess
is the number of
parameters of the model.
The Y excess is the
average performance
of 20 benchmarks in
literal language,
uh, uh, literal
language processing.
So you don't care about
what the benchmark.
Basically, we normalize
that into from 0% to 100%.
Okay. 100% is
perfect performance.
Zero is basically the
zero performance.
And once we normalize
it you observe that
when we skill the
model size, okay?
And we try to measure
the average performance on
all these 20 benchmarks,
you will see basically
the performance will
just keep increasing.
Okay. Okay, this
gives hope, right,
because if you can achieve 100%,
you are basically achieving AI.
True AGI. Okay. That's
the first reason.
Okay, Skinny model size
can give you a lot of
performance improvement.
That's simple.
The second is people
start observing
that big models have some
emergent capability,
and I really like
this Jif produced,
um, by Google, okay?
So what is this Jif try to
illustrate is basically,
when you continue to
skill the model sizes,
Be able to do some very
complicated tasks.
Okay. So this is kind of like
a leap pas leap forward.
It's like a baby that
every few months,
it's going to
develop a new skill.
Suddenly, yeah. Okay. And
people indeed observe this.
Today, I think people
are already talking
about some very advanced
skills, reasoning,
When you skill your model in
some way and your
model start to reason,
start to solve this kind of
mathematical questions, okay?
No. I try to do is
basically I'm going to align
the two curves I should.
One is the model sizes.
The other is chips capability.
This is the model sizes,
ten X every 18 months.
This is the Morse law, you can
see the gap is widening,
a lot of widening,
Which means that Morse
law is not going to work,
Morse law is basically
characterized
in the development of CPU, okay.
Okay. I hope you still
remember my slide this slide,
right? So we have two options.
One is accelerator. The
other is quantum computing,
and quantum computing
is going on,
and we can basically project
our accelerator story
into that curve. Okay.
And if we project
the growth of the
capability of accelerators,
what happens is basically
still wide gap, right?
It's basically in the middle
of what we need and what
we actually what CPU
current currently offer.
Okay? So the growth
of the VD GPU,
the compute flops is still
not catching up, okay?
That's a problem.
And the TPU curve green curves
a little bit better than GPU.
Okay? Yeah. Cool. And
this gap is increasing,
uh, 256 times every 18 months.
Yeah. So basically,
all the accelerators,
if you use a single accelerator,
you're not going to catch up
with the model sizes
we need to develop.
Okay? And this is from
the compute perspective.
And you can also draw
this kind of curve on from
a memory perspective.
What happens is basically,
um, the memory increase
even crazier, okay?
So the memory that we
need to store the model to
train the model basically,
uh, it increase 35
times every two years.
But the GPU memory girls
is much flatter, okay?
So basically, there's no way
that you can catch up. Okay.
And the largest model fit on
single GB basically
we stop at BRT.
Okay. BRT is basically
the model that
we can store on single GI, okay?
And at some point, we
basically face the change.
That is we need more than 100
GPOs to just store
the parameters,
not mentioning those
openmeter states
and activations, okay?
Yeah, I hope this figure
this is real data, okay?
This real data, it's not like
I made up this, okay, real data.
And I hope it's basically
justify that there's
no way out, right?
The only way that we do is
basically we do part addition.
That's why we need to
study paraliztion, okay?
Cool. Then let's talk
about part addition.
Okay. So I think many
of you probably already
worked on this part, right?
Like, if you do Petro
you do whatever kind
of thing today,
you probably have already
started working with like
Petroc distributed
or Tinder flow
distributed kind
of library, right.
And, um, and I think most of
you when you work on this,
you are basically educated
with two concepts.
One is called data parism.
The other is called the Mtopism.
So what is data palism
and topolism? Okay?
I think the dataparism is very
easy to understand we have
been talking about that at
the accelerated levels
basically SIMD.
Uh I GPU you hold
many many cores you
give each part of data.
That is basically data parism.
And in this part of
the lecture, uh,
data paralisis means that you
have many many different GPUs,
you give each GPU a part
of data. It's the same.
So in data parism we
have many many GPUs.
Each GPU is probably installed
on some notes, right?
And we have a huge dataset.
And we basically split
the data set and we
give each GPU a paro dataset,
and we let them
proceed together,
okay, in parallel. Okay.
So here, Datapism actually has
a core assumption that is,
uh, the entire model needs to
fit on a single machine or GPU.
Okay. So what happens,
if the model does not
fit on a single machine?
That basically give us multipis
We need to party in the model.
Okay? So, meaning that
we need to paralyze the model
itself. So what is the model?
Because in this lecture, I
think we know what this model.
It's basically computer graph,
we define that comminute graph,
and we are going to come
back to that later.
But however, say,
this is a unla model.
It's basically a
lot of mat model,
many many non linear functions,
uh, like composing
complete computer graph.
Okay. So when we talk about, uh,
how we basically
partition these models,
we are talking about
how we partitioning
this kind of tensor
operators, right?
So intuitively, there
are a few ways, okay?
One is like we can cut
in the middle, right?
So say this general
has four layers, we
basically cut in the middle.
We give the first
GPU two layers,
the other GPU another
two layers, right?
This is a model type number one.
Okay. Another way is, um,
we can even pipeline execution
to make it even more
complicated but more efficient,
but we can talk about
this layer, okay?
Um, Okay. And what's the
second way of doing mod party?
So this is vertical cut right.
I can do horizontal cut.
Okay? Yeah, so it's
very intuitive.
I can also horizontal cut.
So for each layer, I'm
going to cut that layer
into different parts and
I give each GB a part.
Okay? This is another part
of another type of
mod partism, okay?
And you can see this
can become rather
complicated because
each layer probably has
different kind of operators and
each neural network
probably have
different kind of layers, right?
And we also have a
different type of cluster.
We could have a cluster with
eight GPUs installed
in one node.
We can also have a
pretty big cluster where
we have tens of
thousands of GPUs,
and they are distributed
in different ways.
Okay? And that will
basically make the
problem very complicated.
And that's what we are
going to dive deeper.
Okay. But intuitively, I think,
like I said, uh,
you have a classic view of
machine learning partism
where you classify pism into
data parts, Multi partism.
And I think next,
what I'm going to
do is I'm going to
map this kind of like
intuitive explanation of pism
into our definition of models
and data on compute, right?
Because we want to
approach this pism
from sure computation
and system perspective.
So we know what to do what
to deal with on system side.
Okay. Still recap, right?
This is the figure we use
in my second lecture,
where we have
neural networks and
this neural network
can be represented
using this master
equation, right?
Still remember the
definition of each symbol.
Okay.
So from a computational
perspective, what is partsm?
Okay? I think from
a computation perspective,
we care about two things, right?
One is how to compute.
How to compute the computer
graph. Second is memory.
I hope we spend so
many time on memory,
how to basically make sure
the computation will
subject to the peak memory.
Okay? So for computer,
if you look at
this equation, uh,
what are the elements
that require compute?
The first element
is this function,
which perform forward
and backward.
Okay? And when we
talk about parism,
we basically need to parts in
this compute function across
different number of dips. Okay?
A second part is
the F op matters,
right, where we apply
gradients, uh, two parameters.
And we need to
apply this function
F. We need to
perform this function F
across different dipts.
Okay? And this is the main
compute from this equation.
Okay, we are going to
study how to parallelism.
On the memory part, we
have two main sources
of consumption is D,
D is data, number batches.
And if you partition D, it
becomes data pismV clear.
Okay? And Theta, Theta is
basically the uh parameters.
Okay? We need to partition
parameters because we
cannot put the
model into one GPU.
The memory is not sufficient.
Okay. And one part that we
really need to study and take
care of is, um, communication.
Why communication is important
because on a single device,
you do have communication, but
communication basically happens
between memory hierarchy.
You communicate between, uh,
CPU memory to HPM SRM to
catch it to register.
Okay. And that is pure local.
So your device, uh your
GPU library like Coda,
they provide all this kind
of memory copy for you.
It's very easy to implement.
But when you go distributed
this different story,
you have to communicate
these things across
different GPUs and how
different dips get connected.
There is some interconnect
between devices,
and this interconnect could be,
medius Vlink if you
put GPUs in one box.
Or if you want to
continue to scale up,
you have to go
through the network.
Network, you have different
kind of networks.
You have Amazons,
like elastic fabric,
this kind of network technology.
You also have infinivn.
You have TCP IP kind of
basically many layers if you
have studied networking.
Then how to handle
communication.
And that is the main source
of complexity in poison.
So how to carefully handle
communication because we know
communication is much
slower than locality,
because locality, you just
moves between memory hierarchy.
But once you start
doing communication,
you have a high latency.
Okay? We have to handle that.
And how to handle communication
parameters and also, uh,
the communication activations,
and that depends on
how we partition the new
network, the computation graph.
Okay? So that'll be inside,
um, we know what do we
do at a high level.
Then we can basically
try to understand
data and multipaism
from this perspective,
from this computer perspective.
So for data parism,
what we do is
basically we are going
to partition the data.
We are going to piton the
data and we give each GPU
different data and they
compute on their own, right?
But the problem is, um,
each GPU is going to
compute on their own,
but at some point, they
need to synchronize.
Because otherwise, GPU
is basically computer on
their own pace and they are
not basically contributing
to the same job.
You are not making progress
through partition.
So I datapati what kind of thing
will need to communicate.
We are going to soon
figure out. So basically
the part that we
need to figure out
is how to communicate
the parameters
and ingredients, okay?
And the entire algorithm,
um, so basically, we
part in the data, okay?
We give HGPU a different data
where we also replicate
the parameters.
So we give each GPU a
copy of the parameters.
Okay? And then GPU
is going to take the
copy the parameters,
and also a copy of the model
code, of course, okay.
And it's going to
apply this computation
on that specific
designated batch of data.
And once we do this,
what we'll produce?
We will produce a copy
of gradients, right?
And remember in
this optimization,
what we do is we need to apply
the gradients into
primeters, right?
So HTPU could apply
the gradients independently
to the parameters.
But it does not make
sense, because otherwise,
EHPU is doing, um,
in other way, GPU is basically
doing their own communion.
There's no
communication. So what
do we do is basically
in daal purism,
we are going to
synchronize the gradients.
Okay? We are going to have
a communication mechanism
where we are going
to connect gradients
from all the GPUs.
We accumulate them, and then
we apply to the parameters.
Okay. And once we apply
to the parameters,
we are going to get a new
copy of the parameters
and we basically redistribute
that copy of parameters to DPS,
and we start next iteration.
Okay? This is data partarism.
And I Mdparism things becomes
more complicated, okay?
So, we don't partition
data anymore.
Okay? We are going to
partition the model.
Uh Partitioning model is
very, very weak, right?
So what do I mean
by parison model?
There are many many
possibilities.
One is I'm going to partition
the model parameters,
which is the Theta.
The other one is I'm
going to petition
the competition, which
is that function.
Okay. Lambda L, okay?
The problem here is how
do we deal with data?
Right? Because in multiparism,
I don't know how
to deal with data.
I could parts or not partition.
Okay. We are going
to figure it out.
And, of course, we
need to partition
optiber states because we
already part in part of
the model and we have to apply
the partial gradients into
the part of parameters.
Okay, we partition. Okay.
Uh, that'll give
you a big picture,
right? It's very complicated.
Okay. You have so many
choices to petition,
and you also subject
to networking latency.
You subject to
memory constraints,
you subject to whatever,
like, uh, well, make
your job slow, okay?
You have to make sure, uh,
you petition in a smart way
that your job is not slow.
Okay? This is part of the issue.
Okay, now, I'm going to
basically start
talking about how we
make this entire picture
much more clear.
Okay. So I hope you still
remember this figure, right?
So we can represent our model
using a computer graph,
and this computer
graph basically is
composed of three parts forward,
backward and with update.
Okay. And eventually we'll
end up with this graph.
Okay. So what is paradisi?
So if you only talk about if you
think that paradiing
at the model level,
you're not going
to figure it out.
Okay, it's too complicated
because there are so many
different kind of models.
So now, let's basically
change your mindset.
We forget about the model.
Okay? All the model are
basically computer graph.
Okay. I'm going to give
you a computer graph,
you just paradi it.
That's paradion.
Okay? So in this lecture,
what I'm going to the way
I taught I taught is,
I'm going to teach parodies
basically I'm going to give
you this computer graph.
I'm also going to give you
a device cluster like this.
I think cluster is
very easy to read,
especially given
to this cluster.
For example, this is
the medius DGX box,
and this is V 100,
but basically E 100
and H 100 is the same.
They are connected in a way
where you can see this GPU.
Okay. And HGPU basically
has a multi way link,
this Mink is very
high bandwidth.
Meaning that HGPU when they
talk to another GPU inside of
this box is
very high bandwidth
communication. Very very fast.
It's almost like a
memory hierarchy,
but just a little bit slower.
Okay. But if you
draw another box
here and if this GPU
wants to communicate
with another GPU here,
the problem exists, they have
to go through this Internet.
They have to move
things from GPU memory
to CP memory and let
the CPU to send those contents
through this Internet.
And you can see the scale of
the communication bandwidth.
Internet is almost
like ten to 100
times slower than link.
Okay. And maybe I
can make this a little
bit more abstract,
that is, we have this
kind of cluster.
Here I have four nodes, okay?
One, two, three, four, right?
And basically each node has
a few GPUs here I give four,
but typically today
is eight, okay.
These GPUs are basically
have a fast connection,
which I use green
green line here.
And if you want to
communicate between
any GPU that is from
different boxes,
you have to subject to
the slow connection.
Okay. And with this repenton
of this device cluster, um,
then our problem is
become a little bit more,
I would say, nicer
than previous version.
That is, uh Okay.
So part of this basically equals
to partitioning computational
graph on device Claster.
Okay? On the left hand side,
we are given committer graph.
Okay? On the right hand side,
we are given another graph, but
this graph is not
a computer graph.
It's basically graph
of devices. Okay.
And here, I don't use graph,
but you can understand
it that way, okay?
And this graph has a very
unique and very determined
characteristics
that is inside of one box,
it's fast connection and
between boxes store connection.
And our problem is basically
how to partition commuter
graph on the device clasor.
Okay? Problem defined.
Okay. Any question?
Of course,
you need to subject to
memory constraints, right?
You need to subject
to, for example,
communicating bandwis.
And you want your job.
Once you partition this graph
on this device cluster,
you want your job to run as
fast as possible
without auto memory.
Okay? Cool. With this
defined problem,
let's start talking about a
little bit on how
to partin this.
Okay, here, I'm going to
start talking about
how to paten graphs.
To simpfy a little bit,
I'm going to give you a
very simple graph, okay?
So here in this
graph, you have, um,
this is the one we used in
the previous lecture it
basically single layer MLP.
Okay? Uh, two met
m1u and one MSC,
two is W one, W two,
and one input X.
But compared to my
previous lecture,
here, I'm going to introduce
a little bit more rotation.
I'm going to give
each node a color.
So here I have a
cluster of two nodes,
Device one and device two,
and blue is the first device
and pink is the second device,
if a node is one color,
that means that
node that operator,
that computation
happens on that device.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Cool. Then this notation,
we can start
partitioning this graph,
and we can use
notation to notate,
what do we do on the
partitioning bar?
Okay. This is our
first strategy.
If you still remember
a few slides before,
I cut in the middle.
I cut in between
different layers,
I give the first two layers to
one device and another two
layers in the second device.
So here, if I reflect
that part in strategy is
basically this one.
I cut in the middle.
I give the first met
to the blue device,
and I give basically
the due and second memo
to the second device. I
cut it in the middle.
I use different color.
Strategy one, okay.
And I can basically do
slightly different,
for example, I can
do a horizontal cut.
I put the weight W one,
W two on first device,
and I put the rest
on on second device.
So remember, when we cut in
the middle when those two
nodes where the halfway at,
if they are on different
devices, what would happen?
They need to communicate, right?
They need to communicate.
And we're going to,
with this part again, but
let's assume that we
know how to communicate.
Okay. So I would
say the two strategy
is the same because
I actually basically
cut those notes,
I put different notes
on different devices.
So could you give me
a different strategy?
So if you remember in
my previous slides
in intuitive slide,
I also can cut
horital card I cut
a layer into half or
one half network.
So for that card,
does that card correspond
to one of these two?
One, you think is one?
No, it's not one,
because in other cut,
I basically cut the metmo I
cut the memo into two parts.
And in these two figures, I
actually don't cut memo at all.
The metamo is always perform
as a whole on one device.
Which means that if I
try to cut operators,
I actually have a different
strategy like this.
So here I use this notation a
little bit more intuitively,
that is I'm going to cut
operator I'm going to give
the operator half and
half different colors,
and one half is performed on
one device and then
the other half
is performing different devices.
So you figure out how
to parse that one.
Uh, if you look at this part,
it means that for
this met more, okay?
I'm going to cut in the middle.
I put the first half of the
met more on one device,
the second half on
second devices.
Be I cut metam
the input and output also
need to be cut, right?
So because I want to perform
the first half of the
metam which is mat,
I want to perform mat
on the first device.
So I have to also cut the
input into two half, right?
And this part is
going to perform Mt.
Okay. And the second device
is going to perform more. Okay.
So I also need to
cut this output.
Sorry, another part
of input, right?
And you're going to
perform the pink bar.
Okay. Makes sense, right?
Cool. Is there a different way?
Of course, I can do a horizontal
cart at operating level.
So sorry this color
is a little bit,
uh, not working, but you get it.
I can basically cut
in this way, right?
Yeah. And so for
Metamor I can cut basically
following different axes,
a, it will result into
different kind of
parting strategies.
Okay. Any question
on this slide?
Cool. So here, I'm going to
introduce two slightly
different strategy.
Okay? So in the first row,
I'm basically
applying a strategy
where I don't cut operators.
I only cut the graph. Okay?
And I call this strategy
interoperatd pism.
Uh, you can infer the
meaning of this lame, right?
Interoperator parism
basically means that
I never cut an operator.
I basically only cut the graph.
I assign different nodes
of the graph to
different devices.
And in the second row, I called
the interoperative pism.
That is, I'm going to
touch the operator.
I'm going to perform
one operator on
two different
devices and I figure
out how to aggregate
results later.
Okay. Um, you can
see the definition of
interoperative prism and
inter operative parism is
much I would say much more or
less uh ambiguous compared
to data and motpoism.
Why? I motoparism when I
talk about Mtoparism,
don't know what I mean.
You probably don't know,
because I can mean
many many things.
But when I talk about inter
and interoperats,
it's very precise.
Interbasically means, I'm
not going to cut operator,
but intra means I'm
going to do that.
Okay. Then let me
ask you a question.
So is datapism inter or
intraoperative parism?
Please. Is Intra Inter?
Intra? Yes, Datab intra Why?
Because you cut X
and X is your node,
and you indeed cut
X X is your input.
You cut batches, so it's intra.
Okay. We're going to come
back to this again again.
Okay? We are going to explore
all different strategies
of Inter intra.
We are going to reason it trade
off, how much it communicate.
How many memory it needs, okay?
Okay. And given these
definitions, uh,
let me expand intra and
intraparism a little bit.
So for matrix, we can
actually partition it along,
um, we can do row parison, okay?
We can also do column pion.
Sorry, this color is different,
it's not working.
I'm going to fix it.
But what I mean, basically,
you can cut it in this way or
you can cut it in this way.
Okay. I call this row partition,
I call this column
partition. Okay.
So I'm going to
introduce a third definition
and a third color,
which I could replicate it.
Which means that
I'm not cutting.
Okay. I'm basically
replicating this tenser.
Okay. If this color is green,
it means that I'm replicating
this note on both devices.
So each device will
have a copy of it.
Okay. So following
this location,
we can visualize more
parlement strategies. Okay.
And next, I'm going to basically
visualize a few notable
parliament strategies.
And basically each
strategy I'm going
to visualize next is
very famous paper,
more than 1,000 stations, okay?
And they are being
adopted in training.
The reason I do this is
because I want to show you
that we can use
this repenton to basically
illustrate many,
many different concepts, okay?
So the first one. Um, plea you
look at it for 10 seconds,
and I'm going to ask
you what what this is.
Anyone want to answer?
I actually talked
about this right now.
What is this? Yeah,
data parison.
Okay. You got it.
Why is data parison?
Because I have two
devices, right?
I replicate the width, right?
Which means that each
device has a copy of width.
And I part in the input.
Because I part in the input,
so this metamo is going to
be partin as well, right?
All the way like propagated
through this neural network.
So each device is going to
calculate different loss.
And I skip the update
green update part,
but we'll come back
to that later.
Okay? This is data
parison, okay.
I hope you basically
after my lecture,
you go back and try to
internalize this repetition
because it's very important.
We are going to make this
arbitrarily complicated.
Okay? How about this one?
Anyone work on M No, this one.
Sorry. Is is one
type of modoparism.
What is that type? Okay? This is
the one I give it to
you in reading megaton.
Okay. And typically, people call
this kind of modopoism
tensor partism.
Okay? It's called
tensor partism it is
a typical pism used in today's
language model training.
And one thing you'll
notice that is
here instead of replicating
weights we are
replicating the input.
And basically, each device
is going to get a
copy of the input,
and we are going to
patina weight. Okay?
And also because
we patina weight,
we are also going to
part in the meto, okay?
And then we also
propagate all the partitions
all the way to next met moo.
But for the next Mtmo we are
going to replicate the memo.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. I want
you to cross boons
this into the reading
I give it to you,
the required reading,
which is microtome paper.
How about this
one? Okay. This is
a little bit more abstract,
but I can tell you.
This one is essentially
pipeline parism
the thing that you notice
here is basically,
I don't do intraperparism,
I never parting operator.
But what I do is basically, um,
I part in this met M.
I cut in the middle.
I give each device
a different metmo.
Meanwhile, I pipeline execution
of metam using a long time.
Each time I'm going
to give a batch and
this batch first comes
into the first device.
And then once the first
device metm finished,
it will forward the computation
or the activation to
the second device.
Meanwhile, in the
next time step,
this device is going to fetch
another batch to the
parallel competion.
This is basically
pipeline parism. Okay.
How about this one? This
is even crazier, right?
No, I have four devices.
Okay. And device three
and device four,
they are using different colors.
Okay. This one is
called I wouldn't call
it three G parison,
but it's very complicated.
Indeed, this is
something that we
use today for language model
training for GBD training.
The thing you'll notice that is
I hold four devices, right?
What I do is I first cut
my devices group
into two groups.
The first group is this
group, blue and red.
Second is green and yellow.
And what I do is if you think of
these two as one mega
device or device group,
what I do is I first to enter
of inter operative partism,
I cut in the middle.
I give this part of Nork to
the first group and I give
this part of N to
the second group.
Okay. And if you
think this two device
are one meta device,
this is pure interpartim.
But instead of
this device group,
what I do is I continue
to do intraop partism.
Okay? I basically cut
in column parison,
for the first group, the two
device in the first group,
and I do another column party
in the second group. Okay?
This is rather complicated
because it essentially
combines inter and intra
op pismoO more devices.
And today, people give the
name that is parism, okay?
And um if you want to
train really large model,
for example, on more than 1,000
GPUs, this is your to go.
I'm going to explain next.
Okay. Then I have
one last slide to
explain why I spent
so much time to onboard
you on this orientation.
Why we care about
intra and intra.
But before that, I want to
summarie a little bit okay.
For interrupted
partism we basically
assign different operators
to different devices.
For interrupted
partism we assign
different regions of a single
operator to different devices.
And that's easy to understand.
Okay. Now, let's try
to see what the
computational pattern
really looks like if we apply
these two types of
partism to a small graph.
Okay, we are going to dive
deeper into this partition and
we basically thinking in a
way that what happens on GPU.
Okay? And this is one of
the most important slides.
So make sure you understand it.
And if you don't
understand, come
to ask me, I try
to explain this.
Okay. Consider this
graph with five notes.
Okay. I got this
graph by basically
skipping the al and the MSE.
I make it even simpler.
Okay. Um,
So in fact, this graph
is essentially doing
two matrix modifications
as this equation shows.
Okay, I want you to
basically internalize
this equation on
this graph, right?
So here, I basically partition
the W into two devices
into two parts, right?
And I replicate X.
And I like each copy of
X column partition the W
which will basically give me,
also I do partition
another uh W and W two,
and I tie them together
on different devices.
I make each part from
different devices.
Okay? Okay, with this
equation, right?
Cool. Okay.
Let's see what's
happening on device.
Okay. Let's start
from the first memo.
So let's start with
this one. So here
I know X is replicated, right?
So which means both device
one and two will have copy x.
Okay? So the way W one,
it is column partition, right?
So which means that device
one has the left part
of W one, right?
And Device two has the
right part of W one.
Okay? So X is replicated, right?
So each device has X
Left par W par, W. Okay?
We are going to perform at
the mall. So what do we get?
We tie them together, right?
For the first device,
I'm going to get
the first half of
the Mdmal result,
which is met, for
the second device,
I'm going to get the
second half of Mdm M,
that's why basically
in this notation,
I get this met and
M. It's our result.
And we can basically check
the result here the
partition here.
We find that basically this
met corresponds to this
met and this mo
correspond with small,
there's no problem it
aligns. We're good.
We are going to proceed
to the next meth mod.
Okay. Okay. In the next met
mode, we start with this.
Okay? No, let's move
right into here.
Okay. Look at this one.
Okay. So in this figure,
we said that we are going
to for the first device,
we are going to have met
for the second device,
we are going to have
mod, meanwhile, uh,
for this W two, right, we
basically do a low
parting, okay?
Which means that for
the first device,
we have the upper
part of W two, right?
For the second device,
we have the lower
part of W two, okay?
And what do we do we are
going to do the multiplier.
Okay? So what are
happen if we do this?
So we all get a matrix met M,
which is the full shape of
the same shape of
the original metamo.
But their values are different.
Because if you still
remember our Mdm cross,
this is called
partial sum, right?
So the invintu metal
value should be we
should add these two
together together the
invent memo, right?
Okay. Then what we do is,
again, we're going
to check this.
This is what we get if
we execute it right.
And this is what we
expect on graph, right?
Okay? We are going to
check this on this.
So let's check it, okay?
So on this one, each device
basically get a partial sum.
But on this graph, we
want each device to
get a replica of the met.
So how we can transition
from here to here,
how we can satisfy the
constraint on life handset.
We add them together, right?
So how to add them together?
So in order to add
them together,
I need the first device to send
this pure sum to the
second device, right?
And meanwhile, I need
to second device
to send this pum to
the first device.
That is, I need this
kind of operation.
That is using to me
and using to me.
And then I do the
summation myself, okay?
Right? That's the way that
I minimize communication.
Okay? What operation basically
perform this operation?
What kind of
communication operation
will satisfy this constraint?
It's called reduce.
Okay? You guys know
reduce, right?
Okay. If you don't
know, it's fine.
I'm going to teach you
next quarter. Okay.
But not next
quarter, next class.
Okay. But essentially,
here, you can see.
When I do this
kind of partition,
I derive what execution,
I try to see how I can satisfy
this kind of partitioning.
And I eventually found that
I actually need reduce,
this reduce is basically how
pardon handles this
kind of partitioning.
Yeah. Okay? Let's look
at second example.
Yeah, please. Strategy.
Sorry. This strategy.
Is this a good strategy.
This is a good strategy.
This is the Mctron.
Yeah. Yeah. It's pretty slow,
because you need to
reduce and reduce is
a very expensive operation,
but there's no cheaper way.
Because eventually, I'm going to
convert this into
optimal problem.
I will prove this
is the optimal way.
You cannot do better.
Okay? Doesn't make sense.
Yeah, let's assume that
this is what we want.
But I want to explain
why we need this because
in order to perform
the next palm,
how to have this met
following this replica.
Yeah. Okay. Then
I'm going to finish
my lecture using
one final example
and the next example
is going to be easier.
This is another part of history,
which I call inter paralization.
It's pretty simple.
What happens on first
device is basically uh,
for following scholar, I know
this memo is going to
perform on the first device.
And it basically has these
two input X on W one local.
So what happens on the
first device is X,
types one, I get the memo
results on the first device.
And then I start moving my
I into the second memo.
Here I want my second
memo to happen on
the second device,
the red device.
So here, in the second device,
I have this W two, which
is also local, right?
And I want my results to be
written in the second device.
But I find that I'm
missing my input, right?
And this input where it is,
is on the first
device here, right?
So in order to satisfy this
kind of competion, what I do?
I also communicate by
the communicating
pattern changes here.
What I do is I ask
the first device
to send the more results
directly to the second device.
Okay? That's what I did, right?
This is called P to
P communication.
This is a slightly different
communicating pattern
from this one.
In this one, I need every device
to communicate with
the other device.
But in this one, I only
need one device to
communicate to the other.
One is sender, the
other is receiver.
I think now you already
spot the difference.
I'm going to give
you a statement.
So for intraoperative partism,
as long as you do this kind
of operator partitioning,
you are going to deduce some
connective communication.
But for this interoperatism,
if you don't party in operator,
you always part in a graph,
you only need PTP communication.
That basically give
you a key difference
because different communication
have very different cost.
A reduce is much, much
more expensive than PTP,
that need to be mapped into
different network hierarchies.
For example, if you
have high bandwidth,
you should prefer to reduce.
And if you have low bandwidth,
you should prefer to use
you should avoid radius.
You should prefer using PTP.
In the next lecture,
I'm going to
introduce this to communicating
primitives to make
sure we understand
the mathematics
behind it. Thank you.