Okay. Yeah, let's get started.
Thanks for coming
on a rainy day.
Yeah. Cool. So where we are.
So I think last lecture,
I justified why we need to
do paralyzation, right?
Because we just need more
computer and more memory, okay?
And I think we also I also
give you parole content
explaining what are
parallelisms and how we
can apply this kind
of parallelisms
onto a continued graph, right?
It will result into
different runtime pattern
or communication pattern,
and we are going to dive
deeper into lecture, okay?
Okay, just to recap, for
parallelism, our
problem superficially,
our problem is basically
how to partition
the continued graph on a
given device class, right?
Okay? Superficially, we are
going to simplify this
problem and we're going
to go deeper and deeper, okay?
And there are essentially
in this class,
there are essentially
two types of
parallelism which with
a precise definition,
one is interoperatism, where
we just cut the graph,
not the operator, right?
And the other is intraparism,
where we cut the operator
but not the graph.
Okay. And we stop here
right in NAs lecture.
I think this is one of the most
important slide in NAS lecture.
We run through these
two types of partism
using example from each type,
and we realize that
for this kind of
intraoperative partism,
we will always cause some
sort of communication,
which I call connective
communication. Okay?
And for the second type,
which is the interop partism it
always cause some type of
communication which we
call PTP communication.
Okay. And in this slide,
I basically give you an
example of two devices.
To enhance your understanding,
um, I'm not going to
generalize a little bit.
I'm going to generalize
this from two devices,
two GPUs to four devices,
four GPUs, okay?
To give you a better
understanding what is going on,
especially on communication
part because like I said,
communication is the
most important thing
in poison, okay?
So this is our case, right?
In this two devices scenario,
we run through that graph
following the defined
partitioning,
and we get two partial
sums on each device.
And in order to get a
replica on each devices,
what we do is we run two
device or reduce, right?
So by two device
or reduce, I mean,
the first device sends
its partial sum to
the second device and the
second device do summarization.
And the second device,
send partial sum
to the first device and the
first device does
the same thing,
right? This is all reduce.
And if we run this
on four devices,
that is we partition this graph,
say in four parts,
we cut three times.
Okay. We'll get basically
one fourth on device.
What we all get is
basically like this, right?
Okay. So each each
of the four devices,
we'll get a partial sum,
but this partial sum
is one fourth of the
total sum, right?
And because we still apply
this partism that is in the end,
we want each device to
have a replica, right?
So here, it's exactly
the same, right?
We need to run or reduce
across all four devices.
Okay. And this
reduce is apparently
more expensive than running
or reduce on two devices, right?
Because in order to
run this reduce,
all you need to do is
you allow each device to
send its partial sum to
all other devices, right?
And once the device
receives all the partial
sums, it will do aggregation.
That is why this communication
is called reduce.
It's not reduced.
It's all reduce.
That is every device needs
to communicate and reduce, okay?
And from this example, you can
generalize even more to
more devices, right?
As you grow the lumber devices,
as you grow the lumber
the size of cluster you are
going to use to train the model,
this reduce is going to be
more and more and more
expensive, right?
It's basically square
square complexity, okay?
But in contrast, uh,
in this interperism,
no matter where you cut,
right, you are not going to
cause or reduce or
collective communication.
You can only cause P
to be communication.
That is one device need to
send to the other, right?
Notter how you cut, you can
cut vertically or you
cut horizontally.
But essentially in this
two device scenario,
you just need one device to
send something to
the second device.
And the second device
doesn't know how to send
something to the
first device, right?
Okay. I hope this
basically enhance
your understanding
a little Okay,
and come back to this slide,
I think, previously we
focused on explaining,
um, what kind of
communication pattern,
it will incur, right?
So now, let's focus on
the uh on the device.
So if there's any
device at the time.
Okay? So if you basically
go through that,
the first row one more time,
you'll find that during
the entire lifetime of
doing this competition,
all devices are busy, right?
For example, here, when you
do this MthmoEdS perform
a part of metamo when
you do this memo,
E device perform
another part of memo.
Basically at anytime
these two devices
are busy, they're
doing some work.
And when you do communication,
each device are
communicating, right?
Okay. How about this
one? So in this case,
the first device
will start compute,
right, and it will
produce its memo results.
But during the computation
of the first device,
what is the second device doing?
It's waiting for the results
to be sent from
the first device.
So which means that if
the first device haven't
finished the compute,
then the second device
is idle, rights waiting,
o same thing, right,
when we proceed when the
first device finished
and forward results or send
results to second device,
and then the second device
start computing, right?
But the problem is during
the second device compute,
the first device is idle.
Okay? Now, you'll see
the difference, right?
The second difference
is basically,
in intraoperpism, yes,
you are going to trigger a
very expensive communication,
but you can always keep
every device busy.
At anytime they are busy.
But in interopism, yeah,
you can do better
on communication,
but you got a problem that is
when some devices computed,
the other devices are
idle because they
are waiting for
the results. Okay?
This is basically the
most important meta point
I want to make about
these two types of pisms.
Okay? Which I summarized
in this slide.
Um, so basically
interim interroparism
requires point to
point communication,
but it results in
idle devices, okay?
But for intero partism
devices are always busy,
but you require connective
communication, okay?
And if we put them side by side,
we basically get
this table where,
for interpartism, the
communication is less.
Um, but the device at
a time is more, okay?
And for intra partism
the communication is more
because it's connective.
But the device at is less. Okay.
Eventually, you are
going to basically
combine all this kind
of parism and you want
to basically make
sure you minimize
communication while minimize
device at the time, right?
So basically you're trying
to solve this problem.
Okay. And in the
next few lectures,
I'm going to
gradually, like, uh,
go deeper and
deeper to formulate
this problem into a
mathematical form so you
can understand what we are doing
for all different
kind of models, okay?
But before I do that, okay, let
me summarize this part, okay?
This is very
important. So the way
that way represent the
different types of partism.
I think at the
beginning, I said,
traditionally, people just talk
about data on modo
partism, right?
But in this class, I give you
a new concept that is
interop and into partism.
I want to make a strong argument
because I think, uh, yeah,
data and modoparism are
very classic concepts, but,
Um, but they have some problems
when you talk about
these two words, right?
For data partism, yes,
it's pretty clean, okay?
When I say data partism, you
know what I mean, right?
I basically part in the
data, I raplic wait, right?
But when I say Multi partarisms
a little bit, like, ambiguous,
a little bit vague, because
there are so many types of
multiparism you can do.
You can cut the graph,
you can cut the operator.
And maybe in some sense,
data partism is also a
type of multipism right
if you see the entire data
as a big tenser, right?
So you're basically partion
over the batch dimension, okay?
That's why I bring in this
new definition
interrupt interrupt.
And I think the definition
of inter interop partism
are very computational centric.
In a sense, basically
when I say interrupt,
you know, I'm not operator,
but I'm just cut the graph.
And when I say
interrupt, you know,
I'm cut the operator
but not graph.
So in the rest of lecture,
I'm going to
probably use more of
this part of definition
because I think
it's very precise.
Any problem about this?
Cool. Then let's continue.
Okay. Then under this new view,
we can basically try to
simplify our problem, right.
Previously, the version
of our problem is we need
to partition the graph
over the class around
the right, right?
And now we are basically
trying to figure out
what is the most
efficient way to ask
you to the graph using
a combination of inter
and interoperabism.
You already know
that my interperism
can represent datapism.
So data partism is already
kind of like included
in this sentence, okay?
And of course, you
need to subject
to memory constraints, right.
Memory means that when
you're partition,
you need to fit that
model into a device,
part of model into a device.
And of course, you need to
subject to communication
constraints.
But here, I still
feel this definition
of all this statement of
this problem is still
too complicated,
because I think for
memory constraints,
it makes sense, right.
You basically you cannot
exceed the peak memory.
But for communication,
what do I mean by
subject to communication
constraints, right?
So the last step
into communication,
what do I mean by communication?
But before I dive
into communication,
let's look at the most
important objective here.
So for this problem, the
most important objective
is we want to be
efficient, right?
That is always always the
goal of this entire class.
We want to be efficient. We want
to compute as fast
as possible, right?
So then if we start
considering this kind of
partism that is we run
a computer graph on a
super large cluster,
how do we define efficiency?
I think previously when we run
this kind of thing
on single device,
we already have a
definition of efficiency.
It's basically AI or
arithmetic intensity.
We want each
operator to maximize
his arithmetic intensity. So AI.
But AI is more like a
macro level definition.
For example, when you speak AI,
you probably when
you talk about AI,
you probably mean that
the original intensity of
single operator, right?
Single devices on
single type of course.
Okay. But here we want
a definition that is
more like a global,
more holistic because now we
are running a graph on, say,
thousands of GPUs,
how we measure
the total efficiency of the
thousands of GPUs, right?
And we also care about
the entire graphs efficiency
instead of a single operator.
Okay? So, in order to
introduce this efficiency,
I need to introduce a very
important term, okay?
And this term is basically, uh,
if you go to industry,
so everybody is talking
about this term, okay?
So it's called MF.
MFU. If you read
any language model system
or efficiency or any paper,
they're going to
report MFU because
MFU is basically a way to
show the kind of
the strength of the system
team in your company.
If your system team
is pretty good, uh,
they should give
a pretty good MFU
because the job of the entire
system team in any company,
for example, open air, their job
is basically maximize MFU.
Okay? So what is MFU, okay?
So here I directly give
you the definition.
So MFU equals to the
number of flops.
So here I use a smaller S, okay.
And here I use a capital S,
and I want to distinguish
it a little bit.
So when I do this,
you can see it's
basically that the lumber
flops, a lot of flops.
And the number of flops
here basically means
the total compute
flowing point opera
is needed to finish your
machine learning program.
Okay? So MFU equals
to number of flops
divided by the time T
and T is time spent,
um on finishing
finishing training,
for example, or when interingt
basically finish your job.
And divided by the peak flops.
Here, I use capitals, meaning
that this is a single word.
Okay, these flops
capital S means
the processing capability
of a chip or GPU.
For example, you probably
know that V 100,
the flops capital S is basically
around 150 flops, right?
Um, T flops, sorry, yeah.
There's a Terra Okay, T
flops per second, okay?
So here, from this cavity
you can see MF is basically
a percentage, right?
Okay. So MFU here stands for
model flops UTS addition,
and it is UTS addition.
It basically characterize
how much percentage you
can utilize your peak
capability of your GPUs.
Okay? Because your GPU
once it is manufactured
and you bought a GPU are you
basically have a peak flops
that the GPU can enable,
every generation nearer
GPU have higher peak.
But your program cannot always
use peak flops because you
use different operations and
different operations have
different computation
charistics also,
you can write pretty bad code
and your code could be slowed.
That's why your MFU canot
always reach peak, okay?
Okay. From here, you can see
MF is a udtion which means
that the value is 0-100%.
Okay? And here, the flops
already explained it is
a total compute needed
to compute your model.
Okay? Uh So how
to estimate this?
For example, if your model is
a methemo you already know
how to estimate, right?
It's two M k. I give
you the equation, okay?
But if your model is a lotto,
you'll be add together, right?
It's a total flop needed for
computer model for
iteration, okay?
So this term basically
characterize
how many computer needed
to run the program, okay?
And this is easy to understand.
That is when you write
your program when you
write your software,
and when you deploy this
program and software on GPU,
you run Iteration and
you do a benchmark
and you know how long it takes
this T is basically
how long it takes.
Okay? If you divide
this number by T,
you basically get how good
your program is running,
in terms of flops per second.
For example, you can run
at 100 flops per second.
That is how good you can
achieve on your code.
And then you divide
this number by
the peak flops
offered by the GPU,
that is addition. Okay.
Does that make sense?
Cool. And this term
is so important,
so I spent a lot of
time explaining this.
Okay? So as you can see,
in this class, we try to
build marchearing
systems, right?
And MSU is basically
the verdict of whether
your marche learning
system is good.
Right? If your machine
learning system is pretty bad,
your MFU is going
to be low, right?
Which means that given
the same program,
you are going to run
longer than others, right?
And if your MF is high,
that means you are doing pretty
good job on augmentation.
You are basically squeeze
the last bit of
performance on the CPU.
Okay. Any question
about this term?
Cool. So how we
get these Pi flops,
it's very easy, right?
You just go check
ND products back and ND
will give you the number.
For example, this is
the t hundred products
back here, okay?
And if you are like I said,
when you train language model,
you basically run on
LP 16, 1004, right?
So you basically check
this line, right?
And you can see the P
161004 have this
kind of peak flops.
Okay? Which means
that you need to
substitute this value into here.
Okay. Cool. Yeah.
Doesn't always rect
real performance.
When you're comparing
compare other
number stores, Yeah, exactly.
You compare it to another
system, for example.
Yeah, I will tell you
where we are now.
I mean, for example, how
open eye is doing today.
Okay. But like I said,
media only gives
you the peak flops.
The Pk flops is nowhere
you can achieve.
Because it has a very
strong requirement.
For example, for element
wise operations,
you are not going to
achieve the P flops,
because it's not you
not be able to use element
wise to utilize
all their course.
And basically, in order to
achieve that peak flops, uh,
there's one way that is
you do a very big Mtmo.
And media can basically have
the code or elaborate
to achieve P flops.
But only subject that
only applies to met.
But when I talk about
this program, right,
this program flops,
as you can imagine,
in transformers, you
only have a few metamo.
And between metamo you have
many layer normalization
and a few softmax,
and these kind of operations are
less efficient than Mtmo.
So when you consider
the entire machine learning
program as a whole,
you are not able to
achieve the peak flops.
Okay. Any question about this?
Cool. Yeah, then,
given this equation,
I assume you understand
this equation.
Let's discuss a little
bit more, right?
What are basically in a
TP Commercial program,
what are the potential
factors that can lower MF?
Because the maximum
possible value
of MF is basically 100%, right?
But I told you we are not
going to get there, okay?
So what are the
potential factors
that basically prevent us
from achieving 100% MF?
Okay. So the first one is,
of course, operator types.
Like I said, for met
Mo, you have a chance.
If you only run met Moe you have
a chance to get
peak performance.
But in machining programs,
you have many element
wise, for example,
alo gelo, arm edition,
which are not matm.
So why this kind of element
wise cannot get peak flops?
You basically go back to
that arithmetic intensity.
You need to read all the data
in order to compute
one operator.
But for metam, you just need
to read two matrix and you
can perform a lot of flops.
So your AI is much higher on
Metamor compared to
other operators, okay?
So this means that there
are some good models.
There are some bad
models, right?
Because if a model
always has element wise,
but not metamos bad model.
Right from the perspective
of GPU addition.
Okay? But if a model has
a perfect balance of
metamO and something else,
then you can strike
a balance between,
utilize your GPU
pretty good, right,
and increase
the marchine learning models
basically power, right?
Because you cannot
always do matm for
your model because it will
only bear linear operations.
Linear operation has
very limited kind
of marchinary modeling
power, right?
So a perfect model
should basically
strike a balance
between its own power.
For example, you need to
mix linear operations and
nonlinear operations to express
a sophisticated
enough functions.
And you need to basically
have a way to utilize
GPU pretty well.
Okay? So here I want
to echo a little bit
in my first lecture.
I also echo what our guest
speaker said, right?
So eventually in the current
in contemporary
machinery development,
you when you design model,
you have to think
about this. Okay?
You cannot design model that
you think are pretty good.
A lot of representative power,
like model arbitrary function,
but it's not GPU friendly.
Okay, you have to
think about this.
Okay, you need to
maximize your MF well,
design your model, okay?
That's why transformer
wins, right?
Okay. Cool.
Uh, I already told you,
what are the MF friendly
O and M unfriendly op.
So basically MTM is
very MF friendly, um,
and element we are
not very friendly.
Cool. Okay, of course,
what kind of affect your MMF?
That is the system ogmentation
you applied to your
machining program, right?
If you do telling, if you do
all these kind of like
graph ogmentation,
you do fusion, you do
lower precision, uh,
computation, right?
And you can definitely, uh,
reduce the time you
spend on reading data,
but increase the
time you spend on,
um, on computing, right?
And you can always keep your
GPU busier than before.
So if you know how to
optimize your program,
how to optimize your graph,
how to optimize your operators,
you are going to
increase your MMF. Okay?
So what I ask you to do in
the second homework
is basically,
I hope you can increase
your MF, okay?
And the third factor
primary factor
that affect MMF is basically,
of course, precision, right?
Because for GPO, it has
a different peak flops
at different precision.
Which means that this
number is different if you
use different um precision.
Okay? And of course, the
type of course, right?
I show your products
back of H 100.
So they have
different peak flops
for ten circle and
long ten circle, okay?
GPOtype H 100 is
definitely more powerful
than E 100. Yeah.
So this number is
going to change
once this number
changes, you know,
your MF is going to change,
okay? Anything else?
Basically, it goes back to
our main content of this
lecture, communication, right?
So when you start doing
part addition, you
introduce communication.
And once you communicate,
that means you're going to
spend time on something else,
but not on TPU, holistically,
you are basically lowering M
because this is
going to increase.
Communication takes
time. What are
the possible ways that we
can reduce communication?
There are a few
ways, right. One is,
you choose the paradim
in a way that minimize
communication.
You don't do connective.
You do less connective
compared to PDP.
Second is, you try to put
those expensive communication
on high bandwis interconnect.
Right. And we are
covered next, okay?
And of course, you can also
do some scheduling to make
sure your communication is
overlapped with compute.
That way, you can basically
diminish the time
of communication,
right? And we'll increase MF.
Okay. So that basically give
you a high level picture.
So when we start considering
paralyzation, uh,
our problem becomes a
little bit more complicated
because there's one more
factor here, communication.
Okay. Okay, so to synchronize
a little bit, um,
I think in all previous lecture,
we explain how to make sure
the three items are being
taken care of, right?
And so basically in the
rest of the lecture,
I'm going to start
discussing communication
because that's
a new factor we introduced
once we do part addition.
Okay. But before that,
I still want to spend a
little bit more time on MFU.
So now, suppose you
start working okay and
your boss is going
to ask you to ask me
MF of your marchining
program. What do you do?
What's the procedure? Because I
think this will happen
someday in the
future, yeah for you.
B MF is such an important way to
measure how good you are
using the RTP right.
For example, if you
ask your boss to buy
Mul TPUs, you need
justification.
And your boss will ask you,
Okay, how good you
are using RTPU?
If it's the only 20% of MF,
no, I'm going to reject you.
But if you're already at 50%,
I'm going to buy more
GPU for you, right?
Okay. So how to ask me MF?
So there are a few steps, okay,
I'm going to go through, and I'm
also going to put
this in homework.
Okay. You have to do this,
and you need to write
the programming especially
for language models. Okay.
So the first step, of course,
you look at your machine
learning program,
and you count how many ops here.
And you also try to figure
out the shape or your data.
And so with this data
shapes with the type of
operators and so basically
all the operators
that in that graph,
you are able to estimate,
uh the total flops needed to
run one iteration of
forward and backward.
Because you know the computes
essentially a lot of
math mol linear, right?
So you basically count
how many addition
and basically floating
point arithmetics
you need for running
the tar graph.
So you all get the first
term, which is flops.
Okay? And then suppose you
already have your system,
for example, your
homework one, right?
You wrote at difference
in library, right?
You can run the transformer for
one iteration,
forward and backward.
And you run on your
target type of GPU
and you basically try
to benchmark how long
it takes, right?
And that give you since
that how long it
takes for running
while it using your
system, for this program.
You get a second term T. Okay?
And third, of course, you
go to Media's website,
you check their product spec.
You check, for example,
if you are running
on T four in homework two,
or if you are running
on H hundred in future,
you check their P flops and
you make sure that you
indeed use the core.
For example, a P 16 core or
they mentioned in the spec.
You basically get a third term
which is the P flops, right?
And then you are able
to calculate MF.
You'll know how many percentage
you utilize for the GPU.
Okay. So I'm going to
put this into homework.
Okay, I'm going to give you ama.
I'm going to give you amas back.
So Lama has many layers
like the table I
showed for GBD ray.
Okay. I basically
defines how many layers,
transformer layers for each
layer, what's the shape?
I'm going to give you
ama, and you tell
me the lamas flops,
how much flops you
needed to train ama.
Okay? And then I'm going
to give you a program,
and you estimate the MMF
for training Llama IT.
Okay? Yeah. Mix I'm
going to simplify.
You only consider
FP 16. Yeah, yeah.
Okay. Yeah, because the majority
of compute takes place
on IP 16 course.
Just a little bit compute
takes place on IP 32 course.
Okay? Okay, so why
this is so important?
Be Because in next week when we
start touching base on
skinning lows and you start
to realize that the way that
people design your networks
especially design
language models is all
basically anchored on
this MF and flop scene.
Okay? And I'm going to
dive deeper later, okay?
Uh, so to repeat,
MF is becoming a metric,
highly indexed in today's
language model industry, okay?
And I'm going to give
you a few real numbers.
So basically four years ago,
our class is mainly
composed of the V 100,
so basically two
generations ahead, okay?
Two generation
before, sorry, um,
so the best machine learning
system running on, for example,
1,100 can basically
get 30 to 50% of MMF.
Okay, that is we only
utilize half of the
power of our GPU.
Okay? The best system,
okay, on Viva hundred.
And you can see here the
peak flops for Va hundred
is essentially 112 T
flops, right, Terra flops,
which means that four years ago,
we can only use like
almost 50 to 60 T flops
per GPU on class,
120 language model.
Of course, Mchani
system is developing
and hardware is also getting
more powerful, right?
So fast forward to
Eva hundred, uh,
we basically get 30% of MFU.
Okay? Not very good.
Okay. And once flash
attention is out,
we can get to 60%.
So now you know why flax
is so important, right?
It basically means that you
just save billions
of dollars. Yeah.
Okay. Uh, so once how fly ation,
we can basically
boost from 30% to 6%.
Okay? And 60% is
already pretty good.
Like I said, the only
way you can achieve
100% is that you only
run matm, nothing else.
But here you already get
60%, which is pretty good.
Okay. And to give
you a reference,
the peak flops of P 30 P 16,
tircle of A 100
is basically 312,
which means that we
can already run at
almost 160 flops
per E 100, okay?
And recently, we are all moving
our cluster from E
100 to H 100, right?
So so we are
becoming a little
bit worse because
HI hundred peak flop
is much higher.
Okay, and our software
is not catching up,
so we can only run
between 30% to 50%.
Okay. So basically, if
you work for a company
and your company system is
running within its range,
you are not going to be fired.
Okay. But if it's below
30, you have a problem.
Okay? And why is that is
depending on model size?
Apparently, running
larger metamol
will be more efficient
than running
small metamR Running
larger metamol
will give you a higher MF.
So if you train a
really big model,
you're going to hit 50% one.
But if you to a smaller model,
you hit you're going
to get 30%, okay?
And for your reference,
at hundred has 992 flops,
which means that we can
utilize we can operate at
almost 300 flops per
GPU for t hundred.
Yeah. About what is
dividing factor. Yeah.
In the previous what are
the things that detector?
What is the major factor?
Why is model architecture?
If you do transformer,
you're not going to hit 100.
Unless you can invent a
model that is only matma,
but that model
will be super weak
because it only
have linear openon.
The other is communication
because you are going to run
this on thousands or 10,000
GPs and those
communication takes time.
I slows down things. Okay.
Apparently, this year,
media promised to shape B 100,
uh, I would like to
take a guess. Okay.
And in Homework three, I'm
going to ask you to
write the essay.
Okay. It's open problem.
I'm going to give you
a few open problems.
For example, one open
problem you make a guess of
what MF will be on B
100 clacers and you need
to provide evidence.
You need to argue, justify it.
Okay. Cool. Okay,
not finished yet.
I still need to in
something relative to MF.
Okay? So besides MF,
we have another
concept called HF.
Okay, HFU here, MU
is the same, right,
flops utilization, but
H stands for hardware.
So to distinguish it we care
about MF, we care about HF.
So SUFU is actually more easy
to understand definition.
It's basically precisely
characterized from
hardware level,
how many ti you have.
For example, this
hardware have say,
1,000 flops and your program,
uh, like on the hardware level,
utilizes 600 flops per second.
Then your HF is 60%.
Then given HUFU why
there is a MFU?o?
The problem is, if you still
remember emergeny programs,
but in the memory
part, right, we have
some tricks that we can
treat a computer for memory.
Still remember the
checkpointing thing, right?
So we can checkpoint a few
at the trasfmer boundary,
and during the backward,
we can recompute, right?
The problem actually MFU of
that kind of optimization
is you actually spend
extra flops in order
to save some memory.
And this extra flops is
not actually contributing
to the progress of
the model training.
Does that make sense?
Okay. Which means that you
need to spend extra flops or
something else and something
else is meaningless.
Which means that
your TPU is actually
operated at a very
high tition level.
But because you spend that
amount of extra flops,
your MF is actually pretty
low. You got my point, right?
Which means that you're
still wasting money because
eventually your OKR is training
the model to converge.
It's not like saving
memory, right?
Okay. So that's why
there is HF, okay?
And already explained
in what case,
HFU does not equal to MF,
that is you spend some
flops for other work,
and that work is not
contributing to your
model convergence.
Okay? So like I said,
in Silicon Valley,
people only index on MF.
So if your boss asks
what's retention,
you cannot report
HF because HF is
sometimes is not
equal to MF, okay?
Um, I can ask one more question.
So if we use those kind of
checkpoint in strategy, right,
we checkpoint at the
transumer boundary,
then what is the mathematical
relation between HU and MF?
Anyone want to answer?
Okay. Let me explain.
So it's very easy to
understand, right?
So without checkpointing,
you basically perform
one forward and went
backward, right?
And with checkpointing, I
think I explained
in the lecture,
you perform two forward
and went backward.
Then you are basically
comparing two things, right.
One is you perform one forward
and one backward, right?
And the other you perform two
forward and one backward.
So what are the relation?
So essentially, in
most near training,
we can think that one backward
equals to two forward.
Can anyone explain why?
If you are going to take
grads against the
parameters and activations,
basically for most math,
you basically do twice
during backward,
compared to forward.
Okay? So if we substitute
this into the equation,
without checkpoint,
when we treat
one interregional neurork we
get three forward, right?
But if we're unable
to check pointing,
we are actually every time
we finish one inter or training,
we are spinning
four times forward.
Okay? That is basically the
relation between MF and SF.
So um, like when you're
unable to check pointing,
you can observe a pretty high F,
but indeed, your MF is only
like three fourths. Okay?
Cool. Any problem on this
one? Cool, cool, cool.
Yeah, that basically finish
my definition of this very,
very important concept, and,
um, yeah, let's continue.
With that, with the
introduction of MF,
our goal can be simplified,
basically we want to maximize MF
subject to memory constraints.
Why? Because communication
is slowing down MF, right?
So we want to minimize
our communication,
which is equivalent
to maximize MF.
So our eventual goal in
part addition is basically,
we want to maximize MF,
and this is our only goal. Okay.
Um, yeah, that basically,
I think define a problem,
okay, of p addition.
And next, I'm going to dive
deeper into communication, okay?
Uh, I think in the
previous side,
I said, in machine learning,
we basically have two
types of communication
connective and P to P. Okay.
Let's basically study
them a little bit in
case you don't know
that before, okay?
So what is PTP?
I think this one
everybody knows, okay?
So this is PTP, right.
You have two devices
and you want
the first device to send
something to second device.
And in a PTB communication, um,
you basically have a sender and
a receiver and the
sender tries to
initiate basically the
communication happens by
you first initiate
some connection
between these two
devices, right?
And then you ask
the sender to send
the content to receiver,
okay? That's simple.
Yeah, very simple. I
think whenever you take
any course on networking, I
think you learn this, right.
Okay. But I think
the part that really concerns
us is basically
connective communication.
What is connective
communication?
How many of you have
taken courses in HPC,
high performance
computing? No. Okay.
Then let's spend
some time, okay?
Um, so basically connective
communication is a very very,
I would say central concept in
HPC, high performance computing.
So basically, 40 years ago,
people when people are not
doing machine learning,
they are basically doing HPC.
And they try to
build this kind of
like super computing center
to estimate the universe,
to estimate some
physical laws, yeah.
And they try to do a lot with
this kind of stuff
they be computing.
And this connective
communication is
basically invented back then,
okay? So what are the?
I think I give one example that
is this example,
you already know.
This is all reduced
between two devices.
And what happens
behind the scenes, uh,
you basically need this to send
this and this to send this and
then every device do the
reduction in order to get here.
Okay. Um if you
ever played with pipeword and
they have this interface,
DDP distribute data
per behind the scenes.
Basically inside of this GDP
they are doing this reduce,
which I will explain next.
But mathematically,
what already is doing?
That is, you are given four
devices in this example,
and each device is going to give
a name, which we call rank.
Here I hold four devices from
rank zero to rank three and
their initial state is each
have a different copy of array.
Uh, different values of array.
In this example is in zero
in one in two in three,
and they want to communicate.
They want to
communicate in a way
that they will end up with
all the ranks have basically
the same copy of the output
array, which is out.
And here, they require the
out to be the sum of
all these in arrays.
Okay. That is
basically all reduced.
Okay. And basically,
you need to perform
a communicating pattern to
basically move the contents
between these ranks.
So the values of
the risk change from here to
here. That is all reduce.
Okay? I think you can also
infer the meaning from
the lanes all reduced,
so I need to perform
or reduce and
this reduce need to be
performed across all ranks.
Is is why it's
called reduce. Okay.
Any question regarding this one?
Cool. We have more.
It's not only all use,
and we have broadcast.
We have reduce, and I think
reduce understands not all
use, it's just one reduce.
We have scatter gather,
reduced scatter and use, you
need to memorize all this.
Sorry. Yeah. Be area of
this operation is
going to be used
somewhere in emergency systems.
Let's go through this
one by one, okay.
Broadcast, very easy
to understand, right?
So some rank have array,
and that rank is to
broadcast that array
across all other ranks.
That is the broadcast.
So from this slide, you
already get it, right.
So in this slide, the rank
this rank zero is rank one.
I will use the index
starting from zero.
Rank one has the array the
target state is rank one,
broadcast the array
across all other ranks.
Okay? And this is before and
this upper. Good, right.
Broadcast very easy
to understand.
Reduce and reduced one is
not red just reduced one.
This is also where array
all the ranks has array,
and the west is we want
to reduce the arrays into
one rank rank that target rank
has a reduction of the arrays.
Here I generate a little bit.
In most cases, it's
basically submission,
but sometimes you
want to do some
other reduction
operations for example,
you want to time the value
altogether or you want
to do something else.
That's why people
call it reduce.
Basically, you want
to reduce them.
Any question about this one?
Cool. Next one. So basically,
you can see, broadcast and
reduced over like a reverse.
If you don't do reduce, is
basically broadcast
and reduce reverse.
Yeah. In broadcast, you send
from one rank to all other
ranks and in reduce,
you send from all
ranks to one rank.
Cool.
Next one, scatter. Scatter I
think you can once I shoot
the picture you
immediately get it, right?
So one rank has array,
and the target state is that
I want to scatter the array
across all other
ranks and make sure
each rank has one
divided by N here,
N is equal to the number ranks.
Okay. That is scatter.
Yeah. It's like a
through that array,
all the way to every rank.
Yeah, scatter. Yeah. Okay.
And gather is essentially
the reverse operation
of scatter.
That is each rank has
a part of the array,
one divided by part of the
array portion of the array.
And I want to basically
gather all together
into a target rank.
So the eventual target rank has
the whole array,
okay? It's gather.
And you man get it, right?
So basically scatter
and gather the reverse.
Okay. A question?
Okay, these are simple ones.
Let's go into some
more complicated ones.
And apparently, uh,
those connective operations with
is definitely more complicated
than without, right?
So the next one is
basically all gather.
Okay? All gather is basically
like I want to gather,
but I want all ranks together.
Okay? That's easy way
to understand, right?
So I gather I have
a turkey rank,
and the turkey rank is going
to gather all the values,
from the original ranks.
But all gather essentially
I need all the ranks
together. Okay.
So basically the initial
state is every rank
has one divided by N
part of the array,
but the initial state is all
ranks have the whole array.
Okay, this is all
gather. Any question?
The next one, reduce scatter.
And you already get it's
basically like I first
reduce and then I scatter.
So basically, initially,
each rank basically has
the who rate, right?
And my goal is I first
reduce all the values.
I get the submisson for
example, for ranks.
And then I want to make sure
each rank eventually has
one divided by part of
the submission. That
is reduced scatter.
Essentially, I first
reduce and then scatter.
Okay. Okay.
And you can imagine,
basically, gather
and reduced scatter,
they are kind of reverse, right?
All gather is that I gather
all things together.
And reduced scatter is I
first reduce and scatter.
Yeah. Cool. Yeah. F.
Yeah, you can do that.
Yeah, I'm going to
cover that. Yeah.
But your master is not
efficient. Yeah, yeah.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
So I PA two, I ask you to
introduce two connectives.
One is all reduce,
the other is all.
Okay. You're going to figure
out how to implement that.
And if you are
able to match NPI,
you are going to get a
pretty good bounce point.
Okay? Cool.
And this reduced gutter
Aguer and reduced gutter,
they are reverse.
Eventually, you have
this all reduced
This is the one that I
mentioned most, okay?
Every array has one
Everyb has one array,
and you want to reduce
them and then make
sure event eventual state,
you want to make sure everyb has
the sum, has a reduction.
Okay. Any question
regarding the connectives?
No. Let's continue. Okay. So to
give you a little
bit more background.
Like I said, the
connective operations,
they originated from HPC,
high performance computing.
But you can see today
machinary is like HPC.
Yeah, it's basically
very similar to HPC.
Okay. The first fact
is connective is much more
expensive than PTP, you
can imagine, right?
I'm always asking all my
ranks to communicate.
And in PTP I only need
two ranks to communicate.
Okay. And of course,
I already give you a solution.
So in homework one, sorry,
I question one of homework two,
you can actually implement
your connective, just use PDP.
You can assign modem.
Like you said,
basically like this
rank to send each,
you figure out what's
the right way to send and
you want to get there.
Okay, 40% 40 points guaranteed.
Okay, very easy, right? But
that's going to be very slow.
Yeah, of course. Yeah. Okay.
Connected is highly optimized
in the past 20 years.
If you look out for any library
that is ending with CCL,
CCL stands for connective
Communication Library.
X basically is the branding
of that company
making this library.
For example, when
X is equal to N,
it is DR CCL you got it.
W X equal to M, you
don't know what is.
Okay, I also don't know.
When Xc one is
basically Intel, okay?
This is Intel CCR.
Uh, actually stands
for Microsoft. Yeah.
Microsoft has CCO as well.
So basically, in
the past 40 years,
every company is
developing a CCO.
Yeah. I think Google
also has a CCO,
but I don't know what's the
name. It's internal, okay?
Um, and you asked me
why Odia stock price
is so good, right?
One partial reason is because
NCCO is one of the best.
Okay? So Odia did pretty well
on optimizing its connective
communicing libraries. Yeah.
And there so basically NCR
library is one of the best.
So every company is doing
that, o for MIDI Ds.
But connective communication has
a pretty bad property that
is not fault tolerant.
That is every time
when you initiate
communication
across all devices,
if one device failed,
that communication
is going to fail.
It's not fault tolerant.
That's why today,
if you join a company
doing big model training,
your job mostly is spending
time on babysiting or GPUs.
You need to make sure there's
no GPU, throwing out arrows.
Otherwise, your entire job
is going to be stopped.
Okay. Cool. Any question? Okay.
We basically get
a picture of what
is going on in connective
communication.
Then I'm going to
introduce a few algorithms
to basically make
this communication
operates pretty fast.
But before I introduce
the algorithms,
I want to first establish
a little bit of
mathematical foundation.
So how you can understand
what is going on?
Like how slow or how fast
communication should be.
Okay? So in communication,
we basically use
this alphabet model.
Okay. This model is
just called alphabet.
The reason is because it
has two parameters and bet.
Okay? So basically
in networking,
when we characterize the
speed of communication,
we basically use this alphabet
model and the speed is
basically characterized as
Apha plus ten times better.
Okay? So here, Alpha is
basically the latency.
That is, if I want to launch
a communication
between any two ranks,
I'm suffering a latency.
It's like to a kernel to GPU,
I suffer a latency, and
the latency is constant.
As long as I need
to communicate,
I need to initiate the sockets,
I need to do this kind
of heavy lifting work,
and that takes time.
Okay? That's Alpha.
And this part
is basically very easy
to understand, right?
So this beta is basically
one divided by B
and B is bandwidth.
Bandwidth. That is
the communicating
bandwidth between
these two ranks.
And this bandwidth
was determined by
what? By hardware, right?
So you can spend more money
to buy more bandwidth.
That will make this
one bigger, right?
Uh, the second part
is essentially like,
this is a message size.
That is how much you want
to send between the ranks.
And apparently, you
divide by bandwidth,
you get the time spent
on, basically sending,
um this message, right?
That's how that
basically intuitively
explain this alphabet
model, okay?
So to summarize, when you
start a communication,
you first suffer bandwidth,
suffer a latency,
constant latency,
and then the rest of
time is determined by
how much the message size you
want to send and the
bandwidths you have, okay?
With this model,
you can basically,
uh, uh, try to analyze
it a little bit, right?
So if you are going to
send a very small message,
a very small message,
just one byte.
So in this equation,
this Rhi is going to
dominate Rp dominate.
But if you are going to
send a large message as,
then see an approach infinity,
then this term is
going to dominate.
And this latency
is a smart term.
Okay. The reason I emphasize
this is because, um,
when you send a
small message size,
uh, you want to minimize
this phone, right?
And then when you
send a large message,
you want to make sure you
utilize all the bandwidth.
Okay.
And given this observation,
in the HPC community,
they basically spent a lot of
time optimizing the connectives,
and they develop two types of
implementations
and algorithms to
make connective
communication fast.
And one type of algorithm
basically emphasize latency,
that is they assume that you
are going to send
small messages,
and they want to make
sure they minimize this
pa. And the other
type, they want to,
uh basically maximize the
utilization of bandwidth,
and they assume that you are
going to send big messages.
Okay, I'm going to
introduce both,
and you can choose to implement
either one in your homework.
But let me ask a question.
Immersion learning,
which one is preferred?
Immersion learning, do
you think which one is
likely to dominate? Sorry.
Emotionally, you are
sending big tensors
across DPs and apparently
emersionaly, you
prefer this one.
You prefer to minimize this one.
But I will still take
time to introduce both.
So a little bit more background.
So the first type of algorithm
that try to minimize distance
is called minimum
spanning tree algorithm.
The second type of
algorithm that try to
emphasize bandwidth is
called ring algorithm.
That's why sometimes when people
speak or reduce the always
called ring or reduce.
Yeah. In the past 20 years,
this HPC community,
they have graduated
many many PE students and they
wrote so many papers on opens.
In 2023, I think
the Turing award
was given to HPC
professor, okay?
Cool. So let's come to
the first type, okay?
In the first time, we want
to minimize the latency.
Okay? In order to
minimize the latency,
the Apha, what's
the high intuition?
Le want to minimize
the number of wrongs
needed for communication,
Because every time when you
launch your communication,
you are going to suffer ARpa.
So you want to minimize
the number of pans.
Okay? In this minimum
span entry algorithm,
the idea is like this.
So the message
starts on one rank.
One processor.
And then we try to divide
all the ranks into half.
That's why it's called a
minimum spanning tree.
We try to basically
divide all the ranks
into first half and second half.
And what we do is basically we
send the message from the
first half to the second half.
In this example,
I send a message
to the half of a network that
does not contain this message.
Right? So here, I divide
the ranks into this
group and this group.
I found that my initial rank
is basically in this group.
And in the second group,
there's no such message.
My first step is I'm trying
to send this to here.
Okay? And once I finish
this step, what I do?
I basically use
binary tree message.
What I do is once the
ranks have this message,
I know this group
and this group,
they all have a rank
which contains a message,
and I'm going to do
that recursively.
Okay? I'm going to
It's like this, okay?
And then I'm going
to divide it again.
I'm going to divide here,
right, and I'm going
to divide here.
Okay? I'm going to let this
descend to this and
this to send this.
And I do it recursively.
And I can prove that this will
minimize R because this is
a minimum span entry
and the number
once I needed is
guaranteed is minimized.
Okay.
To give you more
realistic example,
let's run this minimum
spanning tree for Broadcast.
Okay. Still remember
broadcast, right?
This is before, this is after.
So how do we do that? So we
start from the initial state.
We try to divide all the ranks.
Okay?
And we divide all
ranks into two groups.
Without the rank
that has the value
to send its value to another
rank at the second group.
And we continue divided
ranks in each group.
And we sin, right?
And we continue to basically
broadcast these values
like this, okay?
And you can say
after four steps,
I basically have eight ranks
having a message, right?
And I found out there's
one rank that is still
missing message,
so I perform one more step.
Okay? And I can prove
that the steps needed to
initiate the communication
is minimized
using this spanning tree.
Okay? That's why this
algorithm is basically
used for minimize
Alpha term, okay?
Any question? Cool. Okay.
Um, now let's try to explore.
By the way, you can
ignore these equations.
Okay. I'm not going
to cover this,
and it's not covered in exam.
Okay. But the reason
I have this slide is
because I want to
explore some connections between
different connective operations.
Gather gather still remember
the initial end state, right?
So in is each rank
has protein and
ditch the entire global array.
So one way that we
can realize or gather
is we can we can
first gather, right?
We can first perform a gather.
So we gather the values
into one target rank.
And then we do a
broadcast, right?
So basically, uh, or gather
equals to gather plus broadcast.
Cool. Reduce scatter, uh,
you already know from the name.
So you first reduce like this,
and then you do a scatter.
Yeah, you got to reduce scatter.
Or reduce. Can anyone
give me an answer?
How to assemble or reduce?
Yes, you do reduce and
then you do broadcast.
Okay? So basically in
this last scenario,
the way people implement
these three opportunity,
basically, they first implement
those primitive ones
and they assemble it.
Okay.
So in summary, reduced
gutter is reduced by
scatter or reduce is reduced and
broadcast or gather is
usually gather and bracast.
Yeah. Exactly. You
got the point, right?
So that will basically bring
us to the second part,
but I want to answer
your question first.
So this algorithm, it minimizes
the number one to communicate.
But it does not utilize
the bandwidth, right?
Because each node only
send to a target node.
And while this node is
sending all the other
bandwidths are not utilized.
Okay?
Cool. Like I said,
this one is not
preferred Imaginaring,
because it's minimize
the alpha term,
but inverse ing the
second term is larger.
So I'm going to bring all you
into the second part, okay?
But before that, let's
summarize MST, okay?
So for MST, is
extremely useful for
small messages where the first
term is dominating, right?
And it emphasizes
tiency the problem of
minimum span entry
algorithm is that it
prioritize the alpha
term than a better term.
So like that student
pointed out,
when especially
at the initial stage
of the communication,
most of the
interconnects are idle.
You are not actually utilize
the bandwidth here, okay?
And next, I'm going to run
another algorithm which
is ring algorithm,
and this ring algorithm
is essentially
the one that I used
today in macheary, okay?
And the general principle of
this ring algorithm is that we
try to utilize all these links,
and we try to utilize
all these band ways
available between ranks.
Let's assume that
all the ranks are
connected using some
like Iranet or whatever.
Okay? And here,
how many rounds of
communication does not matter.
Because like I said, the Alpha
does not matter anymore.
The main overhead is
the second term better.
So, one algorithm that
enable this basically
we try to form
a logical ring across all ranks
and we send messages
along this ring. Okay?
Let's see, how we do that.
So here, this is
the initial state where
we want to perform,
for example, um,
like gather gather,
something like that. Okay?
So we can basically
construct a logical
ring like this, right?
So here you can see,
this rank has this part.
This rank has this part.
This un has this part.
So what do we do is
we want to utilize
the bandari as much as possible.
So at anytime we
want to make sure
all the ranks are sending
or receiving, okay?
So what do we do we
construct this ring.
And in the next step, we need
each rank to send this
protein to the next rank.
Right? And by doing this,
I can make sure that
all ranks are busy,
at least on networking pair.
Okay? So if we do this,
what happen is
basically we perform
one round of
exchanging messages,
right, and we get here.
Okay? You can compare
the difference between
these two states, right.
The key difference
here is all devices
are busy on communicating.
That's why we can
utilize bandwiys, okay?
And what you do next is
basically you continue to
propagate these messages, right?
And you can construct
another ring and you
continue doing this.
And after you doing
many, many rounds,
you eventually get to a state
where so basically, I'm
going to shoot next.
Okay?
I'm going to shoot next,
and I'm going to run
this kind of algorithm
on a few connectives.
Yeah. So gather, let's
run a ring or gather.
Okay? So we start from
the left hand side and we try
to reach the right
hand side, right?
So this are initial
state, right,
we construct a ring, and
we each rank to send this
protein to the next rank.
Uh, This is the one round
of communication,
right we get here.
Then we run another round, okay?
We'll get to here, right?
Another round here, another
round here, ther round.
Okay, we're good, right?
So you got me right. Cool.
And you can see, this is a
pretty good visualization,
but the problem here
is at each step,
you are utilizing bandwidth,
but you are taking
many many runs,
compared to the
minimum spanning tree?
Because minimum spanning tree,
you are doing a binary
tree, which is super fast.
But in this algorithm,
you basically need to
run the number of times equal
to the number of ranks,
which is more runs.
So the Alpha term we are going
to increase a little bit,
but it doesn't matter
because like I said,
the second term dominates, okay?
Let's run another
version, reduce scatter.
Still remember reduce
scatter, right?
So we first reduce and scatter.
So what do we do is, this
is our united state, right.
We want to reduce them
and scatter results.
So we construct a ring.
On on this part of this
message, we perform a reduce.
And we continue doing
so we send the results.
We propagated to reduce
the results, okay?
Once we propagate basically
each we will have
a partial sum and we continue
to reduce and propagate,
reduce, propagate,
reduce propagate.
Okay. We'll get results.
Yeah. Cool. This is basically
a ring algorithm. Okay.
Then under this ring algorithm,
let's also do some connection
between different connectives.
Okay.
So basically for this broadcast,
we can basically
use this algorithm
to as assemble from primitives,
basically broadcast equals to,
uh we first scatter,
and then we gather.
So broadcast is equal to
scattering or gather, okay?
And for this reduced one,
what we do is basically we
first do a reduced scatter,
and then we gather,
reduce scatter and gather.
We basically um, get this one.
For reduce, we also have
a different types
of combination.
In order to implement or
reduce using this
ring algorithm,
what we do is basically
we first reduce scatter,
reduce the redundant scatter,
and then we do gather.
Okay.
So to summarize a little bit,
uh, in this ring, algorithm,
reduce equals to reduce Getter
plus gather and
all reduced equals
reduce Getter plus or gather
and broadcast equals to
Scatter and all gather.
An An question? Okay, if
you feel a little
bit confused here,
look, just, you know,
review my slides.
I think it's pretty clear here.
The reason I try to draw
this connection is because,
uh, you know,
next week when we start
introducing machinery partism,
you all understand you all
realize that basically
we are basically
decomposing all
these all reduced
and broadcast and reduced
into different primitives,
and we'll try to
schedule them in
different places of execution.
Okay. And that will
result into different
memory utilization,
different memory
requirement, and
also different
computer patterns.
Cool.
Um, I think we're
pretty close to finish this
slide, finish this lecture.
So let's come back.
Okay, let's basically
ground this in
the context of
Machining Pism, okay.
So like I said, interop
always results in
PTV communication,
and this is quite obvious.
Now, you probably start asking
why interop always result in
connective communication.
Okay? And this is a pretty
important topic for next week,
but I want to
finish this lecture
by giving you some
connection between,
uh, basically, um, marching
Pism and the connectives,
I spend almost half an
hour introducing, okay?
So the reason that intraop
always result into
different sorts
of connective
communication is because,
um, um, at least under
this repenton mechanism,
like I introduced basically
coloring nodes and operators.
You realize that when we
do this intraop partism,
we are essentially partition
the operators and its output.
Whenever a
communication happens,
it happens because we
need to repartition it.
Okay. Remember, in the
tensor parallel case,
that is the one
that I run through.
So when the
communication patterns,
uh when or happens,
it's basically each rank
basically get a partial sum,
but you want each rank to
have a replica, right.
Which means that
you need to swap
the array content in a way
that to meet the
repartitioning requirement.
Okay. And in the next lecture,
I'm going to show that uh
basically in all types of
existing pysms that we use to
train language models or
train whatever models today.
Okay. Uh, the
communicating happens
only when that between
two operators,
two adjacent operators,
their partitioning
scheme are different.
Okay? In order to meet
the partiing scheme
of the next operator,
you have to repar in array.
Okay? So here, I give you
an example in two decase
but in reality,
this is a 40 case.
F doming transformer, you have
a 40 array B times times H
times something else, right?
And let's simplfy a
little bit, okay.
In two cases, we have three
types of partitioning, right?
The first type is replicated.
That I device have a replica.
Okay? The second
is row partition.
So horizontal cut.
Okay? And the third type
is column partition.
Like I said, the communication
happens when you need
to switch between these
three states, right?
Sometimes one operator
need a replica,
sometimes one operator
need a row party,
sometimes one opportun
a column partition.
Then I start to ask
a question, okay?
So if I want to switch
from row party to
replicate what I do.
So if I want to draw a edge
from here to here what I do.
It's basically for
gather, right?
So you want each device to
gather it protein, right?
And then you will
get a replica. Okay.
And the next one is if I want to
switch from replica
to row Pisin,
that is, I want to do
a reverse what I do.
A scatter, really? Think
twice. I do nothing.
I just throw it away, right?
I don't need to communicate.
Why? Because I want
to switch between from this
state to this state, right?
So now, each already
have a replica
and my eventual state
I want each state to
only have a half.
I just throw the other half.
I don't need to
communicate. Okay?
I do nothing. Okay? Slice.
Yeah, I do slice. Okay?