Okay. Thanks for coming.
Yeah, let's resume.
Logistic update.
Next lecture, Thursday, we'll
have our guest speaker,
you don't have to be here,
just go attend on Zoom,
our speaker was, in my opinion,
the only guy that is truly
doing open language models.
Because you know, there's
a strong debate in the
language model community.
What do you define by open?
What do you mean
by open? Like if
you release language
model weights,
you can call it open Ws,
but you cannot call
it open source. Why?
Because people cannot
reproduce with with compute.
You how to release your data,
your infrastructure, uh,
your training recipe, and
your weights so
people can reproduce.
So on Thursday, our speaker
is a guy who basically
release everything, okay?
Weights, data, um,
infrastructure,
code checkpoints,
every checkpoint.
That's why the project
is called RM 360,
because they release
60 checkpoints
for you to reproduce, okay?
And you guys after
listening to his talk,
you can think about
what is so what
is basically RM thing is
going in open source.
So should we embrace
close models
like open eyes or should
we embrace open model?
Yeah, think about that.
Okay. Um, let's come back.
I think, last Thursday,
we talked about connective
communication, right?
And I think we somehow
arrive here, right?
So we connect connective
communication
with our machine
learning parallelisms,
right, especially intra parism.
And we find that in machine
learning parallelism,
we have to do this
kind of recharting
and the cost of recharging
is essentially connective.
And depending on how you do
recharting you switch from role
pating common parting
or you switch
from replicated to row patting,
you are going to have
different sorts of
connective, right?
So here, if you
switch from sorry.
If you switch from
parts to replicate it,
you have to do or gather
right across two devices.
And this is a partial sum.
I think in last week,
I missed this part,
but I added here.
So if you want to switch it from
partial sum to replicated,
you have to do or reduce, right?
Okay. So basically,
we connect connective
communication
with machinery partisms.
Okay. Next, I'm
going to so we are
going to talk about all
sorts of pisms and we
are going to put this in
practice because I think I have
spent enough time to give
you to give you
an understanding of pism
at a very abstract level,
and now I'm going to
put it into practice.
Okay? I'm going to
ground this with
all different papers like people
publish and people
use tree models.
Okay, we are going to
start with data parism.
Why? You're probably
wondering why because,
like I said, data partism is
just a special case of
intra partism, right?
But I still want to spend
some dedicate time on
data pism because,
first, it is one of the
most adopted one, right?
Because no matter what kind
of pism you are going to use,
you always have data parism.
Second, as you know,
big model is just
a recent thing.
Before 2020, I don't think
the models are that big,
the motivation for motoparism
is because we want
to train big models.
Our memory is insufficient.
But you need to
remember in many cases,
we have a small enough model
that we can fit into one TPU.
In that case, we
probably don't pursue
any sort of motparism because
it's too complicated.
We want something as simple,
datapoism is really simple,
it can guarantee to give you
pretty good performance
on scaling up.
Okay, to review a
little bit on history.
So basically 2012-2016, that's
when Diplnary networks become
very, um, popular, right?
And we actually, in this paper,
which is published by
Jeff Dino, from Google.
And they basically build this,
um, um, framework
called disbelief.
That is the first kind of,
um, distributed system for
training neural networks, okay?
And the palism that is adopted
the primary palism
that is adopted in
the system is basically
data pism, okay?
It's very early, like
more than 15 years.
Okay. And since that paper,
I think a lot of people
basically in the
margining community,
Machine learning
plus Pism community,
they are basically just
studying datapoism
because like I said,
the multipoism is not necessary
at that moment, okay?
So people have invented a lot of
techniques to make data
parison better, okay?
And we are going to
talk about that.
And then you probably know
in 2016, Petrog was out, right?
And the first partism
that is added into Petrot
is also data partism
because that has the
most user, okay?
And if you look at
this piece of code,
um, you'll probably notice
this interface which
is super familiar,
DDP distributed data
parlo It is basically
data per data pismimplementation
in, uh, in Petrich.
And, I already told you
in my previous lecture,
this DDP behind the scene
is basically or use.
I performs on use, okay?
Yeah, this interface
is pretty good right.
That is, I think what Piper
team did pretty well.
So what you need to
do is essentially
you just wrap your
model with GDP
and it automatically
becomes data Parod, okay?
And at some point, I think,
we also have a lot of
open source frameworks
that is trying to
optimize the
communication and in
data partism
essentially optimizing,
um, uh, D make allds fast.
I think that's part of
your homework, okay?
And you've probably
already known this right.
This is early interpretation
of data partism
where we have four ranks and
we basically reduce
their results,
reduce their gradients, okay?
Now, if you look at this, it's
pretty simple because I'll give
you a deeper interpretation of
partism which is
intra and inter.
Okay. Um to put this
into context, okay?
So what is data partism?
Like I said, data partism is
essentially a special case of
opt partism let's use
our interpretation to
interpret data partism.
So this is data partism.
I will let you look at this
for maybe 20 seconds, okay?
Okay. Yeah. I think if you
just look at this part,
it's very easy, right?
And we have been going through
this many, many times.
So this is the forward part of
this graph, single layer MLP.
Sorry, two layers MLP.
Okay. And this part
is this data part, how
we explain many times.
What do we do is basically
we do parti in the data.
Right. We parting the
batch di machine.
We replicate it to
with trainable width,
and then we just forward
all the way through
the new network.
So there's no communication
in any of this arrow.
Why? Because there's
no resharing, right?
Every time when we compute
the sharing mechanism agree,
okay, between two devices,
between two operators.
Um, but I add a little
bit more complexity.
That is, I also draw
the Bro graph, okay?
The problem happens
at the back graph.
So if we start developing
the Bro graph,
this part is still good, right?
We still do partition.
That is once we have the loss,
wegate the loss through
the neural network.
So we still like
compute only on that
designated batch device, okay?
But the problem is when we start
aggregating the gradients,
we find that there is a
problem that is this part,
right, and this part.
Okay. So when we
start aggregating
gradits we find that E device
only have a partial
gradient, right?
But what we need is
we need each device
to have a replica gradient so we
can apply the gradients
to the parameters.
So you already know what
happens here, right?
Or reduce Okay?
Yeah. I hope this interpretation
makes this super
easy to understand.
Okay. And after you
apply the gradings,
you basically have a
new copy of weights,
which are replicated
across two devices,
and you basically substite here,
you assign to here,
and you are good.
You start next generation.
Okay. Any questions
about this graph?
Cool, very good. And
we're going to do this a
lot in following
Multi pari section.
Okay? So then you
can actually spot that
the key change here,
compared to without pitism,
the key change of data parism
basically how we
implement this prior,
how we implement this dice,
how we implement a
very efficient way.
Because otherwise, all
the rest is basically
data flow graph execution,
nothing changes, right?
Okay. So how do we
implement this?
Like I said, it's
all reduced, but d
has um many ways
to make it fast.
Okay? So in history,
there are two ways
to implement this.
The first is a
very famous paper.
I would say the first,
like a famous machine paper
is called primary server.
Okay? The second way
essentially all reduced.
Okay? Let's talk about
primary server first. Okay?
So in primary server, um,
but for both implementation,
I think they how to respect
um the key assumption of
data parism that is the
model parameters can't fit
into EDS, you can
do that replica.
Okay, so for primary
server, um, actually,
the primary server
comes much earlier
than like any parallelism.
Why? Because it comes even
earlier than neur networks.
Why? Because primary server was
invented for doing
distributed grading descent.
Okay. But, you know,
before neural network,
we already have grading descent.
We can use grading
descent to optimize
many other kinds
of models, right?
So I want to basically um
change your mindset
a little bit.
Now, let's look at grading
descent instead neuralnetwork.
Okay. Now, this model
can be anything.
And if you look at
grading descent,
right, this is the equation.
I said it's master equation.
And here, compared to the
previous master equation,
what I did is I basically
add add this sum, right.
Okay. So what's the difference?
So in my previous writing,
I don't have the sum, so
I only have one worker.
So here P is a worker index.
Okay, I have capital P workers.
So in my previous so
called mass equation,
I just have one worker to
work on that batch data
and derived gradients.
But now what I do
is I add a sum.
That is, I have multiple
workers to work on
different batiel data to
perform other
gradients in parallel.
And at some point,
I'm going to aggregate
their gradients,
and then I apply the update.
Okay? This is the
primary server.
Uh, the reason is called
primary server
because you can see,
this is a parameter, and
this is a gradients.
So you can basically invent
a distributed system
where you put
the parameters at some server.
You have a lot of workers
to perform this update.
And once they have
the gradients,
those worker is going to send
the gradients to the server.
And the server will aggregate
gradients and then
apply updates,
get a new version of
parameter and send it back.
It's like doing a traditional
distribute system,
right, a server work archicture
call server archiecture.
Okay. Itis is pretty
natural, right,
because if you look
at this equation,
you just want to
build that system.
You think that system
is pretty good, okay?
Um, and there are two key,
um, assumptions about
primary server.
That is, it assumes that
the communication is very
heavy and the compute to
communication ratio is 1210.
So I will explain this later.
Okay but remember this. And
to put this illustration,
so basically, this is
the primary server.
Okay? You can see there's a PS
which is the parameter server,
centralized server, where
you home manual workers.
And each worker basically
take a batch of data
and compute the gradient.
And then once the gradient
is ready here, right,
each worker is going to send
the gradient to server.
Okay, server aggregate
updated parameter and then
send this new parameter
back and then start
next iteration.
Okay? This is pretty easy.
So what's the problem
with this architecture?
Anyone want to answer? Yeah.
I guess there's
one. Yeah, exactly.
So you can see the
primary server becomes
a centralized server
where it needs
to receive all the
kind of parameters,
which means that
you have to have
a very strong server to
receive for many workers.
Is communication
is four times with
other workers, in this
figure four times.
But you can imagine, there
are many many workers.
Then, this primary
server becomes,
bottleneck. It
will be very slow.
Second, this primary server
can be a single point failure.
Like if this primary
server failed,
then we lose our parameters,
lose our gradients, we
need to restart. Okay.
This is apparently not syllable.
But before I present to you,
better architectural
primary serve,
uh, I want to basically
connect this with connective.
So if you look at this one,
uh, you just think
about communication.
So what is the
communication? Like I said,
essentially they are
doing or reduce, right?
But how this
archiecture reduce or
reduce into different
connectives.
So basically in question, we
basically decompose
or reduce into two.
One is reduced to one.
That is, we reduce from workers
to server, and
then we broadcast.
So like I said, in Max lecture,
all reduce equals to
reduce plus broadcast.
Okay. Good, right?
So yeah, and this is the idea.
Okay. I try to connect primary
server with connectives.
But like I said, primary S is
not scalable for a few reasons.
One is the primary server
is a single point failure.
Secondly, the primary S is going
to become communication
bottleneck.
So how we can do better?
So basically, we don't have
to have a centralized server.
We can do a distributed server.
But we can further sharp
the primary server into
different workers and each
worker become a server,
but a share of the server.
Okay? So basically in reality,
what do we do is we do this
kind of primary server.
Many we have many many nodes,
and some nodes are just servers
and some nodes are workers.
And in a more and more
adopted case, more real case,
what do we do is basically we
let each node to be a server and
a worker. Does that make sense?
Okay. That each node is a
server and the worker itself.
It will basically compute
its own copy of ingredients,
but it will also store
the centralized shard of
part of the parameter.
Okay. In that way,
we basically address
that centralized
failure problem, right?
Because now each
node, each worker,
each GPO has a share
of parameters,
and they need to basically
play a role as a server.
They need to connect they
need to reduce gradients
and and then
broadcast gradients.
So all the bondaries all GPOs
and devices will be
utilized, right?
So basically, we kind of, like,
distribute the server's job into
many many different devices
like interconnect networks.
Okay. And if I do this,
think about in extreme case,
if basically the red nodes and
the pink blue nodes and
blue devices and
the pink devices
are basically the same devices.
So each device is basically
a server work itself,
then could you connect
this to the connective?
So we are still doing,
but now we change a
little bit, right?
So basically, it
becomes we first
perform a reduced scatter
across all nodes.
Because now each node
will hold one share
of the parameters.
So each worker will hold
a whole copy of
its own gradient,
which means that we have to let
each worker to send
that shard of um,
gradients to server
which holds that shard.
This is a reduced scatter.
And then after reduced scatter,
we have to get a new copy
of the new parameter,
which is another gather.
Okay? So this interpretation
basically decompose or reduce
from the previous one that
is reduced broadcast into
reduced scatter and orgater.
And you can see this one
is much better because
it elevates the
server bottleneck.
Okay. Any question
about this one?
Each worker is a server,
doesn't that still mean
that one worker fails?
Like partnership, right?
Yeah. Very good question.
Yeah. So each worker
is still a server,
and if that worker failed,
then that shared parameter
is going to be lost, right?
So what do we do is we a each
worker to hold two shards,
a backup. In reality, yeah.
So you can reduce
the probity that
like a shard basically completely
get lost, right? Yeah.
Okay. Does that make sense?
Cool. Um, okay.
And then I'm going to
tell you something
that is even deeper.
Okay. So if you
look at this one,
right, from this
speaker you can see,
no, we have a few workers,
and we have a primary server.
And what do we do is we
need to do a
synchronization operation.
That is every time we
each worker finish the
gradient calculation,
it has to send the gradient to
the server server aggregate
that and send it back.
But in reality, this is not
always the case
because you can have
different workers that probably
some worker will be slower
than other workers.
You have stragglers
in reality, right?
It could be due to power
issue could be due to,
you have different
kinds of GPUs or
just that program runs slower
than another program, right?
So in this case, you can see
this distribute system will
become extremely slow, right,
because you have to synchronize
the gradients from all workers,
and the speed of iteration is
basically determined by the
slowest worker in this group.
Okay. That's a big problem.
This will bring us into another,
I would say, very very
active area of research.
That is people also study
consistency model for
um primary servers.
How many of you know
consistency model dist systems?
No. Basically, that
is a consist model,
basic characterize
when you should
synchronize your copy
gradients in machinearn.
This figure give you an example.
You can see, I have three
devices device A, B, and C,
EC device is a worker,
at some point, they
need to communicate,
like I said, at the
end of competition.
So here, I make a
simplified assumption that
is every worker will
basically never have a fault.
They will never make any error.
The program will run perfect on
every worker and everyone
will run in the same pace.
Okay? So basically
following above equation,
what do we do is every time
each worker will calculate
the copy of gradients, right?
And then they will send
the gradits to the
primary server,
and they will wait, right?
They will wait because
they have to wait
for the next version of
parameter to be sent back to be
broadcast back from that
server. So they will wait.
And this black bars
basically wait.
It's called a global barrier.
Okay. And once all
the workers finish,
receive the new
copy of parameter,
they will basically commence
the next iteration of
computer and they
repeat, they will wait.
Okay? And this timeline
looks pretty cool,
assuming that your
class is perfect.
But in reality,
that's not the case
because in you will see this.
Right? So device A is
just slower than DSB.
USB is the fastest, but DVI
A is a little bit faster.
And what you do is if you do
this kind of like
a global barrier,
um, Device B,
finish basically using
half of the time, right?
But device A, like I
said, is super slow.
So basically, B and C how
to wait for A, right?
Because they have to wait for
the server to aggregate
gradients and send the
new parameter back.
Okay, you can see this is
called it's called bubbles.
Like I said, it's bubbles.
It's bubbles in the
tribute system.
And, so basically USB and
are wasting money, at this time.
Okay? And people have
this actually was pretty
common before Neural Networks,
because before New Networks,
I think a lot of models they
have so many parameters,
but they don't have a
lot of communication
bandwidth you know,
back then in the area
of Spark Maple produce,
people build clusters with a
lot of heterogeneous nodes.
But heterogeneous,
I mean, each node
has different kinds of
CPU and GPU, right?
It's basically connection or
very diverse hardware setups
and each device can actually
work with a different pace.
But today is different
because today
now people are building kind of
supercomputing center where you
basically have the
same type of GPU,
this problem is
kind of elevated.
But back then, this
is true, okay?
So what those people
are thinking about
is how to basically reduce
these kind of bubbles, okay?
How to reduce the
bubbles. So basically,
you can see, this is
the consistency, right?
This is called a strong
consistency, like, BSP.
Okay? I think it's called a
box synchronous consistency,
Which means that
all workers have to
wait and how to be synchronized
with the same pace.
But we can find something
that's better, right.
Red we can relax this
consistency a little bit.
So how to relax. Um,
so why we can't relax?
Because think about
what we are doing here.
So basically, every
worker is computed copy
gradients and the serve is
trying to grade the gradients
and then perform a
grading descent.
And we probably know
that marcheering
programs they have a very
nice characteristic.
That is it is very
error tolerant.
So what do I mean
by error tolerant?
So I think you
already experienced
one part of error tolerance
is in quantition.
You introduced some errors, but
the model can still work, right?
Uh, so as long as you
don't deviate too far,
I think the model will converge
in some way. Okay,
that's the idea.
So in grading design,
that's the same case.
So basically, you can think
about grading design.
Here, I'm doing green accent,
okay? You are climbing a hill.
Right?
You can collab this hill
using different paths, right.
So assuming like you
have a perfect grading,
then you basically
collab all the
way up, right, like this.
Okay? And you all take
the least time to reach
reach the top, right?
But like I said, machine
learning program is
pretty error tolerant
green isn't is the same.
So you can collab with different
paths like this, right?
You can deviate a little
bit like this, okay?
Like this, like this,
like this, like this.
Okay, you all take a
little bit more steps,
but eventually because of
the nature of green isn't,
you are going to reach
the top of the hill.
Okay. Which means
that you don't how to
exactly use the precise version
of the gradient derived
at the current state.
You can use probably slightly
wrong version of it.
But as long as you
follow some conditions,
you can still get there.
Okay. And with this situation,
what people does is basically,
uh, I think this basically
explain what I said, right?
So you don't how to
follow the grading line.
And you can slightly debate,
you still get the top.
And with this one,
people want to basically relax
the um consistency model.
One way to relax the consistency
is I don't how a consistency.
So every worker will basically
compute at their own pace.
I don't bother to know other
parameters or gradients.
I just compute at their
own pace. I don't update.
I only update at, say,
100 ingredients or
200 ingredients.
In that way, you are
doing much better
because you don't
how to compute,
you don't have to synchronize
at every iteration gradients.
Okay. But the problem is then
every worker will basically take
their own pass to
update the parameters.
At some point, you just
average the parameters,
and it's likely that all
workers are divided, okay?
So this is basically,
uh, the case I explained.
So here, device one
is the slowest.
So in this window time,
device one only
perform one iteration.
But in this window time,
Device two and three, four,
they basically perform
many many interes,
and there's no
barrier between them.
Okay, you just do your own job.
And this apparently
doesn't work because
it defeat the purpose
of data parism.
You are not aggregate
ingredits at all.
Okay? So what we ended
up with is we find
the middle ground between
strong consistency
and no consistency.
Okay. And this is called SSP.
It's called steel consistency.
What do I mean by
steel consistency?
That is here, I introduce
additional variable,
which is stillness.
And this stillness
specifically characterize how
steel the copied gradients
is or the parameters.
So I'm going to give
you an example.
So here, device A and B,
they all proceed
with the same pace,
and we'll finish intercon.
And then because
device B a bit faster,
it goes interon more, okay?
And do another fast device.
I got more and B,
even faster, right?
And you can see during this
process, I don't synchronize.
I just like the US ABC to
proceed the pace,
procedure competition.
But at some point,
device B is too fast.
I find that the slowest worker,
which is USA and the
fastest work which is USB,
they already have
three steps apart.
And when the three steps
apart is basically exceeding
my stills threshold,
I'm going to tell
them, you should
stop and you guys should
synchronize little.
Okay. Does that make
sense? Cool. As long as we
maintain this relaxation window,
uh, we can basically,
greatly reduce the lumber,
like global synchronization
across the entire classroom.
So we just let them go and go,
you know, uh this
web block, right?
And we just let it go.
And we can effectively
reduce the,
um, lumber communication.
Therefore, uh, but we still
preserve some sort of like club
in the hell right, green accent.
Okay. And indeed,
I think back then
before neuro networks,
uh, people do this a lot,
okay to accelerate the
distribute training and,
um, and it can prove
that basically,
if your model converges,
it really depends on
the value of stillness.
So basically, when
steels is equal
to the zero you are doing
strong consistency, right.
When stillness is infinity,
you have no consistency.
So it's actually a
continuous spectrum.
So people do a lot
of this kind of
experience by experimenting in
different stis against
different models,
and they find that basically
this region of Stines is okay.
But if you go beyond
this, you know,
your model is going
to break. Okay.
And people also prove a lot
of despite the open by people,
they become very fascinated
about this because this is,
there are a lot of beautiful
theory behind all that.
Okay, they want to prove
and they want to publish.
And this is one equation
I quoted, okay?
And I think the way to interpret
this equation is pretty simple.
You can ignore all the symbols.
Okay, I'm going to tell
you what it means.
It means that the
difference between
a stillist estimate and
the true estimate can
be bounded by a term.
And this term is basically a
function of the stillness.
Okay. That means that as long as
your stillness is not too large,
I think you are going
to achieve the optimal.
Yeah. Okay. Like I said,
this is a very active
area of research and
people are still
doing this today.
Okay. If you check slightly
more theoretical work
in distribute machining,
people are doing this.
But the problem is, this
does not work well
in your networks.
Uh, because like I said, if
you look at this equation,
in order to get here,
you have to make
a lot of assumptions
about your objective.
For example, it
has to be certain,
there are some convex
characteristics
about the objective,
and you have to perform grade
always given learning rate.
But you probably know
that in deepen network,
a lot of things cannot
be proved, right?
And, um, people are
not able to make any
theoretical progress on this.
And empirical, when you
apply this units into,
uh internar networks, I don't
think it works pretty well.
Yeah. Okay? Any question
about this part?
Cool. That is basically
primary server.
I think there are a
lot of other issues
about prime server like
you already mentioned,
there are some for issues
but I think I give
you a reading,
and you can check on that paper.
So another way of implementing,
um, data parism is basically
like this or reduced, right?
You basically perform a ring
or reduce across all workers.
And this due is basically
what we have today.
This is the most commonly used,
um, scheme for
performing or reduce.
Okay, providing the
system support.
Like I said, this is one of
the most popular
reduce interface.
And what you do is
basically you import
this torch the disc,
you import DDP.
And then you initiate
a process group.
You have this in your homework,
you're going to do this.
You basically declare the ranks
between all the
processes all threats.
And then for each rank, you
are going to declare a model,
right, because you are
going to replicate
the model for each
rank for each thread.
And what you do is basically
you perform the training,
and I think behind the strain
step is going to basically,
they will perform reds for you.
A little bit more
history about reduce?
It was initially implemented
in a framework called Harwood,
and this one is by Uber.
Okay. Uber was pretty good
at sometime
imagyemergen systems.
And roughly in 2015.
Okay. And this Hord,
if you still check,
it has more than ten k
starts on Github today,
later, I think, at
the time of HR Word,
you don't have abraries
like Nick and CCO.
You only have library like MPI.
That's why you use
in your homework.
Okay. But like I
said, MPI is for
CPU and Niko is for DPU. Okay?
And later, I think media start
realizing that this connect
is going to take off,
and uh, uh, they basically have
a very strong team of Koda
engineers implement NCL.
Uh, I think this NCL no
essentially become the default
back for performing any type
of connective communication
between GPUs.
Okay? It's highly
optimized by ODM.
And this is one
of the ODS modes.
This justifies the ODS
stock, by the way.
And later when Niko takes off,
I think Petrog start to adopt
this Nichols and
they build this GDP.
Due to the popularity of petrog
I think people basically move
away from Word to use Petros
native DDP interface.
Okay? And one more thing
I want to mention
about datapoism is
because now all the data
parts are implemented using
ORD AD has a very bad thing
that's not fault
tolerant, right?
Because when you perform ORD,
you have to mobilize
all the workers to
perform that ring
in communication.
And if one worker failed,
then this De will fail.
Which means that due is
not a fault tolerant.
And if you compare Ds to
primary sur you'll
find that primary
SR is more fault
tolerant, right?
Because you can have
different shares,
you have different workers.
So I one worker field,
you're still good,
you probably have
some way to remedy,
but in dus, no.
Okay? But it seems that
image learning system,
people don't care about
fault tolerance. Okay. Yeah.
That's what I at least in
my past five years
of experience, yes.
Yeah. But if you talk
about big data processing
you talk about database,
I think for tolerance
is a pretty big issue.
Yeah, everybody
talks about that.
Yeah. Okay. Okay,
one discussion is,
as you can see, uh,
one thing I want to
point out is actually,
2010-2020, I think people
publish, like I said,
people also published
more than 1,000 papers on
primary server on
distributed green descent,
right on that studs thing.
But at some point,
Ad just takeover.
Or du very simple thing,
no fault tolerance,
no consistency.
So basically, just implementing
just coding, strong
kernels, okay?
So I want to ask you why.
Think about this, why? Like why?
Like Academia always do this,
they grand something so hard
and something simpler
takeover, right?
I think one reason is like
I said, or du is simple.
I think industry really
like simple things.
Okay. Second, it's really
because of hardware.
So like I said, at
the beginning, uh,
the reason people introduce
this consistency on
this primary server client
architecture is because they
assume the communication
is going to
be a bottleneck, right?
And, they
introduce consistency
because they want to reduce
lumber synchronization
and reducing
lumber synchronizing equals
to reducing communication.
But at some point, AD
just shape a new hardware
technology called unveilink.
Unwilink is basically as
long as you train
a model inside of
one box with GPS you
basically have almost
infinent bandwidths.
And once this becomes a fact,
then the value of prime
error basically get
lost because communication
is not about neck.
Wing basically save
the communication address
the communicing problem.
And you can just basically use
fact whatever is the
simplest to perform that
communication, which is orgs.
But like I said,
when we move on to
Multipoism then communication
will become another
problem, why?
Because previously
when we do data parism
we just scaled to GPS inside
one box where we have wink.
But now model size
explode again,
Model size becomes
like 175 billion.
Then you have to scale
beyond one node, right?
Beyond between two
different nodes,
you don't have a meink anymore.
Then communication
becomes another problem.
That basically brings us
to the next topic, Mdpism.
I have to switch slide.
Give me 1 minute.
Okay. Um, yeah, we
finish data partism.
But still, data paris is a
very commonly adopted thing.
I'm not saying it's
being duplicated.
I'm just saying primary
sur is being duplicated.
But in reality, you
have to combine
data pism with other
sort of multiparism.
And now let's talk
about Multipism.
Okay? And the way we talk
about Muliparism
basically we start with
interop partism and we try to
derive some mathematical
understanding of
how to optimize inter partism.
And then we try to map
this understanding
with all sorts of,
uh, system artifacts
people build for this.
Hopefully, we finish Intern
next week we'll do intra.
Okay. So I hope
everyone still remember the goal
or the definition
of intero partism.
So if I give you a
neural network as
this computer graph on
this slide and also
a set of devices,
device one, two,
three, four, uh,
for example, GPUs, and I
ask you to partition, uh,
this computing graph
onto these devices and
then what's the most
straightforward way?
Yeah, I can just partition,
right, like this. Okay?
I just partition. Yeah, I
just count number nose.
I try to make sure
each note each device
has almost equal
number of node, right?
And this is one way of
partition, um, um, um,
and here, I'm going to introduce
one new concept in inter
partismo? It's called stage.
So basically here, I partition
this original como graph
into four stages and I like
each device to hold one stage.
And one stage is
basically a part
of a subgraph of the
original graph, okay?
It's a stage. Okay. Once I
finish this partition, I can
start asking you, right?
So how to ask you. So I can
ask you in this way, okay?
So to actually basically ask
you this pion near network,
what do we do, Because we
put the first stage
on Device one, right?
So we also give
the input to the device one.
We start from device one.
Okay? We ask you device one,
to get the output of
stage one, right?
And then we forward
device one to forward
this output one to
Device two, right?
And here, if you still remember,
we have to do a sens we
have to communicate,
but it's B to B
communication. Okay.
Uh, like I said,
the output tensor
of stage one will be
transferred to device two as
the input of stage two
requires the output.
Now that the time spent on
the data transfer
is typically small
because we only communicate
stage outputs at the stage
boundaries between two stages.
And then what we do is
basically we continue this.
We let Stage two
to execute and get
the output and we
forward forward.
Okay? This is pretty
clear, simple.
And finally, we run Stage
four on device four
and we get the
output of the loss,
for example, the
whole new network.
Okay. So in the literature
about intero partism
the execution,
we described just now is
basically often visualized
as this timeline. Okay?
So here, uh, this Y access
is basically the devices.
Okay? This access is time.
Okay? So we can
visualize the execution.
The schedule I just
described on this figure.
Okay? So, uh the execution
on the previous slide is
looking like this, right?
So device one ask
device device device
four. So what's the problem?
You see, there's a bubble
bubble again, right?
Basically, think about it.
I paran, we are always
fighting bubble.
Okay? So the remaining
gray area indicates
the device being idle and we
typically call them bubbles.
Okay. This bubble
exists because of
the data dependency between
different stages on
different devices.
Like device two
requires the input of,
uh, the output of device one
and et cetera, you know,
and as we can see,
at any given moment,
in this case, at
any given moment,
there's only one
device running, right?
And this means that
the device utilization
is super low, super low.
Uh, to quantify this
device utilization,
uh, we measure how
much gray area.
Um we measure how much or
the pipeline bubble will take
on the uh whole timeline.
And for example, uh with
this acuton schedule here,
the pipeline bubble percentage
will be this number.
Okay? This is pretty easy
to understand, right?
So basically, you just look at
this column and there's
only one device running.
So basically the bubble
is D minus one device
by D. Very bad.
All right. Your MF is going
to be terrible. Okay?
If you do this, you
know, very dangerous.
Okay. Cool. I think
you got my point.
So the main way to
improve so we want to
improve this, right?
So the main way to improve
the ascen efficiency
for inter partism
is basically through pipeline
ASQonu different inputs.
So let's see right now,
the input, A is basically
asq on stage one, right?
So after input A finishes
Asking on stage one and
start Sceving on stage two.
What do we do is, at the
same time because stage one,
uh, is idle, we can basically
fit another input B
like this, right?
So here, stage two,
askeed input A and stage one can
take another input
and askew on it.
Okay? And we can fit another
input B into stage one
and as skewed at the same time
as input A skewed on stage two.
And again, next time,
okay, input equals
to stage three,
then we can give B
for B to stage two,
and we can at stage one to
take another new input input
C. This is called
pipe planning. Okay?
Um, yeah, we just repeat
doing this and we basically form
a pipeline and this pipeline
ask you what goes on, right?
We'll go on. With pipeline
in multiple inputs,
then the pipeline bubble it
can be reduced to
basically that figure.
Only the first step we
only have one device.
But once the pipeline starts
and start rolling out,
you can see the utility
is going to grow.
Can anyone tell me
what's the utility here?
Equation. I'm going to
give you the answer.
Think about that.
Essentially, like this,
you keep rolling the pipeline.
The percentage bubble is
basically D minus
one divided by D,
minus one plus N
where N is the input.
Okay. Does that make sense?
Cool. Think about
that, after we talk.
So here, if you look
at this equation,
you will find a very
interesting phloma that is
N is lumber batches,
you're going to pipeline.
Emotionally we have
infinite batches.
You can assume we
have inflint batches,
which means that when
N goes to infinity,
this bubble is going to diminish
and we are good again, right?
Agree? Anyone disagree.
I disagree. Okay, we
are not going to be
good again, okay?
I assure you, okay?
So it seems that
if you have infinite batches,
um, we are good again.
But this is only for
inference, right?
Because in inference of
assuming you have
infinite batches,
you basically perform
forward, right?
And you are good again, yes.
That's why PublmPis pretty
good for inference.
If you do inference,
you can do this publi
paris, there's no issue.
You only suffer a
little bit bubble,
but that bubble is
basically what diminished.
But like I said,
the fundamental problem is we
need to do training, okay?
And so what happened here?
So Okay,
um, Pipeline different
input batches
doesn't simply
work for training.
The reason is that for
new network training
after the forward pass,
um and then um,
and basically after we
getting the loss on
the specific input,
we need to perform a
backward pass, right?
And so what do we do is, um,
we need to perform the backward
pass to calculate the gradient
and the data dependency in the
backward pass is reversed.
Okay? So for example,
for stage two,
it requires stage
one's um output
to run the forward pass, right?
But in the backward
pass, stage one
requires Stage two uh,
grading information to calculate
its own gradient on
the current stage.
And in addition, after we
calculate the gradient,
we need to update the
neural network with
the gradient and then start
the forward and backward pass
of the next input. Okay.
So in that case, we all
get this timeline, right?
This is a backward pass.
Here, I only have
one batch, okay?
And this is pretty
easy to understand.
I just do this exact the exact.
And you can see there's a
middle point where I have to
update perform an
oppment update.
That is why I have update.
Okay, we are good
with this one, right?
Um, so in this case,
screening timeline
will be like in
figure because of the forward
and backward dependency,
the execution will be
from device one to
device four and then
from four to device one,
um, you know, and
then we perform
a green update and continue
on the next input.
As you can see,
the pipeline efficiency
here is still very
low and device are being
idle, most of the time.
And, Okay.
And we are going to have
a solution for this.
But before that, I
want to probably,
this is a theory part,
okay, for papel empaism.
But I want to ground
this on some real works
that people doing in
training their models.
Okay. And we gradually,
like reveal more
and more solutions
to how to fill those bubbles.
Okay.
So there's quite a few previous
works focus on reducing
the pipeline bubbles,
and, uh, therefore,
by reducing bubble,
they can increase the
device addition, right.
And we generally categorize
the previous work into
three categories.
The first one is called
device placement.
Okay? You probably
read this paper.
It's a very famous paper
from machining commitee,
again, published by
JFD, okay, from Google.
And, um Uh, and
the second category is
called synchronous,
the pipeline algorithm.
And the third category
is a synchronous.
And here synchronous
or synchronous,
I think you already get an
understanding because I talk
about that in data parism right?
So synchronous means you
have a strong consistency.
And asynchronous means that you
try to relax my consistency
a little bit, okay?
And we all reveal. Okay.
First, let's take a look
at this device placement.
The goal here is basically
slice the branches of
neural network into
multiple stages
so they can be
calculated concurrently.
So for example, if
the new network can be
decomposed into these
four stages, right?
If there's a new
looking on this, okay?
Here Sg two and Std three
are two branches that do
not depend on each other.
They are parallel
branches. Okay. And we can
basically ask you to Std two
and three in parallel, right?
And if we wish you a the
timeline of these approaches,
um, we basically get
this one, right.
So basically, um, you can
say at this time points, uh,
device two and three are
executed concurrently,
so we effectively
reduce bubbles.
Does it make sense? Cool.
The biggest limitation of
this device placement is
that it only works for
specific new networks.
Like I said, you have
to have this kind
of branching out
data photograph.
For example, it can work
for this inception model,
which includes branches of
different sizes of convolution.
This inception wiser is
a very famous new network
invented at Google, okay?
Um, and it can also work
with contrastive models,
which basically, uh,
includes two branches
for two inputs.
And this contrastive model
at some point is very
popular in coervon.
Okay. However, it
cannot be used to
accelerate model like other sort
of conal works and
also transformers.
This is bird. Okay,
no such case.
And in addition,
uh, as you can see,
you and I do this,
the device utilon is
still quite low, right?
For example, when the first and
the last device is running,
all other devices become,
um, basically idle.
Okay? So device placement
basically need to
be combined with,
um, um, other
pipeline schedules,
which we'll discuss next.
Okay, another type of methods
to improve efficiency
is what we call synchronous
pipeline parallel.
Okay? The idea
here is basically,
we modify the pipeline schedule
to improve efficiency,
but keep the computation
on the convergence
semantically the same,
exactly the same as if you
are training on a single device.
So the very first work, okay,
the very famous work
which I gave you at
reading is basically GPipe.
Okay? G stands for Google,
again, invented by Google.
Okay? So the first work was
pipeline parison is GPipe.
The main idea here is to
split the input batch.
Here I'm going to use the
one I introduced, okay?
I'm going to split the input
batch into micro baatches.
Here I use my
definition microbtch.
I hope you don't get confused.
I'm going to split
my input batch into
many micro baatches
then we perform
the pipeline as tuition
for these micro baatches.
It's very similar to
the green accumulation.
But it's a distributed
orchestration.
Let me show you.
Basically, since
the gradient of the
whole input batch can be
decomposed into the main of
the gradients of microbatches,
I gradient accumulation,
and we can basically
accumulate gradients
into different microbatches
and updated with altogether
later once we finish
a micro batches.
So let's say this.
So for example,
let's say we split our input
into six microbatches,
then we can basically run
the forward pass like this.
No problem about 44 devices,
six micro baatches.
The problem here is when we
run the four pass in
pipeline fashion,
for all inputs, we have to
keep all the intermediate
activations.
We cannot through them
right. Why? Because we
need to perform backward, right?
We have to preserve them.
Okay? And then we
perform a backward pass
for all micro baatches
like this, right?
So here I hold the microbtg
five ready, right?
A activation computed.
And then I schedule
the backward or micro baat
five on the device four.
And then I basically start
pipelining the backward.
It's a kind of reverse figure.
And finally, we update
the model with the
accumulated reading,
and we get the new
version model with,
and we continue with
the next batch.
Obviously repeat this pattern.
Okay. Any problem?
Yeah.
What do you mean by overhead?
Yeah, that can be done
before I launch a job.
Yeah. It's something
before runtime.
Yeah.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. I can prepare that.
I can do pre compute pre
processing, Okay? Okay.
Here I'm going to ask
another question
and very important.
So in this case, what's
the pipeline bubble percentage
in mathematical form?
Okay, I'm going to
give you equation.
You should internalize a
little bit. Let me finish.
Okay. So this is the
same thing, right?
Forward backward is reverse,
bubble is exactly the same.
Dmus one device by
Dmus one plus, please.
For you combine
everything into one thing
You don't have enough memory.
Yeah. You don't
have enough memory.
Even if you have enough memory,
you are going to if you look
at this equation,
assume you can.
Assume you can.
What's the problem.
The problem is you really
want to reduce your bubbles.
And if you combine
your microbatches
into a bigger battery,
the problem is is
going to decrease.
Previously, have a lumber
microbaty equal to six.
So if you consolidate
the microbatch into one,
you reduce it to three.
And once you reduce it to
three what's the problem.
Your bubble is going
to increase, right,
because this number
is decreased.
So the bubble is
going to increase.
Your device will
have more atle time.
Sure. So the sooner What do
you mean by update sooner?
Yeah, you are going
to update sooner.
Yeah, the cycle is
going to be shorter,
the percentage of these
bubbles is going to increase.
Yeah. Any other question?
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Very good question.
I can tell you there's a limit.
Okay. And actually,
I talked about
this somewhere during
the memory section.
So think about this, okay?
You are locked to
train a model with
a badge size equal
to one K. Okay.
So basically, that's a result
from hyperprimy tuning.
That is training with
the basis equal to
one K will give you
the best convergence.
Assuming that that's
not available.
That's a constant,
you have to do that.
And then if you do Pip
parism the best you
can do is basically you
train with 1,000
microbatches, right?
You use the basis equal to
one to train with 1,000
microbates and this bubble
is going to be minimized, right?
Because this one is here.
But what's the problem?
Can anyone tell?
Yeah.
Exactly.
Because every time you
increase microbaties,
you are going to decrease
the effective body size.
So what's the effect of
decreasing effective body size?
You are going to reduce
your matamo size, right?
Once you reduce the mamosize,
your GPO is going to be the
original intensity is
going to decrease.
So you decrease lamer bubbles,
but you also decrease the AI.
Eventually, when you train
arg models in company
like Open At this is a
pretty hard decision that
they have to figure
out the microbdy sizes
and effective body size.
Number microbachies. They have
to strike a balance between
AI and deviszon. Okay,
does that make sense.
I'm glad you ask because I'm
going to cover that anyway.
Yeah. Okay? Cool. This
equation is pretty important.
You need to remember, if
you do pipeline partism,
your device utilization is
a function of lumber microbches.
Okay? You want to increase that,
but you cannot
increase too much.
Okay. Okay, so in this case,
the pop bubble percentage
is this equation.
And from the experiment results
of the original Pip paper,
we can see that with only
this depip schedule,
uh, the parallel efficiency
is actually pretty good.
Okay? And we can achieve
almost linear speed up when
the lumber microbt is uh large,
like I said, because when
lumber microbt is large,
your ti is high.
Okay?
Now, I'm going to
tell you even more
complicated problem
about Poplin prison.
Okay? So but one important
issue of GPipes memory usage.
Remember, every time when
you perform the commutation,
it's better on the forward pass.
For a microba you have to
preserve its activations.
Okay? So the per device of
the GPip schedule can be
visualized in this plot.
Okay? And this part
is a memory that is
basically this part
is a memory that
is basically used to store
the motor parameters.
It's a constant.
Like I said, basically it's
active during the entire
forward backward pass, right?
And there's a fixed.
This is a fixed cost, and
we cannot do much about it.
Okay? However, this part,
this part is
basically occupied by
the intermediate
activations, right?
Because whenever you
introduce more microbatch,
you are going to
save one copy of
the activations for
that microbatch.
So at some point, at some point,
especially at the last
microbat forward.
This one, basically
achieve peak, right?
And then you start doing
backward on this microbatg file.
And because you do backward,
you get the gradits
so you can release
the memory for the activations.
So at some point, you're
going to decrease.
That's why it is
like this, okay?
Does anyone basically spot
this fundamental conflict?
I said, in that equation,
I showed in my previous slide,
you want the lumbomcrobtches
to be as large as
possible to minimize
the device Id.
But from this
figure you can see,
if I increase lambermcrobatches,
this is like this.
It's going to always
grow to some point
where my GPU memory
is going to explode.
Which means that this
schedule doesn't work.
It looks pretty beautiful
but it doesn't work at all.
Basically, at the peak, we have
to store the
parameter as well as
the intermediate activities
for all input microbatches.
Okay.
So memory equals to
perimeter plus activation
times number of microbages.
I want this to be large
to minimize bubble.
But I also want
this to be small to
minimize the peak memory.
Basically fundamentally
contradictory.
Okay. Cool, what's the solution?
The indeed is a solution.
That's why we still cover
problem meorith If
there's no solution,
this is not going to
be covered in course.
One optimization of
GPipe schedule is
a so called 1f1b
schedule, one forward,
one backward schedule, and it is
a re order of the
original GPipe schedule.
And as shown in this figure,
you can see, uh,
if you go okay, I highly
recommend you go back,
look at this, and you try
to basically play this
game by yourself.
You try to play how to place
a bubble each block on this
timeline, play by yourself.
And, as long as you assume
the forward and bawd is
exactly the same time,
you want to figure out this
11b under the GPP schedule,
they have exactly the same
latency for interact.
The only difference is I
basically play this game.
I try to reorder this one, two,
three, four, different
colors 1234.
So, you know, uh,
the above and the
bottom are different.
But this creates
a huge difference.
What's the difference?
So main difference
between 11b and G pipe
is that 11b will
prioritize the execution
of the backwards.
Okay. Remember, in
my previous, um,
if you look at this schedule,
I'm going to schedule
this pipeline execution all
the way to finish of forward.
And then I start backward.
But like I said, you have
to suffer that memory peak.
But here, as long
as I have batch
one microbtch that is
ready to perform backward,
I'm going to schedule
the backward.
I'm going to interwind forward
and backward in some ways,
so this backward
can be prioritized.
So why prioritizing
backward could be better?
Because if you look
at this if you just
track this microbt zero,
right, at this point, the
memory can be released.
Okay. Pretty nice, right?
Yeah. And if you look
at microbay one,
in the PIP schedule, the one,
the last microbg will
be the one will be
asked here, right?
But I reorder it. I'm
going to ask you here.
But if you check this
one, at this point,
the memory for microbg
one is going to
be released. Okay?
Pretty nice, right?
Okay, you'll spoil
the difference.
So, uh so basically,
um I don't know how
to repeat, right?
So we just need to perform
backward as early as possible.
But just redo this, we have
the same iterating latency,
but our memory is much better,
if we visualize the memory
specifically with
this one B schedule,
the memory will no longer
grow once we start
performing backward.
Whenever we perform
a forward pass,
we will immediately follow
with a backward pass that
can free the amount
of memory occupied
by the forward
intermediate activions.
Therefore, the memory usage will
plate somehow in the
middle, like this.
It will just grow here and then
plateau and then decrease.
And with this f1b schedule,
we will only need to straw
amber devices shares
of activations,
instead of amber
microbatches, copies.
So basically reduce
this factor from
amber microbatches
to lumber devices.
Think about this
by yourself, okay.
You should be able to
dive this equation
because I'm going to ask
you exam about this.
Okay. Please.
Uh huh. In most cases, yes.
Yeah. Okay. Especially when
you want to minimize
your bubble.
Yeah, you have to use a
pretty large micro badges,
lumber microbges. Yeah.
Okay.
So like I said, If B,
the WiFi schedule
allows us to perform
pipeline parison with infinite
number of microbtes now.
Okay? Now, I can
basically, like you said,
I use just super
large microbates
to diminish the device bubble,
but I won't suffer from a
super high peak memory.
Okay?
I think this is
basically the most
important part of this lecture.
And like I said, this and B
is the one adopted
today for twin GBT.
Okay. Uh, I think also
for t A language model.
Okay.
Actually, we can still
grand it a little bit more.
This is going to be a little
bit more complicated.
I'm not going to dive deeper,
but if you are interested,
you can dive deeper on this, but
I'm going to give you pointers.
A further optimentation, of
the f1b schedule is
basically to slice
the neural network into more
fine grained pipeline stages
to reduce pipeline bubble.
Let's say we are training
a new network with eight
layers on four devices.
Previously, we cluster
contiguous layers
to form four stages,
and each device will basically
responsible for one stage.
So we have a new schedule
called interwine 11b.
And in the interwineO
B schedule,
we put more than one stage
onto a single device.
Specifically, we can
let each layer be
a stage and then put
stage one and stage
five on device one,
and stage two, and stage
six on device two,
and so on. Like
this figure shoot.
The main benefit of this
method is that the latency,
a single stage, the latency
of a single stage
becomes shorter.
Therefore, for example, device
two only need to wait half
of the time to start excusing
instead of waiting for
the entire two layers.
Okay.
If we further visualize the
execution, in a timeline,
we can see that the new schedule
further reduce the
pipeline bubble.
You just need to compare this.
Okay. And this one, like I said,
GPip has latency,
and WiFi B has the same
inter latency with GPip.
But if you do this
interleave WIF and B,
you are going to reduce this
latency. You become faster.
Okay.
And, and the downside
of this method is,
since we have more
stages, right,
so we need to communicate
more often between devices.
Okay. So basically, you
pay a communicating cost.
And since the communicating
cost is typically small for
interoperor partism and we can
basically get speed
up, yeah, it's fine.
Okay. And if you want to
it's not required, okay?
I'm not going to
do this in exam,
but if you want to grant this,
you can try to pass that.
Yeah, it's very complicated.
Um, yeah, another complexity I
didn't mention is this is
very difficult to implement.
One key this ti problem parism
is very hard to provide a very
efficient implementation.
It's very hard to
debug. Especially when
you launch this kind of problem
parism across many devices.
And if there's an error, you
don't know where it happens.
Okay. Okay. Any question?
If you basically
try to grind this,
I can tell you the
bubble is basically
this lumber and you can see,
where are the factor end.
Okay. And there are more.
I'm not going to cover. I think
people are grading
this pretty hard.
Okay.
Then let's move on to next word.
So next word, TerraPp.
Tara pup is basically
a pipeline parts
work to aggressive models,
for example, TPT
language models.
And, like I said,
most stable art
language models are
basically, uh,
transformer architecture.
And if we use the transformer to
evaluate probative
of syndem like this,
um, basically cats are the best,
and we will first mod
probability of cats
conditional on a special
token, start off sequence,
which is this okay
then mod probability of cat
and then R and then the best,
and then we stop with the US.
This is autoregressive model.
Um, so here, one key
observation we have is, uh,
the computation of
one input token,
only depends on the
previous token,
but not the future tokens.
This is what we mean
by auto regressive.
Okay? For example,
when we calculate
the probability of
the word there, uh,
the model only looks at
cats R, these two words,
but there's no dependency on
the best, the following words.
So why is it important?
So basically in this
trap pilin parison,
the way we do is we use
this property to perform pipe
laning within a sequence.
So what do we do is
for example here,
we can not the first
token run on device one.
Okay. Run it first,
and then we send the
results to device two.
Meanwhile, well the first
layer to run a second token.
Remember, look at
this difference.
Here I this layer stage
to take one token,
once I finish it, I'm going to
forward this activity
to this layer.
Meanwhile, I'm going to
this transform layer
to take another token.
The reason we can't do this is
because now we are
doing language models.
We have a sequence
input. Like this.
Once you see it two steps,
you know what I'm
going to do next?
I'm going to
continue to do this.
Wall form partsme
this, like this. Okay.
This is basically
the idea of Trapap.
We can do this kind
of parts but this is
only special to language models.
Yeah.
Another key this advantage of
this work is you can only
do bicycle equal to one,
which is not super
good for small models.
Okay.
Then I'm going to tell
you another work.
Okay. It's called Chimera.
Okay. And in my previous
offering with lecture,
I don't cover this work because
this is very complicated.
But today, I have to cover it.
You know why? This is the
one that is used in TipsIk.
Okay. Deep six basically
uses PipelHizon.
Okay? So do spend some
time grading this because
I'm I'm going to come back to
this when we start talking
about language models.
Okay?
So Chimera is another
work that try
to further optimize
the one B schedule,
let's say we have four
steady pipeline and
two input micro baatches
if we ask them with 11b,
we basically get
this schedule, 11b.
Okay. And we can
find it out here.
If you just look at
this figure, okay?
This figure does not
have many microbges,
but let's use as an example.
If you look at this figure,
you can see, there are
some bubbles, right?
Here, here, here,
here, here. Okay.
And these bubbles looks
like we can insert
another pipeline.
Right? We just do a
reverse pipeline,
and we insert asc
into these bubbles.
Okay? So so look at this fire,
we can see that we
find out we can enter
another 11b pipeline
or reverse 11b.
So more specifically, um,
if we also maintain
a reverse pipeline,
in other words, we
start the pipeline on
Device four and then
finish it on device one.
Basically, we put
two copies of the model
parameters, right?
One is from device one
all the way to four.
The other is Device
four all to one, okay?
And we can basically get
another pipeline with
two micro baatches one from
here, the other from here.
Okay? And if we
merge this pipeline,
basically get this kind of
schedule, okay on this slide.
Oh, sorry, this is
the second bubble.
If we merge them together,
we get this one.
Okay, you can see this
is pretty smart, right?
We basically do a
forward and backward,
but using a rewards all over
the devices and we
put allom together,
you can see atom
bubble diminish.
We can maximize our utilization.
Okay? What's the problem?
You have two copies already
parameters, not activations.
Basically, which
means that you have
to waste some memory to store
two copies of parameters.
Um, before Deep sick,
before the big models,
I think this is a problem
that people do not accept.
But at some point, people
continue to skill and skill
to skill and skill
training to like two KTPs.
At that point, you find that
you have many many memory.
You have so many memory
that you are able to
afford two copy of parameters.
That's why Tip stake
is a win, right?
Deep uses one to minimize
the dias bubble.
Okay. Today, I'm
going to stop here.
I think there are
so many contents
that you have to
digest a little bit,
and we are going to deeper
and deeper next week.
Okay. Cool. Thank you.