Okay, let's get started.
Yeah. So I hope you
enjoy APA two, right?
You got a reference answer
for second question
yesterday, right?
And you get a reference
answer to question one
today from Deepsk, right?
I hope you enjoy. And if
you have no idea
how to optimize,
you can actually
check your code.
Yeah. Okay. And today,
we are going to
finish parallelism.
We have a lot of
deep contents today.
So starting from
the next lecture,
we are going to dive
deeper into Ms.
We are going to use what we
learned in the previous lecture,
and we apply them into Ms.
Let's try to finish today.
Just to recap, right? Um, so
basically, in my last lecture,
we developed a model that
help you analyze the overhead
from Interop or pipeline parts
the overhead of Pipeline
partism, right?
This is the ganchart.
And I think
the core of this model is
basically you care about
the bubble, right?
You want to minimize
the bubble, okay?
And we develop our
first schedule,
which is the GPip schedule,
which is a very structured
and nice looking schedule,
but it doesn't work.
Why? Because the memory
is green with lumbar
microbde size.
Okay? And we fix it, right?
We make the schedule
a little bit messier,
but it works, okay?
And we try to advance
it further and further.
We start developing another
mode schedule, which
is bidirectional.
And we said that this is one
used to train deep, okay?
This one called Chimera.
Okay, and I think
we stopped here.
Okay. Then let's continue.
So for all the schedules I
introduced in my last lecture,
I give them a name that is,
um, they are called
synchronous Pipeline
parallel schedule.
So here, you can understand that
synchronous are
something very similar
to what we discussed
in data parism that
is we always make
sure like all the workers,
they are in the same place.
So what do I mean? So the
main benefits of this kind
of like method is that it
keeps machine
learning semantics.
So in other words,
the whole training competition
will be exactly the same.
Uh, as if you're actually new on
single device because if you
look at the pre schedule,
we always have this barrier.
We update when all the micro
baatches are finished.
Okay. But actually,
there's a little space
that we can play around
that to make this a little bit
more synchronous
but much faster.
So um, like I said,
in this kind of
synchronous schedule,
the main downside
is we have bubbles,
and although the bubble will
diminish as you increase
lumbar microbachs but
we have bubbles, um,
and we have discussed
many algorithms to
reduce the bubble, but,
reducing this pipeline
bubble requires you
basically very radically
increase lamb microbatches.
So for example, if you
have a smaller input,
which you don't have a lot
of space to make many,
many microbtches in that case,
your pipeline parism is not
going to be super efficient.
Okay. Now, let's look at
another line of work.
So another type of pipeline
parallel schedule or what
we call the synchronous
pipeline parallel schedule,
where we basically remove
the synchronization point in
the pipeline schedule, um,
and now we can start
the next round
forward forward pass before
the backward pass of the
previous round finished.
Okay. That is we remove
a barrier update.
Okay. And a synchronous schedule
actually don't have
pipeline bubbles,
but it also breaks
like I said, the
synchronous semantics.
That is, if you use this
kind of pipeline schedule,
your model trained with this
pipeline schedule
is different from,
uh, as if you are training
on a single device. Okay?
Because your grading
becomes steel in some way.
Okay, like what we did
in, um, data parism.
Okay, let's see. The first
one is basically this one.
If we like all the devices
to go free and acute
at their own pace,
we basically get this schedule
which I called AMP net.
And each device
basically performs
forward pass whenever free.
And they update the wise
after every Brod pass.
Okay. And with this schedule,
the different stages in
the forward and Bro pass
can be on different
versions of the WIC, right?
Because each device
update on their own pace.
Okay? For example,
here for the Data 0.1,
for the data one, the forward
pass of stage one and two,
on the initial width, where the
forward pass on
who backward pass
and backward pass on weights
updated by data zero.
Okay? So this discrepancy
brings noise to the
training process, right?
Because in original SED,
we make sure we update and
then dp gradient
and then update.
But here, every device basically
follow a different pace.
And that's why this one
actually doesn't work
pretty well, okay?
On smart that's like
a mist or Cipher
this kind of small um,
image classifier models.
It works, but very likely
that amor language models.
This will lead to divergence.
Okay? Um, and there are
also some work that,
improve the convergence of
this MP net, um, algorithm.
One is called pipe Myer
and it modifies the
grading optimizer
to improve the convergence,
um, but just a
little bit improve.
It cannot fundamentally change
the drawbo this way, okay?
Um, and pipe dream is another,
algorithm that achieves
better convergence
by reducing this synchrony.
So, the timeline
of the pipe dream
algorithm looks very
similar to 1f1b, right.
It looks very similar to 1f1b.
But, um, the main
difference here is,
um, we updated the model
was once the backward
has finished.
Okay. The main idea
here is basically we
try to enforce in
the same version of
weight for the forward
and backward pass
of a single input data point.
It's basically
relaxed constraint.
And let's focus on device one,
okay? So this is device one.
And for the forward and backward
pass of the input batches,
zero to three, we use
the same initial
weight. You can see.
Okay? Um, but for
input batch four.
Um, it uses the width updated
by input battery zero.
Since we still need to use
the initial weights for
the backward pass of
input one to three,
and at this time point,
we will have two
copies of weights.
One initial weight and
one width, that is,
basically updated after we
compute on input zero, right?
Um, and again, for input B five,
we need to update weights, um,
we need to use width updated
by the input zero and one.
Okay? And for input six,
we need to use width updated
by data bat zero, one and two.
Therefore, in total, um,
we need to store
four copies of it.
Okay? But we only divide
the neural network
into four stages.
The biggest downside
of this pipe dream is
that there will be no
memory saving at all.
Right? Remember, when
we do pipeline prism,
we divide the neural
network into four stages.
That's why we consume memory.
But this algorithm basically
defeat our purpose.
You need to store four
copies on each device.
Okay? But this was
just a very initial,
kind of like paper discussing
a synchronous pipeline
barrel schedule
and discussing that possibility.
That's why I bring
this up, okay.
And today, I think people
have been following up
a lot of new work which can
do better than this one.
Yeah. Okay. And to
reduce the memory usage,
um, the pipe dream authors,
they propose a modification
to the original pipeline,
papeream algorithm by updating
the width less frequently,
um, which is called
pipe dream two PW.
For example, here, input patch,
four, five, six, still
use the initial width.
And starting uh, input seven,
we will use the width updated
by inputs zero to three.
Therefore, the greens are always
only stored for one update, y.
And you can reduce the story.
Okay. And this Pablo Author,
he's a very famous guy.
He basically was a pioneer
in doing Pipeline Pism
and he joined Adia,
and the entire Megatron
library was written
mostly by him.
Okay? Megatron is basically
the framework that people use
a lot in community to train
language models. Yeah. Okay.
This is pretty good work, okay?
Uh, there might be
different there
will be more different pipeline
schedules that we
haven't covered,
but one important issue,
we haven't discussed
is basically
for all the pipeline
scheduling algorithm,
um, we showed just now, right,
we assume the running times of
different pipeline stages are
exactly the same as in
this figure above, right?
So basically ABCD they are
of the same lens, right?
Um, But if the latency of
these stages are not the same,
for example, the
timeline will be
looking like this, right?
So basically for a single input,
for each different
input, you will have
different kind of
like executing time.
And you can see this
is much worse, right?
In the upper figure,
when we execute four
batches, we are there.
But here, basically the
time becomes longer.
Okay? So one important factor
when you do pipeline parison,
you need to make sure each
device has the same workload.
Does that make sense?
Okay. We'll discuss
this later, okay?
Okay. There are many studying
how to partition on New
into different stages,
and the main goal is
basically trying to
minimize the maximum
stage latency
to improve pipeline efficiency,
the overall pipeline
efficiency. Um,
And also try to maximize
the pization of different
branches in device placement.
And here I give you an overview
of these two class methods.
I'm not going to
cover all of them,
but if you want to dive deeper,
read these papers.
Essentially two categories.
The first category is basically
the same recipe you
are very familiar
with because we did
this for compilers for,
um Matamo for like a graph
open that is machine
learning for systems.
We try to learn a model
that can give us
the best schedule.
And this model was
usually trained using
inverse learning.
Okay, the left part.
The second part is we explicitly
model this pipeline schedule
as an oppimentation,
and we try to solve
that openation.
But sometimes this opmentation
is probably in trackable,
so it takes forever, because
it is a bit hard and,
um, so, you know, yeah.
Okay, I will basically give
you a brief idea of
the first scheduling.
And this is a work
that basically
trying to optimize the
pipeline for schedule.
So basically, this
work is called Plato.
So basically, is the example
of RO is partition algorithm,
and the environment for
the I algorithm is
defined as in this figure
where the state is a specific
device placement plan
for computing graph.
Um, the action is to modify
the device assignment
of a node in the graph.
And the reward is basically
a latency difference between
the new and the old placement.
And the R agent is
a graph neural network
that's trying to, um,
try to basically perform as
a policy and try to
figure out what is
the right way to
place these notes on
different devices in order
to maximize the reward,
which is equivalent to
minimizing latency, okay?
And people basically, do this,
and, it's basically
like a search.
You keep trying different
placement strategy and,
you put it on a cluster
observe latency,
and then you propagate the
reward back to new network,
something like that, okay? Cool.
Any questions? Yeah. This
is the spars Wire sparse.
How? They just use more
computer to train a model.
Yeah. Keep trying.
Okay. Okay, um I summary,
the idea of interop
parism is to assign
different operators of
the computation graph to
different devices and then
execute in pipeline
parallel fashion, right?
The device placement algorithm
basically paralyze
different graph branches,
but they have a problem they
are not applicable
on all graphs.
That's the first category here.
Um, the second category,
synchronized pipeline
schedule is the one that
actually we used a lot, okay?
And it has the same convergence
as if you are on single device,
and there are many
algorithms on reducing
the pipeline bubbles and
improving hardware condition.
Um, and the third category,
which I just covered
is basically
a synchronous pipeline
Barrel schedule.
It has the highest hardware
utilization because you can
basically reduce you can
basically have zero bubble,
right, because you just
schedule whatever you want.
Yeah, you don't care
about convergence.
And it has no pipe bubble,
but it introduce
samsung synchrony,
which we heard in
machinering convergence.
So it is only applicable
on some problems,
but not all problems.
Okay? So all these
schedules perform the
best when you have
a balanced stage,
that is each stage need to
have roughly the same workload.
Otherwise, you observe
that graph, right?
Okay. Cool. This basically
marks the end of,
uh, pipeline par schedule.
I think up until today,
people are still
publishing this area.
They are writing
more and more papers
to coming up with a better
schedule. Yeah, please.
Is there a way
synchronous together?
No, you cannot because once
your model parameter
becomes a synchronous,
grading is sequential,
you update,
you update, you
update, you update.
Once at the early step,
you update and you are
using a steel gradit,
then your trajectory is
different from using
a synchronous one.
You cannot go back. Yeah.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, okay. Okay. Then
let's move on, okay.
Let's move into a
more interesting,
like a model or how we model
the intraop partism, right?
I think for interpartism,
we already talk about that.
It's basically the bubble. Okay.
Whenever you talk about
pipeline PismT about interrupt,
you think bubble, okay?
But in intra, this is more
kind of, like, complicated.
Okay? How we model this?
So basically intra Pism
just to recap, right,
we will partition a
single operator and
explore the parism inside
of that operator, right?
And so basically in
the following slides,
we are going to study how to
paralyze a single operator.
And once we know how to
paralyze a single operator,
we can generalize it to
basically how to paralyze
all the operators in algram.
And we are going to develop
a model mathematical model
to help you analyse
the cost, okay?
So let's move on.
So let's still begin
with the simplest case.
I think this one I have
covered this many,
many times in
different lectures.
So this is animal
wise operator, right?
And here's a code for
an animal wise addition on
two dimensional tensors.
Okay? And the code corresponds
to two level four
loop, which is there.
Okay, by observing this
two level four loop,
you observe that there's no
dependency on these 24 loops.
Okay. So basically,
no dependency.
This follop just go independent.
You can swap the order.
Okay, doesn't matter.
Okay. The reason I
highlight this is
because um because
there's no dependency,
so we can arbitrarily split
the four loops on
different devices for
paralyzation, right?
Now, if we have four devices
denoted by the four
different colors,
then there are multiple ways
to paralyze this
operator, right.
So for example, we can paralyze
this loop N, which is
the outer loop, right?
We can also paralyze the loop D,
which is the inner loop, right?
And uh so basically,
when we pariselop
N in this figure,
and in this case, all
three confers how to
be row partition, right?
Because you need to give
each device some work to do.
And if you choose to
partition the loop N,
then, um, the input
array A and B,
they need to be partitioned
following the low partition,
right on four devices,
and the result
will be written in
a row parting way at the
output device. Okay?
Makes sense, right.
Cool. One thing
you observe is when you do this,
there's no communication cost.
You just do your
partitioning. You are good.
Or we can paralyze
both loop and loop D,
as shown in the right figure.
In this case, all
tensors are partitioned
along both row and
column machine.
Each device basically
stores a sub region of
the original tensor and
works on its own separation.
In this case, there's
still no communication.
Yeah, because the difference
between these two is
basically you partition or you
assign regions differently.
But there's no communication.
Okay. So basically,
depending on the dimension
of the tensor and
the lumber devices,
for example, I can
generalize this into
four dimensional tensor or
the in transformer, right?
I can have 1,000 devices.
Okay. And depending
on this dimension of
tensor and also the
lumbre devices,
there are a lot of
other variants.
And, for example, for
five dimensional tensor,
there's a five level four loop,
and, which leads to
more part histrgs.
But the thing here
is no dependency,
so there's no communication.
Okay? Of course, we're
going to do this, right?
So let's move on to more
complicated case, met M. Okay.
Met mo basically corresponds to
this three level
for loop, right?
And similarly, we can paralyze
one loop or we can paralyze
several loops together,
and assign the computation
to different devices.
Okay. So basically, let's
look at each loop, okay?
So loop I and loop J,
they are very easy to paralyze
because there's no
dependency, right?
They are the independent loops.
Okay. And no carried
on these four loops,
and we can arbitrarily split
these two loops on
different devices.
But the complicates in
Mami basically we have a
loop K. This loop K,
we call it a reduction loop
because in this loop k,
we are accumulating the results.
I think you did this
in your homework.
This is a reduction loop,
and if we paralyze loop K,
we basically need to accumulate
the partial results
from all devices,
which can be done by by what?
Bio coommunication
primitive, what is that?
Or reduce. Yeah. Because
we have partial results,
so basically accumulate results.
Again, if we have
four devices denoted by
four different colors,
we also use gray
here to denote if a tensor
is replicated or not.
So first, we can paralyze,
uh, basically loop I.
This means that matrix C and
A have to be partitioned.
Each device, um, so here,
this difference okay.
This is different from pre
phis Y is element addition.
But here, if I choose
to partition A loop I
then A will be
partition Be I is basically
a dimension of A,
and I is also dimension
of the resulting matrix.
But here, I cannot
part in B, why?
Because if I choose
to partition loop,
then B has to be replicated
across all devices.
No the difference, MO
is quite different.
Okay. Um, okay.
In order to compute
this assigned portion,
each device has to access
the whole matrix B.
That's my point.
Therefore, to run this computation
without communication,
matrix B has to be
replicated on all devices.
And this can also be illustrated
by this block matrix
application notation,
where C and A are split into
four blocks where B are
replicated on all devices.
Okay? Any question?
Good, right? Okay.
We're going to make it
more and more complicated.
Okay. The second case is
basically to paralyze loop K,
which is the reduction loop.
Similarly, we can't
derive that matrix
A has to be column protein
and B has to be partin.
Why? Because K is a
dimension of both A and B.
If we choose to part in loop K,
then we have to part
in both A and B.
Okay? To get the result of C,
we need to use reduce,
like I said, because after
this commutation device
only have a partial sum,
reduce the results to
get the result C. Okay.
Um, so basically we need to
use reduce to accumulate,
the partial reduction results.
And the final C is replicated on
all devices because of it
as a result of reduce.
Okay? This can also be
illustrated by, this notation.
The red notation,
I think you are
very familiar if I read
it in this form, right?
I part in A, following
these columns,
I part in B, following us
and just add them together.
And each part of communication
happens only on one device.
Okay. This basically give you uh
some very low level like
visualization of what's going
on when we paralyze memo.
We can also paralyze
two loops together,
and things will become
more and more complicated.
For example, we can
paralyze loop I
and loop J because
these two loops are
not reduction loop,
so we don't need or reduce.
As figure.
Matrix C is both
column partitioned
and lo paritioned
into four regions,
and each device is responsible
for computing one region.
In order to compute this
C without communication,
matrix A and matrix B how
to be partially tiled.
So do you know what
is partially tiled?
You first decompose it
into two parts and
then you tie it.
Okay? And I will
give you some reading
material later, but uh,
let's grind this a
little bit later,
basically images and B have
to be partially
tiled matrix A is
partitioned along the
row into two parts.
The first part is
replicated both
on device one and
device B. You got.
Basically we part Images
A using row party,
and then we replicate the
upper part onto two devices,
the right part into
another two devices.
That is how we part
matrix A here.
The second part is wrap it on
both device three and four.
By storing A and B in this way,
we can basically compute C in
parallel without
any communication.
Same for matrix B, what
do we do is basically we
first column part in
matrix B into two parts.
But here we have four devices.
We rap eftter part on
two devices and wrap on
another two devices,
we can proceed this computation
without problem
no communication.
Similarly, we can parallelze
both loop I and loop
K. The results,
this basically results in
partially tiled output C. Um,
and because we
parallelse loop K,
we also need an use to get C.
Okay? And as you can see,
uh, there are a lot of variants,
depends on which loop you
choose to paralyze and,
and how you map the loops
to your devices, right?
And actually, it
is very tedious,
um, to basically
go through this.
It's very tedious. There are
many many possibilities,
but it's not impossible.
I just take a p like one
day to grind this, okay?
And I hope you spend
some time grind this.
And for this two dimension memo,
there are only like 16 cases.
Yeah. And you can basically
understand all these cases.
You can enumerate them, okay?
But there's something
that even more difficult,
that is um, column two D. Okay?
A is basically actually,
it's before, right.
E is basically seven
level for loop.
And we can characterize
loops one by one.
So like I said, I think
I did this before.
This is the spatial loops,
and it's very easy.
There's no reduction. So you
can arbitrarily split it.
Okay? And these are basically
another stencil computton loop,
and um this is basically
handling the boundary condition.
You need to be very careful
because you sliding
the uh convolutional
filter from left to right,
from up to bottom and you want
to handle the boundary
condition, okay?
Apparently, this one is the
most difficult because it is
a reduction loop you
are accumulating
results in this loop.
And another two reacting loops.
But you don't have to
paralyze it because it's
a very small reaction
only five elements.
Be most convolutional
two implement,
you only use a small filter.
Okay. In order to
paralyze this operator,
you can imagine how many cases
you need to enumerate a lot.
But we're not going to do this.
Okay. It's fine.
Yeah. Let's give.
Okay. I think the reason
I go through this is because
I want to give you first,
understanding how we
paralyze a single operator.
It's essentially like we choose
a few loops to paralyze to
partition and then we might
each partito um a device.
And because of the
way we partition, uh,
it will result into
different commuting patterns
and communicating
patterns. Okay?
So so far, you have learned how
to paralyze a single operator.
Now, let us basically
move to a graph and
see some examples.
Okay? So in this page,
we all show that basically
data partism is actually
a special case of
intraoperatism.
I think we did this, but
I just want to recap.
Okay? So first,
we'll use legends
to represent whether tensor
is replicated row parison
and common parison,
of course, and we
will use two types of
intra parallel strategies
for matm here.
Okay? Um, so the type one
is basically we partition
the met along row, right?
If you still remember
this type one,
we don't need any
communication, right? Okay.
Because if we choose this
type one partitioning,
the input A is partition and
the input B is replicated and we
get subaring results
on the result matrix.
Okay? The type B
basically partitions,
the inner loop
reduction K, right?
And so if we do this
type two partitioning,
then type two basically parting
both inputs along the
reduction dimension,
uh it basically requires
finish this computation,
it requires or reduce, right?
Okay. Now, let's draw
them graph for two
layer MLP, right?
So here is a forward path.
The wet W one and W two are
basically replicated.
This is data partism?
And all other communications
such as Mat Moss and Relu,
um, they are partition
along the batch dimension.
Okay? Uh, there's
no communication.
So running this requires
Then we draw the
backward graph, right?
And now, I reveal the
whole figure to you.
I think I did this when
I talk about data pism.
Um, the backward
pass consists of
one type one memo
and Type two memo.
Right. One type one memo and
two Type two memo. Okay.
Um, so it requires some
reds on the gradients,
and this is basically
the same as datapism.
Okay? Now, I basically connect
this datapism communication
to this operative partitioning.
And now you can see, Datapism
the reason dataparism
requires reduce is because we
choose to partition the loop,
the metamo in this way, okay?
Later, I will show you a lot of
other parallel
strategies that they
are basically just
special cases like this.
So basically, we're basically
playing this coloring game,
we give different color
to different regions
of the operator,
and it will result into
different communication.
Okay? Any question?
Cool. Let's continue.
Okay. So when you're applying
this intra alismu
for whole graph,
there are repartitioning
communication cost on the edges.
Okay, let me explain. This is
because different operators
paralyzing strategy
might require
different partitioning
formats of the symptoms.
So we need to do
repartition or recharging.
Let's still use this two
layer MLP as an example.
Consider the edge between
Lu and the second
mano, the longer edge.
The partitioning
format of this al uh,
follows the partitioning
format of the previous memo.
It's basically inherent
from there. Okay?
Assuming this figure, assuming
the Lu is low partition.
That is, I assume the previous
graph was low partition.
Okay. It basically
inherits the sharding,
although it's Lu because Lu
is element wise, you don't
have to do anything.
Okay? So for the second memo,
um, depending on its
chosen paten strategy,
type one or type
two or type three,
it may have a
different requirement
of the input for the
input partin format.
So if the second,
meto also use a type one
partitioning strategy,
which I showed two
slides before, right?
You parting along the row.
Okay? If you choose type
one paren strategy,
then this Lu actually also
needs to be row paten, right?
Remember in type one,
the first input need to
be row partition and the second
input need to be replicated.
Okay? So if we like
this memo to choose
the type one partin
strategy, Okay, um,
We found that this rio
actually matches with
the previous rival.
They are both row partition.
Therefore, this one is
good because you can
proceed with the competon
without any problem.
Because that alo has
all the content it needed
on each device, okay?
But if the second Mdm use
a slightly different par
strategy, freedom here.
I choose a different
type of strategy.
Well, I require this
u to be replicated,
but the W two to be column part.
Okay? And in this case,
this alo needs to be
replicated, right?
Which means that
both devices need to
have a copy of the Lu results.
Okay? Uh, in this case,
you can see the edge becomes a
slightly different one.
So what is that edge?
It is a connective
communication parameter.
I think I cover. Okay.
Yeah, it's all gather.
Yeah. So in this way, if you
choose different
patina strategy for
different metamol you suffer
a repartitioning cost,
and this repartiting
cost will become
a format of a connective
permissive. Okay.
And in this figure is
basically all gather.
Okay. Cool. So in
order to minimize the cost of
executing the entire graph,
we also need to carefully
choose strategies
for each operator to
minimize this
repartining cost when we
design our partin strategy
for the entire new network.
That's the point I want to
make. Just to recap, right?
So I think now you can
basically enumerate
all the possible
communicating costs
when you do recharging, right?
I think you guys are very
familiar with this
figure already.
Um, repartitioning is basically
like we ask you to swap
the coloring scheme of
the tensors, right?
And depending on how
you want to swap,
you basically introduce
connective primitive.
Okay. Okay, let's summarize
the problem of paralyzing
all the operators in
your graph, okay?
So given a graph,
for each operator,
there are multiple paralyzing
strategies for it, okay?
And our goal is to pick
one parallel strategy for
each operator so that we can
minimize the cost of
executing the entire graph.
Does that make sense?
So I'm basically
stating this problem as
an optimization now.
Okay? You want to pick a
coloring scheme for each node,
and then you enumerate
all the possible commuting costs
and you want to
minimize that cost.
That will basically make
your graph run fast. Okay?
So the cost basically consists
of the node cost
and the edge cost.
Okay? The node cost are
basically computation
and communication cost.
Because when you choose,
when you choose a
particular type
of pigon you already
have some cost.
You choose type two mama
paig you have or reduce.
Right. Okay. And the
second cause is edge case.
That is, you choose protein
srgy for that node,
and you choose protein
unit for second node.
And because of the sharing
of the first node,
output and the second nodes
input are not all green.
So you're suffering edge case.
That is, you need to reshare and
that shard comes at a
form of connecting.
Therefore, if you want to write
down this problem is basically,
um, that equation, node
cost plus edge cost.
Edge cost is a resting cost
and nod cost is a cost
inherent to the specific type of
parting strategy you
choose for our p. Okay.
And now I think you roughly have
an idea how to solve
this question, right?
One easy way to solve this
problem is basically,
you enumerate all
the possibilities.
You keep enumeraating the graph,
and you basically enumeraating
every type every possibility,
how you can partition operator.
And once you lock down
a possibility of the partitioning
of all the operators,
you basically can't derive
all the cost, right?
You write down, how many
connective communication
I incurred because
I choose this.
And basically, then
you start optimizing
right you try to figure out
the one that basically
has the lowest cost.
Okay. That is
basically intraparism.
Okay? It is slightly
different from Inter.
Still remember in Inter, our
goal is to minimize bubbles.
Who a schedule that
minimize bubbles,
and we want to make sure
the stages are equivalent.
Okay? But in Intra is
basically this equation. Okay?
Any question? Cool. I
hope you get it, okay?
If you don't I hope you
spending more time
understanding the slides, okay?
And this is very
important because
once you understand mathematics,
you will be able to understand
all the partisan
people invented today.
Okay? What they are doing is
basically try to
minimize this cost.
Okay? So to solve this problem,
people have used
various solutions,
including, manual design,
randomized search,
dynamic programming, and the
integer linear programming.
As I said, they
are basically the
optimizing servers to
solve this problem.
Okay? And I will show
a few solutions which
are very notable.
Okay. I will first
introduce some
strategies that are
manually designed
for specific notes,
including AlexNet
Makaton RM and THR MOE.
AlexNet is the beginning
of deep learning, right?
Macron RM is the one for media,
okay? Use every day.
TR is a one by Google.
Okay? As well I introduced
several systems that
basically, designed for this.
Okay? So right from
the beginning of
modern deep learning,
um, people start
using intra partism.
Okay? Um, Alex a good example.
This figure was quoted
from Axon paper, right?
And I also showed this figure
in my first lecture, okay?
Um so basically in this
figure, you can see,
the author tries to
convey a idea where
the layer was partitioned
and each layer has a part,
acute different uh on
different devices, okay?
And basically it partitions
a group convolution,
uh into two parts and
align them to GPS
this enables Alexa to
basically increase
the top one accuracy.
Uh, buy almost
like 2% on EB net.
But just doing this because
you home multi people who train.
E. A more recent example
is basically Microtron RM,
and this is a given reading.
I think at this point,
you guys already
understand that paper.
But what I try to do is
I basically try to draw
the connection between the
strategies in that paper and,
what I explained in the
mathematical modeling.
Okay? So basically, it used
intraoperatism to train
the language models,
and it designs a very
specific strategy to
paralyze the MLP and math
attention in the transformer.
So here, um, I basically
show the figure
three from the paper on
how to paralyze the MLP.
Um, and a similar
stretch is also
applied to the multi head
attention if you read a paper.
Okay? These figure looks
very very complicated.
And we can simplify it once
you understand our model.
No cost and edge cost.
So how to simplify it.
Basically for this
two layer MLP,
we cannot do data
parison because
the weight matrix is too large.
To partition it while minimizing
the communication cost,
we can make the first weight
matrix column partition
and the second row partition.
And by doing this, we
only need to do one or
reduce during the forward and
another reduced during backward.
Okay. This is basically
our visualization for
the microtome paper.
Does this make sense? Okay?
Yeah. And if you just read
try to parse the graph,
you can see, we basically
just have to use.
Okay. Yeah. Um, and
note that some compution
such as dropout
are replicated because
dropout is pretty minimal.
Okay, so we just need
to replicate them.
Okay? But this is pretty
affordable, yeah.
Okay. And today, this
strategy has a lame.
It's called tenser Perl.
Okay. If you go to
any library like
VOMhuinf deep speed microphones
called tenser Barrel.
And it's essentially described.
Okay. Okay. Now, you
understand Megatro RM.
Another example is
basically G hard MOE,
this hard MOE is basically
the first inventor of the
so called per parallel.
Okay. It is a new strategy
for partitioning
experts in MOE model,
and I'm going to cover
the next lecture.
Okay. Per parallel is basically
the key technology
enables Deepi with three.
Okay? Again, I will
show the figure from
the paper on how to paralyze
model you can see this
figure is very complicated.
And uh I'm going to simplify
it using our notation.
So basically what this
paper is doing is
basically for the normal
transformer layers,
it basically does data paring
which is straightforward.
So basically the weights, and
basically replicate it
for the normal layers.
But for the MOE layers,
we partition the weights and
the batch met along
the expert dimension.
And this minimize
the communication.
And you can go back and enumerate
all possible partition.
This is the one that
minimize the communication.
Okay. And you can see
expert design is
indeed expert design.
Okay? Yeah, a lot
of augmentation.
And to switch between
the normal layers to
the MOE layers, we
need a communication.
So what is the communication?
Let me highlight it.
So what is the
communication here?
Sorry? It's at.
Yeah. It's basically auto.
Okay. Makes sense, right?
Because we are swapping the
partitioning dimension.
So that's why it's auto.
Now, you understand why
deep sig inte a lot of
effort on implementing a really,
really fast auto
auto is super small,
because you want to
partition in dimension,
you have to do Auto and
that's all need to be
fast otherwise sonal, okay?
Cool. You get it.
In this homework,
I ask you to implement auto,
but I never ask you to use it
because in the third
part of the homework,
I ask you to basically
use or reduce you
write to Tinder Parl which
is this one ask you to do this.
But in the next homework,
the first assignment,
you're going to do this.
Basically you use your own
auto to implement this part.
Okay. Okay. So this slide is
pretty important for you
to finish the alignment,
first problem of
the next homework.
Okay. Cool.
Okay.
Any question. These
two are basically
the most used intra
parallel strategy.
Let me repeat again,
ten parallel,
where basically you partition
the two weed matrix follow
in different one row,
column, and you
incur one or reduce.
Another is expert parallel,
where you basically partition
the patch met follow the
expert dimension at the MOE,
but you do data parallel
at the normal layers.
And when you switch from
the first party to the second
parity you incur auto.
Okay. That is the idea.
Okay? Now I'm going to introduce
a third part of interop.
It's called zero optimor.
This one was invented
by Deep Speed Team,
this one is also one of
the most used um optimizer,
parting strategy.
In petrology you want to find
a different name for it.
It's called FSDPFully
shared data parallel.
But essentially, their
mechanism is basically
based on this zero
opmeor. Let me explain.
So basically, uh, this
project is called
Zero oppmentar and it's
a memory oppmentation,
um, of data datapoism.
So recall in datapoism we
replicate motor ways, right?
Um but this is not the
only thing we replicate.
So for example, when we choose
to use that atom Oppener, um,
uh, when we do this kind of
mixed precision training,
we also need to store FP
32 master copy, right?
I still remember
in memory lecture,
we also need to store all
those optimal states,
first and second moments,
which are also stored in
LP 32 high precision.
Okay? And this
auxiliary states from
optimor actually is much
larger than LP 16 weights.
It takes a lot of memory.
I hope you still
remember the factor.
So for the atom Opmeor it
takes a factor of 12, right?
And for the rest, it only
take a factor of four.
Okay, it's three times
the weight and gradients.
Okay? And to solve this problem,
this paper proposed to
partition all these sensors,
okay, into three stages.
Okay. Uh This table
basically shows,
the memory usage and
communicating cost of
one in a data parallel and
three stages of their oppumentu.
Okay? And this table is one
of the most important
slides today as well, okay?
And you should
internalize this later.
Okay. And this will be
super helpful for you to
analyze the cost when
you do FSDP, okay?
Um, and here, basically,
let me introduce a notation.
So let M be
the amber parameters and
M be the ambo devices.
You are going to
perform parallelism.
Okay? Um assuming we use
Atom optimizer with LP 16
mixed precision training,
the optimeor states,
it takes how many?
12, right? I repeat this many,
many times. Okay. You
need to remember.
The gradients is two, right?
Because it's PC 16, right?
It's two bytes. That's what two.
The model is two,
because it's also two.
Okay. Therefore, if
you do data partism,
sically you are saying,
I'm going to replicate all on
all devices only partision
along the badge dimension.
Therefore, the memory cost of
each device is basically 16.
Does that make sense?
Okay, you replicate
everything, right?
And what's the
communicating cost?
I already explained
many many times,
In data partism the
communing cost is
basically all reduced
of the weights.
Therefore, it's all reduced to.
And depending on the stages
you choose to apply zero,
you are essentially partitioning
different parts of this.
In zero stage one, you choose
to parti in optimal states.
In zero stage two, you choose to
partition optional
states and ingredients,
and in stage three,
you pi in all and depending
on how you partition it,
you will incur different
communication,
which I will help
you go through next.
But now, assume you already
know this petition,
we are able to derive
the memory cost
and communicating cost, right?
So maybe let's skip
communicating cost first
because I need to explain it.
But for memory it's very
easy to understand, right?
So if you're part
various states but
not partying ingredients
and model ways,
then your per device memory is
basically these two
will be replicated.
There is a term of four.
But this one is partition
across all N devices.
Therefore, each device only
need to stor 12 divided by
N. This is basically
the memory cost of 01.
Similarly, you can do
exactly the same thing
that you keep piting
more and more,
and then you are
basically amortize
these two terms
across all devices.
That's why in sty three,
each device only need
to store 16 divided by
N. That's a big memory
saving compared to datapat.
Okay. And you also
know that basically,
the difference between
zero stage one, two,
three, they are essentially
like these two.
Okay. And the big part is,
like I said, operal state
because there's a 12.
Okay. Okay. Now, you
understand the math.
Let's go through each stage.
Let's try to understand
the communication.
Any question? Okay.
One more word.
So I petric if you do FSDP
that is fully shaded data
Barrels basically this one.
There will say
three. It's called
fully shaded data Barrel.
That fully means everything
is shared. Okay.
Okay? To help you remember.
Okay, let's see what
zero does, okay?
So the key idea of zero is to
replace or reduce with reduce
scatter and or gather.
Okay? This equation, help
you still remember, right?
I covered this in
collective communication.
Okay, let me change my pin.
Okay. So the left hand side
and the right hand side have
the same communicating cost.
But by doing this decomposition,
we can partition more replicate
answers and computations.
So here is Wanina data parison.
And it runs or reduce to
accumulate partial results,
partial gradients, I said
that other ways and opener
states are replicated.
That's why this graph
looks like this.
Okay? No, I already zoom
into the opener part.
Okay, I ignore the forward
and backward part.
Okay. So here we start with
a partial gradient because
we part in along a row.
And after the backward
recommendation,
each device has a
partial gradient.
But as I said,
in data parism we
replicate everything,
including open mender
states, right?
In order for the open
miner to compute,
we find that there's a there's
a restarting cost, right?
This opium need a full copy of
ingredients on HDS
because it's replicated.
But at the beginning,
we only have a partile.
Therefore, this is all reduced.
Okay? But that makes sense
This is data partism, okay?
So what is 02? In error two, um,
it basically replace or
reduce with reduced
scatter. Okay?
So the result of,
um, so basically here.
In R two, we said
that we are going to
partition all the
operar states, right?
Therefore, open states
this momentum like first,
second moment,
they partisonFolloing
in the batch dimension.
And here in S two,
it replaced or reduced
with reduced scatter here.
The result or reduced scatter
is still partitioned.
Because most of the later
competon are element wise,
the computation can be
done on partition format.
No problem. That is
open states are patina
and each partin only perform
its own competition.
It's fine. Okay.
But at some point,
we need to store
the gradits and open
states in parison format.
But because of this,
right, remember this factor.
We have a benefit
of this, right?
So the open states are basically
amortized across all devices.
Okay. Um, and this
reduce the memory cost.
And after always updated,
we can basically
use them or gather.
To get the replicate width
for the next iteration.
Then we proceed to competation.
In reality, what we do
is we do this per layer.
Every time we go to one layer,
we find that um uh sorry,
it's not per layer.
It's 03, three, we
do it per layer.
But for this in opera state,
that is once we proceed
into the operar
state competition,
we find anything that
is require recharging, we
will perform recharging.
If you do the um, analysis,
you'll find that essentially
we are basically
decomposing or reduce into
reduced schedule and getter.
If you compare the upper
graph and lower graph,
you'll find that
the communicating
cost is exactly the same,
because all reduce equals to
reduce scatter plus
or gather, right?
In this graph, you
do one reduce.
In this graph, you do reduce
scatter plus orgater.
But the memory is much better.
In the second graph, all
the operant states
they are partition.
But in the first graph,
they are replicated.
This is zero C two.
And now let's try to
see how we can
partition more stages,
more tensors to
get zero C three.
Here is still zero C two.
Basically, um, the widths
are still replicated, right?
I zero stage two, we
only partition the um,
gradients and the
operant states.
The widths are still replicated
because both forward
and backward requires a
full copy of the weights,
so we replicate the weights
to reduce the communication.
But if the model is too large,
we can also part in the width,
as well to get zero stage three.
As you can see, compared to
zero S two and zero stage three,
what do we do is we continue
to part in these weights.
Okay. Here in those two,
we replicate the width.
But I said, this width is
going to be pretty big.
For example, when you
GB really is big.
You also want to partition it.
And what's your partition it?
Because during the
spec competition, uh,
you require this one to
be a full copy like this.
So in order to recover
from here to here,
what do you do is basically
you perform all together.
And you can do this
layer by layer.
That is because your weight
is is partion now, right?
And you proceed to one
layer and you find
the layers with partition
across all devices.
But in order to
compute the forward,
you have to get the full
version of the width.
What do you do is you perform
an gather to get the width,
and you proceed to commutation.
And once you finish computation,
you proceed to the
next layer and you
throw away the or
gather results.
You still preserve one
chart on your device.
Okay. To summarize,
the difference
02-03 is basically a trade
off between memory
and communication.
So if you want to upgrade 02-03,
you are going to
see be more memory,
but you are going to pay
the cost of one or gather.
That's why the communicating
cost of 03 is 1.5 ordos.
Because reduce Gater
and orgaeryeach
basically half or
redos. Any question?
Okay. Let me consolidate
this understanding.
I think I explained
the difference between
all these four different
paten the memory cost,
now you understand it
is basically putting
one more into the upper
part of this one.
Now you understand
the community cost.
In dataparism community
cost is reduced.
In stage 12, the
commuting cost is
basically decomposing
this reduced
into reduced setter and
orgether, it's the same.
But if we continue
to evolve into 03,
we are introduced
one more orgether.
It's 1.5 reds.
Yeah. Reason to use one?
Very good question. 01 is
already like no one use that.
Yeah. Why? Because if you
compare these two numbers,
communication cost is the same.
But zero C two
saves more memory.
Yeah. So today,
people start with 02.
Yeah. Okay? Okay, this
is very important,
and I think that give you
a lot of reading on this,
and you should connect those
readings to this illustration,
and I think it will enhance
your understanding.
Okay. Next project is
basically match tender flow,
It is a system
developed by Google for
writing model parallel
tender flow programs.
And the key idea here
is basically specify
the Pagen strategy by
mapping tenser dimension
to match dimensions.
So here is a code example.
User need to use this special
API for writing programs.
And in the code, users give
every tensor
dimension a lime and
every match dimension
lime. So what is mash?
So Mash is basically a
matrix of devices arranged,
for example, arranged in
like two dimension, okay?
And, um the user
defined a mapping
that basically maps
the tinder dimension
to match dimension.
And the system will
basically generate
a paralyzed tinder flow graph
following the specialized
mapping, okay?
And this system requires
a rewriting of the
whole program.
So it is not very
user friendly and
later it was replaced by
another system, okay?
And this is GSMPDPMD is
basically considered as a
successor of the messenger flow.
It follows a very similar
compiler based approach,
but it generates
that idea, okay?
User do not need to
write the whole graph.
Instead, they just
insert some notations
to specify the parallel strategy
of certain important tensors.
And later the compiler
will basically propagate
the partntrategy
to the whole graph
and generate a partons
strategy for the entire graph.
There are some automation here.
Okay. And last, I
want to point out
that intraop and interop,
they should be combined.
Okay? Because there
are trade offs between
these two kinds of
parisms and we can
combine them to
exploit the trade
off and achieve the
optimal performance.
Okay? Here is the
computer graph, right?
And, which we slice
into four stages.
Okay. And instead of assigning
a stage on one device,
we can basically assign each
stage to a to a device mesh.
A group of devices.
And, um, for example,
we can add four GPUs to
ask you the first stage,
two GBs second stage,
and six GB the third stage,
and two GB first stage.
So why would do this? Reason is
pretty simple
because like I said,
in Pipeline parism
you want to make sure
the ascuon time of which
stage is the same.
So model, if your neuralnetwork
graph is heterogeneous,
that it's not like
equivalent layers,
then you have to align
different devices
for different parts
of the stage, right?
Okay. And once you
align this you
notice that actually for
that small stage blue stage,
we are asking them in
four devices and how to ask
you a stage in four devices.
That is where you how to
also do intraparis, right?
So so basically inside
of the G stage,
you hold multiple devices.
And what you do
is basically, um,
you also introduce some sort
of intraparism
inside of G stage.
And this method has actually
achieved the best
scalability, okay?
The way you skill this
deep neuronal computation
beyond say 1,000 GPU
is basically this.
Okay. And I think today,
if you want to train
a neurotro on say,
ten k or 20 GPU,
you have to use this
kind of strategy.
Okay. Any question?
Okay. So to summarize, okay, um,
we can paralyze a single
operator by exploiting,
uh, its internal partism.
To do this, for Hu
computation graph,
we need to choose
strategies for all nodes in
the graph to minimize the node
cost and edge cost. Okay?
Um, and last, this
interrupt and the interrupt
can be combined to achieve
the best performance, okay?
And in this part,
I think we primarily
focus on partism.
But in reality, what
you do is basically,
you also want to combine this
with what I covered in
my previous lecture.
Okay? You want to enable
this partism while
you also enable some sort
of memory opposition.
You turn on grading
checkpointing,
you turn on swapping.
You also turn on quantization,
specification and some low
rank approximation in order to
fit your model into limited
lumbo devices, okay?
Because TPU is so expensive.
You want to treat your model
with a lot of its cost.
Okay, so this is basically
the end of, uh intra partism.
Any question? Yeah.
Okay. Uh huh.
Both. Of course, both.
Yeah. Because inside the
mess you are doing intra op.
You have a me, yes, but
minic is just like you have
a super high bandwidth.
You still want to
minimize the lumbar,
the volume of the message
you communicate between An.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. You does
not mean that you have infinite
the communication has no cost.
Yeah. If you are not careful
on designing the strate,
you are still going to be small.
Okay. Okay, then let's
move on to the final
section, auto part edition.
Okay. Um, I think
the idea of Autopart edition
is very very similar
to compiler.
So, you know, computer
scientists they always want
to automate on workflow, right?
Designing this
kind of, like, um,
Uh, paras reality is very
tedious and very difficult.
You have to enumerate,
like I said,
and you count cost.
Okay? So the idea is why don't
we actually automate them?
In fact, automation
makes lot of sense
because I think in
basically past few years,
you can see people develop
many different models.
Okay. Even today, models are
still evolving a little bit.
For example, you evolving from
GBR rmers into MOE into
something like MLA, right?
And meanwhile, you have
different sorts of
pisms like data.
Operator, zero Pipeline Pism.
And depending on which
model you design
and which partism we
are going to choose?
People roughly design a
system. Okay, for it.
Okay. And you can see, if
we continue to skill the
number of models and pisms,
we are going to design
one more systems.
The idea is basically,
why don't we just
actually reuse some
of the systems,
right? The compiler philosophy.
Why don't we reuse
some component,
so we can automate this process.
Okay. Yeah.
And also it solves the
problem that facing many,
many developers, which are
not parallel system developers.
That is, which one is
which podism is the right
fit for my model, right?
Okay. So if you forget
about exist systems,
so what if I tell you that
there's such a system am?
Given arbitrary model
and class config,
I will automatically figure out
the best suitable
parallel strategy
that maximize the training
performance, for example.
And basically we write down into
this kind of opening
equation, right?
We want to maximize
the performance,
where we want to figure out the
best strategy and the strategy
is strategy shoot as a
combination of inter inter parts.
Okay? And this is
basically the problem
that autoparts
trying to solve, okay?
So how can we solve
this problem?
In the previous content
of the lecture,
we have basically established
some mathematical
understanding of how to
analyze the cost of
inter and intra, right?
Now, what we do is
basically we write down
the cost into one equation
and we try to solve it.
Okay? So remember, our model
is a comio graph, right?
And such as this MLP.
And our class in most
setup is basically
a cluster of nodes
where each node
is installed with a few GPUs.
And like I said, inside of GPU,
you have manik which
you have a decent
amount of bandwidth.
But between nodes, you have
just a little bandwidth
to communicate.
And we try to figure out a
strategy where we put this,
we partition the
graph in a way that
run in the most
efficient way. Okay.
And as you can imagine, um,
I already talked about
so many possibilities
how to partition
operators and stages.
And apparently the
sur space is huge.
To give you a sense how
large the sur space is, um,
the number of operations in
real model is between 110 k,
right? A lot of mad mods.
Okay. Number of operator types
is basically 2,200 and if
you want to model them more.
But I already said
that the most important
operator space is Mm.
Okay. And the
classroom size, right?
You can actually models up
to 1,000 GPS or even more.
Okay. So you have to basically
iterate on this space.
Okay. So in the past,
researchers in the area,
they basically developed
three categories of
methods that can basically
automate this kind of pardon.
The first one is search based.
This one is very
easy to understand.
You just keep enumerating.
Okay. And once you
have a strategy,
you run um on
your classroom and you
get a run time, right?
And once you have a run time,
you basically try to search
around those areas
where you think are
more promising and
you return the
best one after your
budget was exhausted.
Okay? And that's indeed one
of the most effective way.
That most companies are doing.
They're basically searching.
The second way, like I
said, similar recipe,
learning based, merge
learning for systems.
And we basically formulate
it as a learning problem
and we try to train a model
that can predict what's
the best strategy.
And it's slightly better than
search base because
in search base,
you're basically
doing some kind of
a brute force searching.
But in learning
based, what you do
is after you collecting
of your data points,
you are able to train a model.
Hopefully, this data points
some trends that your
model can capture.
Therefore, it can basically
help you accelerate your search.
Okay. And the third method
is basically opienhmbs.
For Opiend hin Base,
essentially the same as search,
but you are introducing
some smarter
like open ended servers that
can accelerate your search.
Okay. What I'm going to do
next is I'm going to very
quickly go through the second
one and the third one.
Okay? So the second one,
I think one of the most
famous work is this one,
it's called device
placement organization,
still from Google Brain.
And the first author now
is faculty at Stanford.
If you're interested
in applying for BC,
she's pretty good. Okay.
And um um, in this
class, basically,
people use learning
based methods to solve
this basically, uh
discrete ogenation.
One of the most
representative approach
is basically this RO,
um, Clock RL also called
device placement organization.
So on the left, we see a
tensor flow, continuo graph,
visualized interparty the
approach basically aims
to design assign a
device placement
for each node in the graph.
That is giving each node
a device color in order to
maximize the distributed
execution performance.
And here, the approach
basically works only on the
space of interoperatism,
as you can imagine,
because it actually
only assigns one
color for each node.
That's why it only captures
the possibility in
interrupt not interrupt.
And given this space,
it's basically use
a machinery model to
predict the placement of
each node in the graph.
Well, sometimes, especially in
the early phase of training,
the machinary model
can go wrong.
I basically evaluated
this prediction on
real cluster to get its real
runtime. Uh, performance.
I need to then fits the
real random data back to
the predictive model and
update its performance
using policy gradients.
So policy gradient is
basically the one we use to
train reimburse
learning models today.
And um PPO, DPO GRPO,
they are all policy gradients.
Okay. I need to repeat
this policy gradient
update process
until a good enough
model is fun.
Good enough strategy is fine.
Okay? Like this.
Okay. And in the circles
the machinery model is
basically materialized as
a simple recurrent neural
network shown on this slide.
Okay. This arm basically
works as follows.
So it first, nearize
the cotero graph as
a sequence of nodes.
And then each node
corresponds to one operator.
That is nariz entire
graph as a sequence,
like a sentence,
sting language model.
Okay. And I give you a name,
for example, op one up to
op 100, blah, blah, blah.
Okay. And then it will embed
each node as a feature
actor embedding.
So it's a typical recipe
of train language models,
but it's for training
commit graph.
Okay. And then you basically
once you get the embedding,
you are able to fit
this into a sequence
to sequence prediction
model, right?
You basically predict
the placement
of each node. That's it.
Okay. Very simple.
Another objective is a
typical reinforced
learning objective,
where you try to maximize
the expected reward
conditional on your placement.
And this objective can
be optimized using
policy ingredient.
Okay, so how does this perform?
According to the paper, um,
it indeed return some
placement strategies that are
20 to 30% better
than the best available
ones designed by experts.
And if you take a look,
um, at the visualization,
which is a strategy
found by this method for
the very famous inception
WT model by Google,
um, I would say
it's certainly something that
cannot be found by human.
Okay? I don't think
a human is very
intuitive to design this
kind of like a placement,
right? Yeah, it's weird.
But like I said, this
method is not very
resource efficient
because it has to
use the entire cluster
to perform a real evaluation
for one given
placement strategy.
That takes a lot of resources.
And as you probably
already know,
O is not very efficient as well.
Yeah, it's not a very
efficient learning strategy,
so it takes a lot of iterations.
That's why this method is only
populated inside of Google.
I think outside of Google,
nobody uses this one.
Let's move on to second
classroom method,
basically optimal
inst based method.
So um, since
this discrete strategy
space is extremely complex.
So the rationale behind
this option based method
is basically, um,
we try to leverage
some structures of
the parting strategy to reduce
the space until the
problem size is,
um, doable, using
existing opiors, okay?
For example, IOP server or
like DP over, this
kind of thing, okay?
And the hope is that this
space reduction, um, uh,
heuristic does not actually
lose any optimality,
which sometimes
could be true, okay?
Um, let me introduce this
method and this is my paper.
Okay. And I think
this is a good paper.
Yeah, I use this paper to
get a faculty at USD. Yeah.
Okay. Um, to begin,
um, recall that at the
beginning of this part,
right, how we explained a lot in
interop and interop parts
and their unique
characteristics.
So basically, basically
interop communication,
uh communicate less, but
has device id, right?
Bubble. But the interop
actually communicate more,
um, but it has a higher unition.
Okay. So given a communal
graph and a cluster,
so how can we find
the good strategy
from the combined space of Inter
and interop partism?
That's our problem.
So we basically design
this algorithm called Opa.
And this Opa basically
leverage the fact that
many today cluster has a
corresponding structure.
That is closely located
devices in one node,
they can communicate with Minik
which is high bandwidth, right?
And distant devices
across different nodes,
they can communicate with they
can only communicate
with low bandwidth.
Okay? And given this
kind of like, um, um,
given this kind of
characteristics
and you can basically
find alignment that is,
in the upper part
of the interperism,
they basically favor, uh
they favor some communication
bandwidths that is not so high,
because it communicate
pretty less.
So basically you can map this
interopism across nodes.
You let most of the
parism happening
between TPUs distribute
across different nodes.
But for interperism,
like I said,
they need a lot of bandwis to
communicate in order
to be efficient.
So you have to map this kind of
inter parism into veining.
So you only allow
those communication
happening into aminis.
And this basically give
you alignment like this.
So how about you just part
in working in a way that
all the inter parism
happening across link.
But all the
interparism basically
happen across different nodes.
This is a strong heuristics
because now you don't have to
search over all the spaces.
You just need to search
for each subproblem.
Does this into make sense?
Okay. Cool. Yeah, this may work.
Yeah, I hope that makes sense.
Okay um the rationale
helps Opa to basically
decouple and reorganize
the search space.
Basically, this Opa generates
a full model parallel.
Asking strategy by hierarchically
specifying interop
and inter parallel strategy
respectively at each level.
More specifically, this
Opa will basically,
uh search for inter
parallel plan at
the first level that is how
to cut the graph into
different stages.
And then at the next level, uh,
upper derives the best
interop parallel plan
for each stage of the
interop parallel plan.
And by designing
an algorithm that
are basically both locally
optimal for each subproblem.
But we don't guarantee
global optimality.
We are just designing algorithms
that can guarantee like we are
optimal at the first level
and optimal at the second level,
and we hope the yielded
strategy is good enough,
because we already leverage
the uretical mapping the
binaries between parisms. Okay.
That's a Halla idea.
Okay. And this slide is
basically give an overview of
ogenation processes, okay?
The inputs, computational
graph and computer cluster.
And this OPA goes through
two passes to do this openation.
So the first interrupt pass,
it basically finds the best
interrupt part strategy
with the dynamic
programming algorithm,
which I explain later.
And then the second
interrup path will find
the best inter parallel strategy
with integer a
programming organization.
Okay? And this optim
is hierarchical,
which means that the higher
level interrupt paths will cause
lower level interruple paths
multiple times to make
a decision based on
feedback format.
That is optimize at
two levels, okay?
And I try to combine the
results in some way.
Okay. So how do you do this?
So let's walk through an example
and show how the
op engine works.
Okay? So for the interrupt pass,
um, so basically, given
this commuting graph,
right, we need to cut graph
into multiple stages
to form a pipeline.
That's interrupt. And there
are different ways of
paging this graph,
um, in this interrupt
strategy space.
So we want to get
the best one. Okay?
I only solve for the subroglem,
I don't worry at this moment
how to solve it
inside of this stage.
Okay. So even if we pick
a way to part a graph,
such as this one choose, suppose
we pick this one,
this one is optimal.
We still need to assign
each stage to a set of
devices to ask the stage
using intrap parti.
That's the second
level of the problem.
So in order to do so,
basically we abstract out
all the devices as two D.
Device mash like
this, four by four.
Okay. And assume that
the device along
each match dimension has
the same communicating
bandwidth.
For example, for TPGPU
classroom like this,
we can set one dimension to
be all the nodes, nodes, okay.
And all the communication
along this dimension
will go through,
like I said, slow cross
node interconnects, right?
We can set another dimension
to be all the GPs
instead of node.
So communicating
along this dimension
is pretty fast. Go
through Milink.
Okay. So what we do is basically
we assign devices, um,
um, uh, to each stage by pick
the best submatch choice
from this device classroom.
So we keep enumerating.
Okay, we partition
the device into
subgroups and we assign that to
the upper partitioning and we
evaluate and find
out the runtime.
And then we keep
trying until we figure
out the one that
is the best. Okay.
Um, so basically we
basically find that
this joint problem
of how to partition
the computi graph and how
to assign each assign
how to assign each
parton stage to
a set of device from
the device mesh.
They can be nicely formulated
as a dynamic
programming program,
which basically minimize
the pipeline
execution time, okay?
Um, but in order to solve
this dynamic programming, uh,
we also need to know
the optimal time
of running a stage
on align mesh.
Because S, if you pick
dynamesh for this device,
if you pick this submash
for this part of stage,
you still need to know what is
the best way of running
that graph on this mash,
using your best introp partism.
So you are subject to
another level option
you probably want to solve,
which is for the intrap.
Okay? Yeah, I think that
is all I have today.
I'm going to finish
this next maybe
on Thursday and then we move
onto Mo. Cool. Thank you.