Okay. Welcome back.
Thanks for coming,
and let's get started.
So first, PA three is posted.
If you check GithHub
there's a p three folder.
I think the TAs will
follow up with post.
Okay. But this slide
gives you an overview.
We have four questions.
The first question, MOE.
Okay? It's basically
a continuation
of the last question in PA two.
In P two, you use or
reduced to TP Ter pl.
And here I ask you to use all
to all to do MOE.
Okay? That's it.
Yeah. There's a slightly
more difficult one
on m inference.
If you take a look
at this basically,
I'd like you to implement
speculative decoding.
Okay, I will cover
that next week.
And then, like I promised, um,
that are basically two
programming assignment,
and we have one more
slightly more
theoretical assignment.
Skinning law, okay? I'm going to
let you I'm going to give
you a few dollars and ask
you to design your own IM,
which is computer optimal,
which I will cover today, okay?
So you have the space to
design your own RM, okay?
And I don't think you need
to write a lot of code.
It's just a few passing
function to help
you navigate the design
space. That's it.
Yeah. And lastly, I ask
you to write an essay,
and it's basically 500 words.
And you can write
whatever you want.
And I want you to basically
make a conviction.
And after you take this course,
and I hope you can argue
your conviction, okay?
That is basically the last one.
Okay, pure essay, pure writing.
Okay, cool. I think TA will
follow up with a post here.
Okay. Let's continue.
I think we are about to
finish parallelism, right?
We talk about autoparalization.
I think I basically mentioned
two categories of matters.
One is learning based.
Okay, reinforced learning.
It's very brute force
that you basically,
search the plis design space and
you try to get some reward
signal, and you train a model.
The second is the
optimization based,
which is basically Opa and
let's continue Opa to recap.
I Opa we basically are given
continue graph and
device cluster.
And we take two passes,
to find out the optimal
pattern strategy.
The reason we design
two passes is
because it's impossible
to do it in one pass.
It's too difficult, okay?
And there are some
heuristics that
we can nverag
because like I said,
interop prefers,
like, low bondis
communication and
the previous high
bodice communication.
So we can basically map
the first path across
nodes and the second pass
inside of the node
using Milink, okay?
That is basically leveraging,
um, you know, hardware
properties today, okay?
So basically, we do this
kind of organization.
We first, um, split
our device cluster into a
few which I call
sub matches, okay?
And then we also split
our neural network
into different stages,
and we map the stage
to matches, okay.
And then after the mapping,
we basically perform
the intrap path,
which is trying to figure out
the optimal intrapb strategy
given stage and mesh.
And we keep enumerating
keep enumerating, okay?
And then we start
asking the problem.
So how exactly should we
solve this oomation, right?
So let's take a look
at each pass, okay?
So so in the interop pass,
essentially, we are trying to
solve for pipeline partism?
The problem is that we want to
split the graph into
stages and we want
to find a way
that basically minimize the
pipeline execution agency.
Okay. Here, we make a very
realistic assumption,
that is, we already know
the pipeline schedule.
For example, you probably
know we probably adopt
one F and B or something
very similar, right?
Because other schedule
probably don't work.
F TPP doesn't work, yeah.
And we probably just say,
we are going to
use, um WY F and B.
And given that, our problem
is essentially we try to
figure out a way that split
the new networks, right?
So if you still remember, uh,
when we try to split new
network, what's our goal.
We try to make sure
that each stage
takes roughly the same
time to acute, right?
Because if there's a straggler,
then the entire
pipeline schedule
is going to be slowed
down, by the straggler.
So this is basically
our problem, right.
So we try to split into
A B CD four stages,
and we also try to split
a match from the
entire device cluster.
So we make sure that stage
when it is assigned
on that match,
it basically exceed with
other stages with the same
time as other stages, okay?
And here I introduce
a few notation.
For example, T one,
T two, T three,
I basically a screening
time when I assign
a stage to a match,
you can see, if I
draw this scan chart,
I basically uh write
down this equation.
I find that uh
the entire Pipeline
screening latency
basically is composed
of two terms.
The first term which
I call warmup phase.
That is basically when
I just get started,
my pipeline is not formed yet,
but I start feeding batches.
I have a warm up phase which
is basically in this case,
T one plus d two plus
T three plus 34.
And then I have a second
phase, which is stable phase.
That is my pipeline
is ready form.
I have infinite stream
of batches, right?
And then I add a second term.
And the second
term is very easy.
It is basically determined
by the slowest stage.
Okay? So I have a
second term, okay?
Essentially, I'm trying
to solve this obit.
So if you do a little
bit algorithm,
you probably know this
algorithm can be solved using
a a very typical dynamic
programming approach, okay?
And you can imagine, when
is this one minimized?
It's basically when
all the stages,
um, are equal, right?
So we can basically enumerate
all those possible mesh
split and stages split,
and we keep using
dynamic programming to
prune space and eventually
we'll reach a
solution where given
the current device mash and
given this neural network,
we figure out one solution
that is closest to the optimal,
that is when all the
stages are equal.
Okay this one is
basically solvable.
That's my point, okay?
Yeah, this is how
we basically solve
the um this basically
interrupt path.
And like I said, this
problem can be solved
using dynamic
programming algorithm.
And in this um DP algorithm,
we all assume that we know
the optimal latency of asking
stage EI on its assigned math
I. Why I emphasize this?
Because when you try
to ask the stage
on assign mesh, you need
to know the optimal.
So why there's the optimal here?
Because when you try to
assign a stage to a mesh,
right, the mash also
have multiple devices.
And in our optimization,
we assume that we
are going to apply
intraperism on top of that.
And there are many possible
ways for you to choose
which intra oper parison you try
to apply for this stage
and math pier, okay?
And we want to know
the optimal here.
That's why, this is a
hierarchic opmentation.
So in the outer
optimization loop,
we assume we know
the optimal solution
in like internal loop, okay.
So So basically, here,
I'll notate it here.
So basically, we assume we
know the best solution,
the best intraop
problem solution
for this stage at
match pier, okay?
And if we know that,
then we can basically substitute
this optimal solution into
that equation and we
use our DP algorithm
to solve for the optimal
path like a solution, okay?
Any question? Okay. So then
the problem is how we can
exactly get that optimal, right?
So that is when we
choose stage partison
choose to split
the neural network
into these stages
and when we choose
to split the cluster into
these matches and when
we make the pairing,
how we know exactly what is
the optimal solution
for each pair,
each of the stages matched pair.
Okay? That basically leads
us to solve a second internal
optimization problem.
That is how we exactly
know like this, right?
The problem is that we
have a stage and we
have a choosing match. We
are enumerating, right?
Okay. And given this stage
and this enumerated math,
we want to figure out what is
the optimal way of executing
it with the best
intraop solution.
Okay? And this is
another layer of ing,
so we need to solve. So
how do you solve this?
I think I mentioned,
basically, in order
to solve this one,
we are basically minimizing
the acuten latency of
this stage on this mesh.
Thecreen latency is
determined by two things.
One is the node cost.
The second is the edge cost.
So the node cost constitute
of when you choose a
particular say partner
strategy, you suffer a cost.
And the edge cost
is when you have
two operators that are choosing
two different
parting strategies.
They need to reshared
that reshared basically
constituted of some
connective communication,
and that is a cost.
So what do we do is we
can write down this kind
of cost and we try to
minimize that cost,
and we'll try to figure out if
we can solve that opmentation.
Okay? Let me give
you an example.
So here, suppose I
use this notation,
I think you are very
familiar with this now.
And let's just look at
a little dataflow graph
where a single memo, okay?
And like I said, this
memo is basically this,
um, uh, summation, right,
this loop. Okay.
It's really a loop.
Okay. So what do we do
is we can enumerate
all possible interrup part
strategies for this mammo.
Okay? And we can basically
enumerate the cost,
corresponding to the part
strategy we choose for it.
Okay? So say, if we choose
to use algorithm one,
where we try to part
in loop I, right?
So if we part in loop I,
then the first matrix
X is row partin, okay?
And like I mentioned
in my last lake,
second matrix is
replicated, right?
Okay. And the result is this.
So what is the cost?
No cost, right?
So there are no communicating
costs, at least.
Okay. And we can also
choose to enumerate
a second possibility that is we
can select algorithm to
where we parti in Lop J.
So you basically
get this solution.
Okay, column partition.
Or sometimes you probably
prefer a third algorithm,
algorithm three, so
you get this one.
Okay? And this is
what you choose.
And there are more, right?
In my previous lecture
I said there are some partially
tiled this kind of thing,
okay, more complicated ones.
Okay. And by enumeraating
the the chosen,
um, pm algorithm, you basically
can associate each
algorithm with a cost.
Okay. Let's make it simple.
Suppose the first
algorithm has a cost one,
the second algorithm
has a cost two, right?
The third has a cost three.
Okay. And here, cost includes
not only communication
but also compute
because when you
split the operating
in different ways,
the computational time will
be slightly different.
Okay. Okay. But anyway,
let's note it as cost
one, two, three, okay?
And then this is basically
like when we try to
choose a split algorithm,
we get a cost, we suffer a cost.
Okay? Then let's extend
a little bit, okay.
And now we have a slightly more
complicated neural network
we have two metmo.
So I also put the
three algorithms,
I just explained on the panel
so you know, you
still remember it.
So what do we do is we
are going to generise
a little bit, right.
We are going to generalize from
one metmo to many many memos.
So what I do is I'm going to
enumerate all possibilities.
I'm going to enumerate
algorithm for
each matmo I will
see what happens.
In this case, say,
how two memos,
they are going to be
connected together,
and they're going
to be paralyzed.
So what I do is basically I
enumerate I first try
my first choice, okay?
I choose algorithm one for
my first memo and also algorithm
one for my second memo.
Okay? And then I
say, what happened?
So what happened is
basically I find
that their partison
are all low parison.
So if I connect them
together, no problem.
There's no cost, right?
Yeah, that's what I found.
There's no layout conversion,
no recharging, okay.
Therefore, the cost is zero.
I can just proceed
to competition
without any problem, okay?
And similarly, I continue
enumeration, okay?
I try to choose
algorithm three for
my first memo and algorithm
two for my second memo, okay?
And if I do this, I find that
that sharding and that sharding,
they are not all green.
So there's a layout
conversion, right?
And this layout of
conversing is basically,
I have to convert from um,
partial sum into
replicate it, okay?
And this has a cost, right?
I repeated this for many, many,
many times, okay?
This is all reduced.
Okay. I suffer or reduced cost.
I keep doing this, okay?
I keep enumerating all
the possibilities.
I already told you this
is the filane space.
You can do that.
And you can write
algorithm to that, okay?
And I keep doing this,
I basically enumerate
all the possibility.
For example, in this case,
I choose algorithm one
and algorithm two,
and I know that the cost
is going to be all gather.
Now, you understand
the problem, right?
So what I do what
I try to figure
out the optimal solution
for intraparism is
because I generate all
the possibilities and I
count cost, and I
add them together.
Then I try to figure
out the one that minimize
the cost equation.
Okay? Good. Cool. Like I said,
this is the cost matrix,
if you swap between
different partien you suffer
a cost and this is the cost.
Okay. And if I do this for
my entire data flow graph,
I can basically write down,
um, something like this.
When I split the operator,
my computation changes, right?
So I know there is some cost.
And when I choose different
split strategy for
different nodes,
I know they are going to there's
a chance that maybe we need
a reshting that
resharing basically
corresponds to, communication,
connective, right?
And I know there's a edge cost.
So basically my
goal is trying to
minimize the node
cost plus edge cost.
Of course, I need to
subject my memory,
like a peak memory kind
of like a constraint.
Okay? And if you are
slightly familiar with this,
and this can also be solved
using an analytical solution,
this is the IOP problem,
integer linear program.
Okay? So you keep
enumerating keeper and you
can use the existing IOP
software to solve it,
and it will give you
the optimal solution.
Okay, cool. That is basically
a global picture of Opa.
So just a recap.
Okay. I have a upper layer,
which I split the
new tw into stages.
I match each stage to
also selected submatch
from the cluster.
And in the internal loop,
I have this very
nice IOP formulation
where I enumerating
the partner strategy
for each operator I count cost.
So my oral goal is
I try to minimize
this two level
augmentation. Okay? Cool.
But if I put all this together,
then this problem becomes uh
insolvable because
it's too complicated.
Yeah, cool.
Okay. And indeed, when
we do this opera work,
it was very popular in 2022.
We get a pretty
good performance.
When we try to put
when we try to select
new work and we run
this opera and to figure out
this performance strategy,
we find that in
many, many cases,
it can indeed find a strategy
that's better than human design.
Okay, yeah. Okay,
back to my argument.
So first, I want to tell you
a fact Opa didn't take off.
Yeah, I use that paper
to get a faculty job,
but that doesn't take off.
So any reason You know argument,
right, because Opa is
automatic perdition method.
So when will this
kind of method shine,
we have a lot of new
network architectures,
Because the key value purpose is
that I can reduce
the developer's time
to figure out the perm srategy.
But what happens is after
I publish this paper,
the model is converging.
There's only one
model, transformers.
Yeah, so people don't use this.
Yeah. They just use like
expert design because there's
only one strategy for it.
Okay. Cool. I hope
that makes sense.
Any question? Yeah. Yeah,
it's better than mine.
Yeah. It's basically the 03.
03 cover last.
Okay. Cool. Yeah, you
can see this is a very
nice formulation. Yeah.
Yeah, please.
Yeah, but the data between
different companies is so
small that it defeats
the purpose of this
kind of compiler.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay, cool.
Yeah, choose the
problem to walk on.
You need to have the
quidty predict the future.
Yeah. Okay. So to summarize,
in this palism space, okay?
I think I introduced two
major classes of prisms,
intra op and interrupt.
I also introduced
a lot of system
artifacts build around it.
It basically I draw
three circles,
Inter and also I covered
automatic approaches.
Basically, megatR Mc
tensor flow and GHR,
these three belong to
Intraop because they
basically are playing with
tensor and expert partism.
And apparently MctGHR
they already taken off,
because Microtron is a
TP that use every day.
DHR, they propose a
EP expert parison
that has been used in MOE.
Okay? And I said,
GCR is basically a
continuation of new version
of Msenerflow so you can think
of them as a same project,
okay and there's a w two,
GPi, Pip dream and Dipo.
I didn't cover Dipo, but
GPiP it failed, right? Why?
Because it has a
drawback, the memory.
Right. Okay. I WY FMB is
basically the one
that implementing
MctroniT and that
project also take off.
Okay? And Pip
dream, like I said,
it has a problem on your
networks because it's
a synchronous pipeline parism
and it affects the convergence.
So this project
doesn't take off.
Okay? And there are also some
automatic systems. Okay?
To flex flow, I didn't
cover this too, but
they are earlier works.
And is basically 01, two,
three, and apparently 03
and 02 take off, right?
Because it's so simple, yeah.
And there's another
colocal error,
the Stanford faculty one.
And this one didn't take off,
unfortunately, because it
requires so many compute.
Only Google can do
that. Yeah. And also,
there's my work Alpha didn't
take off. Okay. Cool.
But it's in the middle.
Yeah. Okay, um, cool.
That's pretty much,
the space in parism.
So given that,
like I said, given
today that models are
mostly transformers,
I would say what I taught
today is basically
the one that is used
in training models.
I would say there
are very few data
that people are inventing on
in the area because model
is not changing anymore.
But maybe someday, like in
one or two years
when people study,
uh better on new models,
probably we will need to
revisit this again, okay?
Oh. Okay, then I
want to spend
probably 10 minutes
to give you a very
very practical guest,
this is very special because
nowhere else in the world,
you can get this 10 minutes,
because this is based on my
five years of tuning this.
I've been working this, you
know, hands on fashion.
I have been tuning
this days and nights,
you know, when I do
this kind of work.
Yeah. I can give you my lesson.
Okay. And if you start
working in this area,
if you start training your
neur networks using pism,
you'll probably find this
slide pretty useful.
So in general, how
do you choose prism?
So so big picture wise,
you can if your model
is not transformer,
okay, you basically can
use these compilers.
Like I said, because
that's where
compiler values
come, right, B okay.
But if your model is
purely transformer based,
okay, essentially, there's
some like design traits.
Okay, and you can
basically manually,
search following this
design traits, okay?
Uh there are a few
factors to consider.
One is, how many GP
you have, right?
Because if you have
a small and if
you have a large cluster,
the decisions are different.
Second is your model size.
You have a small model,
you don't need pism.
Large model, you need
a lot of partism.
Then JCT, job completing time,
whether you can finish
your job in given time,
and also communicating
bandwidth,
how many bandos you
have, et cetera.
Okay? Now, I'm going
to run through this.
I want you to understand
every decision point.
If you don't understand,
feel free to come to
my office because I
think this is actually,
uh the distilled slide
for the entire pism part.
Okay. You start with
asking the question,
if your model can fit
into a single GPU.
Of course, you start with
this question. Okay?
And yes, you're lucky.
You're training a small model.
Okay. And you start asking
if my JCT is okay, right?
So if I can finish my
training in given time, okay?
And if yes, then you are good.
Okay. You don't
have any pressure?
Um, but if not,
what you do is because
your model can fit into
a single GPU, right?
So you don't want to
complicate your system.
So you start skinning
data parism, right?
Because once you start
scanning with data parism,
you can accelerate
your job and you
can stay within JCT, okay?
So you basically skill with
more GPUs and by adding
more data parism you basically
stay within JCO GCT is okay.
Okay? And then, of course,
you're going to have
this branch, right?
And this is the
reality. My many models
cannot fit into a single GPU.
Okay? I think at this point,
you probably know the
first thing is still,
you should avoid
complicating your system.
Whenever you start doing
distributing system,
your code is going to
be very complicated.
So you want to start
with something simple.
You ask yourself if you can use
the memory orientation I
taught in my previous lecture.
I basically still try to apply
some memory orenation and
try to fit my model
into a single Gib.
I think in my memory
orienting lecture,
I also have a ditera.
You can go there and
look at it again, okay?
So yes, you can actually
play a checkpoint
rematerialization,
or this kind of, uh,
still remember micro
Batching, right?
Yeah. Grad accumulation is
kind of trick to fit your model,
then you ask yourself
if your J is okay.
Okay? And if yes, then
you are still good.
You don't need to
distribute systems, okay?
Of course, the next one is no.
Okay? So either when
you enumerate all the possible
memory organizations,
including remotenization,
and also green accumulation,
usually we don't do swap
because like I said,
swap is basically we are
going to slow down
your GCT, right.
So basically, you try checkpoint
remotization and, uh,
green accumulation,
and if you still
cannot fit or your CT
is basically not okay.
You start considering using
piss multiparisms, okay?
You start considering
incorporating
intra or interoperism,
um, at this point,
you should first turn off
your previous exploration that
is memory organization y.
Because most memory
organization will
treat compute for memory,
you don't want to do that.
Now, you have decided
to scale out,
so you have plenty of memory.
So you don't want to
treat treat flops.
Okay. And then at this point
you once you start deciding,
okay, I'm going to use
Multipis what do I do?
I start looking at my cluster,
how many bandos I have.
Okay? So basically,
there are two branches.
One is, I have a cluster where
GPUs are all
connected with mink.
For example, I only have GPUs,
and these GPUs are
inside one node.
Okay. Another case is
basically either you don't
have a meaning at all.
For example, you are
your Chinese firm, okay?
Or, you just don't have
a meaning, yeah, okay?
Let's go to the left
part first, okay?
Yes, I have a meaning what I do.
If you have a, you can
do whatever you want.
Like I said, you bind
basically infinite.
Yeah. Communication is
very minimal, okay?
So you do whatever
kind of pim you want,
but typically it's TP
tenerpis because like I said,
ton is pretty easy, right?
Just a single ore. Yeah.
You do that in your
homework, okay?
But if I apply tinder part
I still cannot fit, right?
Because my model is so
large, Okay? What do I do?
So two ways, one you start
turning on memory ogenation.
You start turning
on checkpointing,
you start turning on
green accumulation,
you reduce your byside effective
biside and say if it works.
The second way, of course,
you need more GPU,
GPU is not enough,
so you skill you skill
beyond GPUs, okay?
So either way, eventually
you will converge to a point
where you need to
skill out GPUs, okay?
And if you skill GPS,
you are facing the
second branch,
which is you have GPUs that are
connected using non
wilink interconnects,
which are Iternet much lower
bandwidth than wilink. Okay?
What do you do? Okay? Of course,
we need to discuss based on
the available bandwidth.
So there are many many different
networking technologies.
So two branches, okay.
If you are a very rich company,
you are open air, you are
like this kind of a big firm,
XI, then you probably in
that branch that you have
high bandwidth connect, okay?
Maybe not unwink but
pretty close, okay?
Like 100 GBPS per GPU bandwidth.
But wilink is 400 GPS per GB.
Yeah, you are only
one first of that.
It's fine. But if you are
not a rich firm, you're
probably in that branch.
So you have a very low
bandwidth. For example, 25.
If you hire if you basically try
to rent some DPs from AWS,
you are in that branch.
Okay. Okay. Let's talk
about the first branch.
So in the first branch,
if you have a lot
of bandwidth we do,
you basically try to skill out,
you need 02, right?
Because in 02, if you remember,
the communicating cost
is one or reduce, right?
Okay. And 02 has compared to 03,
the problem is, it
doesn't share weights.
Remember, the cost is 16, sorry,
it's 14 plus 40 divided
by N plus two, right?
That's 02. Okay.
You start with 02,
and the reason you start with
02 because you have
less communication.
You just have one single reduce.
But the drawback is
you waste a little bit more
memory because you
don't share weights.
Okay? But if you still
cannot fit your model,
02, what do you basically
upgrade to 03, right?
So I 03, your peak memory is
further reduced because the
two was also shared, right?
But you suffer
another 0.5 reduce.
You are paying a 1.5
reduce communicating cost.
Okay. But like I said,
because your GP has high
noise, so all reduce is okay.
Yeah. Yeah, you
start exploring 03.
Okay, you still
cannot fit or it do.
Okay. Of course, you
turn on memory cumation.
You'll start doing checkpoint,
you start doing all this
kind of green accumulation
until you can fit.
Still cannot fit.
Okay? What do you do? You
can just correct, okay.
Um, that's a joke.
Just add multiples
until you can fit.
Okay? Yeah, just pay
more money. Okay?
Does that make
sense? Okay, cool.
But of course, we want
to first minimize
number of GP use because
that was our money, right?
But if you cannot, basically
enumera all these possibilities
you still cannot fit,
you should ask multiples
from your manager, okay?
Uh, then let's explore
a brand, okay?
Now, you don't have this kind of
high banistween
GPUs across nodes.
You only have low band Wis
for about 25 GPS per GP.
Like I said, in this
case, you start
doing interoperatism.
You start introducing
pipeline Pism. Why?
Because like I said,
pipeline parism only
communicate sent residual
between boundaries.
So it's very little
communication.
You are not going to be
slowed down a lot, okay?
Okay. Once you start
considering interpartism,
you are basically introduced
another layer of complexity.
That is you have to tune
your lumber micro baatches
right to minimize
your bubble, right?
But if you increase your
number of mini batches,
like that you point out,
you are going to reduce
your arismt intensity.
So you want to strike a balance
between the lumber bubbles
and the AI on each operator.
So that basically creates
another like decision space.
You have to tune very hard to
figure out good
configuration, okay?
So tune microbatchy and
the micro baades size.
Okay? And you keep doing
this until you can fit.
If you cannot fit,
just add multiples,
okay? No more are the solution.
Okay. And, of course,
there's exception that
is you are Tip Sik.
So in Deep six's case,
you don't have wilink, okay?
You only have a kind
of like a compromise
version of link,
right by the US government.
And you also have a little bit
like boundaries between dips.
So what do you do? We are
going to cover this later, okay?
Yeah. Cool. Does
that make sense?
Okay, I want you to
understand DC in point, okay?
So this is basically today if
you are doing transformer,
you are doing AM, you
follow this dalgram.
Okay. Yeah.
For the bed connect,
do you need to connect each GPU
each other GPO how does that?
I cannot see all the
configures but I can
give you the config in IBS.
Basically IBS, they are going to
install Iranet
hardware for each GPU.
For example, if you are
going to rent, say,
P for instance, from IBS,
where you have four a 100.
Basically EGPU is going
to have one Iranet,
which means that the entire
node has eight Iranets.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. Cool. Okay.
This is the distilled version.
I hope you understand
the rationale
behind this, very important.
Then we can probably
wrap up everything here.
We covered everything.
So typically we can
end this course.
But let's move on into RM.
We are going to actually,
you're not already understand
all the techniques behind
Mergent systems, mostly, okay?
What do we do next is
basically connect the dots.
And we take a model.
That model is basically
RM and we try to
revisit techniques.
So why we make that
decision for that RM, okay?
Cool. Okay, let's move
on to our third chapter.
So in this part
of this course, I'm going
to cover these things.
Okay. I'm going to first,
of course, give you
a very quick go
through of transformers
and attention.
And then I'm going to of course,
I need to introduce skin
law because you need to
understand why we train
such large models, right?
It's because we are
following skin law, okay?
And then probably next week
we are going to
connect the dots.
We are going to tell you why we
apply this kind of
opium training.
I think you all figure out
a lot of things
pretty soon, okay?
And there's one special thing
to that is flash attention,
which is a very fast
attaching kernel,
and we have to cover them.
And then we move on our topic
to serving an inference.
And in serving an inference,
there are a lot of new
things that we didn't cover,
because that's very
special to IM.
And finally, we are going
to connecting the dots,
and we are going to
use our last lecture
to review Deep I'm
going to basically read
Withy paper with you.
I'm going to reason
why they do this.
Okay? I think you'll be
enjoying that, okay?
And lastly, if you have time,
I'm going to cover
hot topics. Okay.
Cool. Okay, so what is ARM?
So ARM is basically
token prediction, right?
So we have a prefix
and we try to model the
probability distribution.
Conditional prefix we
predict next word.
Okay. Lake token prediction.
For example, we want
to model the sentence.
San Diego has very
nice and we try
to output the next token,
right It could be
surfing weather or snow,
but we are going to
align our probability.
Same thing, San
Francisco is the city
of innovation or homess, right?
And we are going to
give a probability.
Okay? And once we have
this probability,
we are going to sample from
this probability
distribution of words,
right? That's basically RM.
Okay. And if we write
down the equation,
we basically know
that u for example,
probability of San Diego
has very nice weather.
We can basically expand
it into a lot of, like,
a factor idton of conditional
probability, okay?
We start with the
first word San Diego.
So here I take San
Diego as a single word,
okay? Uh, bear me.
And then conditional
on San Diego,
we have a probability
of next word being has,
and then we keep doing so
very city and better, okay?
And we factorism together,
we get the probability of
this entire sequence, right?
So if we write
down the mathematical
form, is basically a one,
right and when we
try to so here we
try to try to model this, okay?
And in reality, if you
want to change this kind
of model, what we do?
We observe a lot of this
kind of symptoms, right?
And this is basically
the copies we
connected from Internet
from what human in books,
we observe a lot of
this kind of things.
And we try to use maximum
likelihood estimation
to basically estimate
the primeters,
the way we design the
model is basically we
design model that is
capable of predicting
the next token, right?
And so this model
basically will take
a prefix and predict the
probability of the next token.
And by factorizing all this
together following
this equation,
we basically get a probability
of this observed sequence,
and we try to maximize
the likelihood of all
observed data. Okay?
This is typical
machine learning.
Any questions on this? No,
this is pretty good, right?
So the way that we try to model
this conditional
probability is basically
we use language model, right?
Transformers. Okay?
So how do we do that?
There are many ways,
but despite many ways,
is basically a sequence
prediction problem
where we have input x1x2,
x3x4, and we try
to predict output.
Okay? I M in nextcen predicting,
this is a little bit different
because we are going to
apply cadal relationship
that is we observe X one.
We try to predict the next word.
Okay, we observe
X one and X two,
we try to predict the next word,
because we are model
the condition.
Okay. And this is
a very typical sequence
to sequence model,
and there are many ways
to do that, right?
And I think one way is RN,
but we know RN is bad on this
because it's very
hard to scale, right?
Be ARN has those hidden states
we talked about in our
first lecture, okay?
And today's approach is
basically attention.
Attention is very
capable of doing this.
So what is attention? So
this is basically attention.
Attention is basically, uh
general attention
generally refers to
the approach that we
combine individual states.
So here we observe this
kind of words, right?
We have hidden we have
a representation,
for example, embedding for it.
Okay? And we are going to,
uh stack a lot of attention
layers on top of it.
And here is one layer.
And the way we model that
is we each hidden state at
the token position at the
hidden token position to
basically attend to all
the previous layer states.
And the way we calculate
this hidden states,
basically we try to take
this kind of weighted sum,
and here is the previous
layers observation,
and this is a weight,
and we weighted some of
them and we get the next
layers of hidden states.
This is basically
attention, okay?
And so intuitively here,
SI is a ten square
that computes how
relevant the position Ice input
is to the current hidden output.
And there are
different methods to
decide how ten square
is being computed,
but for some reason, we
convert it to self attention.
Okay. So in self attention,
basically self
attention refers to
a particular form of
attention mechanism.
So in self attention,
we have a special
mechanism to calculate the
atten square S. Okay? So
how we calculate that?
So we're basically given
three inputs Q and Q and
V. They are basically in
shape of T times D. So here,
T is the number of
tokens in a sequence,
and D is the hidden dimension,
and we call QqV
queries Ks and values.
And then remember attention
essentially doing
weighted sum, right?
So here, the weighted sum
is basically we try to do
a weighted sum over
the so called values.
Okay. You can see
here is the values,
and we try to use
Q and K to compute
that S, the ain square.
And you can see the
ten square is here.
It's basically we manipulate
how we compute the ten square.
If you look at this equation,
how we compute the in square,
is basically we add Q
and K to do a Mm, right?
And then we normalize it
using the hidden dimension.
Okay. And once we do that,
we further normalize
it using soft max.
So the weights added into one.
The thing is square
added into one, right?
And then we use this weights to
a weighted sum over the
value and we get the output.
And we keep doing
this layer by layer.
Okay. Any question?
I assume you are very
familiar with this, right?
Cool. Okay. So basically, um,
we all use QT, uh,
like a small Q KTVT to refer to
the RLT of the K matrix. Okay?
And we start asking
the question, how to
compute the output HT based on
the small QT and the bigger
matrix on timestep T, okay?
And to keep this
printing simple,
we will drop the
suffix To We all
simply use Q to refer
to QT next slice, okay?
So we are basically following
this equation, okay?
So conceptually, we compute
the output of the
following steps.
We first compute a pre soft
max at in square, okay?
Which is we take the small Q
and the as okay,
we transpose it.
Okay. And then we do
a dot product and normalize
by some constant term.
And we basically get a so
called at square, right?
This square is a
floating point square.
It could be anything, okay?
But what do we do is we
want to normalize it into,
like, within a range 0-1.
So we can basically
take a weaty sum.
So what we do is we
take a softmax, okay?
We take squares and we use
this softmax to normalize it.
Once we normalize it,
we basically take
a weighted sum over
all the rows of V,
and we basically get output
H. This is basically
self atentin?
Yeah, intuition is basically SI
computes the relevance
of QI to the query Q.
And then we do weighted sum of
the values proportional
to the relevance. Yeah.
Okay. And, of course,
can, uh, write it
in the matrix form.
And if you write
it in matrix form,
it basically that we use Q and
K Q times Q transpose, right?
And the normalizing
factor is unchanging.
And soft max is basically
like normalizing
across the rows.
And then once we
get the ten square,
we time it with V,
and we get the output.
Okay. Any question? A
good. This is simple.
Okay. I think in
previous lecture,
we only talk about
a single attention,
but in Ms, what we do is
we use multi attention.
So we have many many And
each computation is called
basically each of this
panel is called a head,
and we do multiple
casts in parallel.
Therefore, our computation has
another dimension which
is number of heads.
Okay. This is also
very straightforward.
So the intuition
is that each head
can correspond to different
kind of information,
And sometimes we can share
the heads, for example,
GQA is basically like all
has shared QV but
have different Q.
Okay. This thad attention.
And we ala call Multi head
attention MHA. Okay. Yeah.
If you look at MHA,
it basically refers to
Multi head attention.
Okay. Then I think I finished
introducing they mechanism.
Then you are probably wondering
where exactly do we get
Q and Q and V, right?
So this is also simple.
So in order to get Q and Q and,
we basically take the output of
the previous transformer layer
and we apply a
linear information.
Yeah. Here, we introduce
three learnable ways,
WQ WK and WV.
And this X for the first layer,
this x is basically input.
And for the middle
layer, this x is
basically the output of
the previous layer, okay?
And we basically tie them
together, we get QQV.
So basically QQV are all
transposed from the input
using different weights.
Okay. Cool.
Okay. And with the attention,
we can basically start
revealing the uh,
transformer block, right?
So transformer block
is essentially
we take the input X, um,
we do a linear projection to
get the QQV then
we take the QQV.
We do the self
attention. We get the Z.
And we apply some element
wise normalization,
typically layer
loam, but sometimes
we also use RMS worm, okay?
And we transpose it
a little bit, okay?
And after this layer loam,
what we do is we introduce
a two layer MLP.
Okay? We have been
doing this a lot,
right two layer MLP,
basically two matm, okay?
We use this matm to u
transpose this further
and eventually go through
another normalization and
we get the output edge.
And this edge is basically
the input to the next
transform layer.
Okay. And we keep doing
this. Okay. Any question?
Cool. Um, yeah.
But in reality, like I said,
when you train language model,
when you do language model
kind of computation,
uh, you are modeling the
conditional probity.
You want to output
the probability of
next to condition
or pervious token.
And then when you output the
probability of next token,
you don't want to you cannot
see the future tokens.
But when you do training, you
did know the future tokens.
So what do you do you
basically do this kind
of masking, right?
You still compute
the tenting square,
but you mask out
all the tenting squares
of future tokens.
Right? For example,
when you predict
the probability of
the first token,
you only see the first
token, nothing else, right?
When you try to predict the
probity of second token,
you only see the first
and second token.
And all scores on other token
positions, you cannot see.
The way you do it
is you do masking.
But you can be a
little bit smarter
here because like I said,
if you do masking, you are
wasting some competition.
You still in your matrix firm,
you are still computing all
the entries in this matrix,
but you are
essentially throw away
since you don't use them.
So you can be a
little bit smarter,
and we are going to
come back to this.
Okay, this is masking.
So in summary, transformer,
we care about decoders
because decoder is
a default transformer component
for the language models.
In language models, we have
many many transformer decoders.
And in this transformer
decoder is really
just composed of attentions
layer lo and MLP.
Okay? And of course,
our input is a sequence
of tokens, right?
So we need to transform a
discrete token into a vector,
and we use embedding.
So we have this input embedding.
Okay. And we also care
about the relative position
of token in the sequence.
We also have a position
embedding, for example,
a simple position
embedding could
be the first token being zero,
second token being one,
and I try to basically
create an embedding that 01
into another vector space.
But today, we are much smarter.
We are doing embedding called
literal embedding,
which I don't cover.
If you're interested,
you can basically
take a look at that paper.
But essentially, we have
a position embedding to
also tell us the exact
position of each token.
Okay.
And finally, we basically
go through this layer,
input embedding,
positing embedding.
Multi hitension a
few roman additions,
two layer MLP, romanidon
and we repeat.
Okay, we repeat in times,
and it's equals to
a number of layers.
And then we project it
back into the token space.
We compare the token to the
observe token
calculate the loss.
That is our loss
function, softmax.
Okay? This is essentially
transformers,
language models. Okay. Yeah.
And in this four layers,
like I said, it's
essentially a two layer MLP,
where you have input X times
weight matrix plus bias.
And once you get the results,
you take a linear function,
u or something else, time
another with W two plus a bias.
Yeah, simple. We have
been doing this many,
many times, right?
Okay.
Okay. Then let's break it down,
into, like, what are the
computing components?
The computing components is
basically, we have
self attention, right.
We have layer and residual.
We have MLPs, we
have long linear.
Apparently you have learned
this layer wise residual linear,
they are element wise
operations light,
leading just a little bit of
flops, very easy to deal with.
But self attention
very slow wipe.
I will cover this later.
MLP is very slow we because it's
metams big metam and
metamo is taking a lot of
flops to compute and
you guys already
know how to open metal. We
are also good with this part.
You already know that
kernel. Okay, cool.
In order to optimize
the RM, at least,
I think we only have one
problem is self attention,
W cover next week.
And also we have
a word embedding,
but the word embedding
essentially another memo.
Look up table.
Yeah, very simple.
And we have position embedding,
which is also very simple.
No flops. Loss function,
Softmax. You also
implement this.
Okay? No, we break
this M down, right?
So basically, from
computing perspective,
the only problem now is
basically self attention,
how to make it fast, okay?
And like I said,
models like TBD R or all
these kind of models.
So what they do is
basically, they
repeat these kind of
transformatic co layers.
Okay, the input is a sequence,
and they keep performing self
attent in the MLPelf MLP.
They repeat many, many times
and they get a prediction.
Okay.
And depending on
different kind of model,
kind of implementation,
they can basically
change a little bit,
but very small Delta.
Okay? For example,
this is the original
transformer paper,
and this is Matas Lama,
and the only difference
is at least here.
So for example, where you
insert the layer loam,
you could insert layer before
tenting or after attention.
Okay? That is called post
layer or pre layer m. Okay.
But like I said, the computing
doesn't change a lot
because it's a layer loon.
Okay. Also what kind
of normalization you
are going to use?
Some use layer. So use RMS norm.
I think you implement
this one in your
homework environment.
Yeah. Also what is the
lininear function?
The originalm is Valu,
but lama use sl.
SLO and are very similar.
Light linear functions.
And also position encoding
is basically the
position embedding.
Like we probably use different
kind of post embeddings,
but still very light.
You can see from this table,
you can see the compute heavy
part doesn't change a lot,
so it's basically MLP and
tension. They always use that.
Okay. And when training,
what we do is basically, um,
we observe the entire
sequence, right.
But our model is only capable of
predicting the next token,
not the entire sequence.
So we basically decompose
that uh probability of
the entire sequence into
a factoring of many
conditions, right?
So what do we do
is basically, um,
like we fit this
sequence into RM
and we predict at each
output position, right?
And when we predict
this position,
the second word, we are
masking the rest of the words.
Okay? We only look
at the first word,
this one, and we try to
predict the second word.
And once we have a prediction,
we compare this predict to
the exact observed
word at that position.
We calculate loss, right?
And same thing, when
we predict this word,
we only are allowed to
look at these two words.
And we do that kind of masking.
And the pretty thing,
the nicer thing here is,
You can do this in
one pass, right?
You are calcat loss
at each position,
but you can do this in one pass,
because you are basically
doing like I said,
attention is highly paralyzable.
So whenever you compute the
atten scored at any position,
you can basically
do the computation.
You don't have to depend on
the previous hidden states.
If you change this
transformation into a iron,
that's not the case,
because you have to
predict one token,
the next toenxt.
That's why attention is
super good for GPUs.
Any question? Okay. Okay, then
let's start our major topic,
okay, for this part. Okay.
This is just a recap, okay?
So we are doing machine
learning systems, right.
So we know we have talk
about tension, talk
about transformers.
But the real thing
we care about is
basically a few
questions, right?
Like, it's computing
characteristics.
So I think I already give you
this kind of like a model
when you start taking
machine learning program to
analyze. You care
about three things.
One is computer, another is
memory, another
is communication.
You care about computer
because you need
to know how many flops
I need to spend, right?
You care about
memory because you
cannot exceed the
peak memory GPs,
and you care about
communication because
you want to paralyze it, okay?
So in order to analyze
these three charcistics,
we need to basically
understand a few things.
The first thing is we need to be
able to calculate the number
parameters of language model.
Why? Because it matters.
At least we need to allocate
that amount of memory to
store the parameters.
So basically, I give
you a language model,
you need to know how
many parameters it has.
So that will determine
the minimum storage
you use to store that model.
Okay? And of course,
when you start
doing communication
when you start doing partism
sometimes you partition over
the width the width operators,
the width in the Delph graph.
And by knowing how
large the width is, you
know how to partition.
All right. Okay. Second
computer, right?
In order to know a computer, you
need to know how many flops
needed to finish the completion
of the RM program, right?
Okay? So basically,
this basically,
um, determines the
computer needed, okay?
You need to be able to estimate
how many computer needed
to finish this program.
And, of course, you
need to be able
to estimate the memory,
how many memory needs.
And like I said, memory
is associated with
a few since one is,
of course, lumber parameters.
The other is basically internal
intermediate activations,
and optimal states, also,
this kind of, you
get involved with
communication because if you
choose to partition
the activation,
you also, well,
basically influence
how many communication
you need to conduct
between different, uh, GPUs.
Okay. So three core questions
here to understand from
a computing perspective.
The first is how to estimate
the number parameters.
The second is
estimate the flops.
Third is estimate the
memory needs between
R. And once we
understand this, we know
how to paralyze it.
We know how many
to allocate to it.
And we also know
how many storage we
allocate to storage with.
Okay, let's do that one by one.
And this is so important
that I'm going to dive
into details and I'm
also going to give you
homework to do this.
Okay. First question,
how to calculate
the number of parameters
of M? Let's go through it.
So this is RMs computation,
right? Let's go one by one.
Okay. Uh, we have
a input X, right,
and this input X is going
to basically being go through
embedding layer, right?
So the embedding layer,
what it does is basically
embeach token into a vector.
Okay? So commutation
is looking like this.
We take a token. We first
transform the token
into one hot, right?
And the size of this
one hot vector is
the size of the
vocabulary, right?
And then we basically
multiply this
one hot with our
embedding matrix.
We get the vector.
Okay? First layer.
Once we have the vector, we
have a sequence of vectors.
Each vector is of dimension
D or H or each vector is of
dimension and we have a sequence
of vectors. Synchronized S.
Of course, we have
a outer dimension,
which is a backside, number
of sequences, so we have a B.
Okay. And here I choose
a language model which
performs pre mannisation,
which means that once it enters
into this transformer layer,
it will perform
romanization layer loam.
And I think you already
know how layer loom
does in homework. I'm
going to skip that.
Layer lo inside of linear loom
is are a few parameters, right.
Okay. And once you
finish layer loam,
what's the shape?
Still BSH. Okay?
Remember this, BSH is
basically the golden rule,
many boundaries in the
arms, basically BSH.
Okay? So here I'm going to have
a BSH I'm going to go into
self attention, right?
And in self attention.
So what parameters do you have?
You first project
this PSH into QQ.
In order to do the projection,
you have three
metric WQ WK and WV.
Here you have three
parameters, this.
Once you do the projection,
what do you do? You
do self attention.
You Q times K transports
normalization soft max,
then we is sum, you're done.
You can see through
this process,
there's no more parameters.
Only three parameters W
W WV. Then we are good.
Here we are only
continuing parameters.
Okay, good, good, good.
And then we go through
the next layer mization
and you know it, I'm
going to skip it.
Okay, once you
finish layer later,
you enter MLP, right?
In MLP, like I said,
it's basically two layer MLP,
and there's a ln linear function
between these two layer MLP.
So in MLP, what
parameter do you have?
To arithmetrics, and two
biases, very simple, right?
Okay. And once you finish MLP,
you do another romanization.
Another layer.
Yeah. Sorry, once you
finish fit forward,
repeat you repeat many
times number layers.
And this is determined
by the number
of layers and layers.
And once you finish these
times of trans layers,
you basically enter
another layer romanization
to romanize a little bit,
and then you'll go into
another reverse embedding.
Basically, you take your
embedding and you try
to project it back into
the vocabulary, okay.
And in many many language
model implementations,
this embedding and
this embedding they
are shared, same embedding.
So you don't introduce
any new parameters.
You use the original embedding.
And hug in phase is
called time embedding.
Okay. And in many, many cases,
it's time body is enabled.
It's true. Okay. And finally,
you enter softmax, you
calculate your loss.
Okay? I basically took
you through this entire
parameter counting
process, right?
So a little bit difference.
In some models, especially
in modern models,
we are basically making that MLP
a little bit more complicated.
We are using this suit GLU,
and the only difference
between the sued GLU and
the MLP is we are going to
introduce another wid matrix.
We are going to take the
output of the attention.
We first do a linear
transformation,
and then we do this
switch transformation,
and then we have another
linear transformation,
and we do a dot
product between them.
Then we go through a
third layer, MLP W three.
So this is kind of like
the amass architecture,
okay, Sug EIU.
So as you can see,
if you compare
SWOU and traditional MLP,
you are introducing
one more parameter,
one more weight matrix.
Okay? Remember this?
Yeah, Quest in two ways.
Yeah. But usually after
this, we have another layer.
Yeah. Okay. Makes sense, right?
Cool. Okay. If you start
counting the parameters,
I basically put it
here, Embedding layers,
the shape is vocabulary
size times heating
dimension, right?
So this is your
lamer parameters.
Leyenon is basically
d dimension.
You have a single parameter
which you use to romanize.
Okay? Self attention, how many?
So this is the Lama case.
So in Lama case, what do
you do is you have WQ,
WK and WV there's three,
and they are of the same shape,
which transpose you from
edge to edge, right?
So this is three edges square.
Okay. But in ama,
what do you do after attention,
you are going to do another
outer projection. Okay.
Yeah, if you check ama.
So basically, after attention,
we have another outer
projection which
do another layer of
transformation from edge to edge.
So you have another edge square.
So in total, in practice
for self attention,
you have this number
of parameters.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay, you probably ask
in self attention,
why are you using multi
head attention, right?
So we actually have
multiple heads.
So why this is, um,
still edge by edge?
Why this project WQ is
projecting from edge to edge?
A still don't want to answer.
It's because essentially
mart head the lumber head,
times the head size is still
equal to edge. Yeah,
that's a constraint.
You are essentially projected
into another you first apply
this WQ project a vector
from edge to edge,
and then you split
into different heads.
Yeah. That's what I do
for language models.
Okay. So it doesn't change the
number of parameters here.
Then you continue doing midion
which is another
hidden dimension.
You do fit forward. So here,
how many parameters
in fit forward?
So for a single
matrix is basically,
uh, H times I H is
the input dimension.
I is output dimension.
So I GBD three, I
equals to four edge.
Which means that you are
doing upper projection.
You project the hidden
dimension from edge to
four edge, and you
project it back.
But like I said, in
Lama you do sua GLU,
so you house three
of them, right?
So that's why this
number is three square.
Sorry, it's three Hi,
and I equals to four H,
so it's 12 edges square.
A lot of primeters, right?
And then you continue
doing roman edition
on this vocabulary.
Like I said, this one is
the same with this one,
so we don't count, we
don't double count.
Okay. Okay. This is
basically a solution to
your homework, okay?
Try to implement this cool.
Any question? Okay. Now, let
me ask you a question,
you look at this.
You look at. This is a parameter
of RMs, I already give you.
Almost like 90% of RM
basically like this.
My question is when you
try to scale up RM,
which part you are going to see
the bottleneck in
terms of parameters?
Which are the top two places
you are likely to
see a bottleneck?
Which is the first one?
Absolutely, this one.
Like I said, you are doing
times I times three.
And like I said, in most cases,
I is like a four edge.
So when you try to scale
the size of language model,
you ally scale the
hidden size edge,
and this one grows the most is
12 edges square's
square to edge.
So if you try to
enlarge your model,
this one is going to explode.
You are going to have
a lot of parameters
concentrated at the ML piece.
Okay. This also provides
another argument
why in Mcatron we
are partitioning this
because at some point,
we will try to skew
language model
and this one will explode first.
And once it exploded,
the only way to
steal make it fit is
basically doing
partitioning parallelism,
how to partition
this with matrix.
If remember in Mctron
our model we do is we
partition in this way,
this is the math mode.
We column part in
the first input X,
we party in the width W,
and here we get a partial sum.
That's because when
we try to scale
language model,
this one explode.
Yeah, we have to part it.
Where is the second place
that this can get exploded?
Yes, self attention.
You can see there's
a lot of parameters.
So basically, the
primary sources
of language model
parameters come
from this
is the number one factor,
this is number two factor.
That's why all the
part strategies for
parameters basically
are basically
performing some pis
on these two parts.
Yeah. Other parts are
not important at all,
you can see from these
equations mathematics. Okay.
Sorry, what's that?
What's the question?
Is it? This one. Sorry.
Yeah, sorry. Now, you
understand the dynamics
of parameters.
And in P three,
especially in the
skinning law section,
you need to implement
this function
to count number parameters,
and you are going to understand
why Lama seven B is seven B.
Why Lama 30 is 30.
You are going to count that you
have a reference because if
you are not at Opothirty
are wrong, right?
Okay. Cool. Okay. Let's
make it more complicated.
Parameter is easy because
there are just a few parameters.
How about flops, compute.
How many computer we
need? Let's do it.
Okay. Recap. I think
I covered this,
what is how do I
estimate compute?
Mostly meto because other
operators are pretty light.
So we just count matms
MMO is this equation,
M times H times one,
but this Mus one can be ignored.
Basically, for any
matrix multiplication is
basically two M and where
M is the first dimension,
NH is the second dimension.
Is I'm going to
give you a few notations
like I did before,
B equal to B sequence length as
Lambert has hidden
state size of 100 D.
And like I said, D,
when they tied together,
they equal to edge, right?
Okay. Suu project dimension I,
in most cases, are
equal to four edge,
sorry, vocabulary size, okay?
Once we have these dimensions,
let's do the flops calculation.
And this will help you
understand why Lama
needs 1,000 GB to train 30 days.
Okay, cool. Let's
do it one by one.
First, I have X as input,
and I do nothing because it's
input, so there's no flops,
but the shape is BSH,
then I go through the embedding.
I think embedding
is pretty light.
Okay, I don't count it.
And then I enter
self attention and
in order to perform the first
step of self attention,
I do this projection.
Basically, I have B SH and
I'm projecting from edge to
edge and BS is not changing.
So for each, met moo is
basically two B square.
Okay? I'm basically
using my equation,
and I do it three times, right?
QQV. Okay? So the
flop is times three.
Good. Then I have a position
embedding which is the rope.
But the rope is pretty simple.
It's basically this
equation is basically
some linear transformation
on top of the things.
I don't cover it,
but it's pretty light
because you can see,
there's a square here and
there's no square here.
You can imagine it is much
bigger than this one,
then I do this soft max,
this is a complicated part.
So I have two terms here.
The first term is I
need to do Q times K,
what is the shape of Q?
It's BSH K is also BSH.
The reduction that
means is H, and how to.
So therefore, you can see
the flops become this. Okay?
And if you put it, I want
you to pay attention.
And if you put it into this,
you'll find that this
term is pretty bad.
Why? You have S square.
So what is S? Sequence lens.
That means whenever you try
to model a longer sequence,
you are going to quadratically
increase your flops.
Now, you understand
the n connect problem.
If I want to model 1
million connect lens,
this is 1 million square.
So how many flops I need?
I don't know. Infinite
almost, right?
So attention is pretty bad
on sequence lens, right?
As I have a second term
three Ps square N,
and this is easy because it's
basically I basically
take softmax,
I take the exponential
and then I
divide the unimalization, right?
Okay. And finally, after
I get the softmax P,
this is a square,
normalized atten square.
I do another matrix
multiplication that is wit sum,
o over the values.
And this is another metimo which
is to B as square
and D. Pretty bad,
right? Another a squared term.
Okay, very, very bad. Okay, Aten
is so expensive.
Now I understand.
And finally, I have
a ultra projection,
like I mentioned, is another
I take a BSH and
project it once.
And this is the standard
two B s square.
I would say B H squared
is much better than B S
squared Because H is
the hidden state of the model
size, I can't control it.
But S is a sequence,
I cannot control it.
I want to model infinitely
long sequences. Yeah. Okay?
So you can see
this term is okay.
This one is pretty good.
Okay. And then, of course,
I have a residual
connection like this,
and this residual is
basically addition,
so the 14 points BSH easy.
See this basically reveal
the flops needed for attention
and you already
spoil the problem,
and we are going to come
back to fix this problem.
Let's continue. We are
going to enter the MLP.
In MLP, the input input
is basically the output of
self attention, It's PSH.
Okay. And we all assume is ama,
which is suit GLU.
So we do this, right?
We first do a gate projecting,
we do upper projection.
So we have this term and
we time two because twice,
Okay then we have activation.
Activation is pretty simple.
Okay. Element Y
is pretty simple.
And then we have a
down projection,
which is another matmT B SH, I.
This I is the hidden dimension.
Like I said, I equal to four H.
So you can see these two terms,
they are also problematic
because they have
a square term on
top of it, right?
But for other element is,
there's no square term.
It's pure linear.
Okay. So that means that this
two will be the primary
source of flops.
Okay. And finally,
I apply some layer
on all arms but
which is okay because
they're pretty simple.
Okay.
Any questions on this
slide? Okay, then
we can put everything together.
So the total flops of
language model is basically
you count the tension.
You count the swigOU.
You put them together, you
times the number
of layers, right?
And you plus embedding,
you get this equation.
A question? This is
the answer to the second
part of screen law.
You are going to implement
this. And there are also
reference because you can
go check TPD number paper.
They told you how
many flops you need,
and you write this
function and you can't.
And if your number is
not equal to the number,
that means you are wrong,
right? Okay. Okay, cool.
Okay. And if we basically
substitute a few values
into this equation,
assuming we use a batch equal
to one, that is a
single sequence.
And this is the
specification from Lama 27b.
And we basically
get that in order
to basically
perform a single forward
pass, we need these flops.
And this flop is
already pretty huge.
It's 63t flops.
Okay? And if we draw the
distribution of these flops,
you can see embedding layer,
very little, normalizing
little residual little.
Attention, a lot, right?
MLP, a lot. Linear, a little.
I can visualize it here. This is
basically the flops
distribution.
Then I ask the same
question. Now, I
want to scale my language model.
What will be the
primary bottleneck?
So when I skill
my language models away,
by scanning, I mean,
I try to increase lumber
parameters, like I said,
the lumber parameters
is a strong function
of edge, remember,
hidden dimension.
So the first dimension
I try to explore,
when I screw my
language model is
basically I increase
the value of edge.
So if I increase
the value of edge,
you can see which of
these terms will explode.
Apparently this
term this term is
t square and it has a very
strong constant factor here, 32.
This is also t square,
but you can see the factor is
roughly much smaller
than this one,
because it's 32 times z.
So if I skill my language model
by increasing the hidden states,
this MLP is going to
take the primary, flops.
But the problem is, there are
a lot of dimension to
skill language model.
That is, I try to scale the
sequence length and model.
So if I continue to skill
sequence mass, the problem is,
you can see this one will
diminish this one
dish one diminish,
but this one will grow crazily,
because it's quietive
to us. Okay?
So if I try to start modeling
a sequence less of, say,
128 k or 1 million,
this one will take
90% of the flops.
So you basically spend all
your flops on attention.
Yeah. That's a problem
of long sequence.
Okay. And I think that's
all I have today,
and I hope you go back and dive
deeper because this is a
pretty hands on thing, okay?
You have to be able to drive
all this by yourself without
looking at my slides.
Okay? And enjoy. Okay.
And next lecture, we're
going to do memory.
And then we are going to connect
all these three parts
into skinny law.
Okay. Cool.
H
h