Okay. Welcome back.
Let's get started, okay?
A few logistics. The first
one, cross you of, of course.
That's very important
for me and for
TAs to make sure it is
also important for you.
So if you finish,
80% of you finish that,
you are going to get two
points at the final.
Thank you. Um, we also
cancel the reading
summary for next week.
So you can focus
on, uh, homework.
Don't worry about final exam.
I'm going to make
the exam extremely
easy as long as you
attend lectures, okay.
Yeah. Um, Thursday, guest
lecture. Speculate decoding.
I'm not going to cover
that, but I'm going
to give you motivation
today why we do
speculate decoding and the guest
we going to teach you
speculate decoding.
And he is a professor
at U Waterloo and he
wanted the best speculate
decoding method called Eagle.
Ego is the one that
everybody use today.
Okay? I also worked on
speculate decoding,
but my method is worse than his.
Okay. I know P three,
there are some
theoretical questions,
you probably also want some
help on the final exam.
So I ask TA to schedule
recitations on Statue.
Okay. Okay, that's it.
Let's get started.
I think last lecture, we
are doing this, right?
I said this is super important
because once you understand
the math behind this,
you know why people do this,
why people do that, right?
Like what is square, what is
linear. That's super important.
I think we finish
the parameters.
Parameter is simply square,
right you just can't.
And the flops is a little
bit more complicated,
but we finish that, okay?
And today we are going
to finish the memory.
Memory is one of the
most complicated one,
but I think we already did
some in previous lectures.
Yeah. But before
we move to memory,
let's do one more
thing on flops, okay?
I think the last lecture,
I show this slide,
it's a summary of the flops,
basically the computing
requirements for training Ms,
and I think there are a
few messages I missed,
but I want to emphasize here.
So the first message is why
there's times three here.
Because this is training, okay?
When we count flops, we count
the forward path, right?
But remember in neural networks,
the backward pass has
doubled flops forward.
So in order to train
neural network,
you have two times three
here, one plus two.
Okay? That's the
true flops you are
using for training one
pass forward and backward.
Okay? And the second
important question
we are going to
visit today is, uh,
I think the last lecture
I emphasized that,
So this term is
pretty bad, right,
because it has a
quadratic, right?
S square. And this term
is also vd because
it has a square, right?
So anything that is
square is bad, okay?
Um, but I want to ask
a question that is,
so what happens when B
is equal to one and
S equal to one.
So BS is essentially
the batch size.
In what cases will have B
is equal to one as equal to one.
A equal to one means that we
are only computing on one token.
So in what cases we are
computing on one token.
Basically in language
model inference,
when you try to decode,
you always compute on one token.
And in what cases will
have B is equal to one?
Many few cases you have this.
But sometimes when you run
your language model
on your laptop,
when you deploy your
local language model
and the only user is yourself,
you ask your language
model questions,
then BS equal to one.
That means that in
the worst case,
in a minimal case,
you only submit one sequence
to language model and
you start to decoding.
You can see when BS equal
to one S equal to one,
these terms are super small
because you already have 21.
So like I said,
on GPS when these things
are super smalls also bad.
Why? Yeah, your GPO is
underutilized, okay?
So here, the message
I want to give to you
is when these two numbers
are small, it's also bad.
That means language
model inference
is super hard to optimize, okay?
Because in decode, we
only decode 12 at a time.
I'm going to read
it out again, okay?
But remember this. Okay.
That's the two messages I want
to emphasize on the flops.
I think now you basically
understand the
computing requirements.
What are the bad components
in transformers.
And now let's move to memory.
I think for memory, you
have been already very
familiar with that, right?
We have the four parts,
model weights, intermediate,
activation values,
optimial states,
and weight gradients and
activation gradients.
Okay? First term, two
M. I make sure
this number is basically in
your brain forever. Yeah.
So basically, two
for models, okay?
Optimal stays 12:00 A.M.
Right? So because we use
mixed precision, right?
So four plus four plus four.
Okay. First, second
moments and mask copy.
Okay. We gradients two, right?
Because you are also using P
16 version of the gradients.
Okay? So these three
terms we are good, okay?
We have been talking about
this for quite a while.
So the only remaining
question is
basically how large is the
intermediate activations,
and how large is
activation gradients.
Okay. Let's go into that.
We are going to break this
down into attention and then
MLP because transformer is
essentially a tension
plus MLP, okay?
So for attention, our
input is BS V, right?
B by size, a sequence lens,
V is vocabulary size. Okay?
You start with mapping each
token using a one hot vector,
where the lens of the one hot
vector is vocabulary size,
okay? This is your input.
And your first step you
through this into your
embedding, right?
And your embedding,
this is your weight,
right, is by edge, okay?
And the activation you get
is basically BSH right?
Because you map from
one hot into Okay,
H is the dimension
of your model.
The dimension. And then
you go into attention.
Like I said, attention does
not change your shape, right?
We are going to
dive deeper here.
But now, after you
finish your attention,
you still have a BSH, okay?
And then you go into RMS norm
and it will not change
your shape, okay?
And then you go into
that MLP, right?
MLP will not change
your shape, okay?
Of course, inside of
MLP you are going to
change the shape,
but after you finish the MLP,
you basically project back into
the original shape which is BSH.
Okay. And then you
go into softmax to classify
each token position,
right, you have to map
the hidden machine
back to the cabory size.
Okay? Which is softmax,
like a distribution over
all the categories. Okay?
So your output is VSV.
Okay. And finally, you
do training, okay?
Okay, this is basically
from a global view,
from a holistic perspective,
the activation value.
This is super simple, right?
I have a few questions.
The first question is still
remember the checkpointing,
the way we do memory savings.
So like I said, previously,
when we transformers,
what do we do we checkpoint at
the boundary over two
transformer layers.
Okay? Then my question is,
if we checkpoint at the
transformer boundary,
what is the activation memory?
Example question. Let's
see ignoring embeddings.
So basically, you can see we
checkpoint at the end
of the MLP, right?
So at the end of MMP, we get
the activation which is of
shape BSH we have many
many layers, right?
So each layer is going
to give you one BSH.
That means you checkpoint
out here, right?
Between two transformer
layers, okay?
So the activation memory is
basically BSH times
number of layers.
Super easy, okay? We are good.
Cool. Okay. This is
simple, but now,
let's dive deeper into
attention and MLP respectively.
Let's see what happens
inside of this.
Because this is not
a primitive graph.
This is a global graph. We
want to dive deeper, okay?
But before that, I also want to
ask a very trivial question
just to remind you.
Remember when we do
interop partism we try to
partition this language
model using interoperatism,
we often partition
at different at the
boundary or transformer
layers assign
different layers to
different devices.
If you still remember, if
we do this kind of parism,
the communication between
two devices is basically
an activation from one
device to the other.
If you do interperism at
the transform boundary,
the message you are going
to communicate is also
BSH it's a PTP,
it's not connective,
it's super cheap.
Linear, Okay. Okay, then
let's dive deep into
attention and you are going
to describe the problem.
So let's repeat, okay?
The previous layer, after
monisation we get a BSH.
And then what we do is we enter
the next transformer layer.
We first do projection
QQV what do we
do this QQV is going to project
your previous activation
into mart head input,
the input for Q QV they
are all BS and D, right?
B, but as sequence length number
has D high dimension, okay?
And here, we have times
D equal to H if you
still remember, okay.
Good. Okay. And then the
problem comes, okay?
So next, we are
going to perform,
um, self attention, right?
So still remember the equation
of self attention, right?
We have Q on Q, and we are
going to do a dot product,
and then we go through softmax,
right we get, um, the weight.
And then we do a weighted
sum over B, right?
So here we are doing dot
product of this, right?
And this B is a
better dimension.
So we are essentially
doing dot product
on these three dimensions.
And the problem is that
u what we call this?
This is called
attention was, right?
And the problem you can find is
the tenon waist is
of shape B and SS.
Okay? And this is
a bad term, right?
And you can imagine this
is super big Y because
it's square S. Okay?
Which means that if you do
self attention language model,
you have activation,
which is squares.
And S is if you still
remember it a six dimension,
that means if you want to
model a long sequence,
for example, 1 million
uh six lengths,
then you have activation,
which is 1 million
times 1 million.
It's impossible to save
this kind of matrix, right?
Okay, this is pretty bad.
And apparently, this
is a bottleneck.
And if you still remember
the computer here is
also quadratical, right?
So the lumber flops needed for
this operator is also quit S. So
also emphasize my second point
that is for modeling
line contexts,
we have a problem on compute
and we have a problem memory.
Okay. But fortunately
unfortunately
we are not able to solve
that problem on compute.
We need that many flops.
But we can solve this
problem on memory.
And there's algorithm that can
avoid basically materializing
this SPS matrix.
And algorithm is called
flash attention.
Okay? And I'm going to
cover that next week.
Okay. Yeah. But
remember that, okay?
This memory bond,
this memory barrier
is already addressed
by flash attention.
That's why flash
at is great, okay?
And then what we
do is we continue
doing weighted sum over
the value, value matrix,
and we basically
project back from
BSS into BSN D. BSN
D equal to B SH.
Okay? And we are good again.
Okay. And then we output,
right? BSH, nothing changes.
Then let's move forward to
the MLP, fit for layers.
Fit for layer, the input is
still the output from
attention right is BSH, okay?
And this is Lamar sue
GLU, and I cover this.
So basically, you are going
to do linear projections,
and what do you do is
project from edge to I.
And usually I is much
greater than edge,
for example, four
edge or something,
a factor of four, okay?
And you project back
from I to edge.
Like this. It's basically
an upper project and
down project, okay?
I'm putting things together,
and you can see, um,
this is our memory usage,
activation usage, um, of
attention plast MLP, okay?
So let's summarize
a few messages.
Okay, we'll do this. If we
try to skew up the model,
what is the potentials neck?
Okay? The first thing I want
to emphasize is basically,
all the terms are at
least linear with edge,
which means that remember
when we skew up model,
usually we enlarge edge, right?
So which means that whenever
you tween a bigger model,
all this term is
going to linear,
increase with model size.
Okay? That's quite obvious.
And again, this term
is conductive tus,
which is very bad, okay?
And if you look at this, right,
we start thinking
about paralysms, okay?
And there are many many
dimensions in this
compute, right?
There are B, and there are D,
there are S. So what
are the dimensions
that we can apply
intraop partism?
So still remember
intra op, right,
we basically choose
matrix dimension
or tensor dimension
and we partition it,
right, and assign it
to different devices.
So let's look at
this Bo notations B
and Ds and what
are the dimensions that
we can piton along? Okay?
So for B, can we
partition it along?
Quite obvious, right datapism,
if we parting B is
data parism, okay?
For N, can we a number of heads,
and I might attention,
each he basically perform
independent competition.
Partition is trivial because
you just assign different
heads to different devices.
The compute following
their own pace is good.
For this D, can we part in it?
Of course, it's microtron.
In Microtron we part in D. How
about S? Can we part in S?
We can, but it's
super hard because
if you look at this dot product,
this S is inner dimension.
Still remember in memol if
you part on inner
dimension, what happens?
S is a reduction loop, right?
In the math mood If you parting
along the reduction loop,
you are going to
need to accumulate
the results that will create
a lot of communication.
Yeah, please. This is
Market hadoten Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. So I'm just
give you some picture,
some color if you want
to parallelze this
kind of communication,
what are the possible choices?
But I want d deeper here.
Okay? So the first thing
I want to remind you,
okay, I want to
connect the dots here.
The first thing I
want to connect is,
if you look at the MLP, right,
like I said, this I is
usually like for
example, four edge.
Which means that this
matrix is pretty big.
It's a square of edge for I
square, four edge square.
Which means that this
weight when you try to
scale the model when you
try to increase
number parameters,
uh, the first choice is
basically you make this
large, this width large.
And once this width becomes
super large, what will happen?
Like, a single device cannot
basically afford to put
weight on it, right?
And we start considering
partition the weight.
And this probably reminds
you of one thing, right?
I basically this dalgram
I showed two lectures
before, right?
This is basically Mctron
style of tense parism
here because we observe
that is by the way,
this is not Lama.
This is GPT three.
There's no VGOU but
there are just two,
like met mo, okay, in MLP.
And so the motivation of um,
Macron is essentially they
observe that W two and W one,
the weight matrix,
which is this, okay,
super super large, and
a single device cannot
basically, afford them.
So they pion this. And because
of the parton they want to
minimize the communication.
So this partion has
to be propagated all the way
through different animals,
and, you know, that's
basically what the Micron
paper is talking about, right?
Okay? And at some point,
okay, at some point,
we continue to skill
language model to longer and
longer sequences, right?
And this S is going to explode.
And when S is going to explode,
we still need to partie along.
Like I said, even it
is super costly, okay?
So okay.
Actually, for the um,
for this lecture, you just
need to understand this.
That is how we connect, microton
style tropism to
this communication.
But I want to expand
a little bit.
Okay, I'm going to give you
some very, very advanced stuff.
This stuff I just published
a few months ago. Okay?
Um, okay. So, like I said,
you already know Microthn'
style of Tater partism, right,
which is essentially party in
two ways in the MOP, okay?
And I also give
you a motivation.
For example, if we want to
model super long contexts,
then the S is super
large and at some point,
we have to pertain, because
we are going to have a
lot of a lot of devices.
And you also know like for
tenso parism we cannot
skill beyond GPUs why?
Because there are too many
Ds and these IDs are
super expensive that,
if you don't have meaning,
you don't want to do that,
it's super small, okay?
So at some point, when
S is large and when
we try to continue
skew our model to more
and more and more
GPU way beyond GPs,
we are going to have to
pertain along S. Okay.
So if you look at this, okay,
uh, if we choose
to part in align S,
what will happen? Okay?
The simple case in this MLP,
this is the MLP, and
this is the attention,
attention MLP at MLP.
Transformer layer basically
connects these two components.
So in this part, can
we part in aligns?
So here, if you
observe this MLP,
you'll find that
this computation,
in this competition, S is
not the reduction loop,
because the H and
I here are basically the
reduction loop and S,
which means that
you have a number
of how many tokens
you have, right?
So each token will basically
perform their own competition.
They're independent, okay?
So in this competition,
if you part in along is very
similar to data partism.
Yeah, you are basically assigned
different token competition
to different devices.
It's very straightforward,
okay? So we are good.
But like I said, in this
competition, can you part in S?
It's super hard because
self attention,
S is a reduction loop,
and if you part ins,
your communication
is pretty messy,
each device compute something,
but you also need to aggregate
others results to get
the final results.
Okay? And aggregation
involves a lot of compute.
And I'm going to leave
this question to you,
okay? A lot of communication.
I'm going to leave
this question to you.
If you have time,
think about what kind
of communication we have
if we part ins here.
Okay? So
So one recent method is
called sequence pluralism.
It is one of the
most recent method
that people use to
train language models.
What did they do is, of course,
they partition S in
this computer in this
combination because like I said,
partition S is super easy.
But in order to avoid
partition S in this part,
they partition along
different axes.
They choose to partition along
the the N dimension,
which is lumber heads.
Basically in transformer, they
first partition along
the lumber heads.
They align different heads to
different devices and
they compute in parallel.
And then at some point, when
they enter this communication,
they partition, they try
to switch access to
partition along.
This basically give you
deep speed Ulysses.
This called the deep Ulysses
style sequence parism.
I give you the
master, but I'm going
to ask a question I
hope you can answer.
In this partitioning scheme,
what is the
communication? Please.
Yes, auto. Why? Because
in the first part,
we parting along in
the second part,
we parting along S. Like I said,
when you're parting a tensor you
need a resharding When
you switch access,
you need to recharting still
remember that triangle dire grab
and give it to you, right?
So what do you do when
you try to switch access?
You perform auto. Okay?
So that's why in deep
uses, people need Auto.
That's because they
partition head and
then lumber head and
then partition S. Okay.
This is very advanced and
at some point, if you
start working on this,
you probably will try to
start hacking on this code.
Okay? Let me give you
even more advanced one.
Okay? So what if
the lumber hats is way
smaller than lumber GPUs?
Why does it happen?
This happens very
often when you train a model
that is on ten k GPUs,
but you are not going
to have ten k hats.
You are going to probably
only have 128 hats.
Which means that you
are not able to part in
128 hats on Tenke dips.
Then you still need
to part in S here.
You need the parting operating
S. But if you choose
to part in S,
then you start having
a problem, that is,
I left to you to think about
what kind of
communication you need.
But I'm going to
give you a name,
If you part in S in both
the attention and the MLP,
you basically get the so
called ring attention.
That is another style, um,
sequence part that people use to
tin super context
language models.
Okay? Cool. This is
advanced topics,
definitely will not be
covered in exam, okay?
Feel free to skip.
Cool. Okay, that basically, um,
finish our very deep dive
into the computing characteristics
of language models.
Let's move on to the next topic.
Okay. We are going to talk about
a very important yet simple
thing, okay, skinning law.
So the reason we put skin law
here is because you
have to understand
these computing requirements of
language models in order to
understand skinning law.
Okay? So let's do simple,
and fun thing, okay?
So so now we understand
computer memory and,
communication is
fact for computer
because computer is the thing
that you really pay, right?
TPU o. And we know
that the compute is
a function of HI B
B is batch size.
I is the upper projection
down projection.
An H is model hidden cd model.
Okay. And we also
spent quite a lot of
time understanding that
the pamemb parameters
is a function of
H and I. H is a
hidden dimension,
I is upper down projection.
Okay? So this H and
I are essentially the
model specifications,
and the B is essentially the
lumber data, right? Okay.
Therefore, we can draw
a conclusion that
is compute clts with parameters.
The more parameters, of course,
you are going to spend more
computer to train the model.
Computer is a function
of parameters.
Also computer is a function
of your training data,
the more data you want to train,
this B will be much larger.
You also need more computer.
Okay. And then,
people start saying,
I'm going to skill
my language model.
I'm going to train
whatever model
that is large and more
powerful because,
like, people have
been believing that
larger model has better
performance, okay?
But the problem here is, we
don't have infinite
computer, okay?
We only have a computer budget.
And this computer budget is
given, you're
constrained by, like,
how much money you have,
because you are
going to buy DPS,
you're going to,
like, going a budget
for your literathy, okay?
Then this is a reality check,
I give you $5 million.
That's what I give it to you
in your homework, right?
I give you 5 million.
And you hold $5 million.
And now I ask you to deliver
your best language model.
And how do you do that?
This is a super interesting
question, because
we have to solve
this question in
a very limited budget scenario.
Okay. So here, if I basically
set a limit on the budget,
then you are facing
these questions, right?
And I think in our
previous guest lecture,
actually we talked about a
so called planning phase.
That is whenever you
train language model,
the really time consuming part
is not actually
trainings like planning.
And this is basically
your planning, okay?
I'm your leadership,
I'm going to give you
$5 million and you
start planning what
do you want to train.
So you face a few decisions.
Should you train a
model that is larger,
should you train
your model longer?
That is, for example,
training more data?
Or should you train a
larger model on fewer data.
Why? Because, like
I said, compute is
a function of data
and model size.
So you're facing two choices.
Oh, you train a
bigger model with
fewer data and you
exhausted your money,
or you train a smaller
model, but with more data.
Okay? So which model will
give you better performance?
This is a very fundamental
question, okay?
Second, should you connect
more data to model?
Because if you try
to decide this path,
you want to go this path,
then you how to
connect more data.
And connecting data is
trial, like I said,
you have to preprocess
the data in a very
trivial way to make
sure language model in a
really good data, right?
Or should you get more tips
you just continue to scale up,
and both will spend your money.
I think the last
lecture, a student come
to me and ask exactly
a very good question.
That is how exactly
should I decide u and I?
What is hidden a
machine? What is
the upper projecting
dump projection?
Okay. And this question
is super important for us to
design our language models,
and this question answered
by the skinning law.
So what is skinning
law essentially?
Before I talk about what is
skinning law, like I said,
the problem that
skinning law tries
to solve these questions.
So given a fixed budget,
how large a model should we
train and how many
data should we use?
And can I get a projection,
if I choose this larger
model and this many data,
what kind of performance
I'm going to
achieve? Can I get a prediction?
And of course, we need to
subject computer constraints.
Okay. And I'm going to,
um, explain spin on you,
very, very, like,
a funny way, okay?
So I will let you look at
this for 20 seconds, okay?
Okay.
This is something like I
believe everybody knows, right?
You study this in underground.
It's basically you have some
data points you observed,
empirical data
that is drawn from
Gaussi distribution and I ask
you to estimate the mean,
you can basically use
whatever mathematics you
studied to give me this
equation and you tell me
that you give me this data,
I'm going to estimate the mean,
and I can make sure
that my arrow on
my estimation of the mean
is bonded by some
equation, right?
This is what Gaussian
distribution told you, right?
Empirical estimation
of the of Gaussi.
And here I state this is
the screening all Why?
Because if you look
at this equation,
I give you more data,
your error is going
to be less, right?
And this screening law
is absolutely correct.
Why? Because this is what you
derived from mathematics.
As long as our mathematics
is correct, it is correct.
Okay. But let's think
differently, okay.
I'm going to switch
this model from
Gasino into a language
model with many,
many transformer layers,
a lot of parameters. So
can you still do this?
No, right, because our
mathematics doesn't
work anymore on transformers.
At least we don't have
that advanced mathematics
to analyze our
language model, right?
Because like I said, uh,
it's very hard to
analyze language model.
It's so many layers,
so many transformers
and long convex,
this kind of like for
this it's super simple.
It's very simple math,
but for language model,
it's super hard.
Okay? So if we
want to do this kind of
thing that do a equation
that whenever I put more
data and more computer
into into the right
hand equation,
um, like, what would be
my arrow looking like?
We're not able to use our
existing mathematical tools
to give this equation.
But I still want to
get this kind of
equation to at least
give me a sense like
how many data or
parameters that I
want to put into my model.
So what should we do?
Okay, your mass become
ineffective and you still want
to get a sense
of how the model would
work. What do you do?
Okay. So here, um,
so basically, skin law is
basically the physics
of machine learning.
Okay? Think about
before language model,
how people do
machinery research.
It's more like a mathematical
way, statistical way.
So everything everything
is analytical.
I can write down the
equation. I can bond
the estimation arrow using
math statistical theory, okay?
And I basically draw
this kind of equation.
Okay? I derive this bond,
and I can make a statement
that if I put this
data into my model,
I'm going to get this arrow,
and this arrow is
going to be smaller
than some upper bound.
But like I said, once your mass
become ineffective,
what do you do?
Okay. Remember, in ancient
society, what do we do?
Like we don't understand
how the world works, right.
We don't understand
physics, but we
still know that one day takes
roughly 24 hours and one
year takes roughly 365 days.
So how are sent get
this kind of knowledge?
You keep observing, right,
you keep observing.
So it takes many many years,
but you basically draw
some conclusion by
observing how many hours
it takes every day,
and how many days
it takes per year.
And after you
observe, for example,
100 years and that knowledge
you are basically um, uh,
boil down into your child,
probably your grandchild and
they will summarize
something called knowledge.
And this knowledge
is called okay,
maybe one day will take 24
hours and maybe one year will
take somewhere between somewhere
around 300 days, right?
But at some point, of course,
we human we invent some signs
and we start understanding
the universe and we
start explaining this more
more I would say
first principle way.
But before that, right,
we actually know that
one day takes 24 hours.
And this is basically a
fundamental paradigm shift
in language model research.
I think that the way language
model go this far and
much much further than
any other machinery model
is because they discover
this kind of physics, okay?
And at some point,
after the GBT paper
was published,
so the machining society,
especially some very small
group of researcher open air,
they start approaching
machinery using
a physics way instead
of a mathematical way.
They don't want to seek for a
very analytical explanation
of my machinery models
behavior like this.
And they know deep learning
is very hard to explain,
and they give up
in this demands.
Okay? What do they do is they
start doing experiments.
They do a lot of experiments,
according to experiment results,
they are going to
draw a law empirical
law, not analytic law.
This is an analytical law's
starting drawing empirical law.
And they use empirical law to
predict the performance
of language models.
Okay? And this is a
very important thing
because this is
also why recently
language models start rising and
system machining system become
really important subject.
So let's see what is going on?
Okay. So one example
question is,
at some point, maybe
five years ago,
people start asking
questions are
transformers better than RSTM.
There is a strong debate
in the community.
Okay? So if you want to
answer this question,
you have one way to
answer it is basically,
you are going to spend tens
of millions of dollars
to train RST based PD,
same amount of parameters,
same amount of compute.
But that is not doable
because no one is going
to give you that money.
It's a waste of
money. So in order
to plate this kind of
question, what do we do?
The way we do is basically
we use in park law, okay?
What do we do is we
have a hypothesis.
At least we train a
lot of small LSTMs,
we train a lot of
small transformers,
and we compare the performance.
And our hypothesis is that
once we have this trend,
we can use this trend to
extrapolate it to larger models.
Okay. So what people
are doing is,
they spend some compute,
still substantial but
not that crazy, okay?
This spend a
substantial compute,
and they train many,
many models with different
number of parameters, okay?
You can see in this figure, it
goes all the way
to ten to eight.
Well, ten to eight is
not large today, okay?
But at that point,
it's pretty large.
And they train these many
models. Every point is a model.
And they try to study the
correlation between number of
parameters and the
testing loss. Okay.
And if you plot
this in a log skill,
you basically get that.
You can see by adding
one more parameters,
my testing loss is
going to decrease,
apparently, this is log skill,
so this is the
exponential curve, okay?
But I also train the same
amount of transformers,
I spent the same
amount of compute.
And obviously, I observe this
blue curve is below curve.
And this can verify verdict
that at this scale
at this skill,
transformer is
definitely better stem.
So we can stop working on R
Stem if our hypothesis is right.
A, This is basically
the skin wall, okay?
You don't have
analytical understanding
of what's going on behind,
from a mathematical way, but
you do this in empirical way.
You do physics and
you hypothesize that
this trend is going
to extrapolate
to larger models. Okay?
And similar thing, I think
one student asked
me why the I is
four of H but
not three H or five And
you can update this.
Okay? You are going to design
a lot of transformer
language models,
and you basically
change, for example,
the value of the factor,
the upper projection or
down projecting factor,
and you draw this kind of curve.
And you can study
the testing loss
and the correlation between
texting loss and
the hyperparameter.
In this example, it is, um,
the depth of the neural network,
and the width of neural network.
But you can study anything.
Okay? And you twin it um,
at a relatively small scale,
and you train many, many models,
and then you can draw
some observations if
this one is good.
One pyper parameter is
better than the other.
You keep doing this and you can
apolte everything
you want, okay?
Very good. Cool.
And this is still,
uh, it looks like a
hyperprimary tuning, right?
It's basically like
actually many models.
Okay. But Okay.
But this hyperprimar tuning way
kind of generates pretty well.
Okay. And, um, and
people have been
studying this since
2018, I think. Okay.
Especially people from
Google open they're doing
this initially for
different hyper parameters.
But more and more they
start doing this and try to
predict the performance
of training
a larger model because, uh,
they really want to
train a larger model,
but they are not
sure because you
need to convince kind of
Google CEO to give you
billions of dollars to
train a model, right?
So they started collecting
this evidence, okay?
And the way they do that is
basically they keep doing
more and more experiment
experiments and they try
to summarize a lot
behind this experiments.
What they do is they
start figuring out
the most important parameter
in this law is
basically two things.
First, the lumber
parameters of your model.
Because we have a hypothesis.
Me parameters is going to
give you more performance,
but we don't have a
precise understanding
how many parameters
we should have
to give me best performance.
But if you look at the previous
calculation of the flops,
you can see the Lumber flops is
actually very complex
function of the parameters.
I cannot arbitrarily skill it.
I have to be very
careful because that
basically boils down to
every dollar I spent
on my training.
Okay. And the second
most important factor
is the amount of data
you're going to train
for your model, and,
how to decide that,
how many data
I should put into the model,
and if I continue to give
more data in the current
size of this model,
will I have a diminished return.
Should I train a larger model
with fewer data or smaller
model with more data?
Okay? At some point,
they start doing all these
kind of experiments,
and they start writing
screen law in this equation,
which is the optimiing problem.
Let's try to understand this.
So in this opening edition,
we try to answer the question
as for a given computer
Okay. We're back. Okay?
I think you been looking at
this equation for a
few seconds, right?
So basically you can
look at this equation.
Okay. So we want to
predict the loss,
which is after we
train language model
after we train a language
model with many many tokens,
what will be the
loss looking like?
Because like I said,
language model is
eventually token prediction
model and we can
create token
prediction capability
with the language models,
actual capability
on many many different
benchmarks and tasks.
We want to minimize the loss,
because a lower token
predicting loss will credit
to a stronger language model.
That's what hypothesis.
And we want to answer
your question.
N is the amount of data.
I should use to trim
my language model.
Oh, sorry, the number of
parameters I should use to trim
my language model and
D is a model data.
I should use Trim
language model.
And I'm subject to a
computer budget which is C.
And apparently C is a function
of NN D. Like I said,
computer is a function
of parameters and data,
I try to solve this
optimizing problem that
is if I want to
minimize my next to
computing loss, that is,
if I want to maximize my
language model performance,
and I'm subject to a
compute constraint,
which is the number
of flops I can spend.
So what is the best
possible N D? Yeah, please.
Her Yes.
Roughly, like a I want
to quote one thing that
Elia said in his talk at
GTC with Jensen Huang.
Okay? So think about this, okay.
What is next token prediction?
It's basically the ability
to predict the next word,
given all the previous
context, right?
So why next token prediction
is creltd to intelligence?
So think about, in this case,
you have a novel where there's
a killer alovel, right?
And this is, uh this is a
pretty interesting love
that there's a major character.
His goal is basically trying
to figure out who is the killer.
And the killer's name only
appears at the last
token of the novel.
Okay. And apparently,
there's a very strong
complicated plot,
right, by this level.
And like I said,
if you want to get the
name of the killer,
you have to be able to
reason among the entire,
basically, plots across
the entire novel
to predict the name
of the killer.
So suppose we have
a language model,
which will basically
read the entire novel
and output the last word.
And this language model, and we
can assure that this
ongoing model is definitely
intelligent if that
model is able to
predict the name correctly
predict the name of
the killer, right?
You see in this way, basically,
we can create next to come
breaking loss with intelligence,
and that's our belief.
Does that make sense?
That's Es case not my case.
Empirically to answer your
question, empirically,
when people train larger
and larger models,
we all observe and when people
give more and more data
to language model,
next bridging loss is
going to decrease.
And if you take the
language model and
evaluate on basically
those academic benchmarks,
it creates the
benchmark performance
will basically improve a lot.
And it's true.
Empirically is true.
At least by today it's true,
okay? I hope that
answer your question.
That being said, okay, I hope we
understand this open
objective right.
This is what the screens to do.
Given a fixed computer budget
and that's that's
our only limit.
Okay? Of course, as
someday we are going to
have infinite computer,
then this doesn't
make sense anymore.
We just train large model.
But now, it's not the case.
So given our limit,
what kind of data and
model should we choose
to train a model?
And this is essentially
your planning phase.
You have to plan this and
you have to study this
by performing a lot of
empirical impairments.
It's like you have
to spend year to
observe one day takes 24 hours.
Okay. Okay? So what people
do is in this paper,
this paper is what I give you as
a reading is a deep band paper.
I would say that is one most
important paper in after 2020,
okay, it's called
China screening law.
And and Google invites a lot of
computer to study the
behavior or the correlation,
the relation between D
and N and loss, okay?
And they start
doing these curves.
And, uh, and all these kind
of study and dollars boil
down into this equation.
This is our language
model physics,
skinning chinchilla
skinning law,
these parameters are basically
fit by the google
researchers and
they perform I would
believe thousands
of experiments and spending
millions of dollars,
almost millions of
dollars to conclude
that given a transformer
architecture, okay um,
which is basically what you
explained in our
previous lecture,
the relationship between
next token brten loss
and lumber parameters and
the amount of data
is this equation.
Okay, this is today's physics.
Okay. And once we
have this equation,
we can basically
backtrack to derive.
If we have a computer
budget right here,
there should be a
constraint here that is
C computer budget is a
function of NN D, right?
So once I have C,
right, which is I give it
to you in your homework,
and you basically use what you
studied in my previous lecture,
you figure out your NND. Okay?
You tell me what is the
best model you tu, okay?
Cool. This is
screening law, okay.
To summarize, skin
law is basically
the physics behind
machine learning, okay?
And screen law basically marks
a new era of machine
learning research.
Previously before
language model,
I think people prefer specially
imaginary researchers,
they prefer rigorous
theoretical analysis.
You want mass proofs.
Okay. But after
this screening law,
people do this in a
more physics way. Okay?
We do empirical observations,
and we try to do
empirical laws, okay?
And, um, and screen is not
limited to transformers.
So if you want to do
a different model,
you can also study screen law
when I increase
lumber parameters,
when I increase the
amount of data,
I train the model, how
the loss will change?
Okay. And apparently there
are good models and
bad models, right?
And that will
basically answer, um,
my question at my
first few lectures.
So what is a good model and
what is a bad model today?
So a good model has
a better screen law.
It's more computer efficient.
That is it can use less
parameters and less data to
achieve a lower loss and
a bad model is on
the contrary, right?
Today when people speak
about good and bad model,
it's basically using
the screen law
as a measurement, okay?
And due to skinning a lot,
people start realizing that
if you look at this equation,
if I continue increase N and D,
my model performance is
very predictable, right?
And so people start
investing into me
genery systems and they
start continue skinning
skinny and skinny Okay,
to get a better model.
Okay? And that skinning
continues today, okay?
I think last week, Open AI
released GPD 4.5, right?
And I know GBD 4.5 is kind
of ten times of GB four.
Yeah. And, yeah. Cool.
Okay. I hope this part of
the lecture give you
some hints how to solve
that PA question.
In the PA question, I
give you $5 million,
I also give you MFU you have
your freedom to choose
what kind of GPU use.
And according to the GPO use and
the number of hours you are
going to rent from Cloud,
you basically have flops,
which is a term C,
Once you have that C,
you can basically infer
the number of parameters and
the amount of data
you're going to train,
you use basically the
functions I ask you to write,
which I covered in my
preference lecture,
the number of parameters
and the number of
flows function.
Once you have those
two equations,
what do you do you use
this one to find
the optimal, right?
Cool. I hope this helps
you understand basically
the empirical rationale behind
why people in snicvale
they are buying one tips.
It's because they are basically
climbing the screen wall.
Yeah, please. Yeah, of course,
every long more to
follow the screen.
But I will cover that next.
Yeah. Okay. Cool. Okay. Once
you understand the screen,
I'm going to explain Deep
sik why Deep sik stands out.
Deep sk stands out
because they adopt
a slightly different
architecture, MOE.
What is MOE? Let's look
at that. This is MOE.
I think I covered this
at my second lecture.
MOE superficially is basically
remember in typical transformer,
you have atenin and then MLP.
But in MOE, what you do is
you have a tengin and then
you have a connection of MLPs.
Each MLP is basically
um, a so called expert.
And that's why MOE is
called a mixture of expert.
Basically, you have
a mixture of MLPs,
and this is illustrated
in this figure.
So you have attention,
you have normanization, right?
In the previous lecture,
I said in typical transformer,
after this normalization,
you go into MLP,
upper projection
down projection.
But now, what you
do is you replicate
that upper and down
projection many many times.
And the number of times
you replicate is equal
to the number of experts
you are going to do, okay?
In there are FF and one
apt, three and four.
So here roughly four times.
And what you do is before you
forward the output of the
attention into the MLP,
you first go through
a so called router,
this router basically
look at the output
often and decide which
MLP should I go into?
For example, you can set the
routers output into two,
that is the router will
basically route each um,
token in a sequence
to two experts.
If you set it as one,
it's basically the route,
um, it's token into
one expert, right?
It's basically you
choose one of this ab
and you forward that token
into F to perform a compute.
Okay? The thing here
is you can see this
basically create a so called
conditional execution,
right?
Basically, depending on the
value output this router,
I'm going to choose one
branch to execute. Okay.
Very good, right? So you
can say if I only
have one expert,
this is equivalent to
transformers, right?
If I have many many experts,
what's the problem.
Before we talk
about the problem,
let's first look at the
exact competition, okay?
So the exact competi MRP is
illustrated on this slide.
So what do you do is you add
another gating function,
which is implemented using
a software max, okay?
And you take the output
of the tentin which is X,
and this getting function has
a weight WG and you
do a multiplication,
and then you go through
a softmax, you get
a so called gate.
And this gate is basically,
uh a distribution right
over all the experts, okay?
And for example,
if you choose to
do top K gate and
K equal to one,
two, three, four, something
you choose, okay?
If you chose top two gate, okay,
you basically look at this
output of the soft max,
and then you choose the two
that is the max, the maximum.
Because the softmax give you
a distribution like
added into one right.
So you basically pick
up the two position
that is largest, okay?
And here you pick up
I zero and I one,
o you basically normalize
it a little bit.
Okay. Romanize a little bit.
Okay. And what you do is
basically you forward
the token X into the chosen
two F. That is the experts,
you do the computation,
and then you do
a weighty sum. Okay. Simple.
It's basically a weighted
sum over many many experts,
but the number of
experts selected is
determined by how many experts
you want to activate
for each token.
Okay? Now, we understand
the competation.
Once you understand
commutation, yeah, please.
Sorry? I mean, self?
Of course, is between tokens,
there's no dependency.
It's like the MLP.
Yeah, each token
choose their own path. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. If you still
remember transformers in MLP,
it can basically perform their
independent communication.
That's why we can partite along
the dimension. Does
that make sense?
That is the same.
Okay? So this is MOE,
MOE is essentially deep seek
to answer your question.
Then let's start looking at it
from a computational
perspective, what is MOE,
Lumber parameters, of course,
key elements parameters,
memory and computer
and of course,
communication, but
communication is
secondary. Let's look at it w.
So for Lambo parameters,
if we transform from
a typical transformer into
a MO based transformer
what will happen?
A few observations, first,
if you still remember
the calculation
we did for Lumber
parameter in transformer,
like I said, in most cases,
MLP parameters will
dominate the R MRI.
MLP is the most symmetric
modules in intransformer.
But here, what we
do is we replicate
the MLP a number of times
the number of times
you replicate it
is umber experts, right?
Typically, you replicate it
by undivided by two times,
sorry, not this one.
Typically, you replicate it
by N times is number experts.
But, the most popular
MOE archecture
is like every two
layers you transformer,
you change the original
transformer into MOE layer.
That's the most
popular architecture.
Every two layers
you have MOE layer.
That is a transformer MOE
transformer MOE like this.
Okay? Therefore,
your MLP parameter
is basically replicated
undivided by two times.
Okay. You know, a typical
MOE, this is equal to,
for example, I choose to do
a eight way expert
or 16 way expert.
But in deep sik, this
number is anyone
knows. No, it's 256.
Okay. You can see how
crazy this is, right?
So as a effect, what happens?
So we drastically increase
the number of parameters
because like I said,
in transformers,
MLP is the most
parameter heavy modules,
and here you are basically wrap
in our parameter many times.
Okay? And the more experts
the more parameters you have.
Okay? So for parameters,
the conclusion is once we
switch from a
transformer to MOE,
our parameter increase
drastically, okay?
How about memory?
Okay. Still memory
we'll look at a few
components, right?
One is the number of parameters,
memory is definitely
proportional to parameters.
You also drastically increase
the memory you need to store
the parameters on
the opiory state
the same on activations.
Activation doesn't change a lot.
Why? Because if
you look at this,
Also I have, like I said,
100 experts, but every
time one token is
only routed to a few,
for example, two or even one.
That brings us to answer
the third question.
What is the computer
looking like?
The computer only
increase mildly.
Why? Because this
is super sparse.
Okay? So every time we
consider compare the original
transformer and the
MOE transformer.
In the original
transformer, each token
basically go through one MLP,
to proceed the commutation.
And you know MOE,
each token only goes
through a K MLP.
And here, like I said, you
can set a K equal to one.
You still have a model that
is with way more parameters,
but the computer
doesn't change a lot.
Okay? So then I
try to answer your
question. So what is MOE?
Like I said, superficially,
MOE is essentially,
um, a mixture of experts.
MOE can be reduced to
the original
transformer by setting,
for example, K equal to one.
You only route it to one expert,
is the same with
original transformer.
But people start working
on the screen MOE and
they observe that basically
not with the same amount
of compute, right?
You can train a
much larger model.
Does that make sense?
Because your parameters
increase drastically and
your computer only
increase mildly.
Instead of training
original transformer,
you can use the same
amount of computer
to train a much larger model,
ten times larger, but without
spending ten times on compute.
People also find that
increasing the parameters in
experts of MOE can also
increase the performance,
for example, net
to computing loss.
That's why people invest into
training MOE why because
MOE kind like slightly better
than the transformers.
You are able to increase
a little bit computer,
but drastically
increase lumber parameters
and assume that
lumber parameters is clating
with more capability,
then this is a much more
computer efficient model.
Does that make sense.
Which means that MOE has
a better screen law
than dran formers.
Then after GBD, after GB,
people start training MOE
and they observe this.
But most American firms,
they are very conservative.
They don't want to
train super large MOE,
so they only give it eight
experts or 16 experts,
and deep Sk takes a risk.
They increase the number
of experts all the
way from eight or 16 to 256.
That creates a super
spark model where
all the parameters are basically
on the experts because
the start dominating and tent
just take a little bit of
pameter that model drastically
increase the performance
of that model,
but it doesn't increase
the compute a lot.
That's why DPC can make
a vari bold statement.
They only spend $5 million
to train a model that
is as good as a super
large dense model.
That's because the screen
law basically cross
all the way over the
screen law of the model.
Okay? That is basically
the internal mechanism
of MOE and how deep Excel. Okay?
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Do they increase,
there are some application
study you need to do,
but I don't think
they decrease attentingh
because attention,
like I said, attention is not
the parameter heavy
module in transformers.
MLP is. Okay. So in summary,
MOE essentially, fundamentally,
is a more computer
efficient model.
Yeah, please. So.
Good question. I'm going
to talk about that.
Yeah. Okay. Cool. Then this
seems to give you a
very interesting thing.
Why I care about
dens transformers?
How about I just continue
increase the number of experts?
I can make 1 minute experts,
my model is going to
have a perfect screen,
much better than
dens transformers.
Why we don't do that?
I think that's basically
your question.
Let's look at this, okay?
So the main problem is
basically at memory.
Like I said, if you continue
to increase the
number of experts,
your memory is going to explode
because each parameter will
take two bites to store.
Another thing is communication.
Okay? So if you
still remember this,
this is tins partism we
did for dent transformers.
What do we do is basically
partition the ww1w2 in MLP.
And now we are
changing our model
from a dense transformer
into a mixture of experts,
which means this w1w2
replicate a lot of times
number of expert times.
If we still apply this,
what will happen?
The cost of R reduce is
going to increase with
the number of experts,
and it will be super expensive.
You guys ready implement reduce.
It's super slow, okay?
So what do you do? That's why
we have expert parism.
Let's connect the dots.
Instead of doing this, uh,
doing ten parism for
part weight W and W
two, we can do this.
That is in the MOE module,
we are going to partison
along the expert dimension.
Okay. Because each expert
is going to compute
independently,
so we can part in along
expert dimension.
We are going to like I said,
we have eight experts, we are
going to part we have two GPUs.
We are going to
give the first GPU
for experts and second
GPU for experts.
But before we enter
this MOE module,
we have another
partitioning that is
not parting expert dimension.
For example, we can
part in along the H,
the S, or the B dimension.
Which means we are
basically come back to
this figure Before we enter MOE,
we part in along row,
for example, role
could be dimension.
It's just a symbol. But
after we enter a movie,
we want to part in experts.
So what do we do here?
Again, auto because now we are
recharging and we want to
recharge if you want to
switch the parting access,
we have to perform an auto.
That's why here you have an
auto and here you have an auto.
That's why Deep see could
release auto because
Auto is on the critical
path, you can imagine, Okay?
I hope this answer your
question. Yeah. And like
I said, MOE is not perfect.
MOE has another problem.
Let's look at this
problem. Please. Yeah.
Across the layers. Yes, I'm
going to talk about that.
MOs third problem is
like I said, if you
start doing this,
you are assigning different GPUs
with different umber of
experts. So what will happen?
So this will happen. Okay?
Let me go through this.
Okay. Another problem with MO
is once you apply this
kind of expert partism,
each TPO is going to have
a different workload. Why?
If I look at this, okay,
I have four inputs.
I have a sequence of four
tokens from X zero to X three.
And like I said, I
have a gating actin,
which will basically
decide which
experts this token will go to.
And here, I assume
my gitting factorin decides
one token will go
to two experts.
Okay. Here I have a
total of three experts.
So for the first token, it
decides to go to zero and two,
and for second zero and
one, blah, blah, blah.
Okay. And once this happens,
I'm going to apply
expert palism?
So I like different GPO
to take care of
different experts, okay?
And if I do this kind
of like a reshuffle,
I find that my expert zero is
going to for this sequence,
my expert zero is going to
compute on three tokens.
Okay. But my expert one
is going to compute
on two tokens.
And my expert to is going
to compute on three tokens.
And inside of
expert is basically
MLP so upper and downjection.
And here you observe
the problem, right.
So you can see expert they are
computing on three tokens,
but expert one is only
computing on two tokens.
Assuming we do
expert partisan we
assign this three experts to
three devices, what will happen?
So Expert one we finish, right?
And Expert and two
is going to wait.
And this is bubble,
or favorite bubble,
okay? It creates bubble.
And you can imagine,
if we give a super big batch,
okay with 1 million tokens,
badges that equal to 4 million,
and this can happen
very drastically.
For example, one expert
only have ten tokens,
but the other expert probably
have like half 1 million, okay?
And that's called popular
hot experts, okay?
And we can have this kind
of hot expert problem.
That's why that's why in
depsig they also invent
a lot of mechanism to make
sure this expert are balanced.
Okay, I value this
to you. Okay. Cool.
So summarize the dis 10
MO is basically first,
you drastically increase
the parameters,
which means that you
have to pay equal amount
of memory to store the weights.
Second, the communication.
You have to do expert partism
instead of tender parism.
If you look at the fire if we
do tender parism we don't have
this problem because
we part in the MLP.
Each MTMo is going to get
a protein with a MLP.
Okay, so it's not
relevant with the
number of tokens, okay.
And because we do
expert partisan,
we are going to have this
expert imbalance problem,
which will require more
engineering and more research.
Okay, please. Yeah.
So in MOE layers,
I'm going to perform
this batch Mdm,
which is I have a batch size.
I have a dimension, which
is the number of experts.
And then I have two
inner dimension
which is the upper
projection down projection.
And I decided that when
I entered this MOE,
I want to give different GPU
different number of experts.
So that means I part in along
the E dimension,
expert dimension.
But before that,
before I enter expert,
I'm not partying on
dimension, right?
That's why I have a wall.
Okay, cool. Okay.
This basically,
give you a global picture and
especially the rationale
of what we are
cooking today in language
modo community, okay?
And now, let's basically
take our brain out from
all these details.
Let's look at this
global picture.
We understand the
computer, right?
We have a teaching at MLP.
MLP could be a MOE,
whatever, right?
And let's think about from
a system perspective,
what are the hard
components to make it fast?
For MLP, we are
super good, right,
because it's MTO
and like I said,
how to make a metmo fast.
We write good kernels, right?
We do fusion. We know
how to solve that problem.
So we are good with MLP.
And for this tension,
there are a few ethamol
there and there.
We are good. We just give
it a good kernel, right?
We provide an
extremely good kernel,
we lower the precision
or whatever, okay?
For layer organization
and for this kind
of like animal wise
operation, what do we do?
It's a bad operator,
right, because you perform
a little competion
but you have to
load a lot of
parameters and width.
So what we do is we
fuse them into ethmol.
That's what we do
in homework, right?
We do extreme fusion to
basically increase
arithma intensity. Okay.
No, basically, I think we
already have a picture how to
optimize all the components in
the language model,
except this one.
This one is super notorious.
Okay? Like I said, it
has a lot of problems.
Flops is a square,
its memory is as square.
Okay? And next week,
let's optimize this one.
That will be the most
complicated program
we are going to do
in this course,
is flash attention. Okay? Cool.
That's why flash attention
is so important.
Okay. But like I said,
I think one thing
you observed from
this course is you have
a rule of sum, right.
So basically in many computer
systems in many algorithms,
if you design something that
is more complex, I mean,
in terms of complexity is
more complex than quadratic,
this kind of thing
is very hard to
get adopted in practice.
Okay. Yeah, I know you probably
study a lot of algorithms
from your algorithm course.
Like there are many algorithms
that is exponential,
like cubic or whatever.
Those algorithms
are not going to be
adopted in practice.
Okay? That's a reality.
Karatic is the most we can do.
Yeah. Okay, in practice.
Okay, like I said, we
want to talk about,
um, flashy attention next week.
The reason is because we
have a guest lecture coming,
talking about
speculati going in.
I want to give you some recap
on inference first so you
can enjoy his lecture.
Okay. Let's talk
about inference.
Okay. First, reality check.
So language model inference
is super slow and expensive.
Always use hATBT you can
imagine the number tokens
streaming to you is very slow.
I never appear
like Google search
is that when you type a query,
immediately you get all
the results, right?
So you have to wait.
Okay. So today, if you serve
this kind of language model,
you perform inference
on top of it.
You need like tens of A
100 or H 100 to basically
support this large model,
and it still take
like 20 seconds,
um, to generate a
few hundred tokens.
And why? Okay, let's look
at why. So recap, okay?
So what is the language model?
Language model is basically
a token predictor.
Okay? Look at the prefix
and pre next token.
This conditional
probability, right?
To recap, inference.
Let's leave our brain from
training to inference,
to recoup the inference
process of language model.
Okay? So, uh so first,
a user provides a
prompt sequence
consisting of multiple tokens
here artificial
intelligence is okay.
The prompt will go through
the layers, transformer layers.
Okay, we are already
very familiar with this.
Okay. And then it performs
competition once it performs
forward computation
there no background.
This is the inference.
Forward. Once you perform
forward, what do I do?
Like I said, it's a
xt token predictor,
so it will give you next token.
Here, the next token is.
The next token was sampled from
the output probability
over the vocabulary.
And once we have the next token,
what do we do we fit this next
token and artificial
intelligence is
the prefix prompt back into
this transformer again,
we repeat, we predict
the next togen.
Sorry. Future. Once we
get this future token,
what we do is we
can cm together.
Again, we repeat. Next token.
This process is basically
called autoregressive decoding.
As you can see, I'm
autoregressive.
I'm keep repeating what I do.
Every time I get a new token,
I feel that token back into
my neural network and I
perform a forward pass
over all the layers
in order to output next token.
Let me ask you a question.
Can you output off before
you get the future?
No, because it is
auto regressive,
that means in order to compute
the probability of of,
you have to know
the previous token.
This is a critical difference
between inference and training.
In training, you observe
the entire sequence.
You already know what's
happening in that sequence.
So you just directly compute
the loss against
the ground truth.
But in inference, you don't
know the future tokens.
You have to compute one token
at a time, one token at a time.
Remember this difference,
very important.
Cool. Okay.
So when will stop. So today,
basically, it will
stop in two scenarios.
One is, we have a
maximum sequence length.
For example, this language model
only support two k tokens,
so it will stop at the
last token at the two
k. Second is there's a special
token in language model,
which is called
unknown sequence.
And once you output the unknown
sequence, we will stop.
Basically, it means that
language model doesn't want
to outp more tokens.
Yeah, it will stop.
Okay. It thinks
that the prediction
is finished, okay?
So to summarize
the process, okay,
you'll get a language
model, right.
You have a pre field phase,
which is the zero iteration
where you take a prom,
you perform the
computation, okay?
And then you have
decoding phase that is
step by step every time you
decode one to at a time.
Okay? Then let's start
grounding this inference
process with our applications.
So what is our applications?
So in language model inference,
there are two applications.
Okay? So the first application
is called serving.
So what is serving?
So think about your open air
or you are Google, right?
So your goal is basically
you train a model and
you put your model into
some provisional GPUs and,
uh, you make it as a server.
And then a lot of users viewers,
they are submitting their
prompts into your server.
Then if you do this
kind of as a business,
for example, you charge
for each submission.
What do you want?
What's your goal here?
So as Gugu as benhan
what's your goal?
You want to minimize
your cost or paying for
that query for running query.
And this is for serving.
So people give you
a flat rate for each
query the submitted,
but you want to
minimize your cost,
then you can maximize
your profile magic.
So how to minimize your cost.
That is I'm going to
run GPU for media,
how to pay some
premium to media.
Yeah, OVDia is monopoly.
Okay? I cannot change that.
Of course, you can
make your own chips.
But let's assume how
to buy from Media.
You buy GPUs and you
serve your model.
So the more queries you can
support and you can
support using the GPUs,
then your cost of basically
completing each query is
lower and you can
make more money.
Okay, that's the economics
in citing valley today.
So everyone is trying to
like Google open air,
they try to basically
minimize the cost per query.
And in this kind of
service scenario,
the characteristic is
that you serve a model,
and this model needs to take
many many requests, right?
And it will receive online
traffic because you don't
know well the user arrives
and when it sub query.
So it can come anytime.
It's like a Google search.
And your goal as
the service provider is you
minimize your cost per query.
And basically per query will be
reflected as a term
called throughput.
That is how many queries
you can process per
second, for example.
You want that value to be
as large as possible. Okay?
But there's another
scenario which
is different from serving,
which we call inference.
And in inference, what
you do is, for example,
you deploy language on
laptop and you will
be the only user.
There's no competing resources.
You probably also don't
care about the cost
because it's your laptop,
you already paid for it.
Then what do you care about?
You probably care about latency,
you want to get the answer
as soon as possible.
You don't want to wait.
In that sense, you basically
emphasize latency.
You are a single user.
Every time you only submit
one request and you
want to minimize
latency to get a response.
So if we basically
boil this map this to
the computing is basically
serving we are serving with
a very large batch size,
we have a very large batch of
requests submitting the language
model and we want to run
over this batch and
we want to maximize
B as much as possible
to save the cost.
In inference, we have
a very small bitize.
Most of the times
B equal to one.
Okay. And I have
one last slide to
make sure you enjoy
the lecture of the guests.
So the gas is going to talk
about speculative decoding.
And speculate coding is basically
a method that trying to
optimize this scenario.
Okay, let me explain why.
So think about if
in this scenario,
every time my model is
going to only prods
one query and my goal is
trying to minimize latency,
then how can I minimize latency?
So the latency is essentially,
uh consisted of
this term, right?
Okay? The total latency
of getting my response
is basically,
uh the latency I spent
on generating one token,
that is a step latency.
I need to generate
many many tokens
and each step only
generating one token.
And also the number of
steps I need to generate.
For example, how many
tokens I generate.
Okay? So the latency in this
basic equal to one scenery is
basically the multiplication
of steps steps.
But like I said,
in language model,
you are not able to predict
a future token without
knowing the current token.
Which means that These
steps is going to be
a very important term
that as long as you
generate mot wins,
the latency is going to
increase the number of steps.
Then can we minimize
this step latency?
It's also very difficult because
every time you perform
a competition over
the transformer from
layer on to layer and
uh and GPU is not
super good at that,
because here you have
a S Equal to one,
your metamol
basically degenerates
into a very small metam GPU
when it process when it computes
smalltm versus
computer bigger met,
the speed is the same.
Because computer
bigger memo will
take more course,
more polarization.
Okay? And what speculate
coding does is they try to
minimize the number of steps to
generate that many tokens.
How to minimize that? I love.
I will leave it to
the gas lecture.
Okay? Cool. That's
all I have today.
Thank you.
A