Okay, yeah, let's get started.
So so logistics update,
please finish the
cross valve, okay?
80% and you'll get two points.
Next Tuesday, we'll have exam,
and I have asked TA
to hold recitation,
probably this Friday
or next Monday,
to make sure you
pass exam, okay?
And we will have a
recording, of course,
if you're not able to attend,
just, you know,
watch the recording.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, let's
back to the main content.
So today, we are going to
talk about some really,
really, I would say
timely content.
So m serving an inference.
Okay? I think this
is basically what the current
Silicon Valley is grinding,
like open Google Demand,
all these infrastructure
companies.
They are basically
opplementing M inference.
Yeah, in order to make
a perfect margin,
um, for serving Ms.
Okay? Let's go back.
Just a little bit recap, okay?
So this is our RM, right?
So we basically get a
ex token predictor.
I think you understand
this, okay?
And this is our M
inference process, right?
So basically, we have a prom,
which is a sequence of tokens.
And we give this token to
RM and we perform forward
pass through all the layers,
and we predict next token.
That is the first step,
which is called prefile
or prompt combination.
Okay. And then after
the first step,
We basically start, um,
generating new token and, um,
we give the new token
back to the neurotw arm,
and we try to
generate next token.
We repeat until we hit in, say,
the maximum sequence
length of the arm or when
we generate end of
sequence token, US, right?
This is the inference
process, okay?
To summarize a little bit, we
can from a computational
perspective,
um, my inference is
essentially two phases.
The first phase we call prefill.
That is you are
computing the prompt.
The second phase is
called decoding.
And apparently
prefill corresponds
to the zeros iteration that is
you process a prompt
and try to generate
it immediately the next
token, after the prompt.
And then this prefill
is only conducted once,
right because you just need
to process your prefill once,
and then you start
repeating your decoding,
Every time you only
decode one token.
Why? Because it's autoregressive
decoding, I already repeat that.
You cannot predict future tokens
before you know the
current token, okay?
Um, remember this, okay,
pre field decoding.
That is the computational
characteristics of inference.
Okay. And one more component
for M inference is,
we actually maintain
another, I would say,
data or data structure,
which is called key value cache.
So here, key value
basically corresponds to
the QQVuh in attention
the key and the values.
Okay. So high level,
at a high level,
this key value cache basically
help us save some competion.
But let's look at what
is key value cache.
Okay. So on the left hand side,
I think it's basically
the conversational graph
that you guys have been
very familiar with.
And on the right hand side
is basically a chief,
I quoted from somewhere,
which shows the
inference process, okay?
When you compute
that left part of,
um, at tensing, right?
So if you look at this, so
when we do our inference,
what do we do is every time
we observe a new token,
generated in the previous step.
And then we concatenate
this new token with
the previous already
generated token and
the prefel and we
forward that into
the neural network
in order to compute
the next togen.
When we compute the next token,
we only care about the query
of the next togen, right?
And we like this query of
next token to attend to
all the key values of
previous tokens, right?
So if you look at
this computation,
this chief is basically
trying to illustrate
the process I just
described, okay?
So why there is a
key value catch is
because basically we compute
this when we continue
this decoding process,
if we are able to save
the previous tokens,
Q and V, we can avoid a
lot of computation, okay?
And to illustrate
this, you basically
can look at these
two differs, okay?
On the upper hand side, um,
you basically see a computation
where the key value
caches are not catched.
Key values are not
catched, okay?
And on the bottom part, you are
seeing a computation
where the keys
and values of previous
steps are catched.
And you can clear the
difference, right?
So basically, every
time, if we don't save
the key keys and values in
attention of previous tokens.
So every time we
decode the new token,
we need to this query
we need to recompute
the previous KV and then
this new token query
to attend to all the KVs, right?
But if you are able to catch
this KV of previous
generating steps,
then we just need
to perform one,
uh attention competition,
and we already know
the previous KVs.
We just like this query
to attend to all the keys
and values to generate,
you know, the results.
Okay? Any questions
on this part?
Okay. Essentially, KV
catch is a kind of
a computation optation where
we treat some additional memory
to save for commutation,
right to accelerate
the decoding, okay?
Then I have two questions, okay,
to make sure you really
understand this process.
Okay? The first one
is what happens
on KV catch in prefilled phase?
So why in prefilled there's
like a so called QV catch?
It's because in pref
we see all the tokens.
We just perform one forward
across all the tokens and
all the KV catches are generated
for each token position.
So we don't how to
basically catch
the previous tokens and
wait for the next
token to generate.
Okay? What happens on KV
catch in perfs phase,
we are generating a QV cache of
all observed tokens in one pass.
Do we need to catch Q query?
Because in attention, we have
QQV do we need to catch query?
No, we don't know
the query because we
have to see that token in
order to know the query.
And when we compute the
results of the next token,
we are using the
current tokens query to
attend to all
previous token QVs.
Don't know if we don't
see that token, we
don't know the query.
Therefore, we cannot
catch Q. Okay?
Okay. Now you
understand QV catch
and then let's do this again,
I think we do this
for training and now,
let's do this for
uh inference again.
So, we also want to look
at computer memory
and communication.
So what happens in
inference and what could be
the potential for the neck.
Okay? If we look
at compute, okay,
like I said, for inference,
the computer essentially um is
consisted of two phases,
prefill and decoding.
So we look at one by one. So for
prefills essentially
the same training.
Nothing changes, right? You
observe the entire sequence,
you just forward that sequence
into language model, okay?
So no difference.
So for decoding,
one thing you noted that is
because every time we only
generate the one token,
we are not able to generate
future tokens, right.
So therefore, in decoding,
when we forward this token
into through the neural network,
we have to set S
equal to one, right?
That is generating one token,
we're computing one token.
Okay? I think if you
look at this graph,
I hoping emphasize
this again and again.
So what is the problem
of S equal to one?
It will hurt our
arithmetic intensity,
because the maximal sizes are
being reduced into one
dimension is one, okay?
The net spoken memory, one
thing new is in training,
we all basically put
all the sequence network
or compute the
QBach in one pass,
and then we drup gradients
and we updated parameters,
and we throw everything
away, right?
But in inference, we cannot
throw this QB cache away.
Why? Because we continue
to generate one token,
one token, one token, okay?
And every time we can
only generate one token,
but not more than one.
So we have to persist
this QB cache,
right through the
lifetime of this request,
this sequence until
all the tokens
have been generated and excited.
That means that we
have to always save
this vocacy for considerably
long period of time.
This will give us a little
bit memory pressure,
which I will talk about later.
What about the communication?
In fact, there's nothing
changed for communication.
It's almost the same because
prefer and decoding
communication is the same.
Whatever kind palism
you want to choose,
you will basically inherit from
the same techniques we
talked about in training.
In fact, inference, the
paralysm is even simpler, why?
Because we don't
have a gradient.
We don't have um,
basically, we don't have
that back chord graph.
We don't have optimal states.
Remember in arm training,
optimal states is where you
consume the most memory, 16.
Remember that factor. And
here we don't have that.
That means that our
memory pressure
on saving the
intermediate states
on saving the parameters on
saving the optimal
states are much lower.
It's mainly caving hash, okay?
Okay, I think we
basically look at this,
we go through computer
memory and communication.
I have additional question.
So how about bit size B?
So what makes this
different inference?
Okay, let's talk
about that, okay?
So in training, you always
fixed a static bisets right?
So because you have a dataset,
you just fetch a
static body sets.
But in inference,
it's different.
Your boy size is determined
by how many traffic you receive.
Like I'm holding arm end point.
I don't know when my users
will submit my request.
It's like when I will
submit a google query,
I have to make a
very smart decision
how I make the battery size.
Should I send a batch of
1,000 to the endpoint to
maximize my original intensity,
or should I just once
I receive one request,
I immediately send
it to endpoint.
This two has difference?
Because if I
wait to accumulate a
batch size of 1,000,
then the first user
will be mad with me
because he's waiting for other
users to submit queries.
But if I receive one request,
I immediately submit, what's
the problem? My bist
is equal to one.
Then my TPU is under utilized.
Okay? So you are facing
a very like a customer
phasing question.
That is how you exactly
make this batch, okay?
Which means that in inference,
the speed is variable.
Okay? You have to
correlate the speed with
your traffic with a
lot of computation
or utilization kind
of thing, okay?
So that's why inference,
basically the techniques are
developed around this B.
Okay. And we essentially
consider two scenarios.
The first scenario is
that we have a large B.
The second scenario,
we have a small B.
And I'm going to make this
even more extreme, okay?
So we have a large B, we are
basically Google and open a.
We are serving arm
where every day we
observe millions
of requests, okay?
And we call this
arm serving, okay?
And in another case,
basically, we have a small B,
for example, B equal to one.
That is, develop you deploy
your arm on your laptop and
you will be the
only user, right?
And you want to
optimize for this small
B. I think in last Thursday,
you have already heard
this data technique
for optimizing small B.
It's basically
speculative decoding.
You don't care
about the bit sets,
and you just want to accelerate
the inference latency
of a single request.
Therefore, we have
been developing
a lot of speculative
coding techniques,
for example, equal
one, two, three.
But today, I will shift your
focus to the first one,
how will optimize RTB.
And here, you probably already
sense why Open and Google,
they put a lot of
resources on this.
Because if you can
do this better,
you can basically you can use
less GPUs to serve
more requests.
And if you're able to solve
more requests using less GPUs,
you are creating a higher
profit margin because
you charge your der for
each token they consumed.
Basically, if you can
reduce your cost,
then the rest is perfect. You
can make money from that.
Okay? That's why a lot of
sitting companies they are
investing a lot to make
sure they can solve
the most request using
the fewest GPUs.
Okay, cool.
Then, in this large B scenario,
I think I already
emphasized the main metric
is one metric we
called cost per query.
That is how much you can
solve a query, how
much you need to pay.
And if we translate
this cross query is basically
a business term, right?
But if we translate
this business term
into something that is
more like a system is
basically throughput.
For example, how many tokens
you can solve per second,
using say, eight
GPs or six GPUs.
Okay? Next, we are
going to talk about
a few very key
techniques that we
can maximize this
throughput, okay?
But before that, I
want to dive deeper
into the problems of
inference at a large B.
So basically a large B size.
So, there are a few
problems that I want to
point out and I want you
to indeed understand this.
Again, I think we are
going to do this,
computer memory
and communication.
And for communication,
not a problem,
because, uh it's the
same with the training.
Nothing changes and it's easier,
even easier because
there is no open state.
So we'll focus on compute
and memory, okay.
So for computer, I
said, I'm inference,
there's prefew and decode.
So let's look at one by one.
So for prefew
what's the problem.
So now you have a
large bite size,
and this batch of requests
are submitted by users,
and your user basically type
a different prompt to the point.
And you have no control of
what prompts the we type.
So what's the first problem?
If you remember my first
lecture in this course, I said,
you are facing a problem where
each request has a different
number of tokens. Right?
Because I can ask a shorter
question and you can
ask a longer question.
And you all give
these questions to
my arm on how I can make
the battery competition.
Okay? I think in my
first lecture, I said,
one way to address
that is basically,
no matter how short or how long,
you basically pad the
shortest to longest.
And this is super stupid.
Like I said, if you do this,
you are going to not make any
money from serving irons.
Okay? So the first problem
is different prompts have
very different lens.
So how you exactly
should patch them?
Okay, definitely not padding.
Padding is wasting TPRs, ok?
The second problem is
undecodeUndecod was a problem.
I can ask you very
difficult query
and another person
as simple query,
like what is one
plus one, right?
And the answer is
a single token.
But I can let you do some
kind of deep research,
basically tell me what's going
on in this entire field.
So the problem is
different user can
submit different queries
and you don't know ahead of time
that how many tokens you will
generate for each query.
It could be super long or
it could be super short,
right? And you never know.
Even as open, I don't know
because this is up to the RM.
And if the RM reach US,
it will basically be terminated.
So the second
problem is ideal in
phase. This is super dynamic.
Okay? You don't know
different prompts
have different unknown
number generated tokens.
Okay? But you still want to make
sure from a service
provider's perspective,
you want to make sure
you maximally utilize
your GPUs to service
kind of requests, okay?
And like I said, another problem
with decoding I reiterate, okay.
So basically for each request,
when they enter decoding phase,
they have a sequence
that equal to one.
And what's the problem?
So if you are not able to make
a super big batch, right?
For all these sequence equal
to one decoding requests,
your GPO is definitely
under utilized,
because GPO is not super good
at scalar recommendation.
It's pretty good at, uh
like met more, right?
Okay? So basically
decoding phase,
you have to make a
super big batch.
But how to make that?
That's a problem.
Okay. And also on memory, we
have another problem, right.
So because B is large,
right, that means that
you are going to have
many many requests.
Ich request is going to
generate generator generate.
So basically, vertically,
you have a large bit size,
which corresponds to many
requests, and horizontally,
you have Is requests
continue to generate tokens,
and you are not going to release
a QB cache for I request
until that request finishes.
That means that if you
continue to increase
your Bdysize and you continue
to generate one more tokens,
you have to linearly increase
the memory you allocate
to see QB caches.
And at some point, that QV case
will dominate your memory usage,
and it will explode your GPU.
So how you manage this is
going to KV cash, okay?
Um, so basically to
address these problems,
we Next are going to talk
about the two very fundamental
and very, very,
timely techniques.
One is called
continuous patching.
That is a key technique
that invented one year ago,
maybe two years ago, 2023.
Um that technique basically
improves the throughput.
That is the number of tokens
you can generate by 20 X.
Okay? That is a
key breakthrough.
And the second
technique is basically
addressing the memory problem.
That is how you can
efficiently manage KB cache.
And that technique is
called page attention,
and that page attention basically
improve the throughput.
That is the number
token you can serve.
But another three
times. Basically, what
I'm trying to say is in
the past 1.5 a year,
all the people are running
this and they are
able to basically,
improve at least provide
improvement of 60 times
compared to two years ago.
Okay. So that means m inference
is being kind of commoditized,
o. Um, but before I
move into techniques,
I want to also,
reiterate a little
bit to enhance
your understanding
of um, would be equal to one.
Okay? So equal to one,
what's the problem.
So why is speculative
coding works?
I think by far, you already
understood the basic
rationale behind speculative.
But let's look at it from
a system perspective,
but not from algorithm
perspective.
So for B B equal to one.
What's the problem?
So for pre field, like I said,
there's no problem, right,
because it's basically
a single sequence and
you proceed the computation
as if you are doing
training. Okay, no problem.
But for decode, it also face
the same problem that
is you don't know
how many token you are
going to generate, right?
But that's okay. It's
better than B equal
to great B is a large number.
Okay? Another problem for
Bequal to one is here,
you have B equal to one,
you have S equal to one.
Okay. And now you
see the problem.
If you basically shift your
uh if you put your eye here,
remember, these are
only three dimensions.
Now, you have two dimension
which are equal to one.
You only have one dimension that
is basically not equal to one.
This means that whatever
kernels you launch here,
it's not going to
be super efficient,
because it's not able
to uti all the GPUs.
Okay? So what's that problem?
Okay? I will review later.
But before I finish, um for
memory I don't have
a problem because
I only need to
solve one request.
So it's very hard
for one request to
set by P memory unless
you generally want me
tokens for that request.
Okay. Then let's go
back to this one.
What's the problem as equal
to one, B equal to one.
If you remember this, we
want to maximize this.
But here you have equals
one, B equal to one.
Remember, when S equal to one,
B one, the floating point
operation is very small.
But how about the lumber bits
you want to read between
memory hierarchies?
It's the same.
Every time when you try
to compute one token,
you have to move at
least the model weights
from GBM to SRM,
and you perform a
competion GPU course.
That means that if you perform
a lot of dance competition,
you move that lumber bats once.
But if you perform
very few competition,
you still move that
lumber bats once,
when B goes to one,
S you go to one,
what happens is that during
this decoding process,
every time when you do a pass,
you pay the cost of moving
the weights from GBM to SRM,
but you only compute
very little.
Okay? That's a problem why
speculative coding works?
Because I think I talked
about this one week ago,
the reason speculating
work is because it
can reduce the number of steps.
You are going to
generate a manual
token, because you speculate.
You use a small model to
speculate, say, five tokens,
and you give all
these five tokens to
the large target arm to
perform one verification.
And when you perform
this verification,
so you pay a lot of cost
to compute four tokens.
But the problem is, this
original intensity don't look
much better because the
lamer ops is increasing.
Say, if you get lucky
and all the four
tokens are accepted,
then you are making this
equity much better.
You are amortizing the cost of
moving width between
the memory hierarchy
across many many tokens.
Okay. So that is basically from
a computational perspective why
speculative coding
can accelerate.
It amortize the
memory movement cost.
But like I said, if
you are not lucky,
if your acceptance rate
is low, for example,
your token was proposed wrong
incorrectly and your target arm
is not accepting these tokens,
then you are paying extra cost,
because you are paying
extra uh verification cost,
which we are making your
inference even slower.
Okay? That is specultive coding.
Any problem? Yeah.
Why speculative or large subset.
That's really great
question. Is basically
what people are
doing research now.
Yeah. We want to apply
speculate coding at a larger
B, but the problem is,
remember, the rationale of
speculate encoding
is that you amortize
the memory movement cost.
But the problem is spectu
encoding will consume
more flops without
a speculate code.
At a larger B, your system is
not memory bond with bond,
it's computer bond,
and you are saying,
I'm going to pay more computer.
Then you are adding
more computer bond into
your equiden system.
That's why very few works
actually do this.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Okay. Okay. No, I think I
hope I connect this back to
the last Thursday's lecture,
and you have a better
understanding of why
si degree works from
a system perspective.
Okay. Then let's move on to
today's major topic, okay?
So how exactly, um,
we solve that problem? One
is the batching problem.
The other is the memory
problem in large bases, okay?
So the two techniques, we
are going to talk
about is basically
continuous batching and pay
your attention. Let's
start with the first one.
Okay? So remember
our problem, okay?
For continuous batching,
we try to solve
the first problem
that is different
proms have different lens.
And different proms
have different
unknown number general tokens.
So how exactly batch them.
Okay. To begin, I think,
we want to visualize, the
arm inference or decoding,
uh, commutation along time.
Okay. So here you basically
can see this figure, right?
So you have a few times step
from T one to T eight, okay?
And basically, you start
receiving a request
with three tokens,
colour a yellow, okay?
And in the first
step, which is this.
This step you compute
prefile prefile compition.
And then once you
finish prefile,
what you do is you do
authorizive decoding.
Every time you decode one, until
you decode that EOS,
and you finish.
This is like visualize
on time. Okay?
Now, I want to
think about say no,
I have multiple requests coming.
How do I do compute on time?
Okay? One way, that is,
um, here, I have four
requests come in, right?
They have different
basically prefer lens.
The first one has three, second
has two, et cetera, okay?
And you make them a batch, okay?
Uh, let's talk about
auto batch later,
but just think about,
you can make it a
batch and forward
a batches work.
And you compute the prefiR
and you start generating. Okay.
But if you look
at the red graph,
you will notice that
the first request,
it will only
generate two tokens,
and then you enter the end,
Simpson, it's only
generate one token.
But this batch was bott
encked by the second request,
which will generate
a lot of tokens.
Until it finished
at the last sems.
But I think from a
service perspective,
what happened to the users?
So actually, for the
first ers request,
it already finished at
the Time step T six.
But because this request was
batched together with
the second request.
So the first der is not going
to observe in the results,
right until the entire
batch completes.
What it means, actually,
ideally, okay,
this request should
immediately exit from
that batch and go back to
the user with the results.
But because they are batting
together in the computer graph,
they have to repeatedly
go through that
doing nothing for
each request. Okay?
And this is one example of
traditional batching and why
this problem only happens
for RM Because in previous,
before RM what kind of
model people are serving?
For example, uh, you know,
very typical
convolutionar networks,
right? You don't
have this problem.
Why? Because if you
are going to solve
this kind of scenes,
you basically have
a batch of images,
and you throw a batch of
images through network,
and all the images in batches,
they all follow
exactly the same pace
to finish and you return.
But in RM, each request has
undetermined lumber
generally tokens, right?
That's the unique
problem to RMs, okay?
And you can say if you do
this traditional batching,
um, we have a big problem.
Like the first problem
is, of course,
the latency of this request
you are delayed. Right.
A second problem is, you
can see, during this left,
during the competition
over the last two wins,
all these sorts are bubbles,
which means our TP
is under utilized.
There's one more problem.
I will review later.
Okay. But to
summarize request may
complete at different
iterations in
arms because different
number of generate tokens,
and we are facing Ido GP cycles.
The third point is basically
imagine when we compute this
batch, what will happen.
So our user is going to
continue to submit
requests to our endpoint,
and we are going to
maintain a queue
here, Queue in requests.
If this batch is
not going to exceed
then we have to
let the order requests in the
queue to continue to wait,
and that will basically increase
a problem called
hydro line blocking.
That is your requests
are being delayed.
Let's see how we
fix this problem.
The way we fix the
problem is that
we can convert this kind of,
like, traditional batching into
a new technique called
continuous batching.
And this continue batching
was designed for arms.
Okay? And highlight was
the benefit of continued
batching that we have
a higher GP radiation
and new request can
start immediately.
And an older request,
once they finish, they can
be basically pushed out.
They can be excited immediately.
So, let's see how we do that.
Okay. Now, let's run
through this iteration
by iteration. Okay.
So here we have a
request to pull right.
This is our queue.
Okay? We are listening.
This is a survey.
Okay. And see. Imagine
yourself is open air.
Okay, you have a
queue here, a lot of
requests on their browser,
they are submitting requests.
And once the submitted request,
this request will
go into a queue.
Okay? So here we observe r1r2.
Okay? And again, we
have execution engine,
which is trying to
perform expedition,
and this happens on GPU.
And here, suppose we are
pretty GPU P and we can only,
um serve a basis equal to
three at maximum,
okay? Just example.
So in the first iteration,
we observe that in our Q,
there are two requests, right?
So we basically fetch them
from CPU to GPU and we say,
we are going to batch
them together to Act.
Okay? So here, my first problem
is how you basically batch this.
Okay, I would like to look
at this and think about
for 30 seconds where I grab
my mouse. Yeah, sorry.
Okay, let's continue.
So this is actually
pretty messy, okay.
The reason I do this in such
detail is because I want
to make sure you
understand this batch is
definitely non trivial.
Why? Because consider
if this is not RM
if this is just a thing
this batching is super
straight forward.
Basically I'm saying you're
observing two images,
and you put these two images on
the batch and you go
through the neural work.
And these two images
is definitely,
will be reshipped
into the same size,
same resolution, so you don't
have a batching problem.
But here, if we break it down,
okay, let's be very
hands on this.
If we decide to batch r1r2,
the first problem we facing is,
they likely have
different seqns.
But here, I give you
a pretty bad example
or have three works.
But let's think about they
have different umber tokens.
Then what's the problem.
So we are going to
forward two requests with
different sequence
through first attention
and then MLP, right?
So let me ask two questions.
So can we batch them
together in attention?
We can unless we cannot
unless we basically
pad the shorter one
into six s equal to four, right?
Because attention is
sequence dependent.
Atgen has to operate to.
And if you want to batch
all the operators,
you have to make them have
the same sequence mass.
Which means that at this moment,
you are already basically
losing some flops if you
do this patty, right?
So this is a decision that
many serving frame how to
fix to decide if you want
to batch this a lot.
Okay? I will come
back to this later,
but let's move forward to
the second part. Okay, here.
Suppose you finish
your attention,
and these two requests
basically entering the
MLP module, right?
So can you bet these two
sequence in MP module?
You can, that can be
easily done, right?
Because in MLP module,
it's not sequence dependent.
And this is extremely
important, okay?
So in MLP module,
I even don't care about
sequence dimension.
Right. Because in MLP,
if you still remember
the computation,
is basically each token will
be upper project
and down project.
Which means that in MLP,
I'm in this example,
I'm actually getting a
bit set equal to six.
It's not equal to two.
Doesn't make sense.
Because I enroll my six NS into
previously I B
times times H. Now,
once I enter MLP, this BNS,
my MLP is basically I cannot
speak to this S dimension.
Basically, MLP is performing
a math mode that is the
first dimension is B times.
And set H. Which
means that in MLP,
the computation is
token independent.
Each token will perform
its own communication.
Why this is super
important observation
and we'll review it next slide.
But to answer this question,
in order to batch it,
you are basically observing
two requests and you make
this two requests one
batch and you forward it through
the RM to compute the prefile.
In this prefile competon,
what you do is in the attention,
you probably pad them
together into the same lens,
and you perform a attention.
In the MLP, you can always do
batching without doing any
padding. You are good.
Okay. And then, see,
we are entering our
interim one, okay?
In our interim one,
what happened is,
we finish prefill we
still have two running
requests in the batch,
and we are going to transition
into the decoding phase,
and we are going to decode
the first token
for each request.
And meanwhile, on
our third side,
we are observing a new request?
Then let me ask you
another question.
So in this combination,
okay in the Interim one
competon what happens is
each request is basically
performing the decoding
combination, right?
So my question is, how
you exactly batch
these two decoding.
Okay, let's step deeper, okay?
If you look at left hand
side, same thing, right.
When we perform decoding, we
first go through
attention the MLP.
So for MLP, can we batch?
Yes, like I said, the MLP
is token independent.
So what's the bad inside?
Two, right? Because we
are comparing two tokens.
Okay. But for attention,
can we batch.
No, because here
is a bad example.
Assuming the first has first
token, second half three tokens,
then you cannot
batch because they
basically are performing
different competition.
One is attending to
previous three tokens
and the other is attending
to previous two tokens.
Their ship are different.
You cannot batch.
Okay? If you want to bat,
you have to pad, and if
you pad, you lose, right?
So essentially in
today's framework,
when you do this
kind of competition,
it's much more complexe
than your thought.
It's not like you
forwarding a batch
through petty and
you get results.
And what they do is basically,
they do very detailed
breakdown for tinin and MLP,
and they perform in different
batting strategy for ten MLP.
Okay. So in this
case, what do we do?
For example, in today's
um, serving framework VIM,
they will basically execute
the tensing kernels for
each sequence
independently without
one batch because they
want to save flows.
But once they
finish the tenting,
they are going to
put all tokens into
one big batch and
perform an MLP.
And then unter the next layer,
they are going to basically
break down a batch,
perform separate kernels,
and then batching together,
and then batch batch
and batch batch.
You got me right? Okay. It's
very complicated, okay?
Why did you do that?
Let's see Eteren three.
But before I move to eat three,
let's perform a
mental experiment.
What would happen if we
do traditional batching.
Okay. So now, we move
to interim two, right?
Because at interim one,
if we follow
traditional batching,
we already decided to issue
a batch of two requests,
and we continue to decode
next token for the
current running batch.
But at interim two,
what happens is we
continue to observe another
two requests RF and FL.
But if we follow
traditional batching,
the problem is um,
we issue this batch,
and we have to wait for
this batch to finish,
and then we take another batch,
you can imagine how
bad this is, right?
Basically, when you
are running r1r2,
your queue is increasing.
The size is increasing.
A lot of more requests
are arrival but arriving,
but you are not able
to basically add
or basically add anything into
the current running batch.
Okay? Cool. To summarize
before running interns
for continuous batching,
I want to summarize the
drawbacks or
traditional batching.
So as you can see, in
traditional batting,
once you issue a batch,
you are going to
wait for that batch to complete.
So basically, if you do this,
the issue is that request
in the queue they
cannot enter, right?
And also request finished
early cannot exit.
In this example, you see
this request to it
already hit US,
which means that it
should be exited.
But, you know, in my
previous illustrating,
I showed that you
cannot exit this batch.
And because of this,
GPO could be idle
due to a different number of
general tokens per request.
Then let's see
how continuous batching
addresses this problem.
Okay? So still, this is
our current status at one,
where we have a
running batch or two.
Each request in our
batch already decoded
one token and we
observe a new request.
So what will happen in
continuous batching
is that in continuous batching,
as long as, for
example, space allows,
as long as our policy allows,
we are going to
immediately pick up
the request R three and
put R three into
the running batch.
Okay, we're not
waiting. That is,
we're not making batting entity,
we are making requests
entity, iterating entity.
So as long as space allows,
we are going to
immediately pick up
or request and put
that into queue.
But here you are facing a
very difficult problem.
What's the problem?
If you do this,
if you pick up R three, right?
And you put cary into
a running badge.
You are facing a problem that is
you see what I try
to illustrate.
Okay? So here, three,
just enter the battery.
Remember, inference,
the first step
the zero step for request
is always doing pre fill.
But here, R one and R two,
they are different
states of the inference.
They are decoding
they are decoding.
So here you are saying
I'm making a batch where
some requests need to perform
prefill but some requests
need to perform decoding.
Does that make sense? This is
a totally different
competion, right?
One is like you observe to.
The other is like you
are decoding, right?
Superficially if you
look at this picture,
this is not batchb
at all, right?
Be computation
graph is different.
But again, let's step deeper.
I explain to you why
this is vegetable.
Again, let's break it down.
The computation composed of
two parts, attention and MLP.
Okay? So if you want to make
these three request
computation run together,
we look at one by one, okay?
So for their attention,
can we batch them?
Fundamentally we
cannot because one is
attending to one token
attend to operate tokens.
The other is three tokens,
you need to perform a batch
pass of the neural network.
Which means that they
are not a vegetable,
and this seems wrong.
If they are not vegetable why
are putting them together.
But in fact, if you pay
more attention to detail,
you'll find that if you look
like MLP, can we batch them?
Yes, for MLP, we can batch them.
Even for prefer and decoding,
we can put the MLP into
one single battered
run new network.
Why? Because like I said, no
matter in prefer decoding,
the MLP is always
token independent.
It performs on the
tokens by itself.
Okay? That means that
with this breakdown,
will not get a new inside.
That is, even if
we put prefer and cooling
into the same batch,
we can actually at
least batch their MLP.
Okay? Now, I want to
remind you what we
did last week, okay?
I think we run the flops
calculation for RMs,
and we count the number of
flops in a tensing and MLP.
I hope you still
remember the percentage.
So which component in RM
occupy the most flops?
MLP in most cases, okay?
Unless you have a super
long sequence ance, right?
But in most cases, you have
actually medium
to low sequenans.
Which means that if you do this,
yes, your system is going
to be more complicated.
But you actually can win a lot.
Why? Because like I said, in
most requests in most
sequence ans regime,
that MLP is going to
take 90% of your flops,
and if you are able to
batch it, you win, right?
And for attention, yes,
you are not able to batch it,
but it's fine because
it's only 10% of flops.
Let's just compute if
the sequential is okay.
Okay? So this is the
biggest insight,
taken from continuous batching.
And now you understand.
Okay? So why people
discover this form?
Because before all frameworks
like petrogTener flow,
they don't understand
this kind of
like they are not handled
in detail at this level.
So basically they treat
the computer as static
and they forward about
through the new network.
Okay? That's why
before C batching,
if people put the request
into petrog or into Tinder flow,
you are not going to
get great efficiency.
But later, I think
there's a paper
published in OSDI 2023,
basically 1.5 years ago,
they discourage technique,
and they are able to
break this down into
MLP and they do
different batching strategy for
different parts of the
graph. Okay. Yeah.
Sorry.
Uh huh. Yes, that's a
really good question.
That's a really good
question. So you're
saying if we batch
the MLP of rthter prefer
and Ring together,
because artery is super long,
then r1r2 is going
to be delayed.
Really good question.
I'm going to cover that.
Okay? Yeah, I publish
paper on that. Yeah.
To solve that problem.
Yeah. I can give you more.
It's called prefiw
decode disaggregation.
It's called disaggregated
prevent decoding.
That is the default technique
today for storing
really large bits.
And I think you already
spotted that problem.
But let's finish this
problem. Okay. And now,
you understand the essence of
condition batching, right?
So this is the first,
very good benefit of condi
batching, but there are more.
Why? Because now you
become more flexible,
Previously, you always run
static batch and you wait
for that batch to finish.
And now because you are able
to break this cobion graph
into a tinging MLP and
you do different
batching strategy.
So you can be more flexible.
So what do I mean
by flexibility?
So here, you can
always pick up a new request
and put it into a batch,
and make it running with
other ongoing batches,
which are in decoding.
And you can also do
another thing that is say,
if the art is finished,
okay, I just aced it.
Yeah, I just return it to users.
And that's why leave another
store for me to pick
up another request
from the queue, right?
And this greatly address the
halo line blocking because
if you compare
traditional batching,
and continuous batching.
What happens is in
traditional batching,
that running batch has to wait
for the slowest
request to finish.
But in continuous batching,
because
the batching strategy are
fundamentally different,
I'm going to always
pick up a new request.
I batch their attention
on MLP differently.
Okay? And in that way,
you can see at its sp in
traditional batching,
artery is waiting, but
in continuous batching,
artery is going to enter
the battery and
start competition.
And from a user's perspective,
they will basically experience
a much lower latency, okay?
And I will continue
to finish this, okay.
So at this step, you are
computing the prefer ASR and
decoding environment at two,
but you observe one er
two request, right?
And what you do is you continue
to pick up to request.
So here, apparently,
you cannot pick up
because like I said,
this TP only have capacity
to support request.
So what you do is you observe
that two is hitting US.
So you basically exit that
request, return to users.
Right? And you pick
up our immediately.
In this batch, what
happens is R three,
R one are basically
entering decoding,
but R four is doing pre few.
You basically act their
attention kernel separately,
but you batch the MLP
communication into
one big batch to
leverage diplls.
Okay? And same thing, right?
So same thing, you keep doing
this until you
observe no requests.
Okay. To summarize, okay?
So continuous batching
is really smart because
it handles early finished and
little rate requests
more efficiently.
And apparently because you
are able to make a
bigger batch size,
so you can improve your tion.
And the key insight here is
attention consumes small
percentage of flops,
Okay, at least for short
to medium six lengths.
And MLP kernels are agnostic
to the six dimension.
So you can always
batch whatever kind
of computation in transformer
prefer decoding into one
big batch to improve don.
Okay. Any question for
continuous batching? Cool.
We are good. Previously,
I thought I could
make a homework for you to
write connection, but
I don't have time.
But I think this is a
pretty good practice,
because you have to
be able to implement
this server client architecture,
which is a default here today.
But maybe let's do
that next time.
Then let's try to address
the second problem.
I think a second
problem is even more
opaque and many people they
cannot discover this problem.
It's hidden in a lower layer.
Let's see what's
the problem, okay?
So so in inference process,
let me repeat, right?
So M has a unique component,
which is called KB catch, right?
Um, so basically, in
processing new tokens,
the model actually needs to
not only the repent
of the current token,
it also needs the repenting
of the previous tokens,
and that rent is
basically the KB cache.
Okay? So this states of
previous tokens should
be kept in memory,
and this is basically
called KB catch.
Okay? So so a new
token, for example,
in this example, the future
uh the future comes, right?
So besides the token itself,
we also need to attend
to all the KB caches
of the previous tokens, right?
So we basically keep attending
to the previous KB catch
and we generate next token.
Okay. So basically, to
recap a little bit, okay.
So basically KV catch
is a memory space to
store the intermediate vector
representations of tokens.
And um, and basically,
we can understand
it as a working
set rather than a catch.
So I want to correct
this word, okay?
People in this field,
they call this catch,
but you probably know what
is the formal
definition of catch.
So catch is something that
you can hit or may not hit.
But in this example,
it is not a cache
why because it'll
always be hit, right?
Um I had a weird name because
the name was come up with
by machinery people,
not system people.
It's not rigorous.
But let's just understand
it that way, okay?
This is 100% hid cache, okay? So
So if you look at the memories,
kind of like a pattern, there
are two patterns, right?
One is, the size of the
QVC what dynamic grows.
Because as your
decoding continues,
the size of the QB cash
corresponding to the
request is going to grow.
But at some point,
it will shrink.
Why? Because that
requests finishing.
And because we apply
conditions batching.
Once that request is finished,
we are going to act request,
return it to users, and
we are going to release
the memory space corresponding
to the Qcache of that request.
Basically, from our
request perspective,
the memory of the QB
caches like this it inarly
girl and then suddenly
becomes. Okay?
Does that make sense? Okay.
Cool. Okay, so with that,
um, uh, we can just put K
catch in memory, right?
So why do we care
about these catches?
Okay. And next,
I'm going to give
you one of the most important
slides for today's lecture.
So why QBCach matters.
Okay. So what if I tell you that
basically efficient
management of Kcatch in
memory can actually improve
the AM service throughput.
This is pretty
counterintuitive, right.
Why managing memory can
improve throughput.
But this is the case.
Okay? So let's see,
we run a 13 billion model.
Um, 40 gigaGPU, this
is A 100 right,
40 giga memory, and
we are basically running
a 13 billion ama.
So if you look at
this breakdown,
because we have 13
billion parameters,
so we are going to first
consume 26 giga to store we,
right time two, okay?
And in addition, we
have a small other area
which will basically generate
those intermediate states.
But because it's inference,
we don't have to store them.
Once we generate the
we throw them away.
We forward to next layer.
So it's a small area.
So basically, uh, if you
look at the pink part,
is basically the rest
of memory that is
used to store QB
case for inference.
So, we basically have
a curve plot where um,
the X access is
running byte size.
Continuous batching continue to
pick up requests into the batch.
So the X access is the
running batch bite size,
which is the number of
requests you are
running concurrently.
Where access is
the memory usage.
So your starting point is 26.
Why? Because you already
consuming 26 motorways.
Then if you continue to pick up
more requests to run on
the GPU like I said,
the QV pattern will continue
to grow and then shrink.
But now let's assume
we are running
spatch we continue to
increase bite size.
Then your memory curve
will be looking like this.
So you will continue to grow.
Once you pick up request,
you consume some
memory for bias.
And at some point, you
are going to kit 40 giga.
That means that full
you're full on memory.
Okay? Okay, you probably
wonder why I draw this scroll,
but if you do a projection,
you'll find that at some
point, okay? I'm serving.
This running bitty size is
limited by memory size.
If you don't have
enough memory, you
are not going to accommodate
a larger bit size. So
why is this important?
Yeah, exactly,
because this is GPU.
As long as your GPU
compute is not bottleneck,
you can continue to
increase your bad size,
and your commutation is going to
finish in the same
amount of time,
even if you have a
larger bite size.
Which means that in serving,
basically, your workload
becomes memory bottlenecked.
You first hit the
bottleneck memory,
and then you hit the bottnFlops.
Okay? So suppose if we have
a way to basically flatten
this green curve from
this pretty steep curve
into a slightly more flattering
curve, this blue one.
That means that every
time we add a new request
into running batch my curve
is only going to
increase a little bit,
much slower than previous curve.
Then if you continue
to trouble this curve
until I hit the 40 giga
memory limit, you can see,
I do another vertical projection
if I'm smart enough
to make that curve,
then I can run
running bats of 40.
The problem is GPUs computation
is looking at less.
Basically, the throughput
is a function of bite size.
So if you are able
to uti GPU better,
then your GPO is not going
to increase significantly if
you increase the bite size,
which means that running a bat
equal to eight and
running at equal to 40,
they take same amount of time.
But because you are running
a battery equal to 40,
you are going to produce
more tokens per second.
Therefore, your throughput, if
you draw another
horizontal curve,
you say, the throughput
increase almost four times.
Okay. And this is a
pretty deeper inside.
If you don't do this, you
probably never observe this.
And this is my paper, VM.
Apparently, the
reason we did this
is because we are GPU four.
Consider you are
Google and you are
serving a lot of requests
using a lot of GPS,
you are never
observing this because
you are not hitting that
memory of the neck.
Okay? And we observe
this and we basically
build a system called VM,
and this VM basically using
this trick to efficiently manage
P memory and convert
that P memory into
improved throughput.
Okay? Now, you
understand the inside.
So how exactly did that?
Let's dive into the technique.
So basically why
existing systems
there memory inefficient, okay?
So so this is a snapshot of
the KV catch when using
a previous system, okay?
So where we find out three
types of memory waste.
So the first is reservation.
So which means that you
hold many memory stores,
right, and each story
basically saives
the QV cache for
each token, okay?
So, the first type of width
is physical reserviion.
So what is retbon?
Rtobon means that those words
that are not used
at this moment,
but will be used um for that
sequence in the future.
Why why there is such a case?
Because you're talking
generally one by one.
So when you allocate memory to
see the keV for that token,
you can first ask the
allocator to give,
uh, I'm going to
generate 100 tokens.
Why don't you just
give me 100, right?
But once you ask for this 100,
at the moment you ask you
are granted this 100 slots.
You're actually not
generating 100 tokens.
So that's called
retribution, okay.
So so here these
words in the middle.
Okay, they are reserved
because they don't store
any token at the current step
at the current deconing step,
but will be used to store,
uh like future tokens.
Okay? So the second
is basically called,
um, this is a reserved token.
You see that right.
So it will be
used eventually but not used
at the current step. Okay?
The second is
basically called, um,
I hope you have taken
operating system class,
right? You know this right?
It's called internal
fragmentation,
which means that those words
allocated for sequence,
but will never be used.
That is all allocated.
Okay. So this happens because
the output length of the
sequence is not known or priory.
So, in fact, you
don't know how much
to allocate at all, okay?
So you just try.
For example, I just allocate,
for example, the maximum
sequence length,
and I hope my sequence is
going to use that many tokens,
but in fact, it will exceed
earlier than using
the maximum signals.
So this is what calls
internal fragmentation.
And, of course,
finally, you have
some sort of external
fragmentation that is because you
allocate different
different sorts
to different requests
and there are
some fragmentation between,
and you're not able to
use this kind of thing.
So so how severe this is, okay?
So if you look at this,
memory breakdown, okay?
The memory waste is
very significant.
So basically in this profile,
data with different memory
management schemes,
we observe only 20 to
30% of kebic ash is
actually utilized to
store the token ss.
The rest of the space
is basically being
wasted for reservation for
internal and external
fragmentation.
Okay? And basically what
we do is, we basically,
try to leave that we
basically try to leave that
green ban all the way to 99%.
Okay? That is all
the memory will
be eventually utilized
to save tokens.
And I think at this
point, you already,
if you are very familiar
with memory management
in operating systems,
you probably know what's
our trick, right?
It's basically you can use
a so called virtual memory,
okay, use page tables.
Okay. But you have to do this
machine learning systems.
Okay, that is basically like
we try to connect the dots,
what you have learned in OS and
what we are doing today
emergency systems.
So now you understand
the problem. So
what's the solution?
This is a very old
problem, okay?
So the way we solve this
problem is basically we
employ the old idea of
virtual memory and paging
in opening systems.
So as we all know,
OS use basically pages to
um to reduce fragmentation
in the physical
memory space, right?
So, and use virtual memory for
efficient space multiplexing
for different processes.
So here, what we do is
basically you can think about
each processing OS as
a request in, Okay.
I use similar kind of
idea to reserve the
fragmentation in
KBCche and the unable
efficient space sharing
between requests.
And this is why the other
attention is called
page attention.
Okay. Cool. Let's see.
Let's run this pretty
quickly, okay?
So to begin with,
we first partition
the GPU memory for
that pink body in my
memory breakdown graph,
into, um, into an
array of token blocks.
So here, a token block is
basically a fixed size
of chunk of memory that can
store the states
from left to right.
Here I hold many
many blocks, right?
My blocks are equal to four.
Okay. So to clarify
a little bit,
so the tokens here
are not strings.
It's basically the KB case
corresponding tokens.
So basically each
token block will store
the key vectors for each token.
Okay. So it's actually more than
just one bites or whatever.
It's a fixed size.
So these are token states
the vector repetition of
the token in sequence.
So for example, in
Lama 13 bin model,
each token state would consume
about 1 megabyte memory.
Which means that each token
block is one megabytte, okay?
Yeah. So, so on top of this,
we basically introduce
page attention.
So this is a new implementation
of the attention kernel.
So we completely change
the way like when you
perform attention,
how you fetch memories
from GPU memory.
Okay. Previously, you
just fetch it from
a continuous trunkil
memory right on
TBM but now we make it pages.
So you have to redo
that kernel inpation.
Okay? So basically, we find
out the fundamental
limitation of
the previous system that they
require all QB states right for
a sequence to be stored in
a continuous trunkil
memory in GPU.
And this is a
convention over like in
typical deep learning workloads
where the input and
output ships are static.
I think this was
taken by granted by
many deep learning frameworks
like entropy and priority, okay?
But it turns out that uh this is
highly inefficient
for inference where,
the sequence length
are highly dynamic
and you don't know how many
token you are going to generate.
So basically page attention
directly address
this limitation.
So with page
attention, basically,
the QV catch are
basically stored
in non continuous
trunkle memory,
and they can be stored
in arbitrary position
in the GP memory,
but we have a mechanism
to many them using pages.
So we basically
virtualize this QV catch,
uh to logical and
physical talking blocks.
Okay? So let's see how it
works with the example.
Here I have a request with
the prompt Alan Turing is a
computer scientist, okay?
So basically in the
logical view, okay,
the tokens are still stored
in consecutive blocks,
um, and the order is
preserved from the first
token to the last token.
But I'm going to
introduce a page table
where the page table is in
the middle, which I who here.
And it's going to map
the virtual table into
the actual physical
table, in the GPO memory.
So basically in the
physical view, um,
on the other hand, the
tokens in the same sequence,
they may not be stored
in uh adjain blocks,
and the order, the orders
between different
blocks are arbitrary.
But we introduce
the mapping here.
Basically, this mapping
is going to tell you how
each other logical view
is going to map to
the physical view.
It's exactly the same
as pages in operating
systems, okay?
So let's continue with
the example, right?
So let's see the model has
generally the next token end.
And we are going
to write this in
a logical view as the
next token continuously.
But what happened is
using the block table,
we are going to
query where exactly
should we write in
the physical memory.
In this table, it tells
that we should write u at
the physical block number
one at the third position.
We do that indexing and we find
a physical block
one third position,
and we basically write
the actual QB catch.
Okay. So then we
generate the next to
mathematician and we keep
querying the table, and
we're right there, right?
You can see the actual
writing is not continuous.
And finally, we generate
another token and we find
the second block is used up.
So what do we do,
we are going to ask
the memory allocator to give
us one more low, right?
So here why I emphasize this.
Because I'm only asking my
allocator to give me one
more only when my previous
talking block was used up.
And this completely
remove reservation.
I never need to reserve anymore.
Why reservation is pretty bad.
You suffer a strong
opportunity cost.
If you reserve memory, you are
not going to make that memory
usable for the incoming
requests in all set.
That's exactly the
same with page tables
in operating systems.
You basically eliminate
the opportunity cost.
Okay. So here, I found my
second block table is done.
I moved to my third
third row and
this third row was allocated
in runtime only when needed.
I keep doing this,
allocate it on
demand and keep writing
to next o. Okay.
And this is even
better when we have
multiple requests coming
to the queue, right?
Because if you have multiple
requests we basically,
give them different
logical views,
and this logical view we all
basically mapped into
the same physical space,
which is paged,
okay, by kernels.
Okay. Cool. To summarize,
okay, uh, let's analyze
the memory efficiency
of page attention.
So first, we have very minimal
internal fragmentation.
Why? This is because
the internal fragmentation
only happens
at the last block
of the sequence.
So our internal fragmentation
is bonded by the block size.
It's not going to be greater
than in my previous
example, four tokens.
At most we only
wait three tokens.
That basically eliminated
the internal fragmentation.
We also don't have
external fragmentation.
Why? Because now we
always allocate a block
of fixed size that
is four tokens,
so there's no external
fragmentation.
Finally, we don't have
reservation because each
block is allocated on demand.
So whenever we need it, we
allocate we're not
reserving anything.
We completely eliminate
the opportunity cost.
Basically as a result,
you can see in VOM
the memory utilition is
greatly improved. Agree.
Yeah. We basically eliminate
the external and retribon cost.
Okay. And we get a 96.3%
okay your addition.
Okay, so that'll
basically wrap up.
Put your attention.
Any question? Yeah.
Um, we need. Yeah.
Okay. I have some rumors here.
Basically when we build
this V I think Jensen
is pretty mad.
Um he sort of like,
you should be media who builds
this B media should be more
familiar with their hardware
and this should manage
their GPU memory in
a way that is page.
But it turns out that
we build this first.
Yeah. That's why we now
collaborating with
media pretty closely,
and we try to push this into
their GPU as a native feature.
Yeah. Okay. Okay, cool.
I think I covered the second
key technique, page attention,
and apparently this
page attention
has already taken
off. Yeah, please.
Yeah. I don't know,
but I think when we
part this in 2023,
we are ahead of open on serving.
Yeah. So basically,
when we put this,
I think this make
a huge impact to
Google Dibne and open air,
they all try to
mimic our technique.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah.
Very good question.
You do application. Yeah.
You run block size of 16,
32, 64 and you figure
out the one that is best,
you tune the kernels.
Yeah. Yeah. It depends
on basically block size.
I think I create with
asking the question.
If you have very
small block size,
then your indexing
cost is higher.
If you have a large piece
you basically go back to
the continuous memory regime.
So you have to tune it.
Yeah. Okay. And this is
basically I think this
is many people's
favorite paper in 2023.
Because this improves the
inference soaring cost
by three X. Yeah, pretty good.
Okay. I hope you enjoy
this part, okay?
And then let's move on to
an even newer technique.
And I think I try to
answer your question.
So apparently
that student already aided
the question, right?
So when you do
continuous batching,
you indeed improve the
addition because you
batch you make a pretty
batch when you run MLP per.
But the problem is, say a
prefew is super long, right?
So a decode only have
one token per request.
Essentially, if you
put all them together,
you are saying only doing
what you maximize
your throughput,
yes, but you are
delaying the latency
for other decoding requests.
So how do fix that problem?
Let's see. This is
a pretty hot topic
I have to cover because
I think this year,
2025, a lot of company they are
moving into this
architecture from C speci.
It's called pre field decode
desegregation and I say,
what's the problem?
Okay. So I think,
as I have already ind
many times, okay?
So at least in 2023 and 24,
people are basically trying to
grind this so called
throughput metric.
They try to maximize
the number of
tokens they can serve
per second given
a limited lumbaus you
can see this limit keep
being pushed higher,
uh, like 24 X,
3.5 X or whatever.
L basically ground
this throughput.
Okay? But besides
throughput, okay?
Many applications,
they are offered
as a service to users.
Therefore, for such services,
we do have some equally
important metrics,
which we call service level
objectives, or in short, SO.
You've probably heard
about this work
many many places many companies,
they want to guarantee
so called SO.
Okay? So in ARM there
are uh two most important
service level objectives.
One is called TTFToh the
other is called TPOT.
This is a pretty weird, word,
but let's try to remember them.
So TTFTT to first too.
TVOT time per output token.
So what do they mean?
Okay. So a chat bot,
like HGBT, they need to have
a relatively fast
initial response.
Therefore, lower TDOT.
That is when you
type a car into HTP,
you expect to see the first
word as soon as possible.
You don't want to
wait. Otherwise, it's
a pretty bad experience, right?
But when the first
token was generated,
if you ever I'm
pretty sure you have ever
used the CHITP right?
You can see the ChatB token
was streamed, one by one.
So once you observe
the first token,
you are going to read
from the first token.
And from a service provider's
perspective, what a problem.
So as long as they
can generate tokens
as fast as your reading
speed, they are good.
Because you are not
going to read faster
than what the generated, okay?
So um so basically, um,
in order to make the
user experience better,
they need to have a lower DFT.
But after that, okay,
the following generated
text doesn't have to
be faster than the average
reading speed over human.
So how many words you
can read per minute?
I can tell you number.
It's roughly 15550
words in English. Yeah.
Okay. So you don't know how
to be faster than that,
but you cannot be
slower than that.
Otherwise, you
don't have to wait.
Okay. So this means
that the TPOT that is
the time per output token
after the initial
token generated,
doesn't have to be fast,
in order to make satisfy
the user experience.
Okay. But in contrast, okay,
say, we have another
task M task,
which is summarization, right?
So der will use a
summarizing application,
and they can actually tolerate
a longer initial response
because when you
try to submit a batch
of documents to RM,
you don't want to see the
first token immediately,
you want to see
the eventual results
as early as possible.
So in that case,
you don't have to
prioritize your time to first
token because the user doesn't
care about that. They
just want to see.
S, after 1 hour I
eventually see,
uh, my summarizations, right.
So in this case,
TTF T is not important,
but TPOT is important because
we want to generate
as far as possi.
Okay. And this gives
you a sense of
what is TDFD and TOT, okay?
So then the question is,
in the presence
of these two SOs,
TDFT and TBOTuh is
throughput sufficiently
good measure
for arm serving systems?
And turns out that this
is not always the case.
So, suggest that we have
a system that can serve
ten requests per second.
That's our system
capacity, okay?
But when we post
actual constraint
on TDFE and TPOT, okay,
that is we need to
solve t requests,
and we also need to satisfy
the service level objective.
That is, TTFT need to stay
within 200 milliseconds,
and TPOT need to stay
within 50 minutes seconds.
Okay, we put these
two constraints.
And if I put this
two constraints,
you can see, many requests
are not satisfying request
this constraint, right?
Meaning that they are
not actually meeting
the service level quality, okay?
So we call the portion of
this throughput
that is subject to
the constraint as as goodput.
So that is the good part
of this throughput.
That's why it's called goodput.
Okay? So you can see,
um, the term goodput properly,
reminds you of some
very old things
that you learned from,
uh, maybe computer networks.
I think when they do
package delivery,
they also put a constraint
on these kind of things, right?
So here, you can see.
Um, I'm sorry indeed share
some more similar idea.
So this basically means that
high throughput cannot
always translate into
high goodput once we
factor the latency into
this picture, okay?
Um, Okay. So this
leads us to ask another
important question.
So why do existing systems
they fail to achieve this
kind of high goodput.
Okay? And let's take
a step back and
understand how a request
goes through the RM.
And here I make a pretty
nice G for you, okay?
So I will let you look at it
for 10 seconds. Okay.
So basically, I think
what I try to convey
in chief is what I introduced
in condition batching,
uh your prefuel and decoding,
they are batched together.
Okay. And I think you
already read that question.
So if the prefel
is pretty heavy,
then your decoding is
going to be delayed
because of the highway
work load prefuel.
Okay? That is one major drawback
for conditions batching.
Okay? So, um,
so let me reiterate
basically prefuel is
very compute bond,
meaning that a small batch of
prefill they are like when
you compute the prefiel face,
they are like you
are doing training.
It's pretty computer heavy,
and a small batch of pre fuel,
they can saturate
the GPU competition.
But on the other
hand, the decode,
right, they need
a much bigger size because
S equal to one, right.
So they need a much bigger size
to actually sat with
the competition,
which means that they have
very distinct computational
characteristics.
And, um, and because
continuous batching basically
cool case prefer decode,
right into the same
batch, the two phases
actually interfere
with each other.
Okay. So let's see
a comparison here.
So on the left, um,
uh, we batch RON R two,
o you can see the first
is RN second R two and RA
is going through the
decoding phase and
R R two is going through
the prefill phase,
and we are going to put
these two batches together.
Okay. So we can
see that in the red window
in the pink window,
when Art arrives, ROs decode
time, which is in blue.
It will once you put it into
the same batch
using con batching,
it will be significantly
delayed, right?
Because Rtools prefer
will take longer. Okay.
And same thing, actually
arts prefel also
get a little bit
delayed because you batch the
decode into Rtools perfil.
Okay. But if I do this,
suppose I have a way.
Basically I run RN RT to prevent
decoding on different dips.
I don't have this problem.
So RN decode will continue
following its own pace,
and RT will just do its profile.
Okay? And I can make
this even more serious.
In reality, what happens is,
you have a streaming of
requests coming. Okay.
Every time you pick
up new requests,
put into the continued batching,
you are going to introduce
a pre fuel that is going to
interfere with the decode
or other requests.
And this can create a
cascade of interference.
So basically, if you continue
to continue batching, yes,
utility is high,
but this decode,
they are going to be delayed.
And if you have a latency
constraint on decode,
you are not going to
meet listening delay.
Okay, listening constraint.
Sorry. Okay. So then
if you want to basically to
a good service like GBT,
you want to maximize your sput
while you still meet
the listening
constraint what you do.
Okay. As a result of
this interference, uh,
when service must satisfy
both TDF and TPOT,
um, what they do is they
basically add multiples.
Yeah, they allocate multiples
to basically diminish
the interference.
Okay. Um apparently,
the reason the problem
of adding multiple is
that you're going to pay
more to satisfy your
service quality, right?
Okay? So what's the solution?
The solution is pretty simple.
I think you already get that.
Why don't we just put preview
and decod on different dips.
We're not going
to batch anymore.
We just basically put
prefer and deco on
different dipUsT if basically
gives you an example where,
um, I allocate two GPUs.
The first GPU basically
take all the preview job.
And once it finishes prefiw,
I'm going to forward
the QB catch
from the first DPU
to second DPU.
And then I batch all the
decode in the second DPO.
In that way, I can
completely eliminate
the interference between
preferent decode.
This makes the system
even more complicated.
Why? Previously, I do
everything on one
single GPU, right?
I just do everything
in a kernel level,
and now you're asking me to do
a distribute system on
how to communicate.
But this is what
we do today, okay?
I'm going to reveal why this
can be better in
the last lecture.
Okay, thank you.