Okay. Let's get started.
The last class.
Yeah. Yeah, let's just step
into the main content,
and I think we were
covering serving serving.
Essentially, we
have large bases,
and we identified here
three bottleneck.
The first one is how to batch.
Second one, managing TV catch.
And the third one, if you have
a latency constraint then
how you should change
your architecture.
For the first one,
I think we covered
the continuous batching which
is a pretty good technique,
20 X throughput improvement.
Second one, page tangen.
We manage the key memory as if
we are managing the memory
in operating systems.
And then we start talking about
the SO service level objective
like we want to maximize through
while we want to adhere
to these constraints.
So how we do that. We
were talking about
the disaggregate prefill and
decode the two phases in
inference. Okay. Let's continue.
This is a pretty nice g.
The only difference
between dis aggregate
gate architecture and the
previous architecture
is that we put
prefill and decode on
different devices,
for example, GPUs.
And because we do this,
so what will happen?
Because prefer and decode,
they will basically
both use model weights.
The first difference is
that we are going to
replicate model weights
on two parts of devices,
and that is a memory
cost, of course.
That means that if you have
a very small scale cluster,
you shouldn't do this because it
was a lot of memory for
replicating weights.
That's why I disagree
with prefer and decode,
they actually work in a
relatively larger scale,
like you have a lot of GPs
where memory is not
an issue, okay?
The second difference
is that because
prefer and decode when
they do this competition,
they only need to
return to v catches.
But the V catch will be first
computed on the prefilled GPUs.
But I said that we want to
put these two phases
on different GPUs.
That means that when we
proceed to the next
phase in decoding,
we have to migrate the V catch
and that will incur
communication.
But this is pretty exampleable
because we only need
to migrate that once.
It's quite different
from in training,
every iteration we
need to do that.
Here, we just do it once.
Okay. So here's the
new architecture.
That's pretty new, okay.
This was developed last year,
but soon this dominates
Aserving and this is becoming
the new architecture,
the default architecture adopted
in big companies like Open Air.
Okay? To give you some
more in depth understanding
of why this works,
I will give you I will go
through the slide, okay?
So let's see a very
concrete example where, um,
why this simple strategy that is
desired in prefer and
decode would work, okay?
So this is the real
profile, okay?
We did from a co located system
that is a system that is
not doing disaggregation
co location
like continuous matching, okay.
And in the XX, you
basically observe
the request rate that is
the incoming rate request
is increasing, right?
And in the Y XX is basically
the basically latency.
And the reason we draw a line
because we want to subject
to latent constraint.
We cannot request
beyond that line.
Okay? And the reason
this curve is
increasing is because as
more requests come
into our system,
they are going to compete
in further resources.
That's why your system is
going to accept more requests.
So those requests will basically
sharing resources and less
requests will be satisfied.
The average latency
will increase, okay?
So we can see
from the upper figure that
this system can roughly
support three
requests per second
that stay within the first
latent constraint,
which is DTFT.
Okay? And if you look
at the second figure,
this system can roughly serve
1.6 requests per second,
that stay within the
second latent constraint,
which is TPOT tokens per second
time per out token, okay?
And if we want to impose
both constraints,
then essentially we need
to take a minimum of
these two, right,
which is a Like,
if we do this kind
of architecture,
we roughly can serve
1.6 RPs RPs basically stands
for requests per second.
That is a pretty good metric
that people talk
about in observing,
like how many RPs you
can serve using one GPU.
Now let's see how this
aggregation changes
this picture, okay?
So here I'm adopting
a disaggregated
architecture where
I use a so called 2p1d.
And this is also a
conventional form
that you represent
the disaggregation.
2p1d means that you allocate
two GPUs for pre fill
and one GPU for decode.
So basically XP D means
that X GPU for prefill
and Y for decode, okay?
And of course, like I showed
you in my previous slide,
they need to replicate
the model with,
okay, and they need
to communicate catch.
But what happens here is
you'll find a pretty
interesting phenomena, right?
So both curves are
flattened a little bit,
right, compared to LY.
It's because you now put
pre fill and decode
on different DPs.
So prefilled phase
is not going to
compete with decoding phase.
They are operating
on different DPLs,
which means that the
prefil can run more
smoothly than putting together
with decode and decode
can also run more
smoothly than putting
together with prefill.
That's why this curve
with flatten that is,
if you want to subject
to constraint,
you can actually
serve more rates.
And if you look at these
two, in the first figure,
if you want to subject to
the let constraint which is
P line TT oft smaller
than 400 milliseconds,
we can roughly serve
5.6 RPs using two GPUs.
And in the second
figure, you can say,
if we only put decode, we
only all GPU to run decode,
we can basically serve
roughly, I think it's ten,
ten RPs and you can
calculate the goodput.
So basically, I use two GPUs,
a Sorry, that figure is
5.6 RPs per GPO, okay?
So if you use two GPO is
basically 5.6 times two, okay?
And on decode, you only
allocate one GPU decode, right?
That is ten, and
you take a minimum,
right, which is
basically ten, right?
And you divide it
by the number of
GPUs total GPOs you use.
So you can see, I
can solve roughly
3.3 RPs per GPU, okay?
That is, I can solve
this many requests per second
that are subject to constraints.
Okay. And if you compare
the per GPO goodput that
can serve on the
right hand figure,
I use G 3.3,
but per GPO 3.3,
on the left hand, I use one
GPU, but it is only 1.6.
I have doubled my goodput.
Okay. That's why, if
you do this kind of
distal aggregation,
you are essentially,
getting a lot of goodput.
Okay? So to summarize,
simple deaggregation helps us
achieve two X output per GPU.
And this is why, like,
as applications mature, people,
especially the
service providers,
they care about latency.
They want to provide the
best quality user experience
to their users,
and they started,
kind of like grinding on
this latency constraint,
and this deaggregation
architecture
basically took off, okay?
A little bit more,
okay, this paper was
published by B, in my lab,
and apparently we betted
on the right thing,
and we wrote this paper
in the end of 2023.
And at the time this
paper was written,
it was not quite popular.
But for some reason, you know,
this am serving like this case,
it's becoming more
and more competitive.
And like open air Anthropic
a lot of endpoint providers,
they try to gain customers.
And the way they gain
customers is that they try to
assure their customers that I
can give you latency
constraints.
Like, if you use my
service, you are
going to have a better latency
as well as good throughput.
And they start looking
at this paper, okay?
And this paper was later
amplified by deeps z three,
which was published
earlier this year.
And I think deeps
Wiz three basically
opens all the
serving techniques,
and one feature they
highlighted is that they use
a disaggregated
serving architecture,
okay, which is this paper.
Okay, cool. And one more
thing I want to add is,
if you compare continuous
patching and deaggregation,
it seems that we are going
back and forth, right?
So in continuous patching,
we are putting it together.
But in deaggregation, we are
putting in separate, okay?
But actually it's not because,
um, they are basically
for different objectives.
So for continuous batching,
I think we don't
care about latency.
We just want to make sure
that the LGP are fully
utilized because by three LGP,
we can basically
maximize the throughput.
But for this aggregation,
we started caring about latency.
That is throughput subject
latent constraints.
That's why later when
this application area become
more and more mature,
people start doing
disaggregation.
And also the key insights of
continuous batching also
carries to this aggregation.
For example, I think
one key inside that
I've been spent a lot
of time explaining
is basically we are
batching MLP differently.
We don't badge, but we
batch MLP at level.
Another key inside
from is that we are
trying to exceed the finished
request as soon as we can,
and we are trying to pick up
new requests in the
queue as soon as we can.
And this is also implement
in deaggregation.
Okay. Cool.
To wrap up this area, okay?
So this is basically
I think I covered
four most important
techniques in serving today.
And apparently inf and
serving is a very high
stake research topic today,
because it correlates with
how much money you can make,
right, if you want
to become a company.
So that's why this is
a pretty hot area.
A lot of PhD students,
they are working on this, okay?
And roughly, I covered
all this, right?
So on scheduling, we
have conduced patching,
we have a disability
prefill decoding,
and there's one more technique I
didn't cover is chunk perfil.
Okay, I will leave it to you.
And the second one is
spectrum decoding,
which is you try to
accelerate single request
inference. In most cases.
And the third one is basically
address the memory
bottleneck of b catch.
So basically how you
manage key catches.
I covered page changing,
but there are a lot
of other techniques.
For example, if
you don't want to
exactly preserve the accuracy,
you can do sparse v catch.
That is, you only
turn to a part of
catch and you discard
the rest, okay?
Or you can even do
sparse changing
without computing like
key catches, okay?
And finally, of course,
as you may know,
we can optimize all this
competition at kernel level.
That's what we did
at the beginning.
Okay. Any questions on
inference? Cool, cool.
Then let's move to our last
topic, flash changing.
So why do we care
about flash changing?
Because I think we
are going to use this
figure again, right?
So we have figured
out how to optimize
every component in this
LRM except attention.
Okay. Let's recap, okay.
For all those mathemad
we just to telling,
we write a pretty good kernel.
For those element wise,
we do kernel filion and
that's what we can do.
But except, I think
it's pretty bad because
as you can see,
it has a quadratic
compute complexity
with respect to sequels.
It also has a quadratic
memory complexity
with respect to, so pretty bad.
And it's quite different.
It's not a simple mathma
because you need to
basically do some mathema
and then do soft max,
and then you do some
mathema again, okay?
So let's break this down.
So we how this
works is basically
that we pick a column
and row from Q and,
right, and we try to
merge them together.
We get a matrix
which is ebined here
is the previous notation
as six lines, okay.
And in language model,
because we are doing,
like, at generation
or causal mask.
So we basically mask out
the upper part, okay?
And we only care about
the lower part because
one token can only to
pre seconds, right?
So we max it out,
and then we take a
soft max, right?
We lobize per row.
And then we use
this lobize weight
to time the value matrix, right?
We get the output, okay?
And in the parent you
can see the problem is
in the middle, right?
So basically in the middle,
we have to materialize
very very big matrix and buy
in here and earn the sixths.
And this is pretty bad. Okay.
So one thing I want to
do before I explain flight
changing is basically,
so how bad this is.
I just want to give
you a sense, okay?
So I'm basically
putting my lamber here.
I think you guys are already
very familiar with lamber, okay?
I'm also putting the today's GPU
most popular GPU as 100
side by side, okay?
And so the compute complexity
is four B as square,
for the attention.
The memory complexity
is as squared,
and I'm going to assume
a few values for
B and H. I basically
take the value from Lam.
Here I'm processing
bases equal to one, one,
and lab has 32
and H is the hidden
dimension, which is four.
Pretty decent pretty
standard numbers
like I get from lama.
Then let's assume
as equal to four K,
then we start computing how
many flops and memory we need.
Fur K is not a crazy lab seque.
I think this language model
can process four K tokens.
If you do this computing, you'll
find that in order to compute,
I roughly need 256 flops.
It is not big because if
you look at the table,
it can process much
more than 256, right?
But if you look at the memory,
it's a little bit crazy.
And if you want to
materialize the YS or matrix,
it basically need
512 gig by memory,
that means that I
need to put this many
content on my HPM.
But even HI hundred
they only have 80 giga.
You can see as we continue to
scale the sequence dimension,
the first bottleneck
hit is basically
memory, and then compute.
So Yeah, that's because
because GP achectal design,
GPU memory is much more
scarce than compute
at this moment, okay?
Then let's look at
the problem, okay.
There's one more problem, okay?
So this is basically the
standard tangen competition.
Let's go with the
line by line, okay?
So here we basically
have we have our Q,
right, which is by D, okay.
We load them into HBM,
that is bandwidth memory.
The first step is we basically
load at Q and into HBM,
and we compute, okay,
and then we write to HBM, okay?
Um, and here, apparently,
this is a mathema,
so you can do ting,
right, and you know
how to do ling.
So that's why I said
this is by blocks,
you load block by block,
and you do ting, okay?
And once you compute,
you basically put
back to HBM, right?
And you start doing
the softmax of S. So in
order to do softmax of S,
all you do is you need to
read back from HBM to SRM?
So you perform softmax,
and you get the P and
P is the same shape
of P is normalized from S, okay?
And you write P back to HBM.
Okay. As once you get P,
you basically load P
from HBM to RM again,
you perform another matmod.
This is P times V,
teen square times
the value matrix,
and you get the result O,
and this O is much
better because
it's not as bad
as anymore, okay?
But you need to
write O back to HBM?
And of course, you know
how to do this, right?
This matmod so you do telling.
That's why you read
block by block, okay?
Okay. But you already
found the problem.
The problem is that
we are repeatedly
reading and writing
the bigger one,
SS and by matrix from
HBM to R. And this
basically is another
issue that is you not
only suffer from the problem
of having SYS matrix,
which is take a lot of memory,
you also need to read
and write between
that matrix between
the memory hierarchy
and which is pretty slow.
Okay? So, like I said,
we know how to
optimize the first one
to avoid a lot of read
and write, right.
We also know how to tell
the third one because both
are basically mathema.
But the problem
is on the softmax
and we don't know how
to do that, okay?
To give you more sense,
this is the memory on today.
So GPHB has, for example,
40 gigayt memory,
but reading and writing to
it is only 1.5 terabytes/second,
but SRM is much better.
If you continue to read between
SRM HBM you'll basically
suffer from that bottleneck,
which is 1.5 tB per second.
Okay? Cool. And then
we start introducing
flight changing, okay?
So basically flight changing
address this one, okay?
That's why it is so I would
say, remarkable, okay?
And of course, today
is three, okay?
And here I basically
took their I
think brand when they
were three at two, okay?
So the idea is pretty
simple, right?
So like I said, the problem
happens because you
have this, okay?
This is pretty bad. And so
this is bad because first,
it takes a lot of memory.
Second, it takes a lot of read
and write between memory.
So in order to address this
is the idea is pretty simple.
Like how is there
algorithms that we
can avoid actually
materializing sense,
but we still get
the final results.
Okay? That is what
we did when we
do telling at the
manum level, right?
So we never read the
entire matrix into run,
but we can still perform
the limitation, okay?
And once we have a
technique to avoid,
we have at least two benefits.
One is we don't have to pay
the peak memory
to stress, right?
Second is we can avoid reading
and writing repeatedly
between memory.
Okay? So but like I said,
we also want to apply
this into training,
not just inference in training,
we need to perform
one backward path.
That means that if
you indeed have
one approach without
materializing grade results,
then the problem is
how you can still
take gradients
against that because
you want to propagate
the gradient all the way
back through this
forward competition.
You need to perform
gradient competition
against and then QK,
and then the parameters.
So that's another problem.
Okay. And essentially
flight extension fix
actually solve both
problems, okay?
To give you a recap,
basically in mathema class,
what we do is, we do telling.
Every time we read a
block and we perform
that competition on tram by
reusing the loading
of the blocks,
and that can basically
accelerate a lot.
And we know how to do telling
for matabol and our problem
is hard to tell in for softmax.
Okay. So let's get started.
Indeed, there's an algorithm
that allows us to tell it,
but not for softmax,
but for something else.
Before we understand
the algorithm,
I want to go one by one,
like I did for Band,
I'm going to tell you
version one, routine two,
sin three, and eventually
we reach flattenion.
So before you can
understand flatten,
I think you want to
understand softmax because
softmax apparently is the
critical component here.
So how to implement softmax.
This is softmax. I would like to
look at this for
maybe 10 seconds.
Pretty simple, okay.
Let's pass this. This
is pretty simple.
We have V inputs which
is basically this X.
What we do is in order
to compute the softmax,
we are having two loops.
In the first loop,
we are basically
take exponential of each input,
we accumulate them into
this D. And once we
finish the loop,
we will basically
get a D capital V,
which is the accumulation.
And in the second loop, we
basically do normalization.
Okay. Very, very simple.
But this is problematic.
I think you already encountered
this issue in your homework one,
this can easily go
overflow because
you are taking an
exponential of lamber?
And if you do this combination,
say if you do integer very
low precision integer,
it can go overflow, right?
So The problem of this like
vanilla original flavor of
soft max is that it
can go overflow.
So apparently, we can
fix this very easily.
That is, we do a save soft max.
So in the sip soft max,
what we do is basically,
instead of directly taking the
exponential of each input,
we are going to minus
the maximum input
from each input and we take
a smaller exponential, okay?
And apparently this is going to
reduce the risk of
going overflow, right?
So this is S max,
I think manual you implement
this in your
homework one, right?
So essentially what is this?
It's basically
another loop, right?
So in the first loop,
we basically try
to figure out what
the max value among
all the inputs, okay?
So in this loop, basically
we will return the
maximum value.
Okay. In the second loop,
it's the same, okay.
With the previous loop, we do
the accumulation of
this expsure term,
and then we do we do oration.
Okay. Okay? Very simple, right?
So let's ask questions, right?
You have been doing
this for a while, okay?
So this loop is not efficient
because you are read
and write between
memory and memory
hieros in three loops.
The most straightforward option
is we do loop operate filion.
So if you look at this,
do you think we can
fill some loops here?
Okay? We indeed can,
because we find that
this loop and this
loop are independent.
There's there's no variable in
this loop that depends on the
value of this loop, right?
So we can basically do
a very quick fiusing
of these two loops,
but if you look at this loop,
and this loop is pretty
difficult to fusion
because apparently this
loop, depends on value,
which is the capital
A and D capital A
was returned at the end
of the second loop,
which means that the
second loop, uh,
if the second loop
does not finish,
we cannot actually, uh,
proceed to the third loop.
Yeah, question. Yeah, I will
tell you how to do that.
We can indeed fill these two.
How do you fill that? Instead of
directly computing
the maximum value,
what we can do is we can
create alternative sequence.
In this alternative sequence,
you can say I define a d prime,
and this DI prime was defined
as accumulation or a
partial accumulation.
Does that make sense a
Basically, DI means that I
accumulate from one to I.
Okay. And in this
partial accumulation,
what I do is basically,
I use my current value X
the current index value to minus
the current maximum,
I already scan.
Okay? And once I define
this alternative sequence,
what I discovered is that
I find the first thing I
find is when I
equals to V right?
Dv prime equals to dv.
That is, if I look
over a sequence,
I still get my dv, which
is exactly the same.
Then the idea is,
how about I just
define I create a
loop that I just loop
once and I will
get dv and once I
get dv I can proceed to my
third loop, which is good.
I'll finish. How to do that.
I can do some very simple
mathematical derivations.
Because I define
this in this way,
right, so I write it down here.
So this is d. And my idea is I
try to find some recurrence
in this alternative sequence.
So I'm going to first
make this term out, okay?
From this line of this
line is basically
like I leave the last item out,
right from the
accumulation, okay?
So here I only accumulate
from I to from
one to I minus one and I put
the last item out, okay.
And then I'm going
to slightly alter
this term to So
from this to this,
what I do is I basically leave
another explained
term amount, okay?
And because I do this,
I found that this is
basically my d minus
one prime, right?
So this is by definition, okay?
So I can basically
substitute this with
my d minus one prime, okay?
And I started finding
recurrence that is
there's a relationship between
d prime and d minus one prime.
And this relationship
is basically show here.
Okay? Any question? Okay.
Why I care about this recurrence
is because by looking
at this equation,
I find that when I
calculate the d prime,
I actually only depend
on a few values,
the first value nine is D minus
one prime that is the value
of the previous iteration,
and a few values
that is minus one,
which is the maximum I scanned
in my previous iteration,
and MI that is
the maximum and maation
X and MI of course.
That means that this is
basically a recurrence.
I can calculate one
value by one by
one by looping over
this high, okay?
And with this, okay,
I can basically start putting
my previous like the first
and second loop together.
I get this one, right.
Previously, I used two
loops to get dv, right?
Now, I can only use
one loop to get dV.
And this is pretty
simple, right?
So I basically let J to
loop from one to capital
V. I first compute the
maximum M so far, right?
And I use this value.
This is my recurrence. I just
derived in my previous slide,
right, and I use that to
calculate the dg, okay?
And once I scan
through this loop,
and I reach my last step V,
I can basically get this dV.
Okay. Very good.
Cool. So this algorithm
is called online Softmax,
and of course, it's also safe
because we have a lower
risk of going overflow.
Okay? And the reason
I introduce this
is because flash attention
is basically built
on top of this.
We are basically using
online softmax to
calculate the accumulation of
that basically this loizer.
So let's see how we
can connect them.
But before that, I want
to ask another question.
Can we further fill these loops?
Because we still have two right?
So ideally we just
want one because
a You can reduce memory
I can fill these two.
It's pretty hard
because like I said,
each step in this loop it
depends on the value of
decapital we and decapital we
is only produced at the last
step of the previous loop.
It's very hard to
fill these loops.
Okay. Let's ignore it first.
We stop here for Softmax,
but let's try to basically
put this into context.
Put this into the
attention context.
Here I'm going to make
things a little bit more
complicated but not
so complicated.
I definitely believe
you can understand.
We're going to put the
online Softmax into selfing.
I think it's pretty simple.
We still like for example,
I have a few rotations.
Here I'm grab a row from
Q. I'm grab a column from.
I do a dot to dot product
to get the ten score,
and then because
in my next step,
what I'm trying to do
is I try to calculate
the soft max of all
these 13 scores.
So what I do is instead of
doing that step by step,
I'm going to do
online version, okay?
I'm going to still remember
this recurrence, right?
This is how I
calculate soft max.
So every time I calculate
the one value Xi
and I look over
this from one to N,
and I basically
compute my MI so far,
and then I use my previously
defined recurrence
to get the DI prime, okay?
Very good. And what I
do is I iterate from
one to N and eventually I will
be able to get
remember DN prime.
And D and prime is equal to
the soft mass accumulator.
Accumulation term, long inter
once I get this
accumulating term,
what I do is I'm going to
perform the standard softmax.
This is my second loop,
which I showed in
my previous slide in soft max
in online softmax version.
And I'm going to get
the thin square,
the thin square that is out.
Once I get this what I do
is I basically to turn to
my value matrix because
attention like this,
this is essentially
like a weighted sum of
all the rules of V. So
I have this thin
square and I basically
accumulate into O and I look
over from one to from
all the rules of
the value matrix and eventually
my final accumulation will be
the output I want in attention.
Okay. Any question
about this one?
This one is basically a
simple application of
online Softmax into
self attention.
Of course, you can do
the previous version that
is 19 version of attention,
but like I said,
you are going to
have three loops,
but this one only have
two loops, right?
Cool. Then assuming
you understand
this online Softmax
version of self attention,
then let me ask you
a few questions.
So let me clean this.
My first question is, can we
further fill these loops?
Okay. Two loops, I mean,
this is the first
loop, Loop one,
and this is my second
loop, Loop two.
Can we further fill these loops?
If you remember our discussion
just a few minutes
ago, what I said is,
we are not able to fill this
one and this one is because
this roman term is D
and this loizer it
depends on the output of
the last step of this loop,
so we are not able to fill that.
But magically, if you only
care about this output,
but not this, you can.
Okay. That is basically
the magic of flex engine.
Remember, our goal is we
only want the output.
We actually don't care
about the actual in score.
And if you only
care about this O,
you can actually
fill them together,
and I'm going to show you, okay.
But remember, if you
care about this one,
you cannot because this
one actually depends on
no and no measure, Okay.
My second question
is how to get XI.
So here, apparently, XI is the
value from Q and Q, right?
So if I ask you to directly
implement this algorithm,
all you do is basically
in the first,
you are going to read
the input tokens,
you do mama, you get X,
and you start performing
online softmax, okay.
And in the second iteration,
you are going to repeat read
those values in order to
get X because like I said,
it's very hard to materialize
the entire by a matrix.
So you have to do
partial combination.
So that's why this one
can be further improved.
Okay. If you
directly apply this,
you are still going
to kind of like a uh,
read this input X
twice into two loops.
If we want to reduce
this into once.
How to basically fill this one,
this one. Let's show that.
What I'll do is I'm going to use
exactly the same trick I
used for online soft max.
That is, I'm trying to define
an alternative sequence,
and I'm going to discover
some recurrence from an
alternative sequence.
The way I try to define
alternative sequence,
I try to define this way, okay.
So the intuition
here is basically,
in self changing, we actually
only want O, not A, right?
So if we can find self find
some recurrent structure
in O, then we are good.
We can actually utilize this
kind of recurrent structure
to just finish every
computation in one loop, okay?
So let's define this, okay.
This is our previous
step in OI, right.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to create the
alternative sequence,
which is OI prime, okay?
And in the O prime,
what I did exactly the same
as I did in line softmax.
That is, I only care about
the accumulation so far.
So basically, this is
like this is like
the accumulation
accumulated value
in the last loop, right.
So you plug in here,
okay, you basically
get this term, okay?
And what you do is nify O
prime as like in the ration,
how many I have accumulated.
Okay. Good. Cool.
You'll notice that,
of course, when I equal to N,
I will get the ON and I
get O prime equal to O.
And this O is essentially what I
want and the large version
of this original loop.
I can basically write
this O back to my result.
So that means that
if we are able to
find some recurrence,
all we do is we just run
this loop from one to N,
and we'll eventually reach
results in one loop.
I'll do that? Same thing.
I'm going to play some
very simple math, okay?
This is my definition, right?
Okay. That is the
accumulation so far.
What I do is, I'm going to,
I'm going to lift
the last term out.
From this line to this line,
what I do is I change
the side to minus one,
and I put the last
term out, okay?
From this to this is I
try to make a term where
I'm able to express
OI minus one prime.
And the way I do it is
I first read this is
Onus one and I try to
compense the rest.
And the way I compense the rest
is I introduce
these multipliers.
And you can check this
and this will get
canceled and this will
get canceled and I
basically return to this.
Okay. But I just do this.
Let's make it slightly
more complicated, okay?
And this is my previous
last term, here.
Okay? And once I get this,
what I do is I'm going
to put this term and
this term out to here, okay?
Because this is
multiplier, right?
So I can put it
out from this sum.
And I basically get
this term times this
multiplier and plus
my last term, right?
Then I find that I
finally get here.
This is by definition,
O minus one prime.
I do a substitution,
I get O minus one prime,
and of course, I carry a lot of
multipliers. And the last term.
Okay. And this is
built here math.
By doing this, you
will find that there's
a recurrence that is OI prime,
and the relation
between O prime and O
minus one prime is that
I need to multiply
O minus one prime with a
multiplier and then
add another few terms.
And if you look at this index,
you'll find that only a few
terms are getting involved.
For example, the inside is in
order to get the OI prime,
it only depends on field term.
For example, O minus
one prime which
is my result in previous region,
and dinus one prime,
which is the result I get
from my previous iteration.
Di current region,
and I minus one,
I get in the recent is not
the N. Because
you're doing this,
you will find that if I'm able
to find these recurrence,
I just need to write
one loop that looping
over from one to N,
and eventually I will
get my On prime.
And I said in my previous slide,
On prime equals to ON.
Okay. Cool. We got good, right?
And then we get this.
This is the flat,
one loop to get O.
That's because we
basically looping
from one to N. Every time
we just pick a small one
row of Q and one column,
we calculate the X and then we
start performing
our online softmax.
Once we finish our
online softmax,
because we notice that
the partial value of only
depends on the recent results
from the recent iterations.
We basically start
computing our OI prime and
as long as we follow this loop
to looping over from one to N,
we all get ON O prime is
basically what we want.
Okay. Thing you'll
notice that if
you compare this algorithm to
the previous version
where I have two loops.
The thing here is you
only need to read
the input once. That's
the first thing.
The second thing is Every time
we are only compute
partial results,
so we are actually not
materializing the YS matrix.
We are not materializing
the matrix in
HBM or in R but we are still
able to get the result.
This is the highlight
understanding of
flashing is that it is
a kernel fusion of QQVftMx
and output projection.
It's a very aggressive
kernel fusion.
It fills everything altogether,
to reduce memory to
reduce material in the
intermediate memory, okay?
Cool. To repeat, we
only read X one,
that is QK once, okay?
We never materialize the full.
We always compute
the partial results,
but we are able to get
the final results, okay?
And we also never materialize
the soft max ones
because we carry that
into the recurrence.
Okay. So of course,
this is a preliminary flax.
I can make it even
more complicated
by telling. This
is the one loop.
So in order to compute this,
I can further tell the
Q and columns of QK.
I can further use the tricks
I introduced in mathema.
So in real flax
changing what I do
is I pick up like
rows and columns.
Every time I only
pick up one block,
I compute results I
accumulate, okay?
And because we avoid
materializing that by X matrix,
so we save a lot of memory.
And here, I'll let you
appreciate this different.
To explain a little bit.
It's basically running
the recursive sequence,
but we add some ting.
In the original loop,
every time we pick a row
and column and then we do
that online softmax and
online combination and we
write the results back.
But here, I'm further
break it down.
I'm trying to pick
just one small block
and compute some results,
that is the partial results,
and then I multiply it with
the value matrix and write back.
Keep up calculating.
Okay. That basically explains
the mathematics behind flash.
It's pretty deep.
I think you'll get the gist,
but if you want to
delve into details,
feel free to check my slides.
And then there, try
to make sure you
understand every symbol.
I think we will address
the first problem,
that is how we can
avoid repeatedly
memory reading and how we
can avoid materializing.
Basically, the S matrix
that saves memory.
But I said there's
another problem.
You want to do backward. You are
not materializing as but
you want to backward.
How to do that. I think you
already know the answer.
I just recompute
during background,
I just recompute math.
This sounds pretty
counterintuitive
flat make compute faster,
but it seems that it is
making computer slower.
But it turns out the
magical thing is,
even if you introduce more
flops, using re competition.
You can still, you can
still make it faster.
Why? Because the main
bone is not compute.
The main bone is you move
contents between HBM and RM.
But because of the introduction
of flax algorithm,
you avoid a lot of memory
loading between HBM and RM.
Even if you introduce
more flops,
you still become way faster.
Does that make sense?
If you look at the
table, so basically,
if you compare the
f theoretical flops
of standard and flat,
you can flat is more because
the intro is more forward,
it needs recompute.
But if you compare the
global memory access
is moving things
between HBM two HRM,
the original ten is
more this large,
but flex only more like 110.
Therefore, if you
run this actually on
real GPO you get it right,
so it's much faster.
Okay. And I don't
want to repeat more,
but flash change is pretty good.
It performs a lot of
speed ups on changing,
and more significantly,
it basically also
reduce memory usage and
memory loading between
memory hierarchies.
Okay. Okay. To summarize the
high level gist of flashing.
So first,
it completely avoid
materializing the largest of
size B as square B
by size equals less
and lamb heads, okay?
It will make compute worse,
but it's okay because we
are memorable next,
so it's okay.
It will greatly reduce
memory movement
between memory here.
That makes sense
because previously,
there's no memory I have
a three layer loop.
I'm basically making a change in
just one loop that
basically reduce
lot of memory memory movement,
and then I can further
tell it so I can
further reduce memory
loading, okay?
I can tell you
more. There's more.
Why flat is successful.
It's not just
because it's three.
There's more, let me tell you.
Flat is even greater
with what you thought.
There's a cascade effect.
I'm going to connect
this to what I told
you in other parts
of this course.
Because it saves the
memory of B as squared N,
which means that
now when you, you
don't have to materialize this.
You don't want to suffer
the peak memory usage.
It enables two possibilities.
The first one is like
before flight changing,
we can only train with basis
equal to one because
of the peak memory.
Because if we increase
by memory increase,
we can mostly just
train with one.
But now with flight changing,
we can avoid
materializing matrix,
which means that now we can
train with much larger bases.
I think you understand
why that's good, right?
Because when you are able
to train much larger bases,
you're going to effectively
introduce increase intensity.
That's the first
cascading effect
brought by flaine. Okay.
Higher original intensity.
The second one is be
full flexion because
we need a lot of memory to
accommodate that peak SIS.
But now you don't
have to do that,
which means that you can also
avoid doing gradient
checkpointing.
You still remember, what is
the next effect of doing
gradient checkpointing?
You basically pay one more
forward during your training.
Now because of flat,
you don't have to pay,
you can allocate all the GP to
your actually MFU not HFU
if you still remember
the definition of MFU and HFU
which means that you save
another 25% of flops.
As you can imagine,
that's why fla is so.
It has a cascading effect.
Because we are able
to save memory,
you are able to
do so many things
and that will greatly boost
the training efficiency. Okay.
And later, I think media
and the original authors
of f by the way,
we have author of f
here as the faculty.
Yeah. He's going to
join us this fall.
His name is Danford.
I think I mentioned in my class.
And un the authors of
flex they are doing
more and more like kernel
network positions.
For example, they're
doing more grad fusion.
They also try to use more
advanced go features
to collaborate with
the media to kind of improve
the memory access patterns.
Okay. Finally, I want
to share my finals why
flattening took curve.
The first one is you need
to bet on the right
thing, right?
One reason is because
changing to curve,
like previously
before attention,
people do various model actors.
But at some point, everyone
only do self attention.
And if you bet the right thing,
you can predict that
in the future in
the next three years,
people will all do.
You should just focus on optimal
attention, not nothing else.
The second, of course, um,
It is due to the
architecture of GPUs.
Like I said, GPU has
very limited memory.
If you are able to save the
materialization of SPS,
you are going to
be a big winner.
That's why when you
develop software,
you should definitely pay
attention to hardware stack.
You should always co design
between hardware and software.
Cool. That's pretty my talk
about flashing. Any question?
If not, then let's move to
the last part of this course.
Now you have learned I
think I have covered
all the important techniques
today emerging systems.
Maybe there are
some more machine
learning oriented
things I didn't cover,
but I think the system
part I already covered.
Now let's try to pass
deeps with three.
Let's try to understand
how deep Sa with three
enable the training of
such a good model
using $4 million.
I think you did that
in your homework.
So let's do that.
But before I do that,
I want to first give you a gist
of how language model
are trained today.
I'm going to connect all the
techniques we trained, okay?
So today, this language
model La language models
will basically use what we
have learned so far and
combine all of them together.
This figure gives you a kind
of impression that basically
how many many GPUs,
you are going to
partition your LLM
into many many stages.
Each stage is a
group of GPUs and
you do pipeline
between these stages.
You have a pipeline
scheduled minus bubble.
And then in each stage,
you are allocated GPUs,
and you perform a different
kind algorithm, for example,
data and model and
enterprism or expert parism?
And you have a large
cluster coordinator
basically orchestrate the
GPUs and make sure you have,
very high MFU, okay?
And if we talk in more detail,
so basically there are
a lot of loops, okay?
The most loop is basically you
have inter alborism
where you probably use
1f1b or some fancier schedule to
orchestrate the
pipeline parism, okay?
And then when they into it,
now you have in PPE,
you basically have many stages,
and inside each stage,
you are assigned a device match
like I covered in my
previous lecture,
and you are basically using
some 0203 data and data prism,
or you are using
some kind of magnris
to basically paralyze
the competition
of that stage on
a group of GPUs.
Okay. And then in
the third loop,
what you do is, like I said,
you probably need to do some
gradient checkpointing or
competition to further
reduce the peak memory.
Okay. And now it
boils down to GPU,
GPU is basically assigned with
a partial graph of
the language model,
and you start running
those petro graph
operators on the GPU.
And what you do is you
employ petrogen inter
and inside the ytrogente you
do graph level definition,
right, you optimize those
operators, fill them, right?
And then you have many
operators filled together,
you'll try to provide a
pretty efficient kernel that.
And that is what you do
for tail inflation
this kind of thing.
Okay. So that's basically
what we do today.
Yeah. Mostly PyPach but
people also use Google's
framework for checks.
I think data flow
is basically out.
Then let's move to deep Syk.
This is deep. This is
performance overview.
As you can see, I
think you don't have to
care about so many parts,
but the message I want to
send from this picture is
deepsk is the first open
source language model
that is on par with GPT four.
Okay. First open model
that is on par with PFO.
And I think TPO
is one of the most used
model by you guys.
Basically, if you go to
open the default model TPO,
I think it already helps you
finish so many homeworks.
And basically, deepsk is
the first open source model
that is the same as ZPRO.
That's why it makes
so big impact.
People love PFO.
Yeah, so they love Deeps
Deeps is by the way.
And they made a
pretty bold claim.
They are able to train
this using $5.576 million.
This is compared to GB four,
I think it's a pretty
small number because I
already give you $5
million in Europe here.
I'm not sure if you
can treat D six.
But this is what they achieved.
But I want to basically
slightly correct this claim
because I think this
is a bold claim
because when I talk about
the skin load part,
I already told you
that the main cost of
training language model is
not training language model.
It's planning for
training language model.
Basically, in order to
yield in order to reach the
architectural detail of deep,
you have to launch
many, many experiments.
For example, you have
to study skin law,
how many data should you use?
What's those terms, like how
many how many parameters,
and you have to study
which should I use
like food changing
slighting slight wind
changing or whatever.
You also have to
basically study all this
like how many has I have,
these kind of details,
and you spend a lot of
money on that to make
sure you get a pretty
high confidence
that with this architecture,
I'm going to try my best model.
So I think boldly
claiming training
model is $5 million is
not very responsible because
it's impossible if I
only give you 5 million,
you're not going to give me
this model, it's impossible.
You have to perform
a lot of study.
Usually the cost of doing
that study that planning is
100 or 1,000 times
of the actual training
cost, the last job.
That is the first thing I want
to make sure you're aware.
But, But besides that,
I think it's pretty
decent model and it has
a lot of innovation on model
architectures on system mo.
Basically, I would say
it's a masterpiece of
code designing model and
systems. Let's look into that.
Um, but like I said, uh,
it's not only Deepi W three,
and I think after deeps W three,
they also released the Deep RI
and they claim that they can use
the reinforced
learning to elicit
the reasoning from D three
as a starting point.
But I'm not going to
cover maybe next course.
So let's look at a few key
innovations in Deep three.
Basically, I'm basically
comparing Deep three to
LMA because LA is the model
that everybody understands,
and so why Deep three is a
huge leap forward from LA.
The first one is they are
going a little bit crazy on MOE.
Okay. I already mentioned this.
So typically, at least
firms in the US,
they are training MOE with
eight or 16 or 32 experts,
but they are going crazy.
They are training MOE
with 256 experts,
which makes the MOE really,
really sparse,
super sparse, okay.
Which also makes the MOE
many, many parameters, right,
because they make sure
that the number of
activated experts is
still only eight.
You can see the
sparse is basically,
This lamb is pretty sparse.
Many manual parameters
are not going to be
used when the token is going
forward the neural network.
The reason I think
you guys already
understand why sparse MOE is
good because like I said,
it has a better skin law.
It allows you to scale
lamb parameters without
the scaling the flops.
That's why it's pretty good.
Um, but it also introduces
a lot of challenges,
especially on systems because
it becomes a super large model,
and then you have
to take care of
all the communication or
expert imbalance problem
I mentioned in my MOE lecture.
But before we delve into
that I'll give you
a few more details.
So they have a design
choice that they have many,
many transfer layers, right.
They make the first layer
dense and the rest MOE.
I don't know why
probably they do
some skin study and
they find the best,
but this is their
hyper parameter.
Okay. Okay, like I said,
once you decide to do this here,
you are basically facing a lot
of these optimization issues.
So let me list this optimization
opportunities, okay?
The first one is because
you are doing a
superstar sampling.
So you have a large amount
of parameters, okay?
And because you have a
large amount of parameters,
you need to communicate
these parameters when
you do be propagation.
So you have a lot of
communicating overhead,
and so you want to
do experts, okay?
Export prism? Because
is cheaper than use.
Because you do experts,
you are basically
facing an issue that
is expert im balancing.
Basically each expert will
see different number
of tokens given
a batch and that will
basically create
a straggler problem I
mentioned in my lecture.
So how do you make sure
your experts are balanced.
Welcome back to this.
But before that,
I want to introduce
another innovation
made on the model lecture.
The introduceion.
This is not main
group is not mark is
called multi latent
and why they do this.
The reason they do
this because you also
reason is because this one
is more inference efficient.
Why is more inference efficient?
Because like we mentioned
in our page lang lecture,
V catch is a bottleneck
for inference,
and by doing this
multi head latent,
you can avoid saving
a lot of V catch.
Okay. And the training
course is roughly the same,
but the inference co is much
cheaper because you can
save a lot of space.
So how do they do that? Let's do
this. It's very
easy to understand.
So on the left hand side
is smart heading, okay?
And I think you guys are already
familiar with what's
going on here.
It's just like
different symbols.
What we do is we have
a hidden state, right.
We do a projecting to get
Q, and then we do this.
This term, I think more
than 100 times here.
Okay. And what is marked
as latent attention.
The only difference is that
they introduce another layer,
which is called C. So instead
of directly
projecting H into QV,
what they do is especially
for the Q and V,
I'm going to first
take the edge,
I introduce the weight W dq,
and I project this edge
into this latent space C.
I do the same thing for
and V. This is for query.
This is for query, and
this is for Q and V. Okay?
So I take my previous layer
output I project into la C,
and then I take the
CI project into key
and V's like this.
Here, the key assumption
here is I can make C much
shorter than the original
key and V. For example,
original key and V could
be four key dimensions,
but I can make C like one key.
I first do down project
and then out project.
So why we do this?
I think if you are
sensitive to C,
you already get the g.
In the previous me inference,
we need to store key and V,
which is pretty high dimension.
But now once we have the C
and we know that the key and
V can be upper projected
from C from low
dimension vector.
So now added inference,
I can adjust need to catch C,
I put C in my memory,
and when I need key and V I
adjust to the upper
project in compute.
I'm basically treating
a little bit flops
for v memory space.
Does that make sense? So that's
essentially what
is the multi la.
That is they call
C latent vector,
and I'm basically doing
one more matam but I
first project into
low dimension and then
back to and B and
I only catch C. In
my previous version,
I need to catch both and V,
and now I only catch one C.
I can use two with matrix
to upper project C back to and
B. I also reduce one copy.
Okay. That is basically the
gist of multi latent engine.
And of course, they
do a lot of study,
and they tried to argue that
this multi latent
engine is it has a very
strong, machine
learning capability.
It can basically model
whatever like multit model,
but it can effectively
reduce the thing that you need
to catch during inference.
Okay? So to put it in a
single sentence, okay,
mult latent is basically
an opation for inference.
Okay. Cool.
There's one more thing
on architecture.
So remember why increase
language model as
a language model
mostly tined using
next token prediction.
But what DC does is they
use next token prediction.
They will train the parameters,
they will introduce
additional head here.
This is the last layer
of language model,
and in second language model,
you basically predict next token
and you calculate the loss.
But what they do is they
introduce another
transfer block,
which is basically deviated
from here and they predict
the next token and they
compute this token,
they compare this token
to the origin sequence
and they try to calculate loss.
Does this look very similar
to what you see previously?
This is the eagle. Basically
the ego architecture
given by Professor
Hong Yan Zung.
Basically, they read
his paper and what
they do differently is
in our guest lecture,
we do that for
spectrum decoding.
But in this they do
this imprinting.
Why do they do this
imprinting, Remember,
one of the main quest
in eagle is that
they try to improve
this additional head
to make sure you have
a very high acceptance
rate as ey.
The belief of D six is
that if they put this
into pre training and they
like this train with many,
many tokens, you basically
get a free eagle.
You get a free eagle.
You don't have to
do post training, you just
do it in pre training.
It's a free eagle that
is this token block.
Is going to have a much
higher acceptance rate.
It turns out they did that.
Basically, I think
if you have already
studied your spectrum homework,
you'll find that it's
very hard to achieve
an acceptance rate
greater than 50.
That's why I give
you a bonus point.
In the guys lecture, I
think Professor Han an also
mentioned at least
before Equal three,
they only have acceptance
rate of 40 or 50.
What DC report is that if you do
this additional hand and
pre training and inference,
basically the additional
handwork will
be 85% acceptance rate.
This is also an inference
time organization.
That is, if you do this a,
basically you get a model that
is quite good at eculical.
You will inference pretty fast.
Okay. Does that make sense?
Cool. So I would say these are
basically the two
major innovations
that are introduced in
deep six architecture.
Then let's move on
to the system part.
So like I said, I already
spotted the system issue.
One is you need to
perform mechanism.
Second is you need to address
the expert imbalance,
and there's a third
issue that is unique
to deep six. So what is that?
They have 800, not H 100.
Do you know the
difference 800-100?
It's subject to export
control from US to China.
800 is basically a word version
of H 100 without a link.
Basically, same flops, same
memory bandwidth,
same memory capacity,
but inside one box they have
HGPs but those cannot communicate
using high bandwidths.
Okay. That's what the US does to
China to control the
development of AI.
But it turns out if you
still remember this decision
tree, you know what to do.
If you don't have a lot of
bandwidth will You just avoid
app protein trying
this left part
of parosm because like I
mentioned in our lecture,
whenever you try to do
intrasm you are going to
subject to connective
communication,
which will eat a
lot of bandwidths.
But now, I'm not given high
bandwidth I do. I
just don't try this.
I just try to do intersm.
I do a little bit data expert.
Okay. So basically, to summarize
their system challenge,
the first one is they
need to do ex second is
exp third is they only have 800,
so they cannot use
the data prism or
this kind of reduced
space algorithms.
So what they do is
they choose to do
a pipeline arithm plus
data prism plus exm.
And of course, data prism
is still quite expensive,
because if you remember,
the communicating cost
of data prism is
still one or radius.
So they have to minimize
the degree of data pais.
They have to maximize
the degree of
pipeline pism and experts.
To give you a sense
why expert is good,
uh I think you figure,
I just repeat.
The upper part is oral,
lower part is or use.
And you can see, a communication
is only one or radius.
A is much better than radius.
Cool. Okay. Then let's start
looking at how they address
all these three problems.
Still of ex imbalance problem.
So that is one token, they
go through the rotter.
They will be dispatched
into this ex
and you have this
problem three to two,
each ex receive different
number of tokens.
So how do they address this?
So the way they address
this is pre force.
So basically, they introduce
the so called Wi Fi equation,
but I don't want you to
spend time understanding
the equation,
but what I try to emphasize is,
this is the router output.
It determines which goes well.
What they do is they add
another bias term into
the router output.
And this bias term
is not trainable.
It's a parameter that can
be controlled by a human.
What does that mean? That means
that they have a
human sitting out
of the cluster and they
observe how many token
go to each expert.
If one expert read much more
token than another expert,
that human will basically
add this term to
the large logic to make
its balance. Very good.
Basically, you just assign
an engineer to sit there,
watch and you fix this problem.
Cool. Of course,
they have a lot of
other arguments saying
that they have a lot
of good tricks to make sure
they can balance that.
But if you read those papers,
at least from my perspective,
I didn't buy that why because
I think my argument is
that they tried to see,
they tried to sell
a point that is,
you know, traditionally
at open air at Google,
the way people do ex balance
is basically they
introduce loss,
and the loss will
promote the balance
between different experts.
But because you
introduce a loss,
you are basically
changing your objective
from the original
prediction into
something more complicated
and that can probably
hurt your machine learning
model language
model performance.
And what they try to say
is they can do this.
That is export control,
human control.
Okay, I'm not going to
incorporate this into my loss,
so my model change
is still a good one.
But indeed, it is not the case
because they actually add
another term here
into sequence level.
So basically, they make
sure all the tokens in
one sequence will be dispatched
into an equal amount of exports.
So basically they're saying
the contra on one hand,
they're saying that I'm
not going to automate
loss and introduce loss.
So this is the one inconsistency
I find in the paper, okay?
Then let's look at parallelism.
For parallelism, I think we
can basically get this
synth from the paper.
They said they have 16 way of
pipeline paism 64
way of ex paism with
the rest in the data
paism they also said
that they are using two GPUs
and which I assume is 248.
Then from this number,
you can basically
infer the actual prism 16 way of
pipeline 64 will export this
and we know this number,
we know this number
with this number.
Basically we just divide
these two from this number,
using two way DP once
we have all this
number, we know this.
Basically, this is the problem.
This is the problem. So
you have two way DP.
That is, you replicate your
model into two replicas.
This is the first replica,
is the second replica.
Does that make sense?
And then you still
have one kgPU to
support 16 wave of pipeline
and 64 wave of export.
What is in each replica
because they are doing
16 wave of pipeline,
so you divide the network
into 16 stages 16 way.
And then the rest is the export.
That is, for each stage,
there are 64 GPUs.
Okay. Does that make sense?
So this stage is performing
intro opism in 16 800.
Yeah. Okay. And apparently
the communication here
is between stages,
we have the interop
communication with PTP inside
the stage we have
intro op which is at.
And between these
replicas one radios.
So we only sublet one radius
between two replicas.
And if we further zoom in,
we have each stage paralyzed
on 64 H 800, right?
And they said they are
doing 64 wave of X.
So what we do is we basically
map this stage to this figure.
In the MOE, we have
64 wave of EP.
And a MO for the changing
we are doing DP here,
when you transform
from DP to EP,
you perform one
out among 64 TPs.
And once you finish
the MOE combination,
you go back to the next layers.
So you roll back to data points,
so you perform another a.
Let's do one.
Okay. The next work pipeline.
In pipeline, I think that
paper basically mentioned
that they have a few
techniques, dual pipe,
communication and
competition overlapping
and you already know this they
release a pretty
good auto kernel.
Now you understand why they
need the auto kernel right
because here they are taught
how to make this fast.
Okay. Then you understand
this. Let's look at these two.
For dopp, I already
told you Dopp
is basically this one Chimera.
Basically, you have two batches,
one is going forward and the
other is going backward and
you basically make
this into the P graph.
Because like I said, still
remember the cons of Chimera.
You have to replicate
the two model weights.
But like I said,
this is on 64 GPUs,
so you have plenty of memory.
Okay. Okay.
And one thing you notice in that
it has a pretty good planned
schedule, very few bubble.
But like I said, when you
do this kind of communication
between stages,
are you are subject to auto.
So inside each stage,
you have an auto.
So which means that
this schedule is not as
perfect as it should because
there will be some
bubbles that is
basically paid for
communication for running auto.
And the way they address
that is they basically
come up with a um, an
overlapping schedule.
Before we understand the
overlapping schedule,
let's first look at the
communicating impact.
Now, I know this is complicated,
but let's finish it.
So So what's coming
looking like?
Let's think about let's run
the neural network from
the first layer to
last layer. Okay?
So because we are performing
pipeline prism, right?
So we enter first
enter stage one,
right, and then we perform third
all the way to the second stage.
And like I mentioned,
inside the stage one,
we do we are doing expert
prism among 64 GPLs.
So what we do is
we first compute
the attention right of the
first layer on stage one,
which is like this part, right?
And then we enter the MOE layer,
we are going to do auto?
Okay. And once we finish,
we are going to
compute this MLP and
experts. That's the first step.
And once we finish
completing the MOE,
we're going to do another
auto on the 64 GBUs.
And once we finish the 64 Gs,
worldw we proceed to the
second stage, right?
So in order to proceed
to the second stage,
we do another PTP communication.
Okay. This is our
workload, right.
I put communication and
committing altogether.
So as you can see a
change in auto, MLP,
MOE, auto and PTP,
and then repeat until I finish.
And this is good why
because you are
adopting a dual pipe,
that there are two
pipelines, two batches.
One is running from
first year to last year
and another is
running from reverse.
So when you try to arrange
this in this pipeline,
you can basically do a
pretty good overlapping.
Okay. So this is the competition,
this is communication.
Like I said, this
is the first batch
backward backward
against activation,
backward against weight, and
then forward competition,
and then at backward attention
like backward against
weight backward and
forward coitation and
each basic triangle
is two batches
running on the dual
path that is on
the Tim because you are
performing two batches,
so you can perfectly make
the communication
competition overlap.
So you can basically remove
and this and this from
the critical path.
It's a pretty good orientation
like combining MOE,
experts, and all and all
these kind of doping.
One last bit. They also
deliver a pretty good auto
communication kernel,
which you already
properly read the GitHub.
This auto kernel is
pretty hard core,
and I think they hired
a media engineer and
that media engineer
knows more than us.
Okay. And so this is
some instruction into
the hardware level and
found that if you up
the instruction that you
run faster than typical.
And you can go to the
GitHub and you'll find
the sentence where
they said that I
can use the read
only PTS instruction
and it will yield
undefined behavior,
but this undefined
behavior is safe and
it will give us a
20% improvement,
something like that. Okay.
Very crazy. Finally,
the last two pieces.
Traditionally, language
model, we are doing
LP 16 and LP 32
mixed in training.
And if you remember,
the cast is basically
16 lab parameters.
Deep goes one step further.
They are doing LP eight,
LP 16, and LP 32
mixed in training.
I don't think I have
time to explain this,
but the way to process is the
same as the way to process.
That is basically some
moments, first moment,
second moments are saved
in different precision,
and some parameters are
saved in lower precision.
And if you basically
run all these together,
you can effectively reduce
that 16 factor into 13.
Meaning that in
deeps you are seeing
a little bit more memory
on optimal states.
Cool. And lastly,
they use metric pre
fill decode deggation.
It is more complicated than
I taught in this class.
Basically, it for decoding,
they are using 320 GPUs,
and for pre fill they are
using much less GPUs.
Still remember PYD.
They have to tune the value
of X and Y to make
sure that they
strike a pretty good balance
between prefer and
decode at three.
Okay. Okay. I know I
run this too quick,
but feel free to come to
me or tomorrow in
my office hour.
I'm happy to explain
all these details.
But essentially, you
can see in deep ke,
what they do is they combine
all these altogether,
and they deliver a
pretty good model and
a pretty good system to
train and solve that model.
With that, I think I finished
all my planned contents
and there are more
like we can cover,
but because the usage is
quarter based, so
I don't have time.
And I want to see a few
ending words, okay?
So in this course,
we covered different layers
of machining systems, right?
So we covered the system itself,
we covered the kernels,
we covered distribute
systems like
how to org managements.
We also talked about the
changing, for example,
flight engine, which belongs
to efficient machine
learning systems.
And we sometimes also joke aside
about the current
deploying market, right?
And I think we covered
many technologies,
some of our latest,
but I think the true lesson
I want to let you know
is So now the world is
changing faster than before.
Okay. So whatever
I taught, okay?
So happens because now
you can write code in
HB and you can write like
80% of the code, okay.
And we developing agent,
agents is going to supposed
to replace humans, right?
Okay, and even those agents
can write kernels So what
I taught what I have learned in
this course likely will be
replaced in one to two years.
This is a very unique time
because I think before this,
this will never happen.
For example, you took
some OS cores you took
some database scores,
at least database
has been there for
20 years, more than 20 years.
But what I taught today and
what I e in the future,
any technology invented will
be replaced in one to two years?
And I want to let you know
that this will be a norm.
Okay. You have to
get used to that.
And so what I really hope
you can learn from this
course is three things.
First one, you need to identify
the problem to work on.
Which problem is
the most important?
Like what methods is not
the technology itself.
What methods is the problem.
Second, I hope we can understand
the technology trends.
For example, by looking
at hardware and software,
you know how things
will change, right?
And third, most important,
I hope we have the ability
to predict the future.
And I think that's one of
the most important
kind of capability.
And why I think
that's pretty good
because if you can
predict the future,
I think you can do a few
quite amazing things.
The first one is you
will be able to write
a pretty good paper
that can quickly
accumulates because
you know the future,
you know what people will
value on the research market.
Secondly, you will be
that person, right?
Yeah, you will basically
invest your career
on something that
is trendy and you will get
appreciated by employers.
If you don't work, you can
probably become very benefit.
You can go invest in red stock
and you'll get pretty rich.
Okay. That's all from me,
and I hope you enjoy this class,